<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pakistan Premier Wants Afghan Refugees to Return Home</title>
    <meta content="05afghan" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/05/world/asia/05afghan.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1816491"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mines, Explosive</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pakistan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gall, Carlotta</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Aziz, Shaukat (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Karzai, Hamid (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Pakistan</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Afghanistan</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Karzai, Hamid</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E3DD1430F936A35752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="437" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pakistan Premier Wants Afghan Refugees to Return Home</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pakistan Premier Wants Afghan Refugees to Return Home</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARLOTTA GALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gall, Carlotta</byline>
      <dateline>KABUL, Afghanistan, Jan. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prime Min Shaukat Aziz of Pakistan, in Kabul for talks with Afghan Pres Hamid Karzai, says he wants three million Afghan refugees still living in Pakistan to go home as one way to end problem of insurgents using his country as haven; two leaders emerge with no agreement on main areas of contention, Pakistan's plan to fence and mine border, and Afghanistan's project to convene two tribal gatherings of national representatives from both countries to try to foster peace between them; Karzai emerges from meeting to acknowledge that relations are only growing worse; Aziz says two leaders did agree to work on resettling three million Afghan refugees back in Afghanistan and removing sanctuary that refugee camps provide to insurgents; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pakistan's prime minister, Shaukat Aziz, said Thursday that he wanted the three million Afghan refugees still living in Pakistan to go home as one way to end the problem of insurgents using the country as a haven.</p>
        <p>It is the first time Pakistan has been so blunt in demanding that the Afghans, to whom it has served as host for more than 20 years since the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan, leave.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shaukat Aziz said he wanted three million Afghan refugees to go home to end the problem of insurgents using Pakistan as a haven.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Pakistan's prime minister, Shaukat Aziz, said Thursday that he wanted the three million Afghan refugees still living in Pakistan to go home as one way to end the problem of insurgents using the country as a haven.</p>
        <p>It is the first time Pakistan has been so blunt in demanding that the Afghans, to whom it has served as host for more than 20 years since the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan, leave.</p>
        <p>Mr. Aziz arrived here for talks with the Afghan president, Hamid Karzai, in an effort to smooth tensions between the neighbors, but after more than two hours Mr. Karzai acknowledged that relations were only growing worse.</p>
        <p>''Unfortunately, the gulf in relations between Afghanistan and Pakistan is getting wider, and it is not getting narrower,'' Mr. Karzai said after their meeting.</p>
        <p>The two leaders emerged with no agreement on the main areas of contention, namely Pakistan's plan to fence and mine the border, and Afghanistan's project to convene two tribal gatherings, or jirgas, of national representatives from both countries, to try to foster peace between the countries.</p>
        <p>Shortly before the meeting, Pakistan announced that it was going ahead with a plan to fence and mine the long mountainous border. Afghanistan has repeatedly condemned the project as a diversion from the real problem of terrorism, which it says is being incubated in Pakistan. Pakistan has also dragged its feet on organizing the tribal gatherings, promising only to form a commission to work on the idea.</p>
        <p>''The Afghan people want to remove all those obstacles which create the divide in our relations,'' Mr. Karzai said. ''Those obstacles are created by terrorist activities which are hindering Afghanistan's reconstruction and making our schools burn.</p>
        <p>''Security will not come to Afghanistan unless together we and Pakistan, with good and friendly relations, become tough in the fight against terrorism,'' he added. He said he wanted to hold the tribal jirgas so people could speak their minds.</p>
        <p>Without offering specifics, Mr. Aziz said the two leaders agreed to work on resettling three million Afghan refugees back in Afghanistan and removing the sanctuary that refugee camps provide to insurgents.</p>
        <p>''Refugee camps on our side of the border sometimes are safe havens for elements who are from Afghanistan and take safe haven there after conducting activities,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He also defended Pakistan's plan to fence and mine the border as one way to restrict the movement of people who represent a threat to security. ''We believe that selective fencing and mining can help achieve the objective,'' he said, adding that the fence and mines would not prevent the ordinary crossing of local tribes.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
