<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Listings: Jan. 5 - Jan 11</title>
    <meta content="05theater" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070112T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1816450"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E2DF1430F936A35752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="15494" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Listings: Jan. 5 - Jan 11</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the New York metropolitan region this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'THE FEVER' Previews start on Tuesday. Opens on Jan. 24. Wallace Shawn stars in his own play about a man who wakes up in a war-torn country feeling under the weather (2:00). Acorn Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'IN THE HEIGHTS' Previews start on Tuesday. Opens on Feb. 8. A new Off Broadway musical about two days in the life of Washington Heights from the vantage point of a corner bodega (2:10). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'THE MERCHANT OF VENICE' Previews start tomorrow. Opens on Feb. 4. F. Murray Abraham plays Shylock in this Theater for a New Audience production. Darko Tresnjak directs (2:20). The Duke on 42nd Street, 229 West 42nd Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'THE SCENE' In previews; opens on Thursday. A buzz-maker at the Humana Festival, Theresa Rebeck's new play is about an out-of-work actor who doesn't solve his problems by having an affair. Tony Shalhoub (''Monk'') and Patricia Heaton (''Everybody Loves Raymond'') star (2:00). Second Stage Theater, 307 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 246-4422.</p>
        <p>'A SPANISH PLAY' Previews start on Wednesday. Opens on Feb. 1. Zoe Caldwell leads an extraordinary cast (Linda Emond, Denis O'Hare, Larry Pine, Katherine Borowitz) in Yasmina Reza's new backstage play, in which real life and fiction blur (1:30). Classic Stage Company, 136 East 13th Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101.</p>
        <p>'TRANSLATIONS' In previews; opens on Jan. 25. Brian Friel's drama about a British officer in 19th-century rural Ireland deals with themes of language, imperialism and culture clash. Garry Hynes directs (1:55). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE APPLE TREE' The amazing Kristin Chenoweth gives Imax-screen-size life to three curvaceous doodles who by rights shouldn't be any larger than figures in the Sunday funnies. Jerry Bock and Sheldon Harnick's 1966 musical, directed by Gary Griffin, shows its age but is given theatrical verve by Ms. Chenoweth, Brian d'Arcy James and Marc Kudisch (2:30). Studio 54, 254 West 54th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BUTLEY' In this uneasy revival of Simon Gray's portrait of a toxic English professor, directed by Nicholas Martin, Nathan Lane fires off witticisms as if they were silver bullets with ''Made in Britain'' engraved on them. A less-than-perfect marriage of a first-rate actor with a first-rate play (2:30). Booth Theater, 222 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'A CHORUS LINE' If you want to know why this show was such a big deal when it opened 31 years ago, you need only experience the thrilling first five minutes of this revival. Otherwise, this archivally exact production, directed by Bob Avian, feels like a vintage car that has been taken out of the garage, polished up and sent on the road once again (2:00). Schoenfeld Theater, 236 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE COAST OF UTOPIA: VOYAGE' The exhilarating first two installments of Tom Stoppard's trilogy about 19th-century Russian intellectuals dreaming of revolution, these productions pulse with the dizzy, spring-green arrogance and anxiety of a new generation moving as fast as it can toward the future. Jack O'Brien directs a fresh, vigorous and immense cast that includes Brian F. O'Byrne, Jennifer Ehle, Billy Crudup and Ethan Hawke (2:45). Vivian Beaumont Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'COMPANY' Fire, beckoning and dangerous, flickers beneath the frost of John Doyle's elegant, unexpectedly stirring revival of Stephen Sondheim and George Furth's era-defining musical from 1970, starring a compellingly understated Raul Esparza. Like Mr. Doyle's ''Sweeney Todd,'' this production finds new clarity of feeling in Sondheim by melding the roles of performers and musicians (2:20). Barrymore Theater, 243 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE' (Tony Awards, best book of a musical and best original score, 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920s stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, it has theatergoers responding as if they were withering houseplants finally being watered after long neglect. Bob Martin and Sutton Foster are the standouts in the avid, energetic cast (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'GREY GARDENS' Christine Ebersole is absolutely glorious as the middle-aged, time-warped debutante called Little Edie Beale in this uneven musical adaptation of the notorious 1975 documentary of the same title. She and the wonderful Mary Louise Wilson (as her bedridden mother), in the performances of their careers, make ''Grey Gardens'' an experience no passionate theatergoer should miss (2:40). Walter Kerr Theater, 219 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE LITTLE DOG LAUGHED' The comedy of manners, a form widely believed to be extinct in the American theater, has actually resurfaced on Broadway with all its vital signs intact in Douglas Carter Beane's breezy but trenchant satire about truth and illusion, Hollywood style. With the wonderful Julie White as the movie agent you hate to love (but just can't help it) (2:00). Cort Theater, 138 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MARY POPPINS' This handsome, homily-packed, mechanically ingenious and rather tedious musical, adapted from the P. L. Travers stories and the 1964 Disney film, is ultimately less concerned with inexplicable magic than with practical psychology. Ashley Brown, who sings prettily as the family-mending nanny, looks like Joan Crawford trying to be nice and sounds like Dr. Phil. Directed by Richard Eyre and Matthew Bourne (2:30). New Amsterdam Theater, 214 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LES MISÉRABLES' This premature revival, a slightly scaled-down version of the well-groomed behemoth that closed only three years ago, appears to be functioning in a state of mild sedation. Appealingly sung and freshly orchestrated, this fast-moving adaptation of Victor Hugo's novel isn't sloppy or blurry. But its pulse rate stays well below normal (2:55). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' Duncan Sheik and Steven Sater's bold adaptation of the Frank Wedekind play is the freshest and most exciting new musical Broadway has seen in some time. Set in 19th-century Germany but with a ravishing rock score, it exposes the splintered emotional lives of adolescents just discovering the joys and sorrows of sex. Performed with brio by a great cast, with supple direction by Michael Mayer and inventive choreography by Bill T. Jones (2:00). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN'  This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a superdeluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE VERTICAL HOUR' David Hare's soggy consideration of the Anglo-American cultural divide stars Julianne Moore (representing the Americans) and Bill Nighy (leading the British), directed by Sam Mendes. The Yanks don't stand a chance. With his irresistibly mannered performance as a laconic doctor, Mr. Nighy mops the floor with Ms. Moore. Actually, he mops the floor with Mr. Hare's play (2:20). Music Box Theater, 239 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE BIG VOICE: GOD OR MERMAN?' Think of two gifted and smart gay men with years of life together deploying their considerable talents from the two pianos you happen to have in your living room. The result is a hilarious and very touching memoir of two decades of love and the funky glories of show business life (2:00). Actors Temple Theater, 339 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Honor Moore)</p>
        <p>*'THE CLEAN HOUSE' Sarah Ruhl's comedy about the painful but beautiful disorder of life has arrived in New York at last in a gorgeous production directed by Bill Rauch. Blair Brown and Jill Clayburgh delight as sisters with different views on the meaning of cleaning, and Vanessa Aspillaga is equally good as the depressed maid with little affection for her work but a deep conviction that a good joke can be a matter of life and death (2:15). Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, Lincoln Center, 150 West 65th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'DAI (ENOUGH)' Iris Bahr's unnerving one-woman show doesn't have much to add to the Middle East debate, but it sure leaves a lasting impression. Ms. Bahr plays an assortment of characters who have the misfortune of being in a Tel Aviv cafe that is about to be visited by the havoc common to such establishments. The attack is rendered in jarring fashion, repeatedly; you watch the play on pins and needles, waiting for the next burst. Gimmicky? Sure. But viscerally effective (1:40). Culture Project, 55 Mercer Street, at Broome Street, SoHo, (212) 253-9983. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'EVIL DEAD: THE MUSICAL' This likable horror comedy based on Sam Raimi's gory movies wants to be the next ''Rocky Horror Show.'' To that end, it offers deadpan lyrics, self-referential humor and geysers of stage blood (2:00). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>'THE FANTASTICKS' A revival -- well, more like a resuscitation -- of the Little Musical That Wouldn't Die. This sweet-as-ever production of Tom Jones and Harvey Schmidt's commedia-dell'arte-style confection is most notable for Mr. Jones's touching performance (under the pseudonym Thomas Bruce) as the Old Actor, a role he created when the show opened in 1960. Mr. Jones also directs (2:05). Snapple Theater Center, 210 West 50th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JACQUES BREL IS ALIVE AND WELL AND LIVING IN PARIS' A powerfully sung revival of the 1968 revue, presented with affectionate nostalgia by the director Gordon Greenberg. As in the original, two men and two women perform a wide selection of Brel's plaintive ballads and stirring anthems (2:00). Zipper Theater, 336 West 37th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'A JEW GROWS IN BROOKLYN' You don't have to be Jewish or Brooklynish to empathize with Jake Ehrenreich, but in terms of fully appreciating his essentially one-man show, it probably helps. Especially the Catskills jokes (2:05). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 560-8912. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'MEET ME IN ST. LOUIS' This musical is too big for its stage, but the young turn-of-the-last-century sweethearts have great chemistry, and there are four terrific songs (2:00). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'MY MOTHER'S ITALIAN, MY FATHER'S JEWISH AND I'M IN THERAPY'  Steve Solomon does skillful impersonations in his one-man show, but some of his jokes are as old as the hills (1:30). Little Shubert Theater, 422 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'NO CHILD'  Teachers will love Nilaja Sun's one-woman show about the challenges of teaching drama at Malcolm X High School (1:10). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, at Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'AN OAK TREE' Tim Crouch plays a hypnotist in this elusive puzzle of a play about grief and the power of suggestion (1:05). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, at Seventh Avenue, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'REGRETS ONLY' Old acquaintance comes under siege in Paul Rudnick's chiffon-thin comedy about the varieties of love and marriage. But no one who sees this latest offering from one of the funniest quipmeisters alive is going to doubt that Christine Baranski is a one-liner's best friend (2:00). City Center Stage I, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'ROOM SERVICE' The Peccadillo Theater Company puts a charge into this comedy from the 1930s, thanks to a brisk pace by the director, Dan Wackerman, and a dozen dandy performances. David Edwards is the would-be producer whose bills threaten to swamp his efforts to put a show on Broadway, and Fred Berman is particularly fine as his director (2:00). SoHo Playhouse, 15 Vandam Street, South Village, (212) 691-1555. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'SUDDENLY LAST SUMMER'  As the luscious (and lobotomy-threatened) damsel in distress in Tennessee Williams's famously lurid melodrama, Carla Gugino gives a gutsy assurance to a production that otherwise lacks compelling confidence. Mark Brokaw directs a cast that includes Blythe Danner, in a fascinating but misconceived performance as a smothering mother from hell (1:30). Laura Pels Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'25 QUESTIONS FOR A JEWISH MOTHER' This is the comedian Judy Gold's fiercely funny monologue, based on her own life as a single Jewish lesbian mother and interviews with more than 50 other Jewish mothers (1:20). St. Luke's Theater, 308 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Phoebe Hoban)</p>
        <p>'TWO TRAINS RUNNING'  Directed by Lou Bellamy, a rough-edged revival of August Wilson's 1992 play about the stark economics of life and death for African-Americans, set in a dying diner in Pittsburgh in the late 1960s. The pace drags in this production, but it remains a bracing reminder of Mr. Wilson's singular talent for making cold, hard numbers sing hot, molten blues (3:40). Signature Theater at Peter Norton Space, 555 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 352-3101. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE VOYSEY INHERITANCE' David Mamet has cleanly and cannily adapted Harley Granville Barker's 1905 play about corruption in the genteel world of Victorian finance. An excellent cast and a sumptuous production bring extra immediacy to a tale of embezzlement and entitlement that feels as fresh as tomorrow's stock options (1:50). Atlantic Theater, 336 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'T J AND DAVE' The comics T. J. Jagodowski and Dave Pasquesi miraculously improvise a one-hour play at every performance. This is an impressive feat of mental athletics, but the results are also observant, complex and frequently enormously funny. (1:00) Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden Theater, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' Singing CliffsNotes for Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' Often more entertaining than the real thing (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS'  The biomusical that walks like a man (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SLAVA'S SNOWSHOW' Clowns chosen by the Russian master Slava Polunin stir up laughter and enjoyment. A show that touches the heart as well as tickles the funny bone (1:30). Union Square Theater, 100 East 17th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT'  A singing scrapbook for Monty Python fans (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' ''A Chorus Line'' with pimples (1:45). Circle in the Square, 1633 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'BECOMING ADELE' Eric Houston's one-woman show about a young Brooklyn waitress's journey to self-actualization imagines a New York where fairy tales are possible even for the very ordinary. The sentiment is heavy and thick, but Kimberly Stern's performance burrows through it to deliver moving moments (1:40). Clurman Theater at Theater Row, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200; closing tomorrow. (Ginia Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'BIG APPLE CIRCUS' One terrific show (2:15). Damrosch Park, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500 or (212) 307-4100; closing on Sunday. (Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'MARTIN SHORT: FAME BECOMES ME' This eager and amiably scattershot satire of celebrity memoirs and Broadway musicals, starring the immodestly modest Mr. Short, arrives a little late to the table for such parody to taste fresh. With serviceably tuneful songs by Scott Wittman and Marc Shaiman (of ''Hairspray'' fame) (1:45). Jacobs Theater, 242 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200; closing on Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'STRINGS' Keir Dullea stars in Carole Buggé's intelligent but ultimately unsuccessful ''Copenhagen''-inspired drama about three scientists on a train (1:45). 78th Street Theater Lab, 236 West 78th Street, (212) 362-0329; closing tomorrow. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'TRUE WEST' This perfectly pleasant new version of Sam Shepard's sibling rivalry drama tries something new: understatement (1:35). Big Little Theater, 141 Ridge Street, near Houston Street, Lower East Side, (212) 868-4444; closes tonight. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>'APOCALYPTO' (R, 138 minutes, in Maya) More blood from Mel Gibson, but more ''Braveheart'' than ''Passion of the Christ.'' Ultraviolent entertainment, well executed (so to speak) but not very surprising in the end. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>'BABEL' (R, 143 minutes, in English, Spanish, Japanese, Berber, Arabic and sign language) This hugely ambitious movie tells four loosely linked, not quite simultaneous stories set on three different continents, with dialogue in several languages. The themes, to the extent they are decipherable, include loss, fate and the terrible consequences of miscommunication. Written by Guillermo Arriaga and directed by Alejandro Gonzalez Iñárritu, the movie is an intellectual muddle but a visceral tour de force, and the power of the filmmaking almost overcomes the fuzziness of the ideas. Almost. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'BLACK CHRISTMAS' (R, 100 minutes) It's been more than 30 years since the original ''Black Christmas'' revealed how much fun it could be to unleash a psycho in a sorority house. Glen Morgan's disastrous remake not only sidelines the original's hilariously obscene phone calls but also drags its unseen killer, and his psychoses, into the light. Smothering terror beneath a blanket of unnecessary information, the movie is no more than a dismal Christmas card to its predecessor. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'BLOOD DIAMOND' (R, 138 minutes) The makers of this foolish thriller about illegal diamond trafficking in Africa, starring an excellent Leonardo DiCaprio, want you to know there may be blood on your hands, specifically your wedding finger. Too bad they haven't thought through what it means to turn human misery into entertainment. (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>'BOBBY' (R, 111 minutes) Emilio Estevez's picture, which follows a score of characters through the Ambassador Hotel in Los Angeles on June 4, 1968, is full of noble ambition. The day in question ended with the assassination of Robert F. Kennedy, an event that hovers over the movie, even though Kennedy himself is visible only in archival clips. A huge cast (including Anthony Hopkins, Sharon Stone, Demi Moore, Ashton Kutcher, Lindsay Lohan and Mr. Estevez) labors to inject a collection of melodramatic anecdotes with portent and significance, but the individual parts of the film tend to be either overdone or vague and slight. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'BORAT: CULTURAL LEARNINGS OF AMERICA FOR MAKE BENEFIT GLORIOUS NATION OF KAZAKHSTAN' (R, 89 minutes) In this brainy, merciless comedy, a Kazakh journalist named Borat Sagdiyev, a k a the British comic Sacha Baron Cohen, invades America. America laughs, cries, surrenders. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'CASINO ROYALE' (PG-13, 144 minutes) The latest James Bond vehicle finds the British spy leaner, meaner and now played by an attractive piece of blond rough named Daniel Craig. Zap, pow, ka-ching! (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'CHARLOTTE'S WEB' (G, 113 minutes) Gary Winick's adaptation of E. B. White's great children's novel is faithful to the wit and feeling of the source. The celebrity-voiced animals are charming, and Julia Roberts is in fine form as the heroic spider, whose writing ability saves the life of a pig. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'CHILDREN OF MEN' (R, 100 minutes) The end is nigh in this superbly directed political thriller by Alfonso Cuarón about a nervously plausible future. Based on the P. D. James book, the film stars an excellent Clive Owen and features equally sterling support from the actors Michael Caine, Danny Huston and Chiwetel Ejiofior, among others, as well as the great cinematographer Emmanuel Lubezki. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'COPYING BEETHOVEN' (PG-13, 104 minutes) The director Agnieszka Holland and her star Ed Harris bring intelligence and passion to a fictional account about the creation of the Ninth Symphony. Diane Kruger also stars. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'CURSE OF THE GOLDEN FLOWER' (R, 114 minutes, in Mandarin) The Chinese director Zhang Yimou aims for Shakespeare and winds up with Jacqueline Susann in this Tang dynasty melodrama roiling with incest, fraternal rivalry and madness-inducing fungus. As an emperor and empress fighting for control of their three sons, Chow Yun Fat and Gong Li lend the film a core of marital toxicity that's deliciously unstable. Directing with operatic delirium, Mr. Zhang has created a movie in which the line between tragedy and black comedy has been all but erased. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'THE DEAD GIRL' (R, 93 minutes) An impressively well-acted movie, ''The Dead Girl'' has a chip on its shoulder. The relentless emotional violence in it, a compendium of five vignettes related to a young woman whose naked, mutilated corpse is discovered on a barren hillside, is of a level rarely found in movies, even those steeped in gore. There is some gore in ''The Dead Girl,'' but it is eclipsed in intensity by the verbal abuse hurled by its desperately unhappy characters at the people closest to them. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>'DEATH OF A PRESIDENT' (No rating, 93 minutes) This fake-umentary, the subject of much hyperventilation since it was shown at the 2006 Toronto Film Festival, imagines what might happen if George W. Bush were assassinated. Condemned as irresponsible wishful thinking by some, hailed as a brave artistic statement by others, the movie, directed by Gabriel Range, is far too banal to merit such strong responses. Its formal cleverness wears thin and after a while exposes a lazy, pretentious form of provocation. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'DECK THE HALLS' (PG, 95 minutes) In the holiday tradition of stale fruitcake, ugly snowflake sweaters and food poisoning comes this piece of junk, in which Matthew Broderick and Danny DeVito compete to see who can annoy the audience more. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'DÉJÀ VU' (PG-13, 125 minutes) In Tony Scott's preposterous action flick, with Denzel Washington, the gaudy pyrotechnics are nowhere near as jaw-dropping as the screenplay that name-checks not one, not two, but three national tragedies. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'THE DEPARTED' (R, 150 minutes) Martin Scorsese's cubistic entertainment about men divided by power, loyalty and their own selves is at once a success and a relief. Based on the crackling Hong Kong thriller ''Infernal Affairs,'' it features fine twinned performances from Matt Damon and Leonardo DiCaprio, and a showboating Jack Nicholson. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'DHOOM 2' (No rating, 151 minutes, in Hindi) A slick and satisfying example of the new, thoroughly modern Bollywood, this cops-and-robbers tale is animated by old-fashioned star power. Hrithik Roshan plays the ''smartest and coolest thief alive,'' and Aishwarya Rai is the small-time crook who loves him. (Rachel Saltz)</p>
        <p>'ERAGON' (PG, 99 minutes) This lad-and-his-dragon fantasy set in a land bristling with Tolkienesque nomenclature and earnest British actors is as lacking in fresh ideas as Tim Allen's manager. Directed by the wonderfully named Stefen Fangmeier, it boasts the usual genre lineup: an evil king (John Malkovich), a whey-faced hero (Edward Speleers) and a serene warrior-maiden (Sienna Guillory), as well as the required rebel hordes and bucolic landscapes. Some of the characters won't be returning for the sequel, but no matter. In all likelihood, neither will the audience. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* '51 BIRCH STREET' (No rating, 88 minutes) The mysteries of ordinary life drive this moving, engrossing documentary, in which the director, Doug Block, tries to figure out his parents' 54-year marriage. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'FLAGS OF OUR FATHERS' (R, 132 minutes) Clint Eastwood raises the flag over Iwo Jima once more in a powerful if imperfect film about the uses of war and of the men who fight. The fine cast includes Ryan Phillippe, Jesse Bradford and Adam Beach, who delivers heartbreak by the payload. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'FLANNEL PAJAMAS' (No rating, 124 minutes) The twin specters of Ingmar Bergman and Woody Allen hover over this film, which might have been more accurately titled ''Scenes From a Mixed Marriage'' or ''Annie Hall Without Laughs.'' This smart, talky history of a relationship between two New Yorkers follows a Jewish theatrical promoter and an aspiring caterer with a Roman Catholic background from courtship to marriage to separation. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'FLUSHED AWAY' (PG, 85 minutes) Sewer rats, singing leeches and whimsical British anarchy -- this computer-animated feature from Aardman Animations (''Wallace and Gromit,'' ''Chicken Run'') is completely delightful. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'FOR YOUR CONSIDERATION' (PG-13, 86 minutes) This satire of pre-Oscar-nomination buzz in Hollywood is far and away the broadest comedy Christopher Guest and his improvisatory company have made. It is also the flimsiest, and unlike Mr. Guest's earlier films, it has no airs of being a fake documentary. As farce trumps satire, the humor's subversive edge is lost, along with meaningful character development, with the brilliant exception of Catherine O'Hara. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE GOOD SHEPHERD' (R, 157 minutes) This chilly film written by Eric Roth and directed by Robert De Niro about a spy trapped in the cold of his own heart, seeks to put a tragic human face on the Central Intelligence Agency, namely that of Matt Damon. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE GOOD GERMAN' (R, 102 minutes) In his adaptation of the Joseph Kanon novel, Steven Soderbergh tries to resurrect the magic of classical Hollywood, principally by sucking out all the air, energy and pleasure from his own filmmaking. It's no wonder George Clooney, who stars alongside a vamping Cate Blanchett, looks confused. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'HAPPY FEET' (PG, 100 minutes) The director George Miller gets happy and snappy, then goes dark and deep, in a musical about an animated penguin who was born to dance. Take hankies. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE HISTORY BOYS' (R, 104 minutes) The current of intellectual energy snapping through this ferociously engaging screen adaptation of Alan Bennett's Tony Award-winning play, set in a north England boys' school in 1983, feels like electrical brain stimulation. As two teachers jockey for the hearts and minds of eight teenage schoolboys preparing to apply to Oxford and Cambridge, their epigrams send up small jolts of pleasure and excitement. How to teach and interpret history is the question. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'I LOVE YOU (VOLIM TE)' (No rating, 83 minutes, in Croatian) In this bleak drama about a young advertising hotshot who learns that he's H.I.V.-positive, the Croatian writer and director Dalibor Matanic conjures a disaffected, post-Communist lifestyle of casual hedonism and emotional bankruptcy. The premise may be trite -- personal growth through unexpected adversity -- but in its pervasive atmosphere of haunting sterility, the movie is as much about the loss of a generation as the redemption of an individual. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* 'INLAND EMPIRE' (No rating, 179 minutes) David Lynch's extraordinary, savagely uncompromised new film stars a dazzling Laura Dern as an actress who tumbles down rabbit holes inside rabbit holes inside rabbit holes. As cracked as Mad magazine, though generally more difficult to parse, the film has the power of nightmares and is one of the few this year that deserve to be called art. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE LAST KING OF SCOTLAND' (R, 121 minutes) Kevin Macdonald paints a queasily enjoyable portrait of the Ugandan dictator Idi Amin from inside the palace walls. Forest Whitaker plays the mad king, while James McAvoy plays the fool. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'LETTERS FROM IWO JIMA' (R, 141 minutes, in Japanese) Another masterwork from Clint Eastwood's astonishing late period, and one of the best war movies ever. Ken Watanabe is especially fine as the general commanding Japanese troops in the doomed defense of the island of Iwo Jima. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'LITTLE CHILDREN' (R, 130 minutes) Todd Field's adaptation of Tom Perrotta's novel of suburban adultery is unfailingly intelligent and faultlessly acted. Kate Winslet and Patrick Wilson are superb as the parents of young children who meet at the playground and enact a two-handed variation on ''Madame Bovary'' against a backdrop of social paranoia and middle-class malaise. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'MAN OF THE YEAR' (PG-13, 115 minutes) Robin Williams plays a comedian and talk show host who plunges into the presidential campaign, telling truths the timid politicians dare not utter. Not really. This would-be satire, written and directed by Barry Levinson, is hectic and tired, with too many plots and too few sharp insights. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'MARIE ANTOINETTE' (PG-13, 123 minutes) In this elaborate, bittersweet confection, Sofia Coppola imagines the last pre-revolutionary queen of France (played with wit and charm by Kirsten Dunst) as a bored, pleasure-seeking teenager trapped in a world of artifice and rigid protocol. Dreamy and decadent, the film is also touching, funny and bracingly modern. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'NIGHT AT THE MUSEUM' (PG, 108 minutes) In this chaotic, overstuffed family comedy, Ben Stiller is a night watchman at the American Museum of Natural History, where the exhibits come to life at night and attack him and one another. This computerized spectacle spares no expense, but the storytelling is weak, and the hit-or-miss jokes miss more than hit. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'NOTES ON A SCANDAL' (R, 92 minutes) Judi Dench and Cate Blanchett play a misogynistic game of cat and mouse from which no one emerges unscathed, including the audience. Adapted by Patrick Marber from a novel by Zoë Heller and directed by Richard Eyre. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'PAN'S LABYRINTH' (R, 119 minutes, in Spanish) Guillermo del Toro's tale of a young girl's ordeal in post-Civil War fascist Spain is either a fairy tale in the guise of a political allegory or vice versa. In either case it is a moving, enchanting, strange and humane example of popular art at its very best. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE PAINTED VEIL' (PG-13, 125 minutes) Nicely directed by John Curran, this version of the W. Somerset Maugham novel draws you in by turning a distaff bildungsroman into a fine romance with Naomi Watts and Edward Norton. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'PERFUME: THE STORY OF A MURDERER' (R, 147 minutes) There's no other way to say it: Tom Tykwer's excruciatingly literal-minded adaptation of the best-selling novel about an 18th-century serial killer with an acute sense of smell is a real stinker. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE PURSUIT OF HAPPYNESS' (PG-13, 117 minutes) How you respond to this fairy tale in realist drag may depend on whether you find Will Smith's performances so overwhelmingly winning that you buy the idea that poverty is a function of bad luck and bad choices, and success the result of heroic toil and dreams. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'THE QUEEN' (PG-13, 103 minutes) Directed by Stephen Frears from a very smart script by Peter Morgan, and starring a magnificent Helen Mirren in the title role, ''The Queen'' pries open a window in the House of Windsor around the time of the death of Diana, Princess of Wales, blending fact with fiction. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'ROCKY BALBOA' (PG, 102 minutes) Surprisingly, the sixth installment of this franchise is no embarrassment. Like its forerunners, it goes the distance almost in spite of itself. It's all heart and no credibility, except as a raw-boned fable. From the very beginning, Rocky Balboa was about as lifelike a character as Popeye pumped up with spinach. But that may be the point of a series that peddles the notion that if you dream it hard enough, you can live it. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE TIGER AND THE SNOW' (No rating, 115 minutes, in Arabic, English and Italian) War may be hell, but for Roberto Benigni it's just another romantic comedy waiting to be filmed. This time that gnomic Italian superstar is a poetry professor who must pose as a Red Cross surgeon to rescue his beloved from a Baghdad hospital. But this contrived setup is merely an excuse for Mr. Benigni to climb onto a camel, blunder into a minefield and confront the American military; to Mr. Benigni, war is simply another stage for his outlandish ego. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'UNACCOMPANIED MINORS' (PG, 89 minutes) The title doubles as an advisory. Your kids may like it; pick them up when it's over. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'VENUS' (R, 91 minutes) A modest, diverting, touching tale of a young woman who attracts the interest -- avuncular and also erotic -- of an aging actor, played with effortless aplomb by the great Peter O'Toole. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'VOLVER' (R, 121 minutes, in Spanish) Another keeper from Pedro Almodóvar, with Penélope Cruz -- as a resilient widow -- in her best role to date. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'WE ARE MARSHALL' (PG, 128 minutes) This fact-based story of a West Virginia college town recovering from the death of its entire football team in a 1970 plane crash is a stiff, manipulative dud that gets wrong everything ''Friday Night Lights'' got right. Matthew McConaughey hams it up as the college's goofy new coach, who whips the replacement team into decent shape. (Holden)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>AN ARTIST AND A GAMBLER: ROBERT ALTMAN REMEMBERED (Today, and Sunday through Thursday) IFC Center's tribute to Altman, the iconoclastic filmmaker who died in November at 81, begins today. This weekend's features are ''M*A*S*H'' (1970), the original antiwar comedy, and ''Short Cuts'' (1993), Altman's ensemble drama about life in Los Angeles. The other more than two dozen features in the retrospective will include ''McCabe &amp; Mrs. Miller'' (1971), ''The Player'' (1992), ''Nashville'' (1975) and ''That Cold Day in the Park'' (1969). (Through Jan. 23.) At 323 Avenue of the Americas, at West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 924-7771, movietickets.com; $10.75. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>CRITICS CHOICE: GREAT DOCUMENTARIES (Tomorrow and Sunday) The Museum of the Moving Image is sponsoring its eighth annual New York Film Critics Circle series, beginning tomorrow. This weekend's features, chosen by member critics, are ''In the Year of the Pig'' (1968-69), a critique of the Vietnam War, introduced by David Fear; the newly excavated ''Winter Soldier'' (1972), introduced by Michael Atkinson; Frederick Wiseman's ''Hospital'' (1970), introduced by Peter Rainer; and Terry Zwigoff's ''Crumb'' (1994), about the underground comics artist R. Crumb, introduced by John Anderson. (Through Feb. 28.) At 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718) 784-0077, movingimage.us; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>ESSENTIALLY WOODY (Today through Thursday) Film Forum's 28-film retrospective of Woody Allen's work continues this weekend with three films. ''Manhattan'' (1979), Mr. Allen's love letter to the city, Gershwin and teenage girls, plays today and tomorrow. ''Take the Money and Run'' (1969), in which an inept bank robber has trouble spelling ''gun,'' and the comic redubbing experiment ''What's Up, Tiger Lily?'' (1966) are the double feature for Sunday and Monday. At 209 West Houston Street, west of Avenue of the Americas, South Village, (212) 727-8110, filmforum.org; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK JEWISH FILM FESTIVAL (Wednesday and Thursday) This 16th annual event is sponsored by the Jewish Museum and the Film Society of Lincoln Center. It begins on Wednesday with a program that includes two United States premieres of full-length features: Christian Delage's ''Nuremberg: The Nazis Facing Their Crimes'' (2005), a French documentary narrated by Christopher Plummer; and ''My Mexican Shivah''(2006), Alejandro Springall's comedy about a patriarch's death. (Through Jan. 25.) Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5600, thejewishmuseum.org or filmlinc.com; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>FRANZ WAXMAN: MUSIC FOR THE CINEMA (Today through Monday, and Wednesday and Thursday) The Museum of Modern Art is honoring Waxman (1906-67), the German composer, with a 21-film retrospective. This weekend's films include ''The Spirit of St. Louis'' (1957), starring Jimmy Stewart as the aviator Charles Lindbergh; ''Objective Burma!'' (1945), a World War II adventure with Errol Flynn; and the classic ''Sunset Blvd.'' (1950), for which Waxman won his second Oscar. Roy and Niuta Titus Theaters, (212) 708-9400, moma.org; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>BRYAN ADAMS (Thursday) In the 1980s this Canadian rocker became an MTV regular by expertly playing an inoffensive rebel: he wore a leather jacket and kept his square jaw in a scowl, but sang chrome-plated guitar anthems that never hid their sentimentality. In time the sentimentality overtook the guitar-rock, as in the 1991 megahit ''(Everything I Do) I Do It for You,'' but that never hurt anyone's popularity. Here Mr. Adams plays a rare concert in New York. At 8 p.m., Beacon Theater, 2124 Broadway, at 74th Street, (212) 496-7070 or (212) 307-7171; sold out. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>BABY DAYLINER (Tonight) Ethan Marunas, the pale, sometimes pompadoured crooner who performs as Baby Dayliner, is a throwback to a few different strains of '80s pop: murmuring about being a ''star without a movie'' over brittle electronic beats, he joins the blue-eyed soul of Joe Jackson, the fragility of Morrissey and the arty synth-disco of New Order and Human League. With the Pierces and Five O'Clock Heroes. At 9:30, Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700, mercuryloungenyc.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BILAL (Thursday) Bilal has huge ambitions, spanning jazz and soul, funk and gospel, hip-hop and pop. Even when his material doesn't live up to those ambitions, he has musicality to spare. At 9 p.m., S.O.B.'s, 204 Varick Street, at Houston Street, South Village, (212) 243-4940, sobs.com; $26 in advance, $28 at the door. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>* BLACK DICE, SIGHTINGS, EXCEPTER (Tomorrow) Noise, noise, glorious New York noise. Black Dice, from Brooklyn, is a big player in the international avant-rock scene, and has remained vital by staying truly experimental: whether playing spacey, hokey psychedelia or alien-invasion squalls of feedback, the band throws itself deeply into its every unpredictable turn. Sightings sticks to guitars and drums for its nightmarish din, and Excepter's songs, with gurgling, irregular electronic blips, evoke the aimless flailings of a damaged robot. At 9 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; $13 in advance, $15 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>JAMES COTTON (Thursday) Playing in Muddy Waters's bands in the 1950s, James Cotton helped define modern blues harmonica with his moaning, wrenching phrases and his train-whistle wails. Recent albums with the younger players who studied him prove that he can still rip into a blues. At 8 p.m., B. B. King Blues Club and Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $25 in advance, $29 at the door. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>FIERY FURNACES (Tonight) In a smart scramble of eras and attitudes, the Fiery Furnaces back flippantly surreal lyrics with blues riffs, teetering analog synthesizers, parlor piano and punky noise, coming up with a 21st-century urban skiffle. With Emergency Party, and Michael Mayham and the Mike. At 9, Northsix, 66 North Sixth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 599-5103, northsix.com; $15. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>TIM FITE, O'DEATH (Tomorrow) Tim Fite's songs about ''kicking every can in New York City'' are booby-trapped with quick changes from clean country-pop to corrosive punk. O'Death draws from the starkness and spiritual purity of Appalachian folk, the menace of punk and the rowdy theatricality of Tom Waits, jumbling sacred and profane. At 8 p.m., Union Hall, 702 Union Street, at Fifth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 638-4400, unionhallny.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PAUL GREEN SCHOOL OF ROCK MUSIC (Tomorrow and Sunday) As seen in the documentary ''Rock School,'' Mr. Green offers an extensive curriculum at his Philadelphia school, teaching youngsters the rock 'n' roll canon, as well as the fundamentals of power chords and budda-budda bass lines. Here his students offer ''The Folk Show.'' At 2:30 p.m., Rebel, 251 West 30th Street, Manhattan, (212) 695-2747, rebelnyc.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>EMILY HAINES AND THE SOFT SKELETON (Tuesday) In her regular band, Metric, Ms. Haines plays a kind of dance-floor defector, singing moodily over bouncy electronic beats and sharp new-wave guitars. On her own, this Canandian songwriter is as far away from the disco ball as she could be, with dark and rich piano ballads about looking for a cure for the ''lonesome lows.'' For her tour, the Canadian neo-surrealist filmmaker Guy Maddin has put together montages of his work set to her songs. With the Tall Firs. At 7 p.m., Hiro Ballroom, 371 West 16th Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-0212, bowerypresents.com; $19.50 in advance, $22 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* 'HIGH SCHOOL MUSICAL: THE CONCERT' (Monday) Cynical parents might compare it to the Monkees. But what in the world could be wrong with ''I'm a Believer''? Or, for that matter, with ''Breaking Free,'' the PG-rated climax from ''High School Musical,'' the Disney Channel phenomenon whose soundtrack was the best-selling album of 2006? Performing the songs from this tween ''Grease,'' to the accompaniment of thousands of squeals, will be the cast of the movie, or at least most of it: Zac Efron, who played the heartthrob, Troy, is replaced here by Drew Seeley, who supplied many of Troy's vocals on the soundtrack. At 7 p.m., Continental Airlines Arena, East Rutherford, N.J., (201) 935-3900, meadowlands.com; $36.50 to $56.50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>IZZYS (Tomorrow) With a repertory of lean, uncomplicated blues-boogies, this New York band worships at the twin retro-rock altars of the Rolling Stones and the Stooges (with maybe a little Gram Parsons country thrown in as well). At 11 p.m., Lakeside Lounge, 162 Avenue B, between 10th and 11th Streets, East Village, (212) 529-8463, lakesidelounge.com; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DAYNA KURTZ (Tuesday and Wednesday) That's not weariness in the plain alto of Dayna Kurtz, a singer-songwriter from Brooklyn skilled at conveying the sting of heartbreak. It's vulnerability, which means that no matter how many times a relationship collapses, she is still hopeful when asking her lover to kiss her ''like a stranger.'' With Kris Delmhorst. At 8 p.m., Union Hall, 702 Union Street, at Fifth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 638-4400, unionhallny.com; $12. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LYRICS AND LYRICISTS (Tomorrow through Monday) The 37th season of the 92nd Street Y's American Songbook series begins with a tribute to Rosemary Clooney that focuses on the writers behind her repertory, including William Saroyan (the co-writer of ''Come On-a My House''), Tom Adair and Billie Holiday. The artistic director and host is Deborah Grace Winer, and the players include James Naughton, John Pizzarelli, Paul West and Karen Ziemba; Debby Boone, Ms. Clooney's daughter-in-law, will appear on Sunday and Monday. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Sunday at 3 and 8 p.m., and Monday at 2 and 8 p.m., 92nd Street Y, 1395 Lexington Avenue, (212) 415-5500, 92y.org; $50 and $60. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* MAN MAN (Tonight) Man Man, from Philadelphia, follows the expressive gutter cabaret of Tom Waits into a kinetic chaos that has more than a little Captain Beefheart in it. With Mixel Pixel and Plastic Little. At 9, Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; $14. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MOUTHUS (Tonight) A fearsome and unpredictable noise-rock duo from Brooklyn, Mouthus delves into guttural depths of vocals and guitar, seldom completing a show without repeatedly knocking over some large instrument or fixture. With Axolotl, Wiseblood, Watersports and Max Cloud. At 9, Silent Barn, 15 Wyckoff Avenue, at Hancock Street, Bushwick, Brooklyn, toddpnyc.com; $7. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ANDERS PARKER, JENNIFER O'CONNOR (Wednesday) Mr. Parker, who led the band Varnaline, immerses his songs in the stoic drama of country and folk music, resulting in a melancholy that is sometimes indistinguishable from cynicism. (''The hours I've wasted here I could have wasted anywhere.'') He begins a four-week Wednesday residency at the Living Room. Ms. O'Connor's portraits of the lovelorn are dry but not unsympathetic: ''Maybe she's on her lunch break thinking of you.'' At 9 p.m., 154 Ludlow Street, near Stanton Street, Lower East Side, (212) 533-7235, livingroomny.com; $8. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>RON SEXSMITH (Tuesday) Ron Sexsmith seems self-effacing and hesitant at first, with a voice that sidles up to notes like a wallflower trying to slip into a party unnoticed. But behind the outward modesty is a craftsman who stubborn upholds the verities of 1960s songwriting, placing supple melodies atop unexpected harmonies and offering wistful regret and consolation in equal parts. With Kim Taylor. At 8:30 p.m., Maxwell's, 1039 Washington Street, Hoboken, N.J., (201) 653-1703, maxwellsnj.com; $12. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>SONIC BOOM (Monday and Tuesday) In the 1980s, Peter Kember, a k a Sonic Boom, was a member of Spacemen 3, an influential British band that found a twilight zone somewhere between jangly garage-rock and the druggy, pulsating minimalism of the Velvet Underground. Later, with Experimental Audio Research, he explored ever purer forms of drone. Here Mr. Kember acts as autobiographical D.J., spinning records that inspired him ''from the '30s through the '90s.'' At 10 p.m., Club Midway, 25 Avenue B, at Second Street, East Village, (212) 253-2595, clubmidway.com; $10 in advance, $12 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>SOUTHSIDE JOHNNY AND THE ASBURY JUKES (Tonight and tomorrow night) While his friend Bruce Springsteen left the Jersey Shore behind and went on to write all-American anthems and parables, Southside Johnny Lyon stuck to the old bar-band basics: rolling R &amp; B vamps and raspy-voiced, good-natured soul plaints, complete with horn section. At 8, B. B. King Blues Club and Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $35. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>WAR (Tuesday) Only one original member, the keyboardist Lonnie Jordan, remains in this pioneering Latin-funk band, which in the 1970s did nearly as much as Santana to integrate Latin percussion and rock 'n' roll. The other four surviving players are in another touring group, the Lowrider Band. What separates them is a lawsuit. At 8 p.m., B. B. King Blues Club and Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $30 in advance, $32 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>CARL ALLEN AND NEW SPIRIT (Tonight and tomorrow night) The propulsive drummer Carl Allen leads a hard-bop ensemble seasoned with gospel harmonies and stocked with heavy hitters: Vincent Herring on alto saxophone, Christian McBride on bass and Aaron Goldberg on piano. At 8, 10 and midnight, Sweet Rhythm, 88 Seventh Avenue South, at Bleecker Street, West Village, (212) 255-3626, sweetrhythmny.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>* HAN BENNINK AND FRIENDS (Tuesday and Wednesday) Mr. Bennink plays the drums with the unrestrained glee of a 4-year-old, but his antics do nothing to hinder his uplifting sense of swing. Here this Dutch master collaborates with a cadre of American modernists, like the trumpeter Dave Douglas, the pianist Anthony Coleman, the tenor saxophonist Ellery Eskelin and the tuba player Marcus Rojas. At 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501; cover, $15; $12 in advance. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* TERENCE BLANCHARD (Thursday) As a trumpeter and composer, Mr. Blanchard favors a sleek post-bop sound informed by myriad contemporary sources. His excellent working band -- with the saxophonist Brice Winston, the pianist Aaron Parks, the bassist Derrick Hodge and the drummer Kendrick Scott -- will play a range of original music, including Mr. Blanchard's haunting soundtrack to the Spike Lee documentary ''When the Levees Broke.'' At 9:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 539-8778, joespub.com; cover, $20, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JANE IRA BLOOM (Tomorrow) Elaborating on material from her latest album, ''Like Silver, Like Song'' (ArtistShare), Ms. Bloom plays soprano saxophone and electronics in a solid working band with Dawn Clement on keyboards, Mark Helias on bass and Matt Wilson on drums. At 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CECIL BRIDGEWATER (Tomorrow) Mr. Bridgewater, an accomplished trumpeter, balances lyricism and aggression in a trio with the bassist Kenny Davis and the drummer Alvin Atkinson. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Sistas' Place, 456 Nostrand Avenue, at Jefferson Avenue, Bedford-Stuyvesant, Brooklyn, (718) 398-1766, sistasplace.org; $25 in advance, $30 at the door. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN JAZZ UNDERGROUND (Thursday) The Brooklyn Jazz Underground is a coalition of artists united by aesthetics as well as geography; its launch party, so to speak, spans four nights at Smalls next week. Opening night will include bands led by the pianist Benny Lackner, the trumpeter Shane Endsley and the violinist and violist Tanya Kalmanovitch. (Through Jan. 14.) At 8:30, 10 and 11:30 p.m., Smalls, 183 West 10th Street, West Village, (212) 675-7369, brooklynjazz.org; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE COLEMAN AND FIVE ELEMENTS (Sunday and Thursday) Mr. Coleman's alto saxophone cuts cleanly through the angular free-funk of his signature ensemble, which includes the trumpeter Jonathan Finlayson, the trombonist Tim Albright, the vocalist Jen Shyu, the bassist Thomas Morgan and the drummer Tyshawn Sorey. At 8 and 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>THE CRUSADERS (Tuesday through Thursday) This crossover soul-jazz outfit, led by the keyboardist Joe Sample, has gone through multiple revisions since its heyday in the 1970s. Here the lineup features one other founding member, the saxophonist Wilton Felder, and includes Nils Landgren on trombone; Ray Parker Jr. on guitar; Nicklas Sample, Joe Sample's son, on bass; and Steve Gadd on drums. (Through Jan. 14.) At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $45 at tables, $30 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LUCIEN DUBUIS TRIO WITH MARC RIBOT (Tomorrow) The Swiss-born alto saxophonist and clarinetist Lucien Dubuis aims for the ragged thrust of a punk band with his trio, which features Roman Nowka on bass and Lionel Friedli on drums. Mr. Ribot, as a guest guitarist, brings raw energy as well as seasoned artistry. At 10 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DOMINIQUE EADE AND RACHEL CASWELL (Wednesday) Ms. Eade weighs a chanteuse's coolness against a jazz musician's exploratory instinct, as she will demonstrate in dialogue with the guitarist Brad Shepik and the bassist Ben Street. Ms. Caswell, who hails from a similar school of jazz singing, will seek to hold her own. At 8:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* FLY (Tuesday through Thursday) The tenor saxophonist Mark Turner, the bassist Larry Grenadier and the drummer Jeff Ballard make up this superb trio, which eschews the usual horn-plus-rhythm hierarchy in the service of an elastic group ideal. (Through Jan. 14.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JAZZ TRIBUTE TO FRANK SINATRA (Tonight and tomorrow night) A few good things promise to lift this salute above the humdrum, like the veteran trombonist Eddie Bert, the versatile guitarist Howard Alden and the precocious tenor saxophonist Tommy Morimoto. At 9 and 11, Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* NANCY KING (Wednesday) Ms. King is a musician's singer, and until recently her reputation barely extended beyond a circle of insiders. Since the release of ''Live at Jazz Standard'' (Max Jazz) last year, she has been more widely celebrated; she returns to that setting next week with a backing trio led by the pianist Geoffrey Keezer. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $30. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LOGN (Monday) This upstart Danish quartet practices a sort of exuberant avant-gardism derived partly from the downtown scene; its members are the multireedist Jacob Danielsen, the guitarist Kasper Bai, the pianist Kasper Bjerg and the drummer Soren Mehlsen. At 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MIYA MASAOKA, SYLVIE COURVOISIER AND OKKYUNG LEE (Monday) Ms. Masaoka extracts a boldly textural sound from the koto, a Japanese zither; Ms. Lee and Ms. Courvoisier do much the same on their Western instruments, a cello and a piano. At 10 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* JASON MORAN AND THE BANDWAGON (Wednesday and Thursday) Jason Moran is a bright pianist who favors jagged and delirious polyphony; his uncommonly cohesive group, the Bandwagon, features the earthy yet slippery rhythm section of Tarus Mateen, bassist, and Nasheet Waits, drummer. (Through Jan. 13.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum at tables. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MOUTIN REUNION QUARTET (Thursday) The brothers François and Louis Moutin, a bassist and a drummer, lead this dynamic trans-Atlantic post-bop ensemble; the other half consists of the tenor saxophonist Rick Margitza and the pianist Pierre de Bethmann. At 8 and 10 p.m., Sweet Rhythm, 88 Seventh Avenue South, at Bleecker Street, West Village, (212) 255-3626, sweetrhythmny.com; cover, $15, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LEWIS NASH QUINTET (Tuesday through Thursday) An engaging and subtle drummer who brings a crisp swing to any setting, Lewis Nash leads a band with Jeremy Pelt on trumpet, Jimmy Greene on saxophones, Renee Rosnes on piano and Peter Washington on bass. (Through Jan. 14.) At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>NIGHT OF THE COOKERS 2007 (Tonight and tomorrow night) Blazing hard bop, in no uncertain terms: the tenor saxophonist Eric Alexander presides, but just as much heat will be generated by his fellow tenor George Coleman, the trumpeters Jim Rotondi and Jeremy Pelt, and the pianist Harold Mabern. At 8, 10 and 11:30, Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, (212) 864-6662, smokejazz.com; cover, $30. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* NYC WINTER JAZZFEST (Wednesday) The Knitting Factory commits all three of its floors to jazz during this sprawling one-night festival, which will feature 17 different bands. Among the highlights are groups led by the alto saxophonists Rudresh Mahanthappa and Steve Lehman, the trumpeter Maurice Brown and the guitarists Liberty Ellman and Joel Harrison. From 6 p.m. to 1 a.m. at the Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3132, knittingfactory.com; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GRETCHEN PARLATO (Tonight and Thursday) Ms. Parlato is a cosmopolitan singer with a lilting tone but sharp musical instincts; her rapport with the guitarist Lionel Loueke, with whom she performs in a duo on Thursday, is ocean-deep. Opening on Thursday is the Polish vocalist Aga Zaryan. Tonight at 6, 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; no cover. Thursday at 7 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 539-8778, joespub.com; cover, $15, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>J. D. PARRAN (Wednesday) Mr. Parran plays alto clarinet, soprano saxophone, bamboo flute and contrabass clarinet on the recent album ''Omegathorp: Living City'' (Y'All), which also features the sitar playing of Mark Deutsch, the vocals of Thomas Buckner, the cello work of David Darling and the percussion of Kevin Norton. There will be no sitar in the mix next week, but the ensemble's texture-oriented approach should hardly be hindered. At 8 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>NICHOLAS PAYTON QUARTET (Wednesday and Thursday) Nicholas Payton, an abundantly gifted trumpeter, has recently oscillated between hard bop and electric fusion, producing good results in both areas. The group he leads here could move in any direction he chooses. (Through Jan. 14.) At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $35, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LONNIE PLAXICO GROUP (Tonight) The bassist and composer Lonnie Plaxico pursues a dynamic brand of contemporary fusion in this ensemble, with Jeff Hermanson on trumpet, Mike Mcginnis on saxophones, Helen Sung on piano and organ and Kenny Grohowski on drums. At 10 and 11, the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* DIZZY REECE QUARTET (Tonight) In the 1950s and '60s, Dizzy Reece was one of the sharper hard-bop trumpeters on the scene; his fortunes since then have been uneven, and these days he performs infrequently. His rhythm section here consists of Mike Longo on piano, Lee Hudson on bass and James Worth on drums. At 7, Rubin Museum of Art, 150 West 17th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 620-5000, Ext. 344, rmanyc.org; $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SHAKERS N' BAKERS (Tuesday) The so-called vision songs of 19th-century Shaker women provide a distinctive repertory for this ensemble, which includes the vocalists Mary LaRose and Miles Griffith, the saxophonist Jeff Lederer, the keyboardist Jamie Saft, the bassist Chris Lightcap and the drummer Allison Miller. At 9 p.m., BAMCafé, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100, bam.org; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* SIM FACULTY CONCERT (Thursday) The School for Improvised Music is a nonprofit enterprise in which the instructors are adventurous musicians; among them are the trumpeter Ralph Alessi, the saxophonists Peter Epstein and Ravi Coltrane, the pianist Andy Milne, the bassist Mark Helias and the drummer Tom Rainey. At 8 p.m., Center for Improvisational Music, 295 Douglass Street, between Third and Fourth Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (212) 631-5882, schoolforimprov.org; $12; $8 for students. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MARVIN STAMM QUARTET (Wednesday) The veteran big band and studio trumpeter Marvin Stamm has focused fruitfully in recent years on a solo career, and on a good working quartet with the drummer Ed Soph, the bassist Rufus Reid and the pianist Bill Mays. At 8 and 9:45 p.m., Kitano Hotel, 66 Park Avenue, at 38th Street, (212) 885-7119, kitano.com; no cover, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MICHAEL WEISS QUARTET (Thursday) Michael Weiss, a pianist with extensive sideman credits, brings sophistication and precision to this band, with Bob Sheppard on saxophones, Ugonna Okegwo on bass and Greg Hutchinson on drums. At 8 and 9:45 p.m., Kitano Hotel, 66 Park Avenue, at 38th Street, (212) 885-7119, kitano.com; no cover, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE WILSON QUARTET (Thursday) An alto saxophonist with a dry tone but a rounded sense of phrase, Steve Wilson leads a strong working band, with Bruce Barth on piano, Ed Howard on bass and Adam Cruz on drums. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>'THE FIRST EMPEROR' (Tonight and Tuesday) The excitement of a world premiere at the Metropolitan Opera, combined with widespread interest among the general public in the composer Tan Dun, who won an Oscar for his score to ''Crouching Tiger, Hidden Dragon,'' have resulted in a sold-out run for this opera. Alas, the story of Qin Shi Huang, the first emperor of China, who unified the country through brutality and conquest, is compelling, but Mr. Tan's ponderous score is a huge disappointment. There are gripping moments, especially some propulsive orchestra passages that incorporate Chinese instruments. But the opera's lyrical flights are slow-moving, ponderous and sometimes cloying. Mr. Tan has tried to meld Chinese melody and Italianate lyricism. His music, though, seems caught in some nowhere land between ''Crouching Tiger'' and Puccini's ''Turandot.'' Even the great Plácido Domingo, bravely taking on the challenging title role, cannot save the show. The colorful production is by the Chinese film director Zhang Yimou (''House of Flying Daggers''). Mr. Tan conducts. At 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; sold out. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'DIE FLEDERMAUS' (Tonight through Sunday) In its 59th season the Amato Opera continues to stage productions in its tiny quarters on the Bowery. Now offered is Strauss's merry ''Fledermaus,'' with a rotating cast. The quality often varies, but the spirit is usually there. Tonight and tomorrow night at 7:30, Sunday afternoon at 2:30, 319 Bowery, at Second Street, East Village, (212) 228-8200, amato.org; $35; $28 for students and 65+. (Vivien Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* 'I PURITANI' (Tomorrow and Thursday) The reason the Met dusted off its stodgy old 1976 production of this Bellini work, and the one compelling reason to see it, is Anna Netrebko. This glamorous, dusky-voiced Russian soprano makes an affecting and vocally lustrous Elvira, the daughter of a stern Puritan father during the English Civil War whose sanity slips away when she thinks her adored Arturo, a Royalist sympathizer, is unfaithful. Ms. Netrebko may not be a bel canto purist's ideal -- her execution of coloratura roulades is sometimes imprecise, and her diction could use more clarity -- but she sings excitingly and stops the show with her Act II mad scene. On the illness-plagued opening night last week, only the fine bass-baritone John Relyea, singing Elvira's kindly uncle despite grappling with remnants of bronchitis, was in the same dramatic class as the star. Patrick Summers conducts. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m., and Thursday at 7:30 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; sold out. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'LA TRAVIATA' (Wednesday) Franco Zeffirelli's overly plush and extravagant production returns to the Met's repertory with the excellent soprano Hei-Kyung Hong as Violetta. Joining this highly regarded artist as Alfredo is Wookyung Kim, a tenor from Ms. Hong's native South Korea making his Met debut. The American baritone Charles Taylor sings Germont. Carlo Rizzi conducts. At 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $15 to $175. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'DIE ZAUBERFLÖTE' (Tomorrow and Monday) This revival of Julie Taymor's production continues at the Metropolitan Opera, complete with the magical puppets and stage effects that made it an audience hit when it opened in 2004. Tomorrow Scott Bergeson conducts a cast that includes the fabulous German bass René Pape as Sarastro, with Erika Miklosa as Queen of the Night, Matthew Polenzani as Tamino, Rodion Pogossov as Papageno and Nicole Heaston as Pamina. On Monday Lisa Milne sings Pamina. Tomorrow at 8:30 p.m., Monday at 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $42 to $295 tickets remain tomorrow; $15 to $320 on Monday. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>AMERICAN SYMPHONY ORCHESTRA (Sunday) Leon Botstein has thought up another interesting afternoon, this time centering on César Franck and including both his famous D minor Symphony and pieces by three of his pupils: Ernest Chausson, Paul Dukas and Albéric Magnard. At 3 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $27 to $55. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>BARGEMUSIC (Tonight through Sunday) The guitarist Jorge Caballero presents a solo recital that includes, of all things, an arrangement of Dvorak's Ninth Symphony, as well as works by Poulenc, Milhaud, Turina and others. A Latinate theme continues in tomorrow and Sunday's program for clarinet trio, with Beethoven's Opus 38 trio balancing out works by Nino Rota, Paquito D'Rivera and Astor Piazzolla. Tonight and tomorrow night at 7:30, Sunday afternoon at 4, Fulton Ferry Landing next to the Brooklyn Bridge, Brooklyn, (718) 624-2083, bargemusic.org; $35; $20 for students; $30 for 65+, tonight only. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>CHAMBER MUSIC SOCIETY OF LINCOLN CENTER (Thursday) The double-bass and the double-bassist DaXun Zhang get something of a workout in a program that includes Rossini's Duetto in D for Cello and Bass, and Schubert's familiar ''Trout'' Quintet for piano and strings. At 6:45 p.m., Rose Studio, 165 West 65th Street, (212) 875-5788, chambermusicsociety.org; sold out. (Holland)</p>
        <p>CHIARA STRING QUARTET (Tuesday and Thursday) ''Mestizaje: Harmony of Differences'' is the title of the Chiara String Quartet's concert at Merkin Concert Hall on Thursday devoted to composers whose music spans two cultures, including Gabriela Lena Frank (Chiara has recorded her ''Leyendas: An Andean Walkabout'') and Zhou Long. This fine, Juilliard-trained quartet, which seeks new paths through the field of classical music, will also play at Rose Live Music in Brooklyn on Tuesday, with a program to be announced from the stage. Thursday at 8 p.m., Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, Manhattan, (212) 501-3330, ekcc.org; $25. Tuesday at 9 p.m., Rose Live Music, 345 Grand Street, between Marcy Avenue and Havemeyer Street, Williamsburg, (718) 599-0960; $5. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>COMPOSERS GUILD OF NEW JERSEY (Thursday) The formidable modernist composer Charles Wuorinen has had major productions and performances of large-scale works in New York in recent seasons, notably his opera ''Haroun and the Sea of Stories,'' given its premiere by City Opera, and his Piano Concerto No. 4, performed at Carnegie Hall by the pianist Peter Serkin and the Boston Symphony, conducted by James Levine. On Thursday the Composers Guild of New Jersey presents a program of recent chamber and vocal works by Mr. Wuorinen, including the New York premiere of ''Fenton Songs II,'' settings of poems by James Fenton on themes of war and political upheaval. The strong roster of performers include the soprano Lucy Shelton, the baritone Thomas Meglioranza, the pianist Alan Feinberg, the violinist Mark Steinberg and the cellist Nina Maria Lee. At 8 p.m., Christ and St. Stephen's Episcopal Church, 120 West 69th Street, Manhattan, (212) 787-2755, cgnj.org; free. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* EIGHTH BLACKBIRD (Thursday) This inventive and energetic young new-music ensemble from Chicago has built its audience with eclectic programming and commissioning. They have also impressed listeners by playing complex scores by memory, a feat rarely seen in ensemble concerts with much more familiar music. The program includes works by Steve Mackey, Jennifer Higdon, Gordon Fitzell and David M. Gordon. At 8 p.m., the Kitchen, 512 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 255-5793, thekitchen.org; $10. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>JUPITER SYMPHONY CHAMBER PLAYERS (Monday) The bassoonist Frank Morelli is the guest of this feisty chamber ensemble in a woodwind-dominated program that includes arrangements of arias by Rossini and Mozart, an unfinished wind quintet by Schubert, Gounod's ''Petite Symphonie'' and an Andante by Reicha. At 2 and 7:30 p.m., Good Shepherd-Faith Presbyterian Church, 152 West 66th Street, Manhattan, (212) 799-1259, jupitersymphony.com; $10 to $25. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* 'MOSTLY OPERETTA' (Wednesday and Thursday) To celebrate a neglected genre that once held Europe in thrall and spawned the Broadway musical, the Austrian Cultural Forum is starting a two-week festival on Wednesday with a program of Emmerich Kalman, Oscar Straus and Franz Lehar, accompanied by visuals by the Austrian artist Victoria Coeln. Kalman and Lehar both wrote for Marta Eggerth, a major stage and screen star from the 1930s who has retained a solid vocal technique into her ninth decade, and gave several sold-out cabaret evenings at Café Sabarsky last year to prove it. On Thursday she will talk about operetta style and demonstrate it with some singing of her own; it's worth hearing. Wednesday at 8 p.m., Thursday at 7 p.m., 11 East 52nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 319-5300, acfny.org; free, but reservations are required. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>MY LORD CHAMBERLAIN'S CONSORT (Sunday) This early-music group was formed in 1997 to present a complete performance of John Dowland's ''First Book of Songs or Ayres.'' Here they will perform four centuries of English carols arranged for lutes, harps, voices and viol. At 3 p.m., Madison Avenue Presbyterian Church, at 73rd Street, (212) 288-8920, mapc.com; $15; $10 for students and 65+. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK GILBERT AND SULLIVAN PLAYERS (Tonight through Sunday, Tuesday and Thursday) ''The Yeoman of the Guard'' is perhaps Gilbert and Sullivan's most operatic work; ''Mikado,'' their most beloved; and ''The Rose of Persia,'' not really a Gilbert and Sullivan work at all, since the book (based on the ''Arabian Nights'') was written by Basil Hood some years after a quarrel ended Gilbert and Sullivan's collaboration. These three works constitute the 33rd season of New York's best-established G&amp;S troupe, led by the indomitable Albert Bergeret. ''Yeoman,'' tonight at 8 and Sunday afternoon at 3; ''Mikado,'' tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., and Tuesday at 7 p.m.; ''Rose,'' Thursday at 8 p.m., City Center, 131 West 55th Street, Manhattan, (212) 581-1212, nycitycenter.org; $40 to $96, 10 percent off $40 to $80 tickets for 65+. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC (Today, tomorrow and Tuesday) Old favorites are making return visits, and this means the pieces and the performers. Zubin Mehta conducts, and Pinchas Zukerman is the soloist in the Beethoven Violin Concerto and Stravinsky's ''Rite of Spring.'' Today at 11 a.m., tomorrow at 8 p.m. and Tuesday at 7:30 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nyphil.org; $33 to $101. (Holland)</p>
        <p>'ONE DOLLAR CONCERT AT CARNEGIE HALL' (Tomorrow) The pianist João Carlos Martins, a Brazilian who has made some provocative but powerful Bach recordings, has moved to the podium and is introducing himself to New York as a conductor in a bargain-priced concert meant also to call attention to the Amazon Region Protected Areas program and its efforts to preserve the Amazon rain forest. Mr. Martins will lead his 27-player Bachiana Chamber Orchestra in Bach's Orchestral Suite No. 1, Villa-Lobos's ''Preludio Bachiana'' and the premiere of ''Amazona'' by Stefan Meylaers. At 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $1. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* SEQUITUR (Monday) This first-rate new-music band turns its attention to contemporary Cuban works, with a program that includes scores by Tania León, Sergio Barroso, Keyla Orozco, Orlando Jacinto García and Jorge Martín. At 8 p.m., Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, Manhattan, (212) 501-3330, sequitur.org; $15; $10 for students and 65+. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>VOLKER VOGEL (Tuesday) The music of the Austrian composer and writer Ernst Krenek ranges from neo-romanticism to serialism. He wrote his tonal ''Reisebuch aus den Österreichischen Alpen,'' a cycle of 20 songs about the Austrian countryside, in 1929, after studying Schubert. Mr. Vogel, a tenor, sings the work as part of the Sound of Song series at the Austrian Cultural Forum, accompanied by the pianist Ann Beckman. At 8 p.m., 11 East 52nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 319-5300, acfny.org; free, but reservations are required. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>JEN ABRAMS AND JACKIE MOYNAHAN (Tomorrow) Ms. Abrams promises to peel back the facade of a New York City apartment building and gaze into the lives of four city dwellers. Ms. Moynahan will delve into desensitizing media images. At 8 p.m., Dixon Place, 258 Bowery, between Houston and Prince Streets, Lower East Side, (212) 219-0736, dixonplace.org; $12 or T.D.F.; $10 for students and 65+. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>LES BALLETS TROCKADERO DE MONTE CARLO (Tonight through Sunday afternoon) Lots of men can wear tutus; point shoes are another matter. If you want to see how real men pirouette, check out the Trocks, as they are called, performing classics like ''Swan Lake'' and creepy 20th-century ballets like ''The Cage.'' Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 3 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 3 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800, joyce.org; $44. (Claudia La Rocco)</p>
        <p>BEYOND THE SILK ROAD: TRADITIONAL AND NEW MIDDLE EASTERN DANCE (Sunday) Part of the 92nd Street Y's informal Sundays @ Three series, this program features dance and talk by choreographer-performers known as Altagracia, Ayshe, Blanca, Layla and Zenaide. At 3 p.m., 92nd Street Y Harkness Dance Center, 1395 Lexington Avenue, (212) 415-5500; $10. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CLARE BYRNE DANCE (Thursday) Ms. Byrne, a nicely quirky longtime presence in New York modern dance, describes her ''Rounds, the First Last Dance, or the Last First Dance, or an Ordination'' as calling up ''the doing-ness of dance. Uh-oh. (Through Jan. 14.) At 8 p.m., Dance New Amsterdam, 280 Broadway, at Chambers Street, TriBeCa, (212) 279-4200, ticketcentral.com; $20. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Complexions Contemporary Ballet (Tuesday through Thursday) This company, founded in 1994 by Dwight Rhoden and Desmond Richardson, is notable for its wonderful dancers and, often, less-than-wonderful choreography. But this season looks promising, with a work by Mr. Richardson to the music of Marvin Gaye; new pieces by Nicolo Fonte and Jodie Gates; and a solo for Mr. Richardson -- one of dance's true stars -- by Taye Diggs. Yes, that Taye Diggs. Tuesday and Wednesday at 7.30 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800, joyce.org; $42; $32 for Joyce members. (Roslyn Sulcas)</p>
        <p>* DANCE ON CAMERA FESTIVAL (Tonight through Sunday, and Tuesday and Wednesday) Presented by the Dance Film Association and the Film Society of Lincoln Center, this festival ranges more widely than ever, with nine programs of dance created for the camera, documentaries and archival compilations. Today at 1, 3:30, 6:15 and 8:30 p.m.; tomorrow at 1, 3:30, 6 and 8:30 p.m.; Sunday at 1, 4 and 7 p.m. Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center; $10; $5 for 65+ and children 6 through 12. Other programs, at other sites, include a retrospective of work by Elaine Summers and discussions on editing and creating dance with a narrative. (212) 496-3809, dancefilms.org. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>COMPANY EAST (Tonight through Sunday, and Thursday) Hiroshi Jin's Company East makes its American debut in a dance-theater production of ''Medea'' that incorporates elements of Noh theater, Western modern dance and karate stances. (Through Jan. 14.) Tonight and tomorrow and Thursday nights at 7:30, Sunday at 2:30 and 7:30 p.m., La MaMa E.T.C., 74A East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 475-7710, lamama.org; $20; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>KELLEY DONOVAN &amp; DANCERS (Tonight and tomorrow) The company will perform ''It's All Forgotten Now,'' created by Ms. Donovan, a Boston-based choreographer with an interest in exploring the initiation of movement as well as abrupt shifts in dynamics and weight. Tonight at 9, tomorrow night at 8, Merce Cunningham Studio, 55 Bethune Street, at Washington Street, West Village, (781) 420-3893; $20; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>'GENE POOL' (Tonight through Sunday) This showcase features dances by B. J. Sullivan, Nia Love, Janessa Clark and Shelley Poovey. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 3 p.m., Dance New Amsterdam, 280 Broadway, at Chambers Street, TriBeCa, (212) 279-4200, ticketcentral.com; $17. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>JEAN ISAACS SAN DIEGO DANCE THEATER (Thursday) This program includes a new piece by Jeffrey Gerodias, a former Alvin Ailey dancer, and four quartets to music by Steve Reich. (Through Jan. 13.) At 8:30 p.m., Danspace Project, St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194, danspaceproject.org; $20; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Movement Research at the Judson Church (Monday) Three or four choreographers show new work each week during this series, which aims to provide an environment for works in progress. Next week the choreographers are Levi Gonzalez, Lyndsey Karr and Sakura Shimada. At 8 p.m., Judson Memorial Church, 55 Washington Square South, Greenwich Village, movementresearch.org; free. (Sulcas)</p>
        <p>* NEW YORK CITY BALLET (Tonight through Sunday, and Tuesday through Thursday) The company director, Peter Martins, has combined the sleekness of 21st-century ballet dancing with elements of the 19th-century classic in this staging of ''The Sleeping Beauty.'' This production also offers a chance to savor familiar favorites and unfamiliars in new roles. Tonight there will be debuts in the leading roles: Prince Désiré (Sébastien Marcovici), Aurora (Yvonne Borree), the Lilac Fairy (Sara Mearns) and the evil Carabosse (a vivid Melissa Barak). The cast will return on Sunday afternoon. The ballet's lead roles will also be danced by Wendy Whelan, Jennie Somogyi, Jenifer Ringer, Philip Neal, Teresa Reichlen and others. Tonight and Thursday night at 8, tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 3 p.m., Tuesday and Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 870-5570, nycballet.com; $20 to $95. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>SLAMFEST/KARL ANDERSON (Tonight and tomorrow night) Mr. Anderson's wild imagination gives much of his work the quality of something uncorked from a genie's bottle. At 8, Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, between Houston and Prince Streets, (212) 334-7479; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* American Museum of Natural History: 'GOLD,' through Aug. 19. Having delved into pearls, diamonds and amber, the museum applies its time-tested show-and-tell formula to gold. An astounding array of art, artifacts and natural samples, larded with fascinating facts and tales, ranges from prehistoric times to the present. Stops along the way include pre-Columbian empires, sunken treasure, Bangladesh dowry rituals and the moon landing. It turns out that gold comes from the earth in forms as beautiful as anything man has thought to do with it. Central Park West and 79th Street, (212) 769-5100, amnh.org. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>Cooper-Hewitt National Design Museum: 'DESIGN LIFE NOW: NATIONAL DESIGN TRIENNIAL 2006,' through July 29. This ambitious show illuminates the volatile, contradictory and ever-expanding field of design, but fails to call it to order. The inclusions cover medical innovation, military hardware, completely frivolous reiterations of received ideas, sundry Web sites and magazines, haute couture, architecture and more varieties of recycling than you can easily count. The show coalesces into deliberately orchestrated skirmishes between conflicting principles and entities: corporate and private, decorative and essential. 2 East 91st Street, (212) 849-8400, ndm.si.edu. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'Spanish Painting from El Greco to Picasso, TIME, TRUTH, AND HISTORY' through March 28. This show is carried along on its sheer star power and optical finesse. There are dozens of Goyas and Velázquezes and Zurbaráns and El Grecos and Riberas and Dalís and Picassos, many famous, many not. The big point is that Spanish art did not constantly reinvent itself over time. It was a bubble culture, sustained for centuries by its political and religious isolation and its national loner mindset. Velázquez's painting of a dwarf is alone worth crossing a continent to see. 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3500, guggenheim.org. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* THE METropolitan museum of art: 'GLITTER AND DOOM: GERMAN PORTRAITS FROM THE 1920s,' through Feb. 19. This show's 100 paintings and drawings are by 10 artists, among them George Grosz, Christian Schad, Rudolf Schlichter and Karl Hubbuch, and most conspicuously the unrelentingly savage Otto Dix and his magnificent other, Max Beckmann. In their works the Weimar Republic's porous worlds reassemble. We look into the faces of forward-looking museum directors and cabaret performers, society matrons and scarred war veterans, prostitutes and jaded aristocrats who were watching their world slide from one cataclysm to the next. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* THE MET: 'LOUIS COMFORT TIFFANY AND LAURELTON HALL -- AN ARTIST'S COUNTRY ESTATE,' through May 20. Laurelton Hall may have burned to the ground in 1957, but this exhibition does an excellent job of reassembling what remains of this extraordinary house-museum and its gardens, which Tiffany created for himself in the early 1900s. The Gilded Age opulence of the place, which occupied 580 acres overlooking Long Island Sound -- and of the Tiffany residences preceding it -- is conveyed most blatantly by the Temple-of-Dendur-size Daffodil Terrace, in wood, marble and glass. The main events are the glass windows, vases and lamps, where Tiffany's genius for color, love of the exotic and reverence for nature coalesce into an unforgettable mystical materialism. (See above.) (Smith)</p>
        <p>* MORGAN LIBRARY &amp; MUSEUM: 'SAUL STEINBERG: ILLUMINATIONS,' through March 4. Saul Steinberg's famous New Yorker cover positioning Manhattan at the center of the world may be his best-known drawing, but he took on everything with visual puns, manic doodles, grandiloquent calligraphy and other inspired artifice. As this show of more than 100 drawings, collages and constructions goes on, Steinberg's progress is evident: from relatively simple cartoons like ''Feet on Chair'' (1946), in which a fellow reading a newspaper parks his feet on the seat of an ornate Victorian monstrosity, to complex comments on the state of the world, like ''Street War (Cadavre Exquisis)'' (about 1972-74), derived from news clips of postcolonial troubles in the Middle East and Africa. The flow of his work amazes. 225 Madison Avenue, at 36th Street, (212) 685-0008, morganlibrary.org. (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>* Museum of Arts &amp; Design: 'Simply DROOG: 10 + 3 YEARS OF CREATING DISCUSSION AND INNOVATION,' through Jan. 14. Droog Design, a many-headed, loosely affiliated collective of usually, but not entirely, Dutch designers and architects has probably generated more discussion than innovation in its 13 years of existence. Presented in a free-flowing, Droog-designed layout, this show vigorously continues the process. It includes about 150 mostly domestic objects by scores of designers. Some are great, some are silly, some are Conceptual Art. But there is plenty to sink your teeth into, especially with help from the small free brochure containing label information and rationales for each item. 40 West 53rd Street, (212) 956-3535, madmuseum.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* MUSEUM OF THE CITY OF NEW YORK: 'A CITY ON PAPER: SAUL STEINBERG'S NEW YORK,' through March 25. A very lively adjunct to the Morgan show, this smaller display of some 40 drawings focuses on New York. An architect, Steinberg was particularly attracted to edifices like the Chrysler Building, which appears here looming majestically over brownstones and in another incarnation, from a perspective directly below it, looking positively squat. New York people, in Steinberg's eyes, could be monuments, too. You may think you know Steinberg's work, but these shows make it new. 1220 Fifth Avenue at 103rd Street, (212) 534-1672, mcny.org. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>Onassis Cultural Center: 'Athens-Sparta,' through May 12. Painted vases, pottery, sculptured steles, tiny carved figures, writings inscribed on stone and a selection of coins are among the nearly 300 objects in this show, whose first section begins with objects from both cities during the Geometric Period (1050-700 B.C.) Two other sections deal with the on-again, off-again relationship between the cities in the fifth century B.C. As society evolved from tribal to civil and felt the first stirrings of democracy during the Archaic Period (650-480 B.C.), rigid geometrical motifs were succeeded by more human forms, like the kouroi and korai, the stone or bronze statues, sometimes life-size, representing young men and women and symbolizing a new emphasis on the individual. On view from the sixth century B.C. are two small Attic representations of kourai, dressed statues of maidens, said to represent the Athenian aristocracy in rites celebrating the goddess Athena. Carved in stone, with long, braided hair (one is headless, but her braids are visible) and beautifully articulated drapery that clings to their bodies, they disappeared as a type after the Persian wars. 645 Fifth Avenue, near 52nd Street, (212) 486-4448. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center: 'DEFAMATION OF CHARACTER,'  through Jan. 15. With 46 artists and a mix of usual and unusual suspects, this exhibition forms a black hole in which Dada, Fluxus, Punk, Pop, Conceptual and Neo-Conceptual mingle like cackling furies along with Performance art, feminism, abject art and various forms of appropriation. While its dour tone becomes a bit relentless, it is admirably consistent and shows artists grappling with reality, which has its own kind of comfort. 22-25 Jackson Avenue, at 46th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 784-2084, ps1.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center: 'THE GOLD STANDARD,' through Jan 15. Gold is both color and subject in this glittering, pertinent show, installed on creamy yellow walls. Even though a generally dim view of contemporary society prevails, it is scary how good gold makes everything look. (See above.) (Smith)</p>
        <p>Whitney Museum of American Art: 'Kiki Smith: A Gathering, 1980-2005,' through Feb. 11. Many things fly and float here: men and women, harpies and angels, birds and beasts, toadstools and stars. And some things fall to earth, or rather to the museum's black stone floors, maybe to rise again, maybe not. The whole show, a midcareer retrospective, suggests a Victorian fairy tale, its tone at once light, grievous and dreamlike. But fanciful as it is, Ms. Smith's art is also deeply, corporeally realistic. It wears moral and mortal seriousness on its sleeve, if not tattooed on its wrist. It is about life and death, the essential things. 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676, whitney.org. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>American Folk Art Museum: 'A Deaf Artist in Early America: The Worlds of John Brewster Jr.,' Few Early American artists painted more incisive and empathetic likenesses than John Brewster Jr. (1766-1854), the subject of a fine traveling show at the American Folk Art Museum. And few worked under such potentially limiting circumstances: Mr. Brewster was born deaf in an era before remedial help or a common sign language existed. The case the show makes that Mr. Brewster's disability is reflected in his art is inconclusive, but the paintings are wonderful. 45 West 53rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 265-1040, folkartmuseum.org; closes on Sunday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Brooklyn Museum: 'Looking Back from Ground Zero: Images from the Brooklyn Museum Collection'  This show presents a historical picture of Lower Manhattan from early on to the present, with the building of the World Trade Center as the pivotal point. A short film, ''Building the World Trade Center,'' produced by the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey in 1983, is an invaluable document of the triumphalist spin surrounding the construction of the complex. A small selection of artworks produced in or just after 2001 hints at the profound and conflicted feelings the destruction of the twin towers has evoked. 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, (718) 638-5000, brooklynmuseum.org; closes on Sunday. ( Cotter)</p>
        <p>* Frick Collection: 'Domenico Tiepolo (1727-1804): A New Testament' The 60 ink drawings by Domenico Tiepolo, son of the Italian master painter Giambattista, have a funny kind of jitter. They look as if they were maybe woven from hair-fine brambles, or done on a ride over rough ground, or in a state of agitated elation. Illustrations of episodes from the four Gospels, they are among some 300 drawings the artist did in a project that seems to have been an extended exercise in personal piety. In them the Christian story of salvation becomes an operatic epic, gravely serious but with notes of homely sweetness: Jesus in Gethsemane delivers his aria of mortal doubt and pain high up on a bare stage, all alone; the Virgin Mary's mother, Anna, aged and stooped, is cosseted by angel-nurses who guide her every step. 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700, frick.org; closes on Sunday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>International Center of Photography: 'Ecotopia: The Second I.C.P. Triennial of Photography and Video' Punctuated by big, black oozing forms that are both comic and ominous, this edifying, entertaining, ecologically aware exhibition is a walk-through version of Al Gore's ''Inconvenient Truth.'' The work on view represents nearly 40 artists and photojournalists and portrays nature as variously ravishing, cute and enduring, and also increasingly dangerous and endangered. Along the way, some of the current uses for, and technical developments in, photography and video are surveyed, adding to the impression that the I.C.P.'s focus on camera-related media, coupled with its curators' determination to be purposefully topical, sidesteps many of the pitfalls of the biennial-triennial genre. International Center of Photography, 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000, icp.org; closes on Sunday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>MORGAN LIBRARY &amp; MUSEUM: 'FRAGONARD AND THE FRENCH TRADITION' AND 'MOZART AT 250: A CELEBRATION' Memorializing Mozart's 250th birthday and the 200th anniversary of the death of the French painter Jean-Honoré Fragonard, these small, paired shows reflect the elegance and brio of 18th-century culture. The Fragonard display consists only of his drawings and those of some compatriots, among them François Boucher, Hubert Robert and Jean-Baptiste Greuze and Jacques-Louis David; 40 works in all, drawn almost entirely from the Morgan's collection. The show effectively displays the virtuosity and variety of Fragonard's many styles, from his skills at depicting foliage-filled landscapes and the play of water in fountains and streams, to his keenness at capturing people, mythological scenes and ephemeral creatures. Although the works in the Mozart display -- letters and musical scores, like the autograph manuscript of the ''Haffner'' Symphony performed at Mozart's first public concert in Vienna in 1783 -- are in quite a different visual language, they go very happily with the Fragonard group. 255 Madison Avenue, at 36th Street, (212) 685-0008, morganlibrary.org; closes on Sunday. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* New-York Historical Society: 'Legacies: Contemporary Artists Reflect on Slavery' Slavery, some would say, didn't really end in the United States until the civil rights legislation of the '60s, a full century after the Emancipation Proclamation. Or the ''Emancipation Approximation,'' as the artist Kara Walker calls it in a series of hallucinatory silkscreen prints. They are among the high points of this large, powerful, subtle group show. 2 West 77th Street, Manhattan, (212) 873-3400, nyhistory.org; closes on Sunday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* A. L. STEINER: 1 MILLION PHOTOS, 1 EURO EACH (MINIMUM ORDER) and UNBORROWED FROM THE EYE: LUKE DOWD, SCOTT MYLES, DAVID NOONAN, BRETT CODY ROGERS AND GILES ROUND Contrasts happen. In the outer gallery five young men explore what might be called Neo-Constructivist quasi-painting with a kind of desperate, post-punk glower. In the inner gallery A. L. Steiner's raunchy, out-there photographs show almost nothing but women having a blast being women. They avoid the all-too-usual connotations of exploitation and sensationalism that plague intimate, often sexual photographs, which is no mean achievement, politically or aesthetically. John Connelly Presents, 625 West 27th Street, Chelsea, (212) 337-9563, johnconnellypresents.com; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* CHEYNEY THOMPSON: 'QUELQUES ASPECTS DE L'ART BOURGEOIS: LA NON-INTERVENTION' A teasing, tantalizing, subtly beautiful show by one of the sharper young artists of the moment explores the tensions between street and studio, skill and skepticism, painting and nonpainting and culture and commerce with seemingly abstract canvases, photographs framed by folding street-vendor tables and tinted off-set lithographs of the gallery's storage shelves. The title translates as ''Certain Aspects of Bourgeois Art: Non-Intervention.'' Andrew Kreps, 525 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 741-8849; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* ATELIER VAN LIESHOUT: SLAVECITY In this only partly satirical show, architectural scale models, drawings, sculpture, a map and an extensive business plan propose a highly efficient, completely self-sufficient city whose ''participants'' each have a desk job, a farm job and very little time off. The tyranny of it all is brought home in the second gallery, which contains the ''Midi Disciplinator,'' a cell built to accommodate 18 people working in shifts, filing logs into sawdust for no good reason. Tanya Bonakdar Gallery, 521 West 21st Street, Chelsea, (212) 414-4144; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* 'When the Revolution Comes' The artist Michael St. John has brought some interesting people together in this scrappy, savory group show. It's great to revisit Nancy Grossman's leather-bound heads, looking as radical as they did 30 years ago, and Holt Quentel's distressed gray banners from the 1980s, out of view since but looking right, right now. Strong young artists like Nate Lowman, Joshua Weintraub and Josh White sustain growing reputations, and a bevy of less familiar figures look good. Also in the gallery: a small solo of vivacious, minutely detailed drawings by Josedgardo Granados that bring pre-Columbian and post-Columbian worlds together in a cultural and psychic revolution still in progress. Kathleen Cullen Fine Arts, 508 West 26th Street, Suite 5A, Chelsea, (212) 463-8500, kathleencullenfinearts.com; closes tomorrow. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* The Whitney Museum of American Art: Mark Grotjahn Mining the early Modernist cusp where the figurative, the geometric, the spatial and the visionary still remain tangled, this Los-Angeles-based painter deploys his abstract pinwheel motifs on paper in eight brash, door-sized drawings. Multiple vanishing points destabilize radiating compositions that are variously Op and buzzy, darkly monochrome (and a little too pretentiously moody) or candy-color bright. In some works the motif is doubled and angled, decreasing the shieldlike frontality and opening up new optical and spatial possibilities. 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676, whitney.org; closes on Sunday. (Smith)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the New York metropolitan region this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'THE FEVER' Previews start on Tuesday. Opens on Jan. 24. Wallace Shawn stars in his own play about a man who wakes up in a war-torn country feeling under the weather (2:00). Acorn Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'IN THE HEIGHTS' Previews start on Tuesday. Opens on Feb. 8. A new Off Broadway musical about two days in the life of Washington Heights from the vantage point of a corner bodega (2:10). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'THE MERCHANT OF VENICE' Previews start tomorrow. Opens on Feb. 4. F. Murray Abraham plays Shylock in this Theater for a New Audience production. Darko Tresnjak directs (2:20). The Duke on 42nd Street, 229 West 42nd Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'THE SCENE' In previews; opens on Thursday. A buzz-maker at the Humana Festival, Theresa Rebeck's new play is about an out-of-work actor who doesn't solve his problems by having an affair. Tony Shalhoub (''Monk'') and Patricia Heaton (''Everybody Loves Raymond'') star (2:00). Second Stage Theater, 307 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 246-4422.</p>
        <p>'A SPANISH PLAY' Previews start on Wednesday. Opens on Feb. 1. Zoe Caldwell leads an extraordinary cast (Linda Emond, Denis O'Hare, Larry Pine, Katherine Borowitz) in Yasmina Reza's new backstage play, in which real life and fiction blur (1:30). Classic Stage Company, 136 East 13th Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101.</p>
        <p>'TRANSLATIONS' In previews; opens on Jan. 25. Brian Friel's drama about a British officer in 19th-century rural Ireland deals with themes of language, imperialism and culture clash. Garry Hynes directs (1:55). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE APPLE TREE' The amazing Kristin Chenoweth gives Imax-screen-size life to three curvaceous doodles who by rights shouldn't be any larger than figures in the Sunday funnies. Jerry Bock and Sheldon Harnick's 1966 musical, directed by Gary Griffin, shows its age but is given theatrical verve by Ms. Chenoweth, Brian d'Arcy James and Marc Kudisch (2:30). Studio 54, 254 West 54th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BUTLEY' In this uneasy revival of Simon Gray's portrait of a toxic English professor, directed by Nicholas Martin, Nathan Lane fires off witticisms as if they were silver bullets with ''Made in Britain'' engraved on them. A less-than-perfect marriage of a first-rate actor with a first-rate play (2:30). Booth Theater, 222 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'A CHORUS LINE' If you want to know why this show was such a big deal when it opened 31 years ago, you need only experience the thrilling first five minutes of this revival. Otherwise, this archivally exact production, directed by Bob Avian, feels like a vintage car that has been taken out of the garage, polished up and sent on the road once again (2:00). Schoenfeld Theater, 236 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE COAST OF UTOPIA: VOYAGE' The exhilarating first two installments of Tom Stoppard's trilogy about 19th-century Russian intellectuals dreaming of revolution, these productions pulse with the dizzy, spring-green arrogance and anxiety of a new generation moving as fast as it can toward the future. Jack O'Brien directs a fresh, vigorous and immense cast that includes Brian F. O'Byrne, Jennifer Ehle, Billy Crudup and Ethan Hawke (2:45). Vivian Beaumont Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'COMPANY' Fire, beckoning and dangerous, flickers beneath the frost of John Doyle's elegant, unexpectedly stirring revival of Stephen Sondheim and George Furth's era-defining musical from 1970, starring a compellingly understated Raul Esparza. Like Mr. Doyle's ''Sweeney Todd,'' this production finds new clarity of feeling in Sondheim by melding the roles of performers and musicians (2:20). Barrymore Theater, 243 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE' (Tony Awards, best book of a musical and best original score, 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920s stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, it has theatergoers responding as if they were withering houseplants finally being watered after long neglect. Bob Martin and Sutton Foster are the standouts in the avid, energetic cast (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'GREY GARDENS' Christine Ebersole is absolutely glorious as the middle-aged, time-warped debutante called Little Edie Beale in this uneven musical adaptation of the notorious 1975 documentary of the same title. She and the wonderful Mary Louise Wilson (as her bedridden mother), in the performances of their careers, make ''Grey Gardens'' an experience no passionate theatergoer should miss (2:40). Walter Kerr Theater, 219 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE LITTLE DOG LAUGHED' The comedy of manners, a form widely believed to be extinct in the American theater, has actually resurfaced on Broadway with all its vital signs intact in Douglas Carter Beane's breezy but trenchant satire about truth and illusion, Hollywood style. With the wonderful Julie White as the movie agent you hate to love (but just can't help it) (2:00). Cort Theater, 138 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MARY POPPINS' This handsome, homily-packed, mechanically ingenious and rather tedious musical, adapted from the P. L. Travers stories and the 1964 Disney film, is ultimately less concerned with inexplicable magic than with practical psychology. Ashley Brown, who sings prettily as the family-mending nanny, looks like Joan Crawford trying to be nice and sounds like Dr. Phil. Directed by Richard Eyre and Matthew Bourne (2:30). New Amsterdam Theater, 214 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LES MISÉRABLES' This premature revival, a slightly scaled-down version of the well-groomed behemoth that closed only three years ago, appears to be functioning in a state of mild sedation. Appealingly sung and freshly orchestrated, this fast-moving adaptation of Victor Hugo's novel isn't sloppy or blurry. But its pulse rate stays well below normal (2:55). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' Duncan Sheik and Steven Sater's bold adaptation of the Frank Wedekind play is the freshest and most exciting new musical Broadway has seen in some time. Set in 19th-century Germany but with a ravishing rock score, it exposes the splintered emotional lives of adolescents just discovering the joys and sorrows of sex. Performed with brio by a great cast, with supple direction by Michael Mayer and inventive choreography by Bill T. Jones (2:00). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN'  This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a superdeluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE VERTICAL HOUR' David Hare's soggy consideration of the Anglo-American cultural divide stars Julianne Moore (representing the Americans) and Bill Nighy (leading the British), directed by Sam Mendes. The Yanks don't stand a chance. With his irresistibly mannered performance as a laconic doctor, Mr. Nighy mops the floor with Ms. Moore. Actually, he mops the floor with Mr. Hare's play (2:20). Music Box Theater, 239 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE BIG VOICE: GOD OR MERMAN?' Think of two gifted and smart gay men with years of life together deploying their considerable talents from the two pianos you happen to have in your living room. The result is a hilarious and very touching memoir of two decades of love and the funky glories of show business life (2:00). Actors Temple Theater, 339 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Honor Moore)</p>
        <p>*'THE CLEAN HOUSE' Sarah Ruhl's comedy about the painful but beautiful disorder of life has arrived in New York at last in a gorgeous production directed by Bill Rauch. Blair Brown and Jill Clayburgh delight as sisters with different views on the meaning of cleaning, and Vanessa Aspillaga is equally good as the depressed maid with little affection for her work but a deep conviction that a good joke can be a matter of life and death (2:15). Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, Lincoln Center, 150 West 65th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'DAI (ENOUGH)' Iris Bahr's unnerving one-woman show doesn't have much to add to the Middle East debate, but it sure leaves a lasting impression. Ms. Bahr plays an assortment of characters who have the misfortune of being in a Tel Aviv cafe that is about to be visited by the havoc common to such establishments. The attack is rendered in jarring fashion, repeatedly; you watch the play on pins and needles, waiting for the next burst. Gimmicky? Sure. But viscerally effective (1:40). Culture Project, 55 Mercer Street, at Broome Street, SoHo, (212) 253-9983. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'EVIL DEAD: THE MUSICAL' This likable horror comedy based on Sam Raimi's gory movies wants to be the next ''Rocky Horror Show.'' To that end, it offers deadpan lyrics, self-referential humor and geysers of stage blood (2:00). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>'THE FANTASTICKS' A revival -- well, more like a resuscitation -- of the Little Musical That Wouldn't Die. This sweet-as-ever production of Tom Jones and Harvey Schmidt's commedia-dell'arte-style confection is most notable for Mr. Jones's touching performance (under the pseudonym Thomas Bruce) as the Old Actor, a role he created when the show opened in 1960. Mr. Jones also directs (2:05). Snapple Theater Center, 210 West 50th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JACQUES BREL IS ALIVE AND WELL AND LIVING IN PARIS' A powerfully sung revival of the 1968 revue, presented with affectionate nostalgia by the director Gordon Greenberg. As in the original, two men and two women perform a wide selection of Brel's plaintive ballads and stirring anthems (2:00). Zipper Theater, 336 West 37th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'A JEW GROWS IN BROOKLYN' You don't have to be Jewish or Brooklynish to empathize with Jake Ehrenreich, but in terms of fully appreciating his essentially one-man show, it probably helps. Especially the Catskills jokes (2:05). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 560-8912. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'MEET ME IN ST. LOUIS' This musical is too big for its stage, but the young turn-of-the-last-century sweethearts have great chemistry, and there are four terrific songs (2:00). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'MY MOTHER'S ITALIAN, MY FATHER'S JEWISH AND I'M IN THERAPY'  Steve Solomon does skillful impersonations in his one-man show, but some of his jokes are as old as the hills (1:30). Little Shubert Theater, 422 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'NO CHILD'  Teachers will love Nilaja Sun's one-woman show about the challenges of teaching drama at Malcolm X High School (1:10). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, at Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'AN OAK TREE' Tim Crouch plays a hypnotist in this elusive puzzle of a play about grief and the power of suggestion (1:05). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, at Seventh Avenue, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'REGRETS ONLY' Old acquaintance comes under siege in Paul Rudnick's chiffon-thin comedy about the varieties of love and marriage. But no one who sees this latest offering from one of the funniest quipmeisters alive is going to doubt that Christine Baranski is a one-liner's best friend (2:00). City Center Stage I, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'ROOM SERVICE' The Peccadillo Theater Company puts a charge into this comedy from the 1930s, thanks to a brisk pace by the director, Dan Wackerman, and a dozen dandy performances. David Edwards is the would-be producer whose bills threaten to swamp his efforts to put a show on Broadway, and Fred Berman is particularly fine as his director (2:00). SoHo Playhouse, 15 Vandam Street, South Village, (212) 691-1555. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'SUDDENLY LAST SUMMER'  As the luscious (and lobotomy-threatened) damsel in distress in Tennessee Williams's famously lurid melodrama, Carla Gugino gives a gutsy assurance to a production that otherwise lacks compelling confidence. Mark Brokaw directs a cast that includes Blythe Danner, in a fascinating but misconceived performance as a smothering mother from hell (1:30). Laura Pels Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'25 QUESTIONS FOR A JEWISH MOTHER' This is the comedian Judy Gold's fiercely funny monologue, based on her own life as a single Jewish lesbian mother and interviews with more than 50 other Jewish mothers (1:20). St. Luke's Theater, 308 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Phoebe Hoban)</p>
        <p>'TWO TRAINS RUNNING'  Directed by Lou Bellamy, a rough-edged revival of August Wilson's 1992 play about the stark economics of life and death for African-Americans, set in a dying diner in Pittsburgh in the late 1960s. The pace drags in this production, but it remains a bracing reminder of Mr. Wilson's singular talent for making cold, hard numbers sing hot, molten blues (3:40). Signature Theater at Peter Norton Space, 555 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 352-3101. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE VOYSEY INHERITANCE' David Mamet has cleanly and cannily adapted Harley Granville Barker's 1905 play about corruption in the genteel world of Victorian finance. An excellent cast and a sumptuous production bring extra immediacy to a tale of embezzlement and entitlement that feels as fresh as tomorrow's stock options (1:50). Atlantic Theater, 336 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'T J AND DAVE' The comics T. J. Jagodowski and Dave Pasquesi miraculously improvise a one-hour play at every performance. This is an impressive feat of mental athletics, but the results are also observant, complex and frequently enormously funny. (1:00) Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden Theater, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' Singing CliffsNotes for Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' Often more entertaining than the real thing (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS'  The biomusical that walks like a man (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SLAVA'S SNOWSHOW' Clowns chosen by the Russian master Slava Polunin stir up laughter and enjoyment. A show that touches the heart as well as tickles the funny bone (1:30). Union Square Theater, 100 East 17th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT'  A singing scrapbook for Monty Python fans (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' ''A Chorus Line'' with pimples (1:45). Circle in the Square, 1633 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'BECOMING ADELE' Eric Houston's one-woman show about a young Brooklyn waitress's journey to self-actualization imagines a New York where fairy tales are possible even for the very ordinary. The sentiment is heavy and thick, but Kimberly Stern's performance burrows through it to deliver moving moments (1:40). Clurman Theater at Theater Row, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200; closing tomorrow. (Ginia Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'BIG APPLE CIRCUS' One terrific show (2:15). Damrosch Park, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500 or (212) 307-4100; closing on Sunday. (Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'MARTIN SHORT: FAME BECOMES ME' This eager and amiably scattershot satire of celebrity memoirs and Broadway musicals, starring the immodestly modest Mr. Short, arrives a little late to the table for such parody to taste fresh. With serviceably tuneful songs by Scott Wittman and Marc Shaiman (of ''Hairspray'' fame) (1:45). Jacobs Theater, 242 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200; closing on Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'STRINGS' Keir Dullea stars in Carole Buggé's intelligent but ultimately unsuccessful ''Copenhagen''-inspired drama about three scientists on a train (1:45). 78th Street Theater Lab, 236 West 78th Street, (212) 362-0329; closing tomorrow. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'TRUE WEST' This perfectly pleasant new version of Sam Shepard's sibling rivalry drama tries something new: understatement (1:35). Big Little Theater, 141 Ridge Street, near Houston Street, Lower East Side, (212) 868-4444; closes tonight. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>'APOCALYPTO' (R, 138 minutes, in Maya) More blood from Mel Gibson, but more ''Braveheart'' than ''Passion of the Christ.'' Ultraviolent entertainment, well executed (so to speak) but not very surprising in the end. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>'BABEL' (R, 143 minutes, in English, Spanish, Japanese, Berber, Arabic and sign language) This hugely ambitious movie tells four loosely linked, not quite simultaneous stories set on three different continents, with dialogue in several languages. The themes, to the extent they are decipherable, include loss, fate and the terrible consequences of miscommunication. Written by Guillermo Arriaga and directed by Alejandro Gonzalez Iñárritu, the movie is an intellectual muddle but a visceral tour de force, and the power of the filmmaking almost overcomes the fuzziness of the ideas. Almost. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'BLACK CHRISTMAS' (R, 100 minutes) It's been more than 30 years since the original ''Black Christmas'' revealed how much fun it could be to unleash a psycho in a sorority house. Glen Morgan's disastrous remake not only sidelines the original's hilariously obscene phone calls but also drags its unseen killer, and his psychoses, into the light. Smothering terror beneath a blanket of unnecessary information, the movie is no more than a dismal Christmas card to its predecessor. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'BLOOD DIAMOND' (R, 138 minutes) The makers of this foolish thriller about illegal diamond trafficking in Africa, starring an excellent Leonardo DiCaprio, want you to know there may be blood on your hands, specifically your wedding finger. Too bad they haven't thought through what it means to turn human misery into entertainment. (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>'BOBBY' (R, 111 minutes) Emilio Estevez's picture, which follows a score of characters through the Ambassador Hotel in Los Angeles on June 4, 1968, is full of noble ambition. The day in question ended with the assassination of Robert F. Kennedy, an event that hovers over the movie, even though Kennedy himself is visible only in archival clips. A huge cast (including Anthony Hopkins, Sharon Stone, Demi Moore, Ashton Kutcher, Lindsay Lohan and Mr. Estevez) labors to inject a collection of melodramatic anecdotes with portent and significance, but the individual parts of the film tend to be either overdone or vague and slight. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'BORAT: CULTURAL LEARNINGS OF AMERICA FOR MAKE BENEFIT GLORIOUS NATION OF KAZAKHSTAN' (R, 89 minutes) In this brainy, merciless comedy, a Kazakh journalist named Borat Sagdiyev, a k a the British comic Sacha Baron Cohen, invades America. America laughs, cries, surrenders. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'CASINO ROYALE' (PG-13, 144 minutes) The latest James Bond vehicle finds the British spy leaner, meaner and now played by an attractive piece of blond rough named Daniel Craig. Zap, pow, ka-ching! (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'CHARLOTTE'S WEB' (G, 113 minutes) Gary Winick's adaptation of E. B. White's great children's novel is faithful to the wit and feeling of the source. The celebrity-voiced animals are charming, and Julia Roberts is in fine form as the heroic spider, whose writing ability saves the life of a pig. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'CHILDREN OF MEN' (R, 100 minutes) The end is nigh in this superbly directed political thriller by Alfonso Cuarón about a nervously plausible future. Based on the P. D. James book, the film stars an excellent Clive Owen and features equally sterling support from the actors Michael Caine, Danny Huston and Chiwetel Ejiofior, among others, as well as the great cinematographer Emmanuel Lubezki. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'COPYING BEETHOVEN' (PG-13, 104 minutes) The director Agnieszka Holland and her star Ed Harris bring intelligence and passion to a fictional account about the creation of the Ninth Symphony. Diane Kruger also stars. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'CURSE OF THE GOLDEN FLOWER' (R, 114 minutes, in Mandarin) The Chinese director Zhang Yimou aims for Shakespeare and winds up with Jacqueline Susann in this Tang dynasty melodrama roiling with incest, fraternal rivalry and madness-inducing fungus. As an emperor and empress fighting for control of their three sons, Chow Yun Fat and Gong Li lend the film a core of marital toxicity that's deliciously unstable. Directing with operatic delirium, Mr. Zhang has created a movie in which the line between tragedy and black comedy has been all but erased. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'THE DEAD GIRL' (R, 93 minutes) An impressively well-acted movie, ''The Dead Girl'' has a chip on its shoulder. The relentless emotional violence in it, a compendium of five vignettes related to a young woman whose naked, mutilated corpse is discovered on a barren hillside, is of a level rarely found in movies, even those steeped in gore. There is some gore in ''The Dead Girl,'' but it is eclipsed in intensity by the verbal abuse hurled by its desperately unhappy characters at the people closest to them. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>'DEATH OF A PRESIDENT' (No rating, 93 minutes) This fake-umentary, the subject of much hyperventilation since it was shown at the 2006 Toronto Film Festival, imagines what might happen if George W. Bush were assassinated. Condemned as irresponsible wishful thinking by some, hailed as a brave artistic statement by others, the movie, directed by Gabriel Range, is far too banal to merit such strong responses. Its formal cleverness wears thin and after a while exposes a lazy, pretentious form of provocation. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'DECK THE HALLS' (PG, 95 minutes) In the holiday tradition of stale fruitcake, ugly snowflake sweaters and food poisoning comes this piece of junk, in which Matthew Broderick and Danny DeVito compete to see who can annoy the audience more. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'DÉJÀ VU' (PG-13, 125 minutes) In Tony Scott's preposterous action flick, with Denzel Washington, the gaudy pyrotechnics are nowhere near as jaw-dropping as the screenplay that name-checks not one, not two, but three national tragedies. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'THE DEPARTED' (R, 150 minutes) Martin Scorsese's cubistic entertainment about men divided by power, loyalty and their own selves is at once a success and a relief. Based on the crackling Hong Kong thriller ''Infernal Affairs,'' it features fine twinned performances from Matt Damon and Leonardo DiCaprio, and a showboating Jack Nicholson. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'DHOOM 2' (No rating, 151 minutes, in Hindi) A slick and satisfying example of the new, thoroughly modern Bollywood, this cops-and-robbers tale is animated by old-fashioned star power. Hrithik Roshan plays the ''smartest and coolest thief alive,'' and Aishwarya Rai is the small-time crook who loves him. (Rachel Saltz)</p>
        <p>'ERAGON' (PG, 99 minutes) This lad-and-his-dragon fantasy set in a land bristling with Tolkienesque nomenclature and earnest British actors is as lacking in fresh ideas as Tim Allen's manager. Directed by the wonderfully named Stefen Fangmeier, it boasts the usual genre lineup: an evil king (John Malkovich), a whey-faced hero (Edward Speleers) and a serene warrior-maiden (Sienna Guillory), as well as the required rebel hordes and bucolic landscapes. Some of the characters won't be returning for the sequel, but no matter. In all likelihood, neither will the audience. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* '51 BIRCH STREET' (No rating, 88 minutes) The mysteries of ordinary life drive this moving, engrossing documentary, in which the director, Doug Block, tries to figure out his parents' 54-year marriage. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'FLAGS OF OUR FATHERS' (R, 132 minutes) Clint Eastwood raises the flag over Iwo Jima once more in a powerful if imperfect film about the uses of war and of the men who fight. The fine cast includes Ryan Phillippe, Jesse Bradford and Adam Beach, who delivers heartbreak by the payload. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'FLANNEL PAJAMAS' (No rating, 124 minutes) The twin specters of Ingmar Bergman and Woody Allen hover over this film, which might have been more accurately titled ''Scenes From a Mixed Marriage'' or ''Annie Hall Without Laughs.'' This smart, talky history of a relationship between two New Yorkers follows a Jewish theatrical promoter and an aspiring caterer with a Roman Catholic background from courtship to marriage to separation. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'FLUSHED AWAY' (PG, 85 minutes) Sewer rats, singing leeches and whimsical British anarchy -- this computer-animated feature from Aardman Animations (''Wallace and Gromit,'' ''Chicken Run'') is completely delightful. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'FOR YOUR CONSIDERATION' (PG-13, 86 minutes) This satire of pre-Oscar-nomination buzz in Hollywood is far and away the broadest comedy Christopher Guest and his improvisatory company have made. It is also the flimsiest, and unlike Mr. Guest's earlier films, it has no airs of being a fake documentary. As farce trumps satire, the humor's subversive edge is lost, along with meaningful character development, with the brilliant exception of Catherine O'Hara. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE GOOD SHEPHERD' (R, 157 minutes) This chilly film written by Eric Roth and directed by Robert De Niro about a spy trapped in the cold of his own heart, seeks to put a tragic human face on the Central Intelligence Agency, namely that of Matt Damon. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE GOOD GERMAN' (R, 102 minutes) In his adaptation of the Joseph Kanon novel, Steven Soderbergh tries to resurrect the magic of classical Hollywood, principally by sucking out all the air, energy and pleasure from his own filmmaking. It's no wonder George Clooney, who stars alongside a vamping Cate Blanchett, looks confused. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'HAPPY FEET' (PG, 100 minutes) The director George Miller gets happy and snappy, then goes dark and deep, in a musical about an animated penguin who was born to dance. Take hankies. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE HISTORY BOYS' (R, 104 minutes) The current of intellectual energy snapping through this ferociously engaging screen adaptation of Alan Bennett's Tony Award-winning play, set in a north England boys' school in 1983, feels like electrical brain stimulation. As two teachers jockey for the hearts and minds of eight teenage schoolboys preparing to apply to Oxford and Cambridge, their epigrams send up small jolts of pleasure and excitement. How to teach and interpret history is the question. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'I LOVE YOU (VOLIM TE)' (No rating, 83 minutes, in Croatian) In this bleak drama about a young advertising hotshot who learns that he's H.I.V.-positive, the Croatian writer and director Dalibor Matanic conjures a disaffected, post-Communist lifestyle of casual hedonism and emotional bankruptcy. The premise may be trite -- personal growth through unexpected adversity -- but in its pervasive atmosphere of haunting sterility, the movie is as much about the loss of a generation as the redemption of an individual. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* 'INLAND EMPIRE' (No rating, 179 minutes) David Lynch's extraordinary, savagely uncompromised new film stars a dazzling Laura Dern as an actress who tumbles down rabbit holes inside rabbit holes inside rabbit holes. As cracked as Mad magazine, though generally more difficult to parse, the film has the power of nightmares and is one of the few this year that deserve to be called art. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE LAST KING OF SCOTLAND' (R, 121 minutes) Kevin Macdonald paints a queasily enjoyable portrait of the Ugandan dictator Idi Amin from inside the palace walls. Forest Whitaker plays the mad king, while James McAvoy plays the fool. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'LETTERS FROM IWO JIMA' (R, 141 minutes, in Japanese) Another masterwork from Clint Eastwood's astonishing late period, and one of the best war movies ever. Ken Watanabe is especially fine as the general commanding Japanese troops in the doomed defense of the island of Iwo Jima. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'LITTLE CHILDREN' (R, 130 minutes) Todd Field's adaptation of Tom Perrotta's novel of suburban adultery is unfailingly intelligent and faultlessly acted. Kate Winslet and Patrick Wilson are superb as the parents of young children who meet at the playground and enact a two-handed variation on ''Madame Bovary'' against a backdrop of social paranoia and middle-class malaise. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'MAN OF THE YEAR' (PG-13, 115 minutes) Robin Williams plays a comedian and talk show host who plunges into the presidential campaign, telling truths the timid politicians dare not utter. Not really. This would-be satire, written and directed by Barry Levinson, is hectic and tired, with too many plots and too few sharp insights. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'MARIE ANTOINETTE' (PG-13, 123 minutes) In this elaborate, bittersweet confection, Sofia Coppola imagines the last pre-revolutionary queen of France (played with wit and charm by Kirsten Dunst) as a bored, pleasure-seeking teenager trapped in a world of artifice and rigid protocol. Dreamy and decadent, the film is also touching, funny and bracingly modern. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'NIGHT AT THE MUSEUM' (PG, 108 minutes) In this chaotic, overstuffed family comedy, Ben Stiller is a night watchman at the American Museum of Natural History, where the exhibits come to life at night and attack him and one another. This computerized spectacle spares no expense, but the storytelling is weak, and the hit-or-miss jokes miss more than hit. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'NOTES ON A SCANDAL' (R, 92 minutes) Judi Dench and Cate Blanchett play a misogynistic game of cat and mouse from which no one emerges unscathed, including the audience. Adapted by Patrick Marber from a novel by Zoë Heller and directed by Richard Eyre. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'PAN'S LABYRINTH' (R, 119 minutes, in Spanish) Guillermo del Toro's tale of a young girl's ordeal in post-Civil War fascist Spain is either a fairy tale in the guise of a political allegory or vice versa. In either case it is a moving, enchanting, strange and humane example of popular art at its very best. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE PAINTED VEIL' (PG-13, 125 minutes) Nicely directed by John Curran, this version of the W. Somerset Maugham novel draws you in by turning a distaff bildungsroman into a fine romance with Naomi Watts and Edward Norton. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'PERFUME: THE STORY OF A MURDERER' (R, 147 minutes) There's no other way to say it: Tom Tykwer's excruciatingly literal-minded adaptation of the best-selling novel about an 18th-century serial killer with an acute sense of smell is a real stinker. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE PURSUIT OF HAPPYNESS' (PG-13, 117 minutes) How you respond to this fairy tale in realist drag may depend on whether you find Will Smith's performances so overwhelmingly winning that you buy the idea that poverty is a function of bad luck and bad choices, and success the result of heroic toil and dreams. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'THE QUEEN' (PG-13, 103 minutes) Directed by Stephen Frears from a very smart script by Peter Morgan, and starring a magnificent Helen Mirren in the title role, ''The Queen'' pries open a window in the House of Windsor around the time of the death of Diana, Princess of Wales, blending fact with fiction. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'ROCKY BALBOA' (PG, 102 minutes) Surprisingly, the sixth installment of this franchise is no embarrassment. Like its forerunners, it goes the distance almost in spite of itself. It's all heart and no credibility, except as a raw-boned fable. From the very beginning, Rocky Balboa was about as lifelike a character as Popeye pumped up with spinach. But that may be the point of a series that peddles the notion that if you dream it hard enough, you can live it. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE TIGER AND THE SNOW' (No rating, 115 minutes, in Arabic, English and Italian) War may be hell, but for Roberto Benigni it's just another romantic comedy waiting to be filmed. This time that gnomic Italian superstar is a poetry professor who must pose as a Red Cross surgeon to rescue his beloved from a Baghdad hospital. But this contrived setup is merely an excuse for Mr. Benigni to climb onto a camel, blunder into a minefield and confront the American military; to Mr. Benigni, war is simply another stage for his outlandish ego. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'UNACCOMPANIED MINORS' (PG, 89 minutes) The title doubles as an advisory. Your kids may like it; pick them up when it's over. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'VENUS' (R, 91 minutes) A modest, diverting, touching tale of a young woman who attracts the interest -- avuncular and also erotic -- of an aging actor, played with effortless aplomb by the great Peter O'Toole. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'VOLVER' (R, 121 minutes, in Spanish) Another keeper from Pedro Almodóvar, with Penélope Cruz -- as a resilient widow -- in her best role to date. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'WE ARE MARSHALL' (PG, 128 minutes) This fact-based story of a West Virginia college town recovering from the death of its entire football team in a 1970 plane crash is a stiff, manipulative dud that gets wrong everything ''Friday Night Lights'' got right. Matthew McConaughey hams it up as the college's goofy new coach, who whips the replacement team into decent shape. (Holden)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>AN ARTIST AND A GAMBLER: ROBERT ALTMAN REMEMBERED (Today, and Sunday through Thursday) IFC Center's tribute to Altman, the iconoclastic filmmaker who died in November at 81, begins today. This weekend's features are ''M*A*S*H'' (1970), the original antiwar comedy, and ''Short Cuts'' (1993), Altman's ensemble drama about life in Los Angeles. The other more than two dozen features in the retrospective will include ''McCabe &amp; Mrs. Miller'' (1971), ''The Player'' (1992), ''Nashville'' (1975) and ''That Cold Day in the Park'' (1969). (Through Jan. 23.) At 323 Avenue of the Americas, at West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 924-7771, movietickets.com; $10.75. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>CRITICS CHOICE: GREAT DOCUMENTARIES (Tomorrow and Sunday) The Museum of the Moving Image is sponsoring its eighth annual New York Film Critics Circle series, beginning tomorrow. This weekend's features, chosen by member critics, are ''In the Year of the Pig'' (1968-69), a critique of the Vietnam War, introduced by David Fear; the newly excavated ''Winter Soldier'' (1972), introduced by Michael Atkinson; Frederick Wiseman's ''Hospital'' (1970), introduced by Peter Rainer; and Terry Zwigoff's ''Crumb'' (1994), about the underground comics artist R. Crumb, introduced by John Anderson. (Through Feb. 28.) At 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718) 784-0077, movingimage.us; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>ESSENTIALLY WOODY (Today through Thursday) Film Forum's 28-film retrospective of Woody Allen's work continues this weekend with three films. ''Manhattan'' (1979), Mr. Allen's love letter to the city, Gershwin and teenage girls, plays today and tomorrow. ''Take the Money and Run'' (1969), in which an inept bank robber has trouble spelling ''gun,'' and the comic redubbing experiment ''What's Up, Tiger Lily?'' (1966) are the double feature for Sunday and Monday. At 209 West Houston Street, west of Avenue of the Americas, South Village, (212) 727-8110, filmforum.org; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK JEWISH FILM FESTIVAL (Wednesday and Thursday) This 16th annual event is sponsored by the Jewish Museum and the Film Society of Lincoln Center. It begins on Wednesday with a program that includes two United States premieres of full-length features: Christian Delage's ''Nuremberg: The Nazis Facing Their Crimes'' (2005), a French documentary narrated by Christopher Plummer; and ''My Mexican Shivah''(2006), Alejandro Springall's comedy about a patriarch's death. (Through Jan. 25.) Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5600, thejewishmuseum.org or filmlinc.com; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>FRANZ WAXMAN: MUSIC FOR THE CINEMA (Today through Monday, and Wednesday and Thursday) The Museum of Modern Art is honoring Waxman (1906-67), the German composer, with a 21-film retrospective. This weekend's films include ''The Spirit of St. Louis'' (1957), starring Jimmy Stewart as the aviator Charles Lindbergh; ''Objective Burma!'' (1945), a World War II adventure with Errol Flynn; and the classic ''Sunset Blvd.'' (1950), for which Waxman won his second Oscar. Roy and Niuta Titus Theaters, (212) 708-9400, moma.org; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>BRYAN ADAMS (Thursday) In the 1980s this Canadian rocker became an MTV regular by expertly playing an inoffensive rebel: he wore a leather jacket and kept his square jaw in a scowl, but sang chrome-plated guitar anthems that never hid their sentimentality. In time the sentimentality overtook the guitar-rock, as in the 1991 megahit ''(Everything I Do) I Do It for You,'' but that never hurt anyone's popularity. Here Mr. Adams plays a rare concert in New York. At 8 p.m., Beacon Theater, 2124 Broadway, at 74th Street, (212) 496-7070 or (212) 307-7171; sold out. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>BABY DAYLINER (Tonight) Ethan Marunas, the pale, sometimes pompadoured crooner who performs as Baby Dayliner, is a throwback to a few different strains of '80s pop: murmuring about being a ''star without a movie'' over brittle electronic beats, he joins the blue-eyed soul of Joe Jackson, the fragility of Morrissey and the arty synth-disco of New Order and Human League. With the Pierces and Five O'Clock Heroes. At 9:30, Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700, mercuryloungenyc.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BILAL (Thursday) Bilal has huge ambitions, spanning jazz and soul, funk and gospel, hip-hop and pop. Even when his material doesn't live up to those ambitions, he has musicality to spare. At 9 p.m., S.O.B.'s, 204 Varick Street, at Houston Street, South Village, (212) 243-4940, sobs.com; $26 in advance, $28 at the door. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>* BLACK DICE, SIGHTINGS, EXCEPTER (Tomorrow) Noise, noise, glorious New York noise. Black Dice, from Brooklyn, is a big player in the international avant-rock scene, and has remained vital by staying truly experimental: whether playing spacey, hokey psychedelia or alien-invasion squalls of feedback, the band throws itself deeply into its every unpredictable turn. Sightings sticks to guitars and drums for its nightmarish din, and Excepter's songs, with gurgling, irregular electronic blips, evoke the aimless flailings of a damaged robot. At 9 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; $13 in advance, $15 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>JAMES COTTON (Thursday) Playing in Muddy Waters's bands in the 1950s, James Cotton helped define modern blues harmonica with his moaning, wrenching phrases and his train-whistle wails. Recent albums with the younger players who studied him prove that he can still rip into a blues. At 8 p.m., B. B. King Blues Club and Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $25 in advance, $29 at the door. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>FIERY FURNACES (Tonight) In a smart scramble of eras and attitudes, the Fiery Furnaces back flippantly surreal lyrics with blues riffs, teetering analog synthesizers, parlor piano and punky noise, coming up with a 21st-century urban skiffle. With Emergency Party, and Michael Mayham and the Mike. At 9, Northsix, 66 North Sixth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 599-5103, northsix.com; $15. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>TIM FITE, O'DEATH (Tomorrow) Tim Fite's songs about ''kicking every can in New York City'' are booby-trapped with quick changes from clean country-pop to corrosive punk. O'Death draws from the starkness and spiritual purity of Appalachian folk, the menace of punk and the rowdy theatricality of Tom Waits, jumbling sacred and profane. At 8 p.m., Union Hall, 702 Union Street, at Fifth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 638-4400, unionhallny.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PAUL GREEN SCHOOL OF ROCK MUSIC (Tomorrow and Sunday) As seen in the documentary ''Rock School,'' Mr. Green offers an extensive curriculum at his Philadelphia school, teaching youngsters the rock 'n' roll canon, as well as the fundamentals of power chords and budda-budda bass lines. Here his students offer ''The Folk Show.'' At 2:30 p.m., Rebel, 251 West 30th Street, Manhattan, (212) 695-2747, rebelnyc.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>EMILY HAINES AND THE SOFT SKELETON (Tuesday) In her regular band, Metric, Ms. Haines plays a kind of dance-floor defector, singing moodily over bouncy electronic beats and sharp new-wave guitars. On her own, this Canandian songwriter is as far away from the disco ball as she could be, with dark and rich piano ballads about looking for a cure for the ''lonesome lows.'' For her tour, the Canadian neo-surrealist filmmaker Guy Maddin has put together montages of his work set to her songs. With the Tall Firs. At 7 p.m., Hiro Ballroom, 371 West 16th Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-0212, bowerypresents.com; $19.50 in advance, $22 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* 'HIGH SCHOOL MUSICAL: THE CONCERT' (Monday) Cynical parents might compare it to the Monkees. But what in the world could be wrong with ''I'm a Believer''? Or, for that matter, with ''Breaking Free,'' the PG-rated climax from ''High School Musical,'' the Disney Channel phenomenon whose soundtrack was the best-selling album of 2006? Performing the songs from this tween ''Grease,'' to the accompaniment of thousands of squeals, will be the cast of the movie, or at least most of it: Zac Efron, who played the heartthrob, Troy, is replaced here by Drew Seeley, who supplied many of Troy's vocals on the soundtrack. At 7 p.m., Continental Airlines Arena, East Rutherford, N.J., (201) 935-3900, meadowlands.com; $36.50 to $56.50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>IZZYS (Tomorrow) With a repertory of lean, uncomplicated blues-boogies, this New York band worships at the twin retro-rock altars of the Rolling Stones and the Stooges (with maybe a little Gram Parsons country thrown in as well). At 11 p.m., Lakeside Lounge, 162 Avenue B, between 10th and 11th Streets, East Village, (212) 529-8463, lakesidelounge.com; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DAYNA KURTZ (Tuesday and Wednesday) That's not weariness in the plain alto of Dayna Kurtz, a singer-songwriter from Brooklyn skilled at conveying the sting of heartbreak. It's vulnerability, which means that no matter how many times a relationship collapses, she is still hopeful when asking her lover to kiss her ''like a stranger.'' With Kris Delmhorst. At 8 p.m., Union Hall, 702 Union Street, at Fifth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 638-4400, unionhallny.com; $12. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LYRICS AND LYRICISTS (Tomorrow through Monday) The 37th season of the 92nd Street Y's American Songbook series begins with a tribute to Rosemary Clooney that focuses on the writers behind her repertory, including William Saroyan (the co-writer of ''Come On-a My House''), Tom Adair and Billie Holiday. The artistic director and host is Deborah Grace Winer, and the players include James Naughton, John Pizzarelli, Paul West and Karen Ziemba; Debby Boone, Ms. Clooney's daughter-in-law, will appear on Sunday and Monday. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Sunday at 3 and 8 p.m., and Monday at 2 and 8 p.m., 92nd Street Y, 1395 Lexington Avenue, (212) 415-5500, 92y.org; $50 and $60. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* MAN MAN (Tonight) Man Man, from Philadelphia, follows the expressive gutter cabaret of Tom Waits into a kinetic chaos that has more than a little Captain Beefheart in it. With Mixel Pixel and Plastic Little. At 9, Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; $14. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MOUTHUS (Tonight) A fearsome and unpredictable noise-rock duo from Brooklyn, Mouthus delves into guttural depths of vocals and guitar, seldom completing a show without repeatedly knocking over some large instrument or fixture. With Axolotl, Wiseblood, Watersports and Max Cloud. At 9, Silent Barn, 15 Wyckoff Avenue, at Hancock Street, Bushwick, Brooklyn, toddpnyc.com; $7. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ANDERS PARKER, JENNIFER O'CONNOR (Wednesday) Mr. Parker, who led the band Varnaline, immerses his songs in the stoic drama of country and folk music, resulting in a melancholy that is sometimes indistinguishable from cynicism. (''The hours I've wasted here I could have wasted anywhere.'') He begins a four-week Wednesday residency at the Living Room. Ms. O'Connor's portraits of the lovelorn are dry but not unsympathetic: ''Maybe she's on her lunch break thinking of you.'' At 9 p.m., 154 Ludlow Street, near Stanton Street, Lower East Side, (212) 533-7235, livingroomny.com; $8. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>RON SEXSMITH (Tuesday) Ron Sexsmith seems self-effacing and hesitant at first, with a voice that sidles up to notes like a wallflower trying to slip into a party unnoticed. But behind the outward modesty is a craftsman who stubborn upholds the verities of 1960s songwriting, placing supple melodies atop unexpected harmonies and offering wistful regret and consolation in equal parts. With Kim Taylor. At 8:30 p.m., Maxwell's, 1039 Washington Street, Hoboken, N.J., (201) 653-1703, maxwellsnj.com; $12. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>SONIC BOOM (Monday and Tuesday) In the 1980s, Peter Kember, a k a Sonic Boom, was a member of Spacemen 3, an influential British band that found a twilight zone somewhere between jangly garage-rock and the druggy, pulsating minimalism of the Velvet Underground. Later, with Experimental Audio Research, he explored ever purer forms of drone. Here Mr. Kember acts as autobiographical D.J., spinning records that inspired him ''from the '30s through the '90s.'' At 10 p.m., Club Midway, 25 Avenue B, at Second Street, East Village, (212) 253-2595, clubmidway.com; $10 in advance, $12 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>SOUTHSIDE JOHNNY AND THE ASBURY JUKES (Tonight and tomorrow night) While his friend Bruce Springsteen left the Jersey Shore behind and went on to write all-American anthems and parables, Southside Johnny Lyon stuck to the old bar-band basics: rolling R &amp; B vamps and raspy-voiced, good-natured soul plaints, complete with horn section. At 8, B. B. King Blues Club and Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $35. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>WAR (Tuesday) Only one original member, the keyboardist Lonnie Jordan, remains in this pioneering Latin-funk band, which in the 1970s did nearly as much as Santana to integrate Latin percussion and rock 'n' roll. The other four surviving players are in another touring group, the Lowrider Band. What separates them is a lawsuit. At 8 p.m., B. B. King Blues Club and Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $30 in advance, $32 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>CARL ALLEN AND NEW SPIRIT (Tonight and tomorrow night) The propulsive drummer Carl Allen leads a hard-bop ensemble seasoned with gospel harmonies and stocked with heavy hitters: Vincent Herring on alto saxophone, Christian McBride on bass and Aaron Goldberg on piano. At 8, 10 and midnight, Sweet Rhythm, 88 Seventh Avenue South, at Bleecker Street, West Village, (212) 255-3626, sweetrhythmny.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>* HAN BENNINK AND FRIENDS (Tuesday and Wednesday) Mr. Bennink plays the drums with the unrestrained glee of a 4-year-old, but his antics do nothing to hinder his uplifting sense of swing. Here this Dutch master collaborates with a cadre of American modernists, like the trumpeter Dave Douglas, the pianist Anthony Coleman, the tenor saxophonist Ellery Eskelin and the tuba player Marcus Rojas. At 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501; cover, $15; $12 in advance. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* TERENCE BLANCHARD (Thursday) As a trumpeter and composer, Mr. Blanchard favors a sleek post-bop sound informed by myriad contemporary sources. His excellent working band -- with the saxophonist Brice Winston, the pianist Aaron Parks, the bassist Derrick Hodge and the drummer Kendrick Scott -- will play a range of original music, including Mr. Blanchard's haunting soundtrack to the Spike Lee documentary ''When the Levees Broke.'' At 9:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 539-8778, joespub.com; cover, $20, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JANE IRA BLOOM (Tomorrow) Elaborating on material from her latest album, ''Like Silver, Like Song'' (ArtistShare), Ms. Bloom plays soprano saxophone and electronics in a solid working band with Dawn Clement on keyboards, Mark Helias on bass and Matt Wilson on drums. At 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CECIL BRIDGEWATER (Tomorrow) Mr. Bridgewater, an accomplished trumpeter, balances lyricism and aggression in a trio with the bassist Kenny Davis and the drummer Alvin Atkinson. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Sistas' Place, 456 Nostrand Avenue, at Jefferson Avenue, Bedford-Stuyvesant, Brooklyn, (718) 398-1766, sistasplace.org; $25 in advance, $30 at the door. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN JAZZ UNDERGROUND (Thursday) The Brooklyn Jazz Underground is a coalition of artists united by aesthetics as well as geography; its launch party, so to speak, spans four nights at Smalls next week. Opening night will include bands led by the pianist Benny Lackner, the trumpeter Shane Endsley and the violinist and violist Tanya Kalmanovitch. (Through Jan. 14.) At 8:30, 10 and 11:30 p.m., Smalls, 183 West 10th Street, West Village, (212) 675-7369, brooklynjazz.org; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE COLEMAN AND FIVE ELEMENTS (Sunday and Thursday) Mr. Coleman's alto saxophone cuts cleanly through the angular free-funk of his signature ensemble, which includes the trumpeter Jonathan Finlayson, the trombonist Tim Albright, the vocalist Jen Shyu, the bassist Thomas Morgan and the drummer Tyshawn Sorey. At 8 and 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>THE CRUSADERS (Tuesday through Thursday) This crossover soul-jazz outfit, led by the keyboardist Joe Sample, has gone through multiple revisions since its heyday in the 1970s. Here the lineup features one other founding member, the saxophonist Wilton Felder, and includes Nils Landgren on trombone; Ray Parker Jr. on guitar; Nicklas Sample, Joe Sample's son, on bass; and Steve Gadd on drums. (Through Jan. 14.) At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $45 at tables, $30 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LUCIEN DUBUIS TRIO WITH MARC RIBOT (Tomorrow) The Swiss-born alto saxophonist and clarinetist Lucien Dubuis aims for the ragged thrust of a punk band with his trio, which features Roman Nowka on bass and Lionel Friedli on drums. Mr. Ribot, as a guest guitarist, brings raw energy as well as seasoned artistry. At 10 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DOMINIQUE EADE AND RACHEL CASWELL (Wednesday) Ms. Eade weighs a chanteuse's coolness against a jazz musician's exploratory instinct, as she will demonstrate in dialogue with the guitarist Brad Shepik and the bassist Ben Street. Ms. Caswell, who hails from a similar school of jazz singing, will seek to hold her own. At 8:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* FLY (Tuesday through Thursday) The tenor saxophonist Mark Turner, the bassist Larry Grenadier and the drummer Jeff Ballard make up this superb trio, which eschews the usual horn-plus-rhythm hierarchy in the service of an elastic group ideal. (Through Jan. 14.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JAZZ TRIBUTE TO FRANK SINATRA (Tonight and tomorrow night) A few good things promise to lift this salute above the humdrum, like the veteran trombonist Eddie Bert, the versatile guitarist Howard Alden and the precocious tenor saxophonist Tommy Morimoto. At 9 and 11, Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* NANCY KING (Wednesday) Ms. King is a musician's singer, and until recently her reputation barely extended beyond a circle of insiders. Since the release of ''Live at Jazz Standard'' (Max Jazz) last year, she has been more widely celebrated; she returns to that setting next week with a backing trio led by the pianist Geoffrey Keezer. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $30. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LOGN (Monday) This upstart Danish quartet practices a sort of exuberant avant-gardism derived partly from the downtown scene; its members are the multireedist Jacob Danielsen, the guitarist Kasper Bai, the pianist Kasper Bjerg and the drummer Soren Mehlsen. At 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MIYA MASAOKA, SYLVIE COURVOISIER AND OKKYUNG LEE (Monday) Ms. Masaoka extracts a boldly textural sound from the koto, a Japanese zither; Ms. Lee and Ms. Courvoisier do much the same on their Western instruments, a cello and a piano. At 10 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* JASON MORAN AND THE BANDWAGON (Wednesday and Thursday) Jason Moran is a bright pianist who favors jagged and delirious polyphony; his uncommonly cohesive group, the Bandwagon, features the earthy yet slippery rhythm section of Tarus Mateen, bassist, and Nasheet Waits, drummer. (Through Jan. 13.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum at tables. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MOUTIN REUNION QUARTET (Thursday) The brothers François and Louis Moutin, a bassist and a drummer, lead this dynamic trans-Atlantic post-bop ensemble; the other half consists of the tenor saxophonist Rick Margitza and the pianist Pierre de Bethmann. At 8 and 10 p.m., Sweet Rhythm, 88 Seventh Avenue South, at Bleecker Street, West Village, (212) 255-3626, sweetrhythmny.com; cover, $15, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LEWIS NASH QUINTET (Tuesday through Thursday) An engaging and subtle drummer who brings a crisp swing to any setting, Lewis Nash leads a band with Jeremy Pelt on trumpet, Jimmy Greene on saxophones, Renee Rosnes on piano and Peter Washington on bass. (Through Jan. 14.) At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>NIGHT OF THE COOKERS 2007 (Tonight and tomorrow night) Blazing hard bop, in no uncertain terms: the tenor saxophonist Eric Alexander presides, but just as much heat will be generated by his fellow tenor George Coleman, the trumpeters Jim Rotondi and Jeremy Pelt, and the pianist Harold Mabern. At 8, 10 and 11:30, Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, (212) 864-6662, smokejazz.com; cover, $30. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* NYC WINTER JAZZFEST (Wednesday) The Knitting Factory commits all three of its floors to jazz during this sprawling one-night festival, which will feature 17 different bands. Among the highlights are groups led by the alto saxophonists Rudresh Mahanthappa and Steve Lehman, the trumpeter Maurice Brown and the guitarists Liberty Ellman and Joel Harrison. From 6 p.m. to 1 a.m. at the Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3132, knittingfactory.com; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GRETCHEN PARLATO (Tonight and Thursday) Ms. Parlato is a cosmopolitan singer with a lilting tone but sharp musical instincts; her rapport with the guitarist Lionel Loueke, with whom she performs in a duo on Thursday, is ocean-deep. Opening on Thursday is the Polish vocalist Aga Zaryan. Tonight at 6, 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; no cover. Thursday at 7 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 539-8778, joespub.com; cover, $15, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>J. D. PARRAN (Wednesday) Mr. Parran plays alto clarinet, soprano saxophone, bamboo flute and contrabass clarinet on the recent album ''Omegathorp: Living City'' (Y'All), which also features the sitar playing of Mark Deutsch, the vocals of Thomas Buckner, the cello work of David Darling and the percussion of Kevin Norton. There will be no sitar in the mix next week, but the ensemble's texture-oriented approach should hardly be hindered. At 8 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>NICHOLAS PAYTON QUARTET (Wednesday and Thursday) Nicholas Payton, an abundantly gifted trumpeter, has recently oscillated between hard bop and electric fusion, producing good results in both areas. The group he leads here could move in any direction he chooses. (Through Jan. 14.) At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $35, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LONNIE PLAXICO GROUP (Tonight) The bassist and composer Lonnie Plaxico pursues a dynamic brand of contemporary fusion in this ensemble, with Jeff Hermanson on trumpet, Mike Mcginnis on saxophones, Helen Sung on piano and organ and Kenny Grohowski on drums. At 10 and 11, the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* DIZZY REECE QUARTET (Tonight) In the 1950s and '60s, Dizzy Reece was one of the sharper hard-bop trumpeters on the scene; his fortunes since then have been uneven, and these days he performs infrequently. His rhythm section here consists of Mike Longo on piano, Lee Hudson on bass and James Worth on drums. At 7, Rubin Museum of Art, 150 West 17th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 620-5000, Ext. 344, rmanyc.org; $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SHAKERS N' BAKERS (Tuesday) The so-called vision songs of 19th-century Shaker women provide a distinctive repertory for this ensemble, which includes the vocalists Mary LaRose and Miles Griffith, the saxophonist Jeff Lederer, the keyboardist Jamie Saft, the bassist Chris Lightcap and the drummer Allison Miller. At 9 p.m., BAMCafé, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100, bam.org; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* SIM FACULTY CONCERT (Thursday) The School for Improvised Music is a nonprofit enterprise in which the instructors are adventurous musicians; among them are the trumpeter Ralph Alessi, the saxophonists Peter Epstein and Ravi Coltrane, the pianist Andy Milne, the bassist Mark Helias and the drummer Tom Rainey. At 8 p.m., Center for Improvisational Music, 295 Douglass Street, between Third and Fourth Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (212) 631-5882, schoolforimprov.org; $12; $8 for students. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MARVIN STAMM QUARTET (Wednesday) The veteran big band and studio trumpeter Marvin Stamm has focused fruitfully in recent years on a solo career, and on a good working quartet with the drummer Ed Soph, the bassist Rufus Reid and the pianist Bill Mays. At 8 and 9:45 p.m., Kitano Hotel, 66 Park Avenue, at 38th Street, (212) 885-7119, kitano.com; no cover, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MICHAEL WEISS QUARTET (Thursday) Michael Weiss, a pianist with extensive sideman credits, brings sophistication and precision to this band, with Bob Sheppard on saxophones, Ugonna Okegwo on bass and Greg Hutchinson on drums. At 8 and 9:45 p.m., Kitano Hotel, 66 Park Avenue, at 38th Street, (212) 885-7119, kitano.com; no cover, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE WILSON QUARTET (Thursday) An alto saxophonist with a dry tone but a rounded sense of phrase, Steve Wilson leads a strong working band, with Bruce Barth on piano, Ed Howard on bass and Adam Cruz on drums. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>'THE FIRST EMPEROR' (Tonight and Tuesday) The excitement of a world premiere at the Metropolitan Opera, combined with widespread interest among the general public in the composer Tan Dun, who won an Oscar for his score to ''Crouching Tiger, Hidden Dragon,'' have resulted in a sold-out run for this opera. Alas, the story of Qin Shi Huang, the first emperor of China, who unified the country through brutality and conquest, is compelling, but Mr. Tan's ponderous score is a huge disappointment. There are gripping moments, especially some propulsive orchestra passages that incorporate Chinese instruments. But the opera's lyrical flights are slow-moving, ponderous and sometimes cloying. Mr. Tan has tried to meld Chinese melody and Italianate lyricism. His music, though, seems caught in some nowhere land between ''Crouching Tiger'' and Puccini's ''Turandot.'' Even the great Plácido Domingo, bravely taking on the challenging title role, cannot save the show. The colorful production is by the Chinese film director Zhang Yimou (''House of Flying Daggers''). Mr. Tan conducts. At 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; sold out. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'DIE FLEDERMAUS' (Tonight through Sunday) In its 59th season the Amato Opera continues to stage productions in its tiny quarters on the Bowery. Now offered is Strauss's merry ''Fledermaus,'' with a rotating cast. The quality often varies, but the spirit is usually there. Tonight and tomorrow night at 7:30, Sunday afternoon at 2:30, 319 Bowery, at Second Street, East Village, (212) 228-8200, amato.org; $35; $28 for students and 65+. (Vivien Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* 'I PURITANI' (Tomorrow and Thursday) The reason the Met dusted off its stodgy old 1976 production of this Bellini work, and the one compelling reason to see it, is Anna Netrebko. This glamorous, dusky-voiced Russian soprano makes an affecting and vocally lustrous Elvira, the daughter of a stern Puritan father during the English Civil War whose sanity slips away when she thinks her adored Arturo, a Royalist sympathizer, is unfaithful. Ms. Netrebko may not be a bel canto purist's ideal -- her execution of coloratura roulades is sometimes imprecise, and her diction could use more clarity -- but she sings excitingly and stops the show with her Act II mad scene. On the illness-plagued opening night last week, only the fine bass-baritone John Relyea, singing Elvira's kindly uncle despite grappling with remnants of bronchitis, was in the same dramatic class as the star. Patrick Summers conducts. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m., and Thursday at 7:30 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; sold out. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'LA TRAVIATA' (Wednesday) Franco Zeffirelli's overly plush and extravagant production returns to the Met's repertory with the excellent soprano Hei-Kyung Hong as Violetta. Joining this highly regarded artist as Alfredo is Wookyung Kim, a tenor from Ms. Hong's native South Korea making his Met debut. The American baritone Charles Taylor sings Germont. Carlo Rizzi conducts. At 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $15 to $175. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'DIE ZAUBERFLÖTE' (Tomorrow and Monday) This revival of Julie Taymor's production continues at the Metropolitan Opera, complete with the magical puppets and stage effects that made it an audience hit when it opened in 2004. Tomorrow Scott Bergeson conducts a cast that includes the fabulous German bass René Pape as Sarastro, with Erika Miklosa as Queen of the Night, Matthew Polenzani as Tamino, Rodion Pogossov as Papageno and Nicole Heaston as Pamina. On Monday Lisa Milne sings Pamina. Tomorrow at 8:30 p.m., Monday at 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $42 to $295 tickets remain tomorrow; $15 to $320 on Monday. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>AMERICAN SYMPHONY ORCHESTRA (Sunday) Leon Botstein has thought up another interesting afternoon, this time centering on César Franck and including both his famous D minor Symphony and pieces by three of his pupils: Ernest Chausson, Paul Dukas and Albéric Magnard. At 3 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $27 to $55. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>BARGEMUSIC (Tonight through Sunday) The guitarist Jorge Caballero presents a solo recital that includes, of all things, an arrangement of Dvorak's Ninth Symphony, as well as works by Poulenc, Milhaud, Turina and others. A Latinate theme continues in tomorrow and Sunday's program for clarinet trio, with Beethoven's Opus 38 trio balancing out works by Nino Rota, Paquito D'Rivera and Astor Piazzolla. Tonight and tomorrow night at 7:30, Sunday afternoon at 4, Fulton Ferry Landing next to the Brooklyn Bridge, Brooklyn, (718) 624-2083, bargemusic.org; $35; $20 for students; $30 for 65+, tonight only. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>CHAMBER MUSIC SOCIETY OF LINCOLN CENTER (Thursday) The double-bass and the double-bassist DaXun Zhang get something of a workout in a program that includes Rossini's Duetto in D for Cello and Bass, and Schubert's familiar ''Trout'' Quintet for piano and strings. At 6:45 p.m., Rose Studio, 165 West 65th Street, (212) 875-5788, chambermusicsociety.org; sold out. (Holland)</p>
        <p>CHIARA STRING QUARTET (Tuesday and Thursday) ''Mestizaje: Harmony of Differences'' is the title of the Chiara String Quartet's concert at Merkin Concert Hall on Thursday devoted to composers whose music spans two cultures, including Gabriela Lena Frank (Chiara has recorded her ''Leyendas: An Andean Walkabout'') and Zhou Long. This fine, Juilliard-trained quartet, which seeks new paths through the field of classical music, will also play at Rose Live Music in Brooklyn on Tuesday, with a program to be announced from the stage. Thursday at 8 p.m., Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, Manhattan, (212) 501-3330, ekcc.org; $25. Tuesday at 9 p.m., Rose Live Music, 345 Grand Street, between Marcy Avenue and Havemeyer Street, Williamsburg, (718) 599-0960; $5. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>COMPOSERS GUILD OF NEW JERSEY (Thursday) The formidable modernist composer Charles Wuorinen has had major productions and performances of large-scale works in New York in recent seasons, notably his opera ''Haroun and the Sea of Stories,'' given its premiere by City Opera, and his Piano Concerto No. 4, performed at Carnegie Hall by the pianist Peter Serkin and the Boston Symphony, conducted by James Levine. On Thursday the Composers Guild of New Jersey presents a program of recent chamber and vocal works by Mr. Wuorinen, including the New York premiere of ''Fenton Songs II,'' settings of poems by James Fenton on themes of war and political upheaval. The strong roster of performers include the soprano Lucy Shelton, the baritone Thomas Meglioranza, the pianist Alan Feinberg, the violinist Mark Steinberg and the cellist Nina Maria Lee. At 8 p.m., Christ and St. Stephen's Episcopal Church, 120 West 69th Street, Manhattan, (212) 787-2755, cgnj.org; free. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* EIGHTH BLACKBIRD (Thursday) This inventive and energetic young new-music ensemble from Chicago has built its audience with eclectic programming and commissioning. They have also impressed listeners by playing complex scores by memory, a feat rarely seen in ensemble concerts with much more familiar music. The program includes works by Steve Mackey, Jennifer Higdon, Gordon Fitzell and David M. Gordon. At 8 p.m., the Kitchen, 512 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 255-5793, thekitchen.org; $10. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>JUPITER SYMPHONY CHAMBER PLAYERS (Monday) The bassoonist Frank Morelli is the guest of this feisty chamber ensemble in a woodwind-dominated program that includes arrangements of arias by Rossini and Mozart, an unfinished wind quintet by Schubert, Gounod's ''Petite Symphonie'' and an Andante by Reicha. At 2 and 7:30 p.m., Good Shepherd-Faith Presbyterian Church, 152 West 66th Street, Manhattan, (212) 799-1259, jupitersymphony.com; $10 to $25. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* 'MOSTLY OPERETTA' (Wednesday and Thursday) To celebrate a neglected genre that once held Europe in thrall and spawned the Broadway musical, the Austrian Cultural Forum is starting a two-week festival on Wednesday with a program of Emmerich Kalman, Oscar Straus and Franz Lehar, accompanied by visuals by the Austrian artist Victoria Coeln. Kalman and Lehar both wrote for Marta Eggerth, a major stage and screen star from the 1930s who has retained a solid vocal technique into her ninth decade, and gave several sold-out cabaret evenings at Café Sabarsky last year to prove it. On Thursday she will talk about operetta style and demonstrate it with some singing of her own; it's worth hearing. Wednesday at 8 p.m., Thursday at 7 p.m., 11 East 52nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 319-5300, acfny.org; free, but reservations are required. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>MY LORD CHAMBERLAIN'S CONSORT (Sunday) This early-music group was formed in 1997 to present a complete performance of John Dowland's ''First Book of Songs or Ayres.'' Here they will perform four centuries of English carols arranged for lutes, harps, voices and viol. At 3 p.m., Madison Avenue Presbyterian Church, at 73rd Street, (212) 288-8920, mapc.com; $15; $10 for students and 65+. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK GILBERT AND SULLIVAN PLAYERS (Tonight through Sunday, Tuesday and Thursday) ''The Yeoman of the Guard'' is perhaps Gilbert and Sullivan's most operatic work; ''Mikado,'' their most beloved; and ''The Rose of Persia,'' not really a Gilbert and Sullivan work at all, since the book (based on the ''Arabian Nights'') was written by Basil Hood some years after a quarrel ended Gilbert and Sullivan's collaboration. These three works constitute the 33rd season of New York's best-established G&amp;S troupe, led by the indomitable Albert Bergeret. ''Yeoman,'' tonight at 8 and Sunday afternoon at 3; ''Mikado,'' tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., and Tuesday at 7 p.m.; ''Rose,'' Thursday at 8 p.m., City Center, 131 West 55th Street, Manhattan, (212) 581-1212, nycitycenter.org; $40 to $96, 10 percent off $40 to $80 tickets for 65+. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC (Today, tomorrow and Tuesday) Old favorites are making return visits, and this means the pieces and the performers. Zubin Mehta conducts, and Pinchas Zukerman is the soloist in the Beethoven Violin Concerto and Stravinsky's ''Rite of Spring.'' Today at 11 a.m., tomorrow at 8 p.m. and Tuesday at 7:30 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nyphil.org; $33 to $101. (Holland)</p>
        <p>'ONE DOLLAR CONCERT AT CARNEGIE HALL' (Tomorrow) The pianist João Carlos Martins, a Brazilian who has made some provocative but powerful Bach recordings, has moved to the podium and is introducing himself to New York as a conductor in a bargain-priced concert meant also to call attention to the Amazon Region Protected Areas program and its efforts to preserve the Amazon rain forest. Mr. Martins will lead his 27-player Bachiana Chamber Orchestra in Bach's Orchestral Suite No. 1, Villa-Lobos's ''Preludio Bachiana'' and the premiere of ''Amazona'' by Stefan Meylaers. At 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $1. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* SEQUITUR (Monday) This first-rate new-music band turns its attention to contemporary Cuban works, with a program that includes scores by Tania León, Sergio Barroso, Keyla Orozco, Orlando Jacinto García and Jorge Martín. At 8 p.m., Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, Manhattan, (212) 501-3330, sequitur.org; $15; $10 for students and 65+. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>VOLKER VOGEL (Tuesday) The music of the Austrian composer and writer Ernst Krenek ranges from neo-romanticism to serialism. He wrote his tonal ''Reisebuch aus den Österreichischen Alpen,'' a cycle of 20 songs about the Austrian countryside, in 1929, after studying Schubert. Mr. Vogel, a tenor, sings the work as part of the Sound of Song series at the Austrian Cultural Forum, accompanied by the pianist Ann Beckman. At 8 p.m., 11 East 52nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 319-5300, acfny.org; free, but reservations are required. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>JEN ABRAMS AND JACKIE MOYNAHAN (Tomorrow) Ms. Abrams promises to peel back the facade of a New York City apartment building and gaze into the lives of four city dwellers. Ms. Moynahan will delve into desensitizing media images. At 8 p.m., Dixon Place, 258 Bowery, between Houston and Prince Streets, Lower East Side, (212) 219-0736, dixonplace.org; $12 or T.D.F.; $10 for students and 65+. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>LES BALLETS TROCKADERO DE MONTE CARLO (Tonight through Sunday afternoon) Lots of men can wear tutus; point shoes are another matter. If you want to see how real men pirouette, check out the Trocks, as they are called, performing classics like ''Swan Lake'' and creepy 20th-century ballets like ''The Cage.'' Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 3 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 3 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800, joyce.org; $44. (Claudia La Rocco)</p>
        <p>BEYOND THE SILK ROAD: TRADITIONAL AND NEW MIDDLE EASTERN DANCE (Sunday) Part of the 92nd Street Y's informal Sundays @ Three series, this program features dance and talk by choreographer-performers known as Altagracia, Ayshe, Blanca, Layla and Zenaide. At 3 p.m., 92nd Street Y Harkness Dance Center, 1395 Lexington Avenue, (212) 415-5500; $10. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CLARE BYRNE DANCE (Thursday) Ms. Byrne, a nicely quirky longtime presence in New York modern dance, describes her ''Rounds, the First Last Dance, or the Last First Dance, or an Ordination'' as calling up ''the doing-ness of dance. Uh-oh. (Through Jan. 14.) At 8 p.m., Dance New Amsterdam, 280 Broadway, at Chambers Street, TriBeCa, (212) 279-4200, ticketcentral.com; $20. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Complexions Contemporary Ballet (Tuesday through Thursday) This company, founded in 1994 by Dwight Rhoden and Desmond Richardson, is notable for its wonderful dancers and, often, less-than-wonderful choreography. But this season looks promising, with a work by Mr. Richardson to the music of Marvin Gaye; new pieces by Nicolo Fonte and Jodie Gates; and a solo for Mr. Richardson -- one of dance's true stars -- by Taye Diggs. Yes, that Taye Diggs. Tuesday and Wednesday at 7.30 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800, joyce.org; $42; $32 for Joyce members. (Roslyn Sulcas)</p>
        <p>* DANCE ON CAMERA FESTIVAL (Tonight through Sunday, and Tuesday and Wednesday) Presented by the Dance Film Association and the Film Society of Lincoln Center, this festival ranges more widely than ever, with nine programs of dance created for the camera, documentaries and archival compilations. Today at 1, 3:30, 6:15 and 8:30 p.m.; tomorrow at 1, 3:30, 6 and 8:30 p.m.; Sunday at 1, 4 and 7 p.m. Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center; $10; $5 for 65+ and children 6 through 12. Other programs, at other sites, include a retrospective of work by Elaine Summers and discussions on editing and creating dance with a narrative. (212) 496-3809, dancefilms.org. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>COMPANY EAST (Tonight through Sunday, and Thursday) Hiroshi Jin's Company East makes its American debut in a dance-theater production of ''Medea'' that incorporates elements of Noh theater, Western modern dance and karate stances. (Through Jan. 14.) Tonight and tomorrow and Thursday nights at 7:30, Sunday at 2:30 and 7:30 p.m., La MaMa E.T.C., 74A East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 475-7710, lamama.org; $20; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>KELLEY DONOVAN &amp; DANCERS (Tonight and tomorrow) The company will perform ''It's All Forgotten Now,'' created by Ms. Donovan, a Boston-based choreographer with an interest in exploring the initiation of movement as well as abrupt shifts in dynamics and weight. Tonight at 9, tomorrow night at 8, Merce Cunningham Studio, 55 Bethune Street, at Washington Street, West Village, (781) 420-3893; $20; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>'GENE POOL' (Tonight through Sunday) This showcase features dances by B. J. Sullivan, Nia Love, Janessa Clark and Shelley Poovey. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 3 p.m., Dance New Amsterdam, 280 Broadway, at Chambers Street, TriBeCa, (212) 279-4200, ticketcentral.com; $17. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>JEAN ISAACS SAN DIEGO DANCE THEATER (Thursday) This program includes a new piece by Jeffrey Gerodias, a former Alvin Ailey dancer, and four quartets to music by Steve Reich. (Through Jan. 13.) At 8:30 p.m., Danspace Project, St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194, danspaceproject.org; $20; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Movement Research at the Judson Church (Monday) Three or four choreographers show new work each week during this series, which aims to provide an environment for works in progress. Next week the choreographers are Levi Gonzalez, Lyndsey Karr and Sakura Shimada. At 8 p.m., Judson Memorial Church, 55 Washington Square South, Greenwich Village, movementresearch.org; free. (Sulcas)</p>
        <p>* NEW YORK CITY BALLET (Tonight through Sunday, and Tuesday through Thursday) The company director, Peter Martins, has combined the sleekness of 21st-century ballet dancing with elements of the 19th-century classic in this staging of ''The Sleeping Beauty.'' This production also offers a chance to savor familiar favorites and unfamiliars in new roles. Tonight there will be debuts in the leading roles: Prince Désiré (Sébastien Marcovici), Aurora (Yvonne Borree), the Lilac Fairy (Sara Mearns) and the evil Carabosse (a vivid Melissa Barak). The cast will return on Sunday afternoon. The ballet's lead roles will also be danced by Wendy Whelan, Jennie Somogyi, Jenifer Ringer, Philip Neal, Teresa Reichlen and others. Tonight and Thursday night at 8, tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 3 p.m., Tuesday and Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 870-5570, nycballet.com; $20 to $95. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>SLAMFEST/KARL ANDERSON (Tonight and tomorrow night) Mr. Anderson's wild imagination gives much of his work the quality of something uncorked from a genie's bottle. At 8, Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, between Houston and Prince Streets, (212) 334-7479; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* American Museum of Natural History: 'GOLD,' through Aug. 19. Having delved into pearls, diamonds and amber, the museum applies its time-tested show-and-tell formula to gold. An astounding array of art, artifacts and natural samples, larded with fascinating facts and tales, ranges from prehistoric times to the present. Stops along the way include pre-Columbian empires, sunken treasure, Bangladesh dowry rituals and the moon landing. It turns out that gold comes from the earth in forms as beautiful as anything man has thought to do with it. Central Park West and 79th Street, (212) 769-5100, amnh.org. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>Cooper-Hewitt National Design Museum: 'DESIGN LIFE NOW: NATIONAL DESIGN TRIENNIAL 2006,' through July 29. This ambitious show illuminates the volatile, contradictory and ever-expanding field of design, but fails to call it to order. The inclusions cover medical innovation, military hardware, completely frivolous reiterations of received ideas, sundry Web sites and magazines, haute couture, architecture and more varieties of recycling than you can easily count. The show coalesces into deliberately orchestrated skirmishes between conflicting principles and entities: corporate and private, decorative and essential. 2 East 91st Street, (212) 849-8400, ndm.si.edu. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'Spanish Painting from El Greco to Picasso, TIME, TRUTH, AND HISTORY' through March 28. This show is carried along on its sheer star power and optical finesse. There are dozens of Goyas and Velázquezes and Zurbaráns and El Grecos and Riberas and Dalís and Picassos, many famous, many not. The big point is that Spanish art did not constantly reinvent itself over time. It was a bubble culture, sustained for centuries by its political and religious isolation and its national loner mindset. Velázquez's painting of a dwarf is alone worth crossing a continent to see. 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3500, guggenheim.org. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* THE METropolitan museum of art: 'GLITTER AND DOOM: GERMAN PORTRAITS FROM THE 1920s,' through Feb. 19. This show's 100 paintings and drawings are by 10 artists, among them George Grosz, Christian Schad, Rudolf Schlichter and Karl Hubbuch, and most conspicuously the unrelentingly savage Otto Dix and his magnificent other, Max Beckmann. In their works the Weimar Republic's porous worlds reassemble. We look into the faces of forward-looking museum directors and cabaret performers, society matrons and scarred war veterans, prostitutes and jaded aristocrats who were watching their world slide from one cataclysm to the next. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* THE MET: 'LOUIS COMFORT TIFFANY AND LAURELTON HALL -- AN ARTIST'S COUNTRY ESTATE,' through May 20. Laurelton Hall may have burned to the ground in 1957, but this exhibition does an excellent job of reassembling what remains of this extraordinary house-museum and its gardens, which Tiffany created for himself in the early 1900s. The Gilded Age opulence of the place, which occupied 580 acres overlooking Long Island Sound -- and of the Tiffany residences preceding it -- is conveyed most blatantly by the Temple-of-Dendur-size Daffodil Terrace, in wood, marble and glass. The main events are the glass windows, vases and lamps, where Tiffany's genius for color, love of the exotic and reverence for nature coalesce into an unforgettable mystical materialism. (See above.) (Smith)</p>
        <p>* MORGAN LIBRARY &amp; MUSEUM: 'SAUL STEINBERG: ILLUMINATIONS,' through March 4. Saul Steinberg's famous New Yorker cover positioning Manhattan at the center of the world may be his best-known drawing, but he took on everything with visual puns, manic doodles, grandiloquent calligraphy and other inspired artifice. As this show of more than 100 drawings, collages and constructions goes on, Steinberg's progress is evident: from relatively simple cartoons like ''Feet on Chair'' (1946), in which a fellow reading a newspaper parks his feet on the seat of an ornate Victorian monstrosity, to complex comments on the state of the world, like ''Street War (Cadavre Exquisis)'' (about 1972-74), derived from news clips of postcolonial troubles in the Middle East and Africa. The flow of his work amazes. 225 Madison Avenue, at 36th Street, (212) 685-0008, morganlibrary.org. (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>* Museum of Arts &amp; Design: 'Simply DROOG: 10 + 3 YEARS OF CREATING DISCUSSION AND INNOVATION,' through Jan. 14. Droog Design, a many-headed, loosely affiliated collective of usually, but not entirely, Dutch designers and architects has probably generated more discussion than innovation in its 13 years of existence. Presented in a free-flowing, Droog-designed layout, this show vigorously continues the process. It includes about 150 mostly domestic objects by scores of designers. Some are great, some are silly, some are Conceptual Art. But there is plenty to sink your teeth into, especially with help from the small free brochure containing label information and rationales for each item. 40 West 53rd Street, (212) 956-3535, madmuseum.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* MUSEUM OF THE CITY OF NEW YORK: 'A CITY ON PAPER: SAUL STEINBERG'S NEW YORK,' through March 25. A very lively adjunct to the Morgan show, this smaller display of some 40 drawings focuses on New York. An architect, Steinberg was particularly attracted to edifices like the Chrysler Building, which appears here looming majestically over brownstones and in another incarnation, from a perspective directly below it, looking positively squat. New York people, in Steinberg's eyes, could be monuments, too. You may think you know Steinberg's work, but these shows make it new. 1220 Fifth Avenue at 103rd Street, (212) 534-1672, mcny.org. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>Onassis Cultural Center: 'Athens-Sparta,' through May 12. Painted vases, pottery, sculptured steles, tiny carved figures, writings inscribed on stone and a selection of coins are among the nearly 300 objects in this show, whose first section begins with objects from both cities during the Geometric Period (1050-700 B.C.) Two other sections deal with the on-again, off-again relationship between the cities in the fifth century B.C. As society evolved from tribal to civil and felt the first stirrings of democracy during the Archaic Period (650-480 B.C.), rigid geometrical motifs were succeeded by more human forms, like the kouroi and korai, the stone or bronze statues, sometimes life-size, representing young men and women and symbolizing a new emphasis on the individual. On view from the sixth century B.C. are two small Attic representations of kourai, dressed statues of maidens, said to represent the Athenian aristocracy in rites celebrating the goddess Athena. Carved in stone, with long, braided hair (one is headless, but her braids are visible) and beautifully articulated drapery that clings to their bodies, they disappeared as a type after the Persian wars. 645 Fifth Avenue, near 52nd Street, (212) 486-4448. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center: 'DEFAMATION OF CHARACTER,'  through Jan. 15. With 46 artists and a mix of usual and unusual suspects, this exhibition forms a black hole in which Dada, Fluxus, Punk, Pop, Conceptual and Neo-Conceptual mingle like cackling furies along with Performance art, feminism, abject art and various forms of appropriation. While its dour tone becomes a bit relentless, it is admirably consistent and shows artists grappling with reality, which has its own kind of comfort. 22-25 Jackson Avenue, at 46th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 784-2084, ps1.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center: 'THE GOLD STANDARD,' through Jan 15. Gold is both color and subject in this glittering, pertinent show, installed on creamy yellow walls. Even though a generally dim view of contemporary society prevails, it is scary how good gold makes everything look. (See above.) (Smith)</p>
        <p>Whitney Museum of American Art: 'Kiki Smith: A Gathering, 1980-2005,' through Feb. 11. Many things fly and float here: men and women, harpies and angels, birds and beasts, toadstools and stars. And some things fall to earth, or rather to the museum's black stone floors, maybe to rise again, maybe not. The whole show, a midcareer retrospective, suggests a Victorian fairy tale, its tone at once light, grievous and dreamlike. But fanciful as it is, Ms. Smith's art is also deeply, corporeally realistic. It wears moral and mortal seriousness on its sleeve, if not tattooed on its wrist. It is about life and death, the essential things. 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676, whitney.org. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>American Folk Art Museum: 'A Deaf Artist in Early America: The Worlds of John Brewster Jr.,' Few Early American artists painted more incisive and empathetic likenesses than John Brewster Jr. (1766-1854), the subject of a fine traveling show at the American Folk Art Museum. And few worked under such potentially limiting circumstances: Mr. Brewster was born deaf in an era before remedial help or a common sign language existed. The case the show makes that Mr. Brewster's disability is reflected in his art is inconclusive, but the paintings are wonderful. 45 West 53rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 265-1040, folkartmuseum.org; closes on Sunday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Brooklyn Museum: 'Looking Back from Ground Zero: Images from the Brooklyn Museum Collection'  This show presents a historical picture of Lower Manhattan from early on to the present, with the building of the World Trade Center as the pivotal point. A short film, ''Building the World Trade Center,'' produced by the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey in 1983, is an invaluable document of the triumphalist spin surrounding the construction of the complex. A small selection of artworks produced in or just after 2001 hints at the profound and conflicted feelings the destruction of the twin towers has evoked. 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, (718) 638-5000, brooklynmuseum.org; closes on Sunday. ( Cotter)</p>
        <p>* Frick Collection: 'Domenico Tiepolo (1727-1804): A New Testament' The 60 ink drawings by Domenico Tiepolo, son of the Italian master painter Giambattista, have a funny kind of jitter. They look as if they were maybe woven from hair-fine brambles, or done on a ride over rough ground, or in a state of agitated elation. Illustrations of episodes from the four Gospels, they are among some 300 drawings the artist did in a project that seems to have been an extended exercise in personal piety. In them the Christian story of salvation becomes an operatic epic, gravely serious but with notes of homely sweetness: Jesus in Gethsemane delivers his aria of mortal doubt and pain high up on a bare stage, all alone; the Virgin Mary's mother, Anna, aged and stooped, is cosseted by angel-nurses who guide her every step. 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700, frick.org; closes on Sunday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>International Center of Photography: 'Ecotopia: The Second I.C.P. Triennial of Photography and Video' Punctuated by big, black oozing forms that are both comic and ominous, this edifying, entertaining, ecologically aware exhibition is a walk-through version of Al Gore's ''Inconvenient Truth.'' The work on view represents nearly 40 artists and photojournalists and portrays nature as variously ravishing, cute and enduring, and also increasingly dangerous and endangered. Along the way, some of the current uses for, and technical developments in, photography and video are surveyed, adding to the impression that the I.C.P.'s focus on camera-related media, coupled with its curators' determination to be purposefully topical, sidesteps many of the pitfalls of the biennial-triennial genre. International Center of Photography, 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000, icp.org; closes on Sunday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>MORGAN LIBRARY &amp; MUSEUM: 'FRAGONARD AND THE FRENCH TRADITION' AND 'MOZART AT 250: A CELEBRATION' Memorializing Mozart's 250th birthday and the 200th anniversary of the death of the French painter Jean-Honoré Fragonard, these small, paired shows reflect the elegance and brio of 18th-century culture. The Fragonard display consists only of his drawings and those of some compatriots, among them François Boucher, Hubert Robert and Jean-Baptiste Greuze and Jacques-Louis David; 40 works in all, drawn almost entirely from the Morgan's collection. The show effectively displays the virtuosity and variety of Fragonard's many styles, from his skills at depicting foliage-filled landscapes and the play of water in fountains and streams, to his keenness at capturing people, mythological scenes and ephemeral creatures. Although the works in the Mozart display -- letters and musical scores, like the autograph manuscript of the ''Haffner'' Symphony performed at Mozart's first public concert in Vienna in 1783 -- are in quite a different visual language, they go very happily with the Fragonard group. 255 Madison Avenue, at 36th Street, (212) 685-0008, morganlibrary.org; closes on Sunday. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* New-York Historical Society: 'Legacies: Contemporary Artists Reflect on Slavery' Slavery, some would say, didn't really end in the United States until the civil rights legislation of the '60s, a full century after the Emancipation Proclamation. Or the ''Emancipation Approximation,'' as the artist Kara Walker calls it in a series of hallucinatory silkscreen prints. They are among the high points of this large, powerful, subtle group show. 2 West 77th Street, Manhattan, (212) 873-3400, nyhistory.org; closes on Sunday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* A. L. STEINER: 1 MILLION PHOTOS, 1 EURO EACH (MINIMUM ORDER) and UNBORROWED FROM THE EYE: LUKE DOWD, SCOTT MYLES, DAVID NOONAN, BRETT CODY ROGERS AND GILES ROUND Contrasts happen. In the outer gallery five young men explore what might be called Neo-Constructivist quasi-painting with a kind of desperate, post-punk glower. In the inner gallery A. L. Steiner's raunchy, out-there photographs show almost nothing but women having a blast being women. They avoid the all-too-usual connotations of exploitation and sensationalism that plague intimate, often sexual photographs, which is no mean achievement, politically or aesthetically. John Connelly Presents, 625 West 27th Street, Chelsea, (212) 337-9563, johnconnellypresents.com; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* CHEYNEY THOMPSON: 'QUELQUES ASPECTS DE L'ART BOURGEOIS: LA NON-INTERVENTION' A teasing, tantalizing, subtly beautiful show by one of the sharper young artists of the moment explores the tensions between street and studio, skill and skepticism, painting and nonpainting and culture and commerce with seemingly abstract canvases, photographs framed by folding street-vendor tables and tinted off-set lithographs of the gallery's storage shelves. The title translates as ''Certain Aspects of Bourgeois Art: Non-Intervention.'' Andrew Kreps, 525 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 741-8849; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* ATELIER VAN LIESHOUT: SLAVECITY In this only partly satirical show, architectural scale models, drawings, sculpture, a map and an extensive business plan propose a highly efficient, completely self-sufficient city whose ''participants'' each have a desk job, a farm job and very little time off. The tyranny of it all is brought home in the second gallery, which contains the ''Midi Disciplinator,'' a cell built to accommodate 18 people working in shifts, filing logs into sawdust for no good reason. Tanya Bonakdar Gallery, 521 West 21st Street, Chelsea, (212) 414-4144; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* 'When the Revolution Comes' The artist Michael St. John has brought some interesting people together in this scrappy, savory group show. It's great to revisit Nancy Grossman's leather-bound heads, looking as radical as they did 30 years ago, and Holt Quentel's distressed gray banners from the 1980s, out of view since but looking right, right now. Strong young artists like Nate Lowman, Joshua Weintraub and Josh White sustain growing reputations, and a bevy of less familiar figures look good. Also in the gallery: a small solo of vivacious, minutely detailed drawings by Josedgardo Granados that bring pre-Columbian and post-Columbian worlds together in a cultural and psychic revolution still in progress. Kathleen Cullen Fine Arts, 508 West 26th Street, Suite 5A, Chelsea, (212) 463-8500, kathleencullenfinearts.com; closes tomorrow. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* The Whitney Museum of American Art: Mark Grotjahn Mining the early Modernist cusp where the figurative, the geometric, the spatial and the visionary still remain tangled, this Los-Angeles-based painter deploys his abstract pinwheel motifs on paper in eight brash, door-sized drawings. Multiple vanishing points destabilize radiating compositions that are variously Op and buzzy, darkly monochrome (and a little too pretentiously moody) or candy-color bright. In some works the motif is doubled and angled, decreasing the shieldlike frontality and opening up new optical and spatial possibilities. 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676, whitney.org; closes on Sunday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Correction:  January 12, 2007, Friday  A dance entry in the Listings pages of Weekend last Friday about Complexions Contemporary Ballet, which is at the Joyce Theater this week, misstated the date its engagement ends. It is Sunday; it did not end yesterday.</p>
        <p>The entry also misidentified the choreographer whose work is set to the music of Marvin Gaye. He is Dwight Rhoden -- not Desmond Richardson, who is a choreographer and dancer who runs the company with Mr. Rhoden. And the entry included an outdated reference to a new work by Nicolo Fonte. The program was changed and does not include that work.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: January 12, 2007, Friday</p>
        <p>A dance entry in the Listings pages of Weekend last Friday about Complexions Contemporary Ballet, which is at the Joyce Theater this week, misstated the date its engagement ends. It is Sunday; it did not end yesterday.</p>
        <p>The entry also misidentified the choreographer whose work is set to the music of Marvin Gaye. He is Dwight Rhoden -- not Desmond Richardson, who is a choreographer and dancer who runs the company with Mr. Rhoden. And the entry included an outdated reference to a new work by Nicolo Fonte. The program was changed and does not include that work.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
