<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SPARE TIMES: Jan. 5 - Jan. 11; FLOODWALL</title>
    <meta content="05bspar" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/05/arts/design/05bspar.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1816455"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE1DF1430F936A35752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="298" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SPARE TIMES: Jan. 5 - Jan. 11; FLOODWALL</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Spare Times - Floodwall</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELENA RYZIK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Jana K. Napoli, an artist born and bred in New Orleans, returned to her hometown a few weeks after Hurricane Katrina hit, she sifted through the detritus in her neighborhood. She found sofas and pianos and hand-sewn lace, but she picked up only the abandoned dresser drawers. Originally she envisioned them as receptacles for a new project. But the more drawers she salvaged, the more she saw promise in them alone. ''I began to realize that these drawers could be a symbol of the households that were lost,'' Ms. Napoli said. She collected 700 drawers from across the city, meticulously labeling each with the address where it was found. They became the basis for ''Floodwall,'' above, an installation now on view on the Liberty Street Bridge, near the World Financial Center. Balanced along the span of the bridge like luggage left behind, the drawers are revealingly empty: once home to family secrets and worldly goods, they now contain only layers of liner paper and imprints from letters and photographs. But they are not anonymous. Working with neighborhood associations, Ms. Napoli found some of their owners. With a partner, she began an ambitious oral history and database, cataloging the lives of New Orleans residents through this most steadfast of possessions. ''My father surprised me with that cedar chest for my trousseau,'' one woman recalled; another kept her son's belongings in a drawer, decades after he was murdered. In ''Floodwall,'' comments like these are broadcast on LED signs as reminders of the lives these wooden survivors touched. (On the Liberty Street Bridge; enter at One World Financial Center on Liberty Street and South End Avenue, Lower Manhattan. Through Feb. 9. For more information or to be a part of the oral history project: floodwall.org.)</p>
        <p>MELENA RYZIK</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>FLOODWALL When Jana K. Napoli, an artist born and bred in New Orleans, returned to her hometown a few weeks after Hurricane Katrina hit, she sifted through the detritus in her neighborhood. She found sofas and pianos and hand-sewn lace, but she picked up only the abandoned dresser drawers. Originally she envisioned them as receptacles for a new project. But the more drawers she salvaged, the more she saw promise in them alone. “I began to realize that these drawers could be a symbol of the households that were lost,” Ms. Napoli said. She collected 700 drawers from across the city, meticulously labeling each with the address where it was found. They became the basis for “Floodwall,” above, an installation now on view on the Liberty Street Bridge, near the World Financial Center. Balanced along the span of the bridge like luggage left behind, the drawers are revealingly empty: once home to family secrets and worldly goods, they now contain only layers of liner paper and imprints from letters and photographs. But they are not anonymous. Working with neighborhood associations, Ms. Napoli found some of their owners. With a partner, she began an ambitious oral history and database, cataloging the lives of New Orleans residents through this most steadfast of possessions. “My father surprised me with that cedar chest for my trousseau,” one woman recalled; another kept her son’s belongings in a drawer, decades after he was murdered. In “Floodwall,” comments like these are broadcast on LED signs as reminders of the lives these wooden survivors touched. (On the Liberty Street Bridge; enter at One World Financial Center on Liberty Street and South End Avenue, Lower Manhattan. Through Feb. 9. For more information or to be a part of the oral history project: floodwall.org.).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Jana K. Napoli, an artist born and bred in New Orleans, returned to her hometown a few weeks after Hurricane Katrina hit, she sifted through the detritus in her neighborhood. She found sofas and pianos and hand-sewn lace, but she picked up only the abandoned dresser drawers. Originally she envisioned them as receptacles for a new project. But the more drawers she salvaged, the more she saw promise in them alone. ''I began to realize that these drawers could be a symbol of the households that were lost,'' Ms. Napoli said. She collected 700 drawers from across the city, meticulously labeling each with the address where it was found. They became the basis for ''Floodwall,'' above, an installation now on view on the Liberty Street Bridge, near the World Financial Center. Balanced along the span of the bridge like luggage left behind, the drawers are revealingly empty: once home to family secrets and worldly goods, they now contain only layers of liner paper and imprints from letters and photographs. But they are not anonymous. Working with neighborhood associations, Ms. Napoli found some of their owners. With a partner, she began an ambitious oral history and database, cataloging the lives of New Orleans residents through this most steadfast of possessions. ''My father surprised me with that cedar chest for my trousseau,'' one woman recalled; another kept her son's belongings in a drawer, decades after he was murdered. In ''Floodwall,'' comments like these are broadcast on LED signs as reminders of the lives these wooden survivors touched. (On the Liberty Street Bridge; enter at One World Financial Center on Liberty Street and South End Avenue, Lower Manhattan. Through Feb. 9. For more information or to be a part of the oral history project: floodwall.org.)</p>
        <p>MELENA RYZIK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
