<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CALENDAR</title>
    <meta content="14njlistingsNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1818747"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E0D61230F937A25752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2345" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CALENDAR</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on around the state this week. Items may be submitted by mail to On the Towns, Sunday New Jersey Section, The New York Times, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036; or by e-mail to njtowns@nytimes.com.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>Fort Lee ''Modern Times,'' with Charlie Chaplin. Thursday at 2 p.m. Free. Fort Lee Library, 320 Main Street. (201) 592-3614.  Jersey City African Diaspora Film Festival. Screening schedule and information: nyadff.org. Friday through Jan. 21. Reception: Jan. 21, 4 to 5 p.m. $6 and $8. Jersey City Museum, 250 Montgomery Street. (201) 413-0303.  Summit ''Waging a Living,'' documentary by Roger Weisberg. Monday, 10 to 11:30 a.m. Free. Christ Church, 561 Springfield Avenue. (908) 273-5549.  West Orange Annual West Orange Classic Film Festival, screenings of films including ''Lawrence of Arabia,'' ''Rear Window'' and ''Casablanca''; some screenings are followed by discussions of the films. Full schedule and information: westorangeartscouncil.org. Jan. 21 through March 15. $6 and $7. AMC Theater, Essex Green Shopping Center, (973) 324-9100.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>Asbury Park Harry and the Potters with Someone Still Loves You, Boris Yeltsin; a rock tribute to the books of J. K. Rowling. Jan. 14 at 3 p.m. $10. Asbury Lanes, 209 Fourth Avenue. (732) 776-6160.  Chatham ''Beauty and the Beast,'' presented by the Chatham Community Players' Fantasy Theater. Through Jan. 14. $8. Chatham Playhouse, 23 N. Passaic Ave. (973) 635-7363.  Newark ''Raps, Rhymes and Reasons,'' a look at African-American storytelling traditions with music, dance and stories; with Sharon McGruder. Jan. 20 at 2 p.m. Free. Newark Public Library, 5 Washington Street. (973) 733-7837.  North Branch Family Series: Mayhem Poets, performance poetry. Friday at 7 p.m. $20. Theater at Raritan Valley Community College, Route 28 and Lamington Road. (908) 725-3420.  Oaklyn ''Snow White and Rose Red,'' interactive play by the Improvisational Children's Theater Troupe. Thursday at 10 a.m.; Jan. 20 at 10 a.m. and 1 p.m. $7. Ritz Theater, 915 Whitehorse Pike. (856) 858-5230.  West Orange ''Schoolhouse Rock Live!'' Musical presented by Surflight Theater. Monday at 11 a.m. $10 and $14. JCC Metro West Center for the Arts, Maurice Levin Theater, 760 Northfield Ave. (973) 736-3200, Extension 253.  West Windsor Russian American Kids Circus. Jan. 20 at 2 and 4 p.m. $12. Kelsey Theater, West Windsor Campus, Mercer County Community College, 1200 Old Trenton Road. (609) 570-3333.</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE</p>
        <p>Bridgewater ''Three Benny Opera,'' annual Benny Goodman tribute, with Dan Levinson, Joe Midiri and Dan Block, clarinetists; presented by Jazz in Bridgewater. Jan. 20 at 2 and 8 p.m. $15 and $20. Somerset County Vocational and Technical School Auditorium, Vogt Drive at North Bridge Street. (908) 526-8900.  Cherry Hill Cellists of the Philadelphia Orchestra, classical and contemporary works. Jan. 21 at 3 p.m. $10 to $15. Croft Farm Arts Center, 100 Borton's Mill Road. (856) 488-7868.  Elmer Howard Jones, singer and songwriter. Jan. 20 at 8 p.m. $35. Appel Farm Arts and Music Center, 457 Shirley Road. (800) 394-1211.  Fort Lee Alan Namery's Jazz Focus, jazz quartet. Jan. 20 at 3 p.m. Free. Fort Lee Library, 320 Main Street. (201) 592-3614.  Lawrenceville Alberto Reyes, pianist; works by Beethoven and Chopin. Jan. 14 at 3 p.m. $8 and $15. Jacobs Music Recital Hall, 2540 Brunswick Pike. (609) 434-0222.  Montclair Peak Performances: Trisha Brown Dance Company. Thursday through Jan. 21. $35. Montclair State University Alexander Kasser Theater, Valley Road and Normal Avenue. (973) 655-5112.  Morristown The Burns Sisters, with the Rowan Brothers, folk. Friday at 8:30 p.m. $7. Minstrel Coffeehouse, Morristown Unitarian Fellowship, 21 Normandy Heights Road. (973) 335-9489.  Morristown Music at Noon: Brass Roots Trio. Thursday at 12:15 p.m. $5 and $6 suggested donation. Morristown United Methodist Church, 50 Park Place. (973) 538-2132.  Morristown Piano concert by students and alumni; works by Shumann, Beethoven, Chopin, Miles Davis and others. Friday at 7:30 p.m. Free. St. Mary's Abbey, Delbarton School, 230 Mendham Road. (973) 538-3231.  Morristown ''Neil Berg's 100 Years of Broadway,'' musical revue with Broadway performers. Friday at 8 p.m. $32 to $47. The Roches, folk. Jan. 20 at 8 p.m. $35. The Community Theater, 100 South St. (973) 539-8008.  New Brunswick Works by Brahms, Tchaikovsky and Wagner, by the Symphonica Toscanini; Lorin Maazel, conductor. Jan. 14 at 3 p.m. $45 to $75. State Theater, 15 Livingston Avenue. (732) 246-7469.  New Providence ''Crystl and Friends,'' with Crystl Baltazar, pianist, and others. Jan. 21 at 3 p.m. $6 and $12. NJ Youth Symphony/Music Center, 570 Central Avenue. (908) 771-5544.  Newton Willy Dalton, Vince Cherico and Mike DiLorenzo, jazz. Friday, 7 to 10 p.m. $10. Bula World Cuisine, 134 Spring Street. (973) 579-7338.  Princeton Garnet Rogers, folk. Friday at 8:15 p.m. $3 and $15. Christ Congregation Church, 50 Walnut Lane. (609) 799-0944.  Princeton Martin Luther King Jr. Day Celebration, with music, lectures and presentations; Stanley Jordan, jazz guitarist, and the Trenton Children's Chorus Covenant Singers with a choir from Princeton Day School. Monday at 1 p.m. Free. Richardson Auditorium, in Alexander Hall on the Princeton University Campus. (609) 258-3000.  Ringwood Tango concert, with Octavio Brunetti, pianist; Sergio Reyes, violinist, and Adam Tully, guitarist. Jan. 20 at 8 p.m. Free. Community Presbyterian Church, 145 Carletondale Road. (973) 962-9007.  Teaneck Scarecrow Collection with Josh Dion Band, rock. Jan. 20 at 9 p.m. $10. Mexicali Blues Cafe, 1409 Queen Anne Road. (201) 833-0011.  West Orange Jay Hoggard and Radam Schwartz Group, jazz. Friday through Jan. 20 at 9 p.m. $15. Cecil's Jazz Club and Restaurant, 364 Valley Road. (973) 736-4800.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>Blackwood ''The Underground Railroad: A Living History Experience,'' dramatization of the lives of Harriet Tubman and William Still, with music and a question-and-answer session. Friday at noon. Camden County College, 200 College Drive. (856) 227-7200.  Cranford ''Opening Nights on a Saturday Afternoon,'' staged reading series: ''The Understanding,'' by Rachel Rubin Ladutke, followed by a discussion with the author and cast; presented by the Theater Project. Jan. 20 at 3 p.m. Free. Union County College, 1033 Springfield Avenue. (908) 659-5189.  Long Branch ''October 1962,'' drama by D. W. Gregory. Through Jan. 28. $25 to $40. New Jersey Repertory Company, 179 Broadway. (732) 229-3166.  Millburn ''Summer and Smoke,'' drama by Tennessee Williams, with Amanda Plummer and Kevin Anderson. Through Feb. 11. $19 to $68. Paper Mill Playhouse, 3 Brookside Drive. (973) 376-4343.  New Brunswick ''I Am My Own Wife,'' one-man play by Doug Wright, with Mark Nelson. Tuesday through Feb. 11. $28 to $62. George Street Playhouse, 9 Livingston Avenue. (732) 246-7717.  New Brunswick ''Aida,'' musical by Elton John and Tim Rice. Friday at 8 p.m.; Jan. 20 at 3 and 8 p.m. $40 to $65. State Theater, 15 Livingston Avenue. (732) 246-7469.  Oaklyn ''Purlie,'' musical by Gary Geld, Ossie Davis, Peter Udell and Philip Rose. Through Feb. 10. $17 to $30. Ritz Theater, 915 Whitehorse Pike. (856) 858-5230.  Oradell ''Brooklyn Boy,'' comedy by David Margulies. Through Feb. 3. $15 and $18. Bergen County Players, Little Firehouse Theater, 298 Kinderkamack Road. (201) 261-4200.  Paramus ''Forbidden Broadway, SVU: A Musical Review,'' parody of Broadway shows. Jan. 20 at 7:30 p.m. $20 and $22. Bergen Community College, 400 Paramus Road. (201) 447-7428.  Pomona ''MacHomer,'' one-man parody of Shakespeare's ''Macbeth,'' with Rick Miller. Friday at 8 p.m. $25 and $40. Stockton Performing Arts Center, Richard Stockton College, Jim Leeds Road. (609) 652-9000.  Red Bank ''The Pavilion,'' by Craig Wright. Wednesday through Feb. 4. $30 to $54. Two River Theater, 21 Bridge Avenue. (732) 345-1400.  Teaneck ''Cheer from Chawton: A Jane Austen Family Theatrical,'' performed by Karen Eterovich. Jan. 14 at 3 p.m. $20 and $45. Becton Theater, Fairleigh Dickinson University, 960 River Road. (201) 569-7710.  Westfield ''Angel Street,'' thriller by Patrick Hamilton. Friday through Jan. 20. $15. Westfield Community Playhouse, 1000 North Avenue. (908) 232-1221.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>South Brunswick Cool Women, poetry performance group. Jan. 21 at 2 p.m. Nonperishable food donation. South Brunswick Public Library, 110 Kingston Lane. (732) 329-4000.</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>Asbury Park ''Winter and Other Seasonal Moments,'' photographs and paintings, group show. Through Feb. 25. Reception: Jan. 20, 6 to 9 p.m. Apex Gallery, 611 Cookman Avenue. (732) 776-7746.  Cape May ''Small Towns, Black Lives: African American Communities in New Jersey,'' photography by Wendel A. White. Jan. 14 through May 13. $1 and $2. Mid-Atlantic Center for the Arts, 1048 Washington Street. (609) 884-5404.  Clark Works by Karolina Szczepanska, Rafal Pisarczyk and Istvan T. Kristo Nagy. Through Feb. 11. Hours: Monday through Friday, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m.; 5 to 9 p.m. Skulski Art Gallery, 177 Broadway. (732) 382-7197.  Clinton ''War in the World: Artists Respond to the Last Five Years,'' and ''Tom Nussbaum, New York: Sculpture, Paper Cutouts, Drawings.'' Through March 25. Donation: $3. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Hunterdon Museum of Art, 7 Lower Center Street. (908) 735-8415.  Edison ''There's a Song in My Heart,'' Edison Arts Society statewide juried exhibition. Through May. Sheraton Edison Hotel, 125 Raritan Center Parkway. (908) 753-2787.  Hamilton ''New Jersey Perspective,'' photographs by Owen Kanzler and sculpture by Kate Graves. Through April 8. $1 to $12; members free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m., April through October; 10 a.m. to 6 p.m., November through March. Grounds for Sculpture, 18 Fairgrounds Road. (609) 586-0616.  Highland Park ''Graffitti Series,'' mixed media by Katja Valeur. Through Jan. 31. Hours: Mondays, Tuesdays and Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Wednesdays and Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 2 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Highland Park Public Library, 31 North Fifth Avenue. (732) 572-2750.  Hightstown Patty Chang, performance artist and videographer. Through Jan. 26. Peddie School, South Main and Ward Streets. (609) 490-7500.  Hopewell ''Mongolia: Where Kazakhs Hunt With Eagles,'' photography by David H. Miller. Through Feb. 4. Hours: Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Gallery 14, 14 Mercer Street. (609) 333-8511.  Lake Hopatcong ''Passage to Progress: The Morris Canal and the Transformation of Lake Hopatcong.'' Permanent. Hours: Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Historical Museum, Hopatcong State Park, off Route 80 West at Exit 28 in Landing. (973) 398-2616.  Lincroft African-American Stamp Art from the collection of Wanda Garbett. Through Feb. 18. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Monmouth Museum, Brookdale Community College, Newman Springs Road. (732) 747-2266.  Morristown ''Nast's Christmas Drawings,'' holiday illustrations. Through Jan. 28. $5 to $6; children ages 12 and under, free. Hours: Wednesdays, Thursdays and Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. Macculloch Hall Historical Museum, 45 Macculloch Avenue. (973) 538-2404.  New Brunswick ''Inviting Words Into the Image: Contemporary Prints from the Rutgers Archives for Printmaking Studios.'' Through Jan. 28. ''By Its Cover: Original Art for Children's Books.'' Through Feb. 4. ''Toulouse-Lautrec and the French Imprint: Fin-de-Siècle Posters in Paris, Brussels and Barcelona.'' Through Feb. 18. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Jane Voorhees Zimmerli Art Museum, 71 Hamilton Street. (732) 932-7237.  Newark '' ..but I was cool,'' works of three African-American artists. Through Jan. 20. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, noon to 6 p.m.; Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m. Aljira, A Center for Contemporary Art, 591 Broad Street. (973) 622-1600.  Newark ''1800Frames/Take3,'' video show. Through Friday. Hours: Daily, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. City Without Walls, 6 Crawford Street. (973) 622-1188.  Newark ''Masters of American Comics.'' Through Jan. 28. ''Portraits of Science Explorers by Mary Alice Copp.'' Through Feb. 18. ''Objects of Desire: 500 Years of Jewelry.'' Through Feb. 26. ''Expanding Africa: New Art, New Directions.'' Through March 18. $3 to $7; members, free. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, noon to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Newark Museum, 49 Washington Street. (973) 596-6550.  Newark ''Night of the Khmer Rouge: Genocide and Justice in Cambodia,'' photographic documents, film and records. Tuesday through Feb. 22. Reception: Jan. 24, 5 to 8 p.m. Paul Robeson Campus Center, Rutgers University - Newark Campus, 350 Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. Blvd. (973) 353-5300.  Plainfield ''Intimate Images,'' mixed-media show by Salomon Kadoche. Through Jan. 31. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 9:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.; Saturdays, to 4 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Swain Galleries, 703 Watchung Avenue. (908) 756-1707.  Princeton ''A New Jersey Treasure: The Large House in Miniature.'' Through March 20. $5 with parking. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Morven Museum and Garden, 55 Stockton Street. (609) 924-8144.  Princeton Township ''Princeton's Civil War,'' images and newspaper accounts. Through July 15. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Historical Society, 158 Nassau Street. (609) 921-6748.  Rahway ''The Naked Truth: Quilted and Sewn Figurative Works and Nudes,'' traditional quilting techniques. Through Feb. 9. Hours: Wednesdays, Fridays and Saturdays, 1 to 4 p.m.; Thursdays, 1 to 3 p.m. and 5 to 7 p.m. Arts Guild of Rahway, 1670 Irving Street. (732) 381-7511.  Skillman ''Science as Muse: Eight Artistic Riffs on Science and Technology,'' curated by Sally Davidson and Alan Goldsmith. Through Feb. 4. The 1860 House, 124 Montgomery Road. (609) 921-3272.  Summit Emerging Artists Series: ''First Look 2007,'' sculpture curated by Rasika Reddy and Janan Weber. Through Jan. 26. Free. Art Upstairs Gallery Exhibit. Award-winning works by the Community Theater's Art Upstairs Gallery. Through Feb. 10. Hours: Mondays through Thursdays, 9:30 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Fridays, 9:30 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Visual Arts Center of New Jersey, 68 Elm Street. (908) 273-9121.  Tenafly ''A Life of Bliss in Photography,'' photographs by Samuel Needelman. Through Jan. 26. JCC on the Palisades, 411 East Clinton Avenue. (212) 420-8080.  Upper Montclair ''Polish Modern Masters,'' An exhibition of works by prominent Polish artists. Through Feb. 28. J. K. K. Fine Arts, 594 Valley Road. (973) 744-0111.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on around the state this week. Items may be submitted by mail to On the Towns, Sunday New Jersey Section, The New York Times, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036; or by e-mail to njtowns@nytimes.com.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>Fort Lee ''Modern Times,'' with Charlie Chaplin. Thursday at 2 p.m. Free. Fort Lee Library, 320 Main Street. (201) 592-3614.  Jersey City African Diaspora Film Festival. Screening schedule and information: nyadff.org. Friday through Jan. 21. Reception: Jan. 21, 4 to 5 p.m. $6 and $8. Jersey City Museum, 250 Montgomery Street. (201) 413-0303.  Summit ''Waging a Living,'' documentary by Roger Weisberg. Monday, 10 to 11:30 a.m. Free. Christ Church, 561 Springfield Avenue. (908) 273-5549.  West Orange Annual West Orange Classic Film Festival, screenings of films including ''Lawrence of Arabia,'' ''Rear Window'' and ''Casablanca''; some screenings are followed by discussions of the films. Full schedule and information: westorangeartscouncil.org. Jan. 21 through March 15. $6 and $7. AMC Theater, Essex Green Shopping Center, (973) 324-9100.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>Asbury Park Harry and the Potters with Someone Still Loves You, Boris Yeltsin; a rock tribute to the books of J. K. Rowling. Jan. 14 at 3 p.m. $10. Asbury Lanes, 209 Fourth Avenue. (732) 776-6160.  Chatham ''Beauty and the Beast,'' presented by the Chatham Community Players' Fantasy Theater. Through Jan. 14. $8. Chatham Playhouse, 23 N. Passaic Ave. (973) 635-7363.  Newark ''Raps, Rhymes and Reasons,'' a look at African-American storytelling traditions with music, dance and stories; with Sharon McGruder. Jan. 20 at 2 p.m. Free. Newark Public Library, 5 Washington Street. (973) 733-7837.  North Branch Family Series: Mayhem Poets, performance poetry. Friday at 7 p.m. $20. Theater at Raritan Valley Community College, Route 28 and Lamington Road. (908) 725-3420.  Oaklyn ''Snow White and Rose Red,'' interactive play by the Improvisational Children's Theater Troupe. Thursday at 10 a.m.; Jan. 20 at 10 a.m. and 1 p.m. $7. Ritz Theater, 915 Whitehorse Pike. (856) 858-5230.  West Orange ''Schoolhouse Rock Live!'' Musical presented by Surflight Theater. Monday at 11 a.m. $10 and $14. JCC Metro West Center for the Arts, Maurice Levin Theater, 760 Northfield Ave. (973) 736-3200, Extension 253.  West Windsor Russian American Kids Circus. Jan. 20 at 2 and 4 p.m. $12. Kelsey Theater, West Windsor Campus, Mercer County Community College, 1200 Old Trenton Road. (609) 570-3333.</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE</p>
        <p>Bridgewater ''Three Benny Opera,'' annual Benny Goodman tribute, with Dan Levinson, Joe Midiri and Dan Block, clarinetists; presented by Jazz in Bridgewater. Jan. 20 at 2 and 8 p.m. $15 and $20. Somerset County Vocational and Technical School Auditorium, Vogt Drive at North Bridge Street. (908) 526-8900.  Cherry Hill Cellists of the Philadelphia Orchestra, classical and contemporary works. Jan. 21 at 3 p.m. $10 to $15. Croft Farm Arts Center, 100 Borton's Mill Road. (856) 488-7868.  Elmer Howard Jones, singer and songwriter. Jan. 20 at 8 p.m. $35. Appel Farm Arts and Music Center, 457 Shirley Road. (800) 394-1211.  Fort Lee Alan Namery's Jazz Focus, jazz quartet. Jan. 20 at 3 p.m. Free. Fort Lee Library, 320 Main Street. (201) 592-3614.  Lawrenceville Alberto Reyes, pianist; works by Beethoven and Chopin. Jan. 14 at 3 p.m. $8 and $15. Jacobs Music Recital Hall, 2540 Brunswick Pike. (609) 434-0222.  Montclair Peak Performances: Trisha Brown Dance Company. Thursday through Jan. 21. $35. Montclair State University Alexander Kasser Theater, Valley Road and Normal Avenue. (973) 655-5112.  Morristown The Burns Sisters, with the Rowan Brothers, folk. Friday at 8:30 p.m. $7. Minstrel Coffeehouse, Morristown Unitarian Fellowship, 21 Normandy Heights Road. (973) 335-9489.  Morristown Music at Noon: Brass Roots Trio. Thursday at 12:15 p.m. $5 and $6 suggested donation. Morristown United Methodist Church, 50 Park Place. (973) 538-2132.  Morristown Piano concert by students and alumni; works by Shumann, Beethoven, Chopin, Miles Davis and others. Friday at 7:30 p.m. Free. St. Mary's Abbey, Delbarton School, 230 Mendham Road. (973) 538-3231.  Morristown ''Neil Berg's 100 Years of Broadway,'' musical revue with Broadway performers. Friday at 8 p.m. $32 to $47. The Roches, folk. Jan. 20 at 8 p.m. $35. The Community Theater, 100 South St. (973) 539-8008.  New Brunswick Works by Brahms, Tchaikovsky and Wagner, by the Symphonica Toscanini; Lorin Maazel, conductor. Jan. 14 at 3 p.m. $45 to $75. State Theater, 15 Livingston Avenue. (732) 246-7469.  New Providence ''Crystl and Friends,'' with Crystl Baltazar, pianist, and others. Jan. 21 at 3 p.m. $6 and $12. NJ Youth Symphony/Music Center, 570 Central Avenue. (908) 771-5544.  Newton Willy Dalton, Vince Cherico and Mike DiLorenzo, jazz. Friday, 7 to 10 p.m. $10. Bula World Cuisine, 134 Spring Street. (973) 579-7338.  Princeton Garnet Rogers, folk. Friday at 8:15 p.m. $3 and $15. Christ Congregation Church, 50 Walnut Lane. (609) 799-0944.  Princeton Martin Luther King Jr. Day Celebration, with music, lectures and presentations; Stanley Jordan, jazz guitarist, and the Trenton Children's Chorus Covenant Singers with a choir from Princeton Day School. Monday at 1 p.m. Free. Richardson Auditorium, in Alexander Hall on the Princeton University Campus. (609) 258-3000.  Ringwood Tango concert, with Octavio Brunetti, pianist; Sergio Reyes, violinist, and Adam Tully, guitarist. Jan. 20 at 8 p.m. Free. Community Presbyterian Church, 145 Carletondale Road. (973) 962-9007.  Teaneck Scarecrow Collection with Josh Dion Band, rock. Jan. 20 at 9 p.m. $10. Mexicali Blues Cafe, 1409 Queen Anne Road. (201) 833-0011.  West Orange Jay Hoggard and Radam Schwartz Group, jazz. Friday through Jan. 20 at 9 p.m. $15. Cecil's Jazz Club and Restaurant, 364 Valley Road. (973) 736-4800.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>Blackwood ''The Underground Railroad: A Living History Experience,'' dramatization of the lives of Harriet Tubman and William Still, with music and a question-and-answer session. Friday at noon. Camden County College, 200 College Drive. (856) 227-7200.  Cranford ''Opening Nights on a Saturday Afternoon,'' staged reading series: ''The Understanding,'' by Rachel Rubin Ladutke, followed by a discussion with the author and cast; presented by the Theater Project. Jan. 20 at 3 p.m. Free. Union County College, 1033 Springfield Avenue. (908) 659-5189.  Long Branch ''October 1962,'' drama by D. W. Gregory. Through Jan. 28. $25 to $40. New Jersey Repertory Company, 179 Broadway. (732) 229-3166.  Millburn ''Summer and Smoke,'' drama by Tennessee Williams, with Amanda Plummer and Kevin Anderson. Through Feb. 11. $19 to $68. Paper Mill Playhouse, 3 Brookside Drive. (973) 376-4343.  New Brunswick ''I Am My Own Wife,'' one-man play by Doug Wright, with Mark Nelson. Tuesday through Feb. 11. $28 to $62. George Street Playhouse, 9 Livingston Avenue. (732) 246-7717.  New Brunswick ''Aida,'' musical by Elton John and Tim Rice. Friday at 8 p.m.; Jan. 20 at 3 and 8 p.m. $40 to $65. State Theater, 15 Livingston Avenue. (732) 246-7469.  Oaklyn ''Purlie,'' musical by Gary Geld, Ossie Davis, Peter Udell and Philip Rose. Through Feb. 10. $17 to $30. Ritz Theater, 915 Whitehorse Pike. (856) 858-5230.  Oradell ''Brooklyn Boy,'' comedy by David Margulies. Through Feb. 3. $15 and $18. Bergen County Players, Little Firehouse Theater, 298 Kinderkamack Road. (201) 261-4200.  Paramus ''Forbidden Broadway, SVU: A Musical Review,'' parody of Broadway shows. Jan. 20 at 7:30 p.m. $20 and $22. Bergen Community College, 400 Paramus Road. (201) 447-7428.  Pomona ''MacHomer,'' one-man parody of Shakespeare's ''Macbeth,'' with Rick Miller. Friday at 8 p.m. $25 and $40. Stockton Performing Arts Center, Richard Stockton College, Jim Leeds Road. (609) 652-9000.  Red Bank ''The Pavilion,'' by Craig Wright. Wednesday through Feb. 4. $30 to $54. Two River Theater, 21 Bridge Avenue. (732) 345-1400.  Teaneck ''Cheer from Chawton: A Jane Austen Family Theatrical,'' performed by Karen Eterovich. Jan. 14 at 3 p.m. $20 and $45. Becton Theater, Fairleigh Dickinson University, 960 River Road. (201) 569-7710.  Westfield ''Angel Street,'' thriller by Patrick Hamilton. Friday through Jan. 20. $15. Westfield Community Playhouse, 1000 North Avenue. (908) 232-1221.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>South Brunswick Cool Women, poetry performance group. Jan. 21 at 2 p.m. Nonperishable food donation. South Brunswick Public Library, 110 Kingston Lane. (732) 329-4000.</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>Asbury Park ''Winter and Other Seasonal Moments,'' photographs and paintings, group show. Through Feb. 25. Reception: Jan. 20, 6 to 9 p.m. Apex Gallery, 611 Cookman Avenue. (732) 776-7746.  Cape May ''Small Towns, Black Lives: African American Communities in New Jersey,'' photography by Wendel A. White. Jan. 14 through May 13. $1 and $2. Mid-Atlantic Center for the Arts, 1048 Washington Street. (609) 884-5404.  Clark Works by Karolina Szczepanska, Rafal Pisarczyk and Istvan T. Kristo Nagy. Through Feb. 11. Hours: Monday through Friday, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m.; 5 to 9 p.m. Skulski Art Gallery, 177 Broadway. (732) 382-7197.  Clinton ''War in the World: Artists Respond to the Last Five Years,'' and ''Tom Nussbaum, New York: Sculpture, Paper Cutouts, Drawings.'' Through March 25. Donation: $3. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Hunterdon Museum of Art, 7 Lower Center Street. (908) 735-8415.  Edison ''There's a Song in My Heart,'' Edison Arts Society statewide juried exhibition. Through May. Sheraton Edison Hotel, 125 Raritan Center Parkway. (908) 753-2787.  Hamilton ''New Jersey Perspective,'' photographs by Owen Kanzler and sculpture by Kate Graves. Through April 8. $1 to $12; members free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m., April through October; 10 a.m. to 6 p.m., November through March. Grounds for Sculpture, 18 Fairgrounds Road. (609) 586-0616.  Highland Park ''Graffitti Series,'' mixed media by Katja Valeur. Through Jan. 31. Hours: Mondays, Tuesdays and Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Wednesdays and Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 2 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Highland Park Public Library, 31 North Fifth Avenue. (732) 572-2750.  Hightstown Patty Chang, performance artist and videographer. Through Jan. 26. Peddie School, South Main and Ward Streets. (609) 490-7500.  Hopewell ''Mongolia: Where Kazakhs Hunt With Eagles,'' photography by David H. Miller. Through Feb. 4. Hours: Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Gallery 14, 14 Mercer Street. (609) 333-8511.  Lake Hopatcong ''Passage to Progress: The Morris Canal and the Transformation of Lake Hopatcong.'' Permanent. Hours: Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Historical Museum, Hopatcong State Park, off Route 80 West at Exit 28 in Landing. (973) 398-2616.  Lincroft African-American Stamp Art from the collection of Wanda Garbett. Through Feb. 18. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Monmouth Museum, Brookdale Community College, Newman Springs Road. (732) 747-2266.  Morristown ''Nast's Christmas Drawings,'' holiday illustrations. Through Jan. 28. $5 to $6; children ages 12 and under, free. Hours: Wednesdays, Thursdays and Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. Macculloch Hall Historical Museum, 45 Macculloch Avenue. (973) 538-2404.  New Brunswick ''Inviting Words Into the Image: Contemporary Prints from the Rutgers Archives for Printmaking Studios.'' Through Jan. 28. ''By Its Cover: Original Art for Children's Books.'' Through Feb. 4. ''Toulouse-Lautrec and the French Imprint: Fin-de-Siècle Posters in Paris, Brussels and Barcelona.'' Through Feb. 18. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Jane Voorhees Zimmerli Art Museum, 71 Hamilton Street. (732) 932-7237.  Newark '' ..but I was cool,'' works of three African-American artists. Through Jan. 20. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, noon to 6 p.m.; Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m. Aljira, A Center for Contemporary Art, 591 Broad Street. (973) 622-1600.  Newark ''1800Frames/Take3,'' video show. Through Friday. Hours: Daily, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. City Without Walls, 6 Crawford Street. (973) 622-1188.  Newark ''Masters of American Comics.'' Through Jan. 28. ''Portraits of Science Explorers by Mary Alice Copp.'' Through Feb. 18. ''Objects of Desire: 500 Years of Jewelry.'' Through Feb. 26. ''Expanding Africa: New Art, New Directions.'' Through March 18. $3 to $7; members, free. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, noon to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Newark Museum, 49 Washington Street. (973) 596-6550.  Newark ''Night of the Khmer Rouge: Genocide and Justice in Cambodia,'' photographic documents, film and records. Tuesday through Feb. 22. Reception: Jan. 24, 5 to 8 p.m. Paul Robeson Campus Center, Rutgers University - Newark Campus, 350 Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. Blvd. (973) 353-5300.  Plainfield ''Intimate Images,'' mixed-media show by Salomon Kadoche. Through Jan. 31. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 9:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.; Saturdays, to 4 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Swain Galleries, 703 Watchung Avenue. (908) 756-1707.  Princeton ''A New Jersey Treasure: The Large House in Miniature.'' Through March 20. $5 with parking. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Morven Museum and Garden, 55 Stockton Street. (609) 924-8144.  Princeton Township ''Princeton's Civil War,'' images and newspaper accounts. Through July 15. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Historical Society, 158 Nassau Street. (609) 921-6748.  Rahway ''The Naked Truth: Quilted and Sewn Figurative Works and Nudes,'' traditional quilting techniques. Through Feb. 9. Hours: Wednesdays, Fridays and Saturdays, 1 to 4 p.m.; Thursdays, 1 to 3 p.m. and 5 to 7 p.m. Arts Guild of Rahway, 1670 Irving Street. (732) 381-7511.  Skillman ''Science as Muse: Eight Artistic Riffs on Science and Technology,'' curated by Sally Davidson and Alan Goldsmith. Through Feb. 4. The 1860 House, 124 Montgomery Road. (609) 921-3272.  Summit Emerging Artists Series: ''First Look 2007,'' sculpture curated by Rasika Reddy and Janan Weber. Through Jan. 26. Free. Art Upstairs Gallery Exhibit. Award-winning works by the Community Theater's Art Upstairs Gallery. Through Feb. 10. Hours: Mondays through Thursdays, 9:30 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Fridays, 9:30 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Visual Arts Center of New Jersey, 68 Elm Street. (908) 273-9121.  Tenafly ''A Life of Bliss in Photography,'' photographs by Samuel Needelman. Through Jan. 26. JCC on the Palisades, 411 East Clinton Avenue. (212) 420-8080.  Upper Montclair ''Polish Modern Masters,'' An exhibition of works by prominent Polish artists. Through Feb. 28. J. K. K. Fine Arts, 594 Valley Road. (973) 744-0111.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
