<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Scottsdale, Ariz.</title>
    <meta content="14hours" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/14/travel/14hours.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1818628"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="36 HOURS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Scottsdale (Ariz)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Arizona</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinhauer, Jennifer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/36 Hours</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Luxury and Vacations/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Spas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona/Scottsdale</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona/Phoenix</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Spas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Spas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Scottsdale (Ariz)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Phoenix (Ariz)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E3D91530F937A25752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1578" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Scottsdale, Ariz.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">36 Hours in Scottsdale, Ariz.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER STEINHAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinhauer, Jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jenifer Steinhauer travel article on 36-hour visit to Scottsdale, Ariz; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT might be tempting a curse from the golf gods to enter the Scottsdale city limits without a set of clubs. But it's easy to spend a full weekend here far from the fairways. Just east of Phoenix, Scottsdale was once home to the Hohokam Indians; it was founded in the 1880s by Winfield Scott, an Army chaplain who bought land to farm sweet potatoes. Today, Scottsdale is associated less with farming than with Frank Lloyd Wright, massage therapists and outdoor sports. Wright's influence can be seen in much of the architecture, though a lot of it sits in the shadows of the telltale cranes erecting condos in this ever-expanding region of the West. Golf, if you wish. Or eat, explore and then float in an infinity pool, contemplating your next cocktail.</p>
        <p>Friday</p>
        <p>7:30 p.m.  1. Starry, Starry Meal  Pay attention on your way to the Star Spangled Tavern (20751 North Pima Road; 480-419-8729; www.starspangledtavern.us), the newest offering from the restaurateurs who created the tiny but popular restaurant row in downtown Scottsdale. The shopping development where this Americana-themed restaurant sits in DC Ranch, an upscale (yes, golf) community in north Scottsdale, can be easy to miss in the dark. Once there, sit under the open sky on the patio and order a flight of wines, like the John Wayne (an array of wines from California, $24), or cold apple cider served in a mason jar ($3). Try the crabby fried green tomatoes ($13), Queen Creek pork chop with creamed corn pudding ($25) and the warm apple and cranberry crisp with brown sugar ice cream ($9). Next door is the Baroque Luxe Lounge, for those who love Champagne, but the scene is a bit snoozy.</p>
        <p>10 p.m.  2. Exotic Vintages  Spurn the Baroque, and seek out Kazimierz World Wine Bar (7137 East Stetson Drive, 480-946-3004; www.kazbar.net). Known as the Kaz Bar, it has all the trappings of hipness -- no sign over the door (which is in the back), sofas and a crowd of varying ages and sexual orientation. There are some 2,900 wines from more than 40 nations available -- yes, this is the place to find that elusive Thracian Valley merlot from Bulgaria. And there is live music after 9 p.m. Cavelike and featuring the occasional moment of decoupage on the wall, Kaz Bar makes for good people watching.</p>
        <p>Saturday</p>
        <p>8 a.m.  3. A Plan Over Pancakes  Scottsdale offers many breakfast options, from the kitschy -- Pischke's Paradise (7217 East First Street, 480-481-0067) -- to the mall-based, like Orange Table Cafe (7373 Scottsdale Mall, 408-424-6819). But the coffee is strong and the banana buttermilk pancakes ($8) yummy at Cafe ZuZu in the Hotel Valley Ho (6850 East Main Street, 480-248-2000; www.hotelvalleyho.com). Sit in the supermodern chairs or comfy booths and plot potential misadventures.</p>
        <p>9:30 a.m.  4. Rising Above It All  Work off the wine and pancakes in the Phoenix Mountains Preserve, where hikes of varying degrees of difficulty are plentiful. Huffing up the summit trail of Piestewa Peak in the preserve's northeast district, one alternately dodges or is dodged by sinewy athletes zipping along alone or tourists in the wrong shoes doing their best not to pass out. Hikers climb nearly 1,200 feet in elevation on this moderately difficult trail. Look for saguaro cactuses and coyotes. The trailhead is in the parking lot at the first driveway on the left in Phoenix Mountains Park and Recreation Area: east on Squaw Peak Drive from Lincoln Drive between 22nd and 24th Streets. For more information on hikes in the preserve, log on to www.phoenix.gov/parks or call (602) 495-5458.</p>
        <p>Noon  5. A Bit of the Old West  Stroll through Old Town (roughly Second Street to Fourth Street, north to south; Scottsdale Road to Drinkwater Boulevard, west to east), where scores of galleries display everything from works of the masters to American Indian jewelry to large contemporary paintings by local artists. There, too, is questionable Western-themed statuary, store names with puns (Coyo-T's) and the obligatory wind chimes and dried chili peppers lilting and listing in the breeze. Of interest nearby is Guidon Books (7117 East Main Street, 480-945-8811; www.guidon.com), which specializes in out-of-print Western Americana and Civil War volumes.</p>
        <p>1 p.m.  6. Then a Taste of the East  While you are in the neighborhood, do as the local residents do and hit Malee's Thai Bistro (7131 East Main Street; 480-947-6042; www.maleesthaibistro.com), a softly lighted room that muffles the sun-drenched action outside. The best bets are the tofu spinach pot stickers ($7.95), evil jungle princess (a pile of chicken doused in coconut cream with mushrooms and fresh mint, $12.25), and the reliable pad Thai ($13.25).</p>
        <p>2:30 p.m.  7. There's Always the Rub  The ways to get pummeled, peeled and rubbed in Scottsdale are endless, and there seems to be an almost Constitutional obligation to do so. From the shoulder rubs at the most commonplace hair salons to the in-room ''ceremonies'' featuring 100 percent freeze-dried seawater (30 minutes, $85) for guests at the gorgeous Sanctuary Spa at the Camelback Mountain Resort and Spa (5700 East McDonald Drive, 480-948-2100; www.sanctuaryoncamelback.com), there is something for every (reasonably generous) budget. Right in the middle is the VH Spa for Vitality and Health at the Hotel Valley Ho (www.hotelvalleyho.com), where the Back, Neck, Shoulders massage was heaven (45 minutes, $95, not counting an automatic 20 percent tip) and the Oh! So Cool Foot Refresher (30 minutes, $65) can literally put you to sleep. The spa even offers treatments for dog guests: a canine massage, 30 minutes for $85.</p>
        <p>5 p.m.  8. Serenity, Inside and Out  Start dinner right at Elements (480-607-2300, www.elementsrestaurant.com), which is at the Sanctuary resort, by angling for just the right seat on the patio at the Jade Bar, where you can watch the sunset while eavesdropping on first-daters as you munch on wasabi-covered peanuts. This moment is best paired with an Asian pear cucumber and ginger martini ($14) or a glass of sparkling rose ($20). Those looking to impress might order the $55 margarita, but we're not sure why. You will want to ask for a window booth inside the restaurant, where the chef, Beau MacMillan, cooks up seasonal fare as you take in Paradise Valley. The view is really the main course, but there are some standout offerings on the changing menu, like grilled salmon ($27), carrot and millet pot stickers ($11) and a diabolical banana Fluffernutter sundae ($10). The Zen-like setting with stone and fireplaces is serene.</p>
        <p>8:30 p.m.  9. Luck Would Be Nice  Somewhere, say, between the glitz of the Venetian casino in Las Vegas and the smoke-choked spots on the Mississippi coast is Casino Arizona 101 &amp; Indian Bend (9700 East Indian Bend Road; 480-850-7777; www.casinoaz.com), a low-key gambling hall run by the Salt River Pima-Maricopa Indians. Try your luck at blackjack (minimum bets range from $5 to $25), or develop a case of repetitive stress injury by yanking on the slots as a cover band oozes the hits of Lionel Richie.</p>
        <p>Sunday</p>
        <p>9:30 a.m.  10. The Architect's Home  Do not miss Taliesin West, the international headquarters for the Frank Lloyd Wright Foundation and the winter campus for the Frank Lloyd Wright School of Architecture (12621 Frank Lloyd Wright Boulevard; 480-860-2700; www.franklloydwright.org). Troubled by poor health, Wright took up half-year residence in this 600-acre ''camp'' in 1937, and the complex was built by apprentices. Take the 90-minute tour, (9 a.m. to 4 p.m. daily on the half-hour for $22.50, children 4 to 12 $15) which takes you through the living quarters, working areas and outdoor spaces that incorporate indigenous materials and organic forms. Then there's all that Asian art.</p>
        <p>Noon  11. Exit Strategy  It's not quite Scottsdale, but just a few exits past the off ramp for the airport on Route 202 is the Phoenix Ranch Market, (1602 East Roosevelt Street, Phoenix; 602-254-6676) a 53,000-square-foot emporium of groceries featuring a food court full of Mexican goodies. One of the best meals around -- and, without a doubt, the best bargain -- is the three tacos for $2.89, with pork or beef or chicken decorated with cheese and cilantro for a tasty goodbye.</p>
        <p>THE BASICS</p>
        <p>Many airlines serve Phoenix Sky Harbor Airport. Carriers with nonstops from from the New York City area include JetBlue, US Airways, Continental and America West. Southwest goes nonstop from Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>The Hotel Valley Ho (6850 East Main Street; 866-882-4484; www.hotelvalleyho.com) is an inviting mid-20th-century hotel made chic by a 2004 renovation. It has a nice, low-key spa, a pool, a Trader Vic's restaurant and the cute Cafe ZuZu. It's within walking distance of Old Town Scottsdale. Rooms start at $259 at this time of year, excluding tax and parking.</p>
        <p>Sanctuary Camelback Mountain Resort and Spa (5700 East McDonald Drive, Paradise Valley; 800-245-2051; www.sanctuaryoncamelback.com) is a former tennis ranch that has become a truly secluded and elegant spot with its infinity pool and serene spa. The rooms are contemporary with Asian accents, wood-burning fireplaces and canopy beds. Rooms start at $495 in high season, excluding tax and parking.</p>
        <p>The 3 Palms Resort Oasis (7707 East McDowell Road; 800-450-8133; www.scottsdale-resort-hotels.com) is a good budget option, with rooms starting at $129 in late January. This contemporary low-rise hotel offers a few things that budget hotels often do not, like views of Camelback Mountain from some rooms, 400-thread-count sheets, down comforters and shuttle service within five miles of the property.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It might be tempting a curse from the golf gods to enter the city limits without a set of clubs, but it’s easy to spend a full weekend here far from the fairways.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT might be tempting a curse from the golf gods to enter the Scottsdale city limits without a set of clubs. But it's easy to spend a full weekend here far from the fairways. Just east of Phoenix, Scottsdale was once home to the Hohokam Indians; it was founded in the 1880s by Winfield Scott, an Army chaplain who bought land to farm sweet potatoes. Today, Scottsdale is associated less with farming than with Frank Lloyd Wright, massage therapists and outdoor sports. Wright's influence can be seen in much of the architecture, though a lot of it sits in the shadows of the telltale cranes erecting condos in this ever-expanding region of the West. Golf, if you wish. Or eat, explore and then float in an infinity pool, contemplating your next cocktail.</p>
        <p>Friday</p>
        <p>7:30 p.m.  1. Starry, Starry Meal  Pay attention on your way to the Star Spangled Tavern (20751 North Pima Road; 480-419-8729; www.starspangledtavern.us), the newest offering from the restaurateurs who created the tiny but popular restaurant row in downtown Scottsdale. The shopping development where this Americana-themed restaurant sits in DC Ranch, an upscale (yes, golf) community in north Scottsdale, can be easy to miss in the dark. Once there, sit under the open sky on the patio and order a flight of wines, like the John Wayne (an array of wines from California, $24), or cold apple cider served in a mason jar ($3). Try the crabby fried green tomatoes ($13), Queen Creek pork chop with creamed corn pudding ($25) and the warm apple and cranberry crisp with brown sugar ice cream ($9). Next door is the Baroque Luxe Lounge, for those who love Champagne, but the scene is a bit snoozy.</p>
        <p>10 p.m.  2. Exotic Vintages  Spurn the Baroque, and seek out Kazimierz World Wine Bar (7137 East Stetson Drive, 480-946-3004; www.kazbar.net). Known as the Kaz Bar, it has all the trappings of hipness -- no sign over the door (which is in the back), sofas and a crowd of varying ages and sexual orientation. There are some 2,900 wines from more than 40 nations available -- yes, this is the place to find that elusive Thracian Valley merlot from Bulgaria. And there is live music after 9 p.m. Cavelike and featuring the occasional moment of decoupage on the wall, Kaz Bar makes for good people watching.</p>
        <p>Saturday</p>
        <p>8 a.m.  3. A Plan Over Pancakes  Scottsdale offers many breakfast options, from the kitschy -- Pischke's Paradise (7217 East First Street, 480-481-0067) -- to the mall-based, like Orange Table Cafe (7373 Scottsdale Mall, 408-424-6819). But the coffee is strong and the banana buttermilk pancakes ($8) yummy at Cafe ZuZu in the Hotel Valley Ho (6850 East Main Street, 480-248-2000; www.hotelvalleyho.com). Sit in the supermodern chairs or comfy booths and plot potential misadventures.</p>
        <p>9:30 a.m.  4. Rising Above It All  Work off the wine and pancakes in the Phoenix Mountains Preserve, where hikes of varying degrees of difficulty are plentiful. Huffing up the summit trail of Piestewa Peak in the preserve's northeast district, one alternately dodges or is dodged by sinewy athletes zipping along alone or tourists in the wrong shoes doing their best not to pass out. Hikers climb nearly 1,200 feet in elevation on this moderately difficult trail. Look for saguaro cactuses and coyotes. The trailhead is in the parking lot at the first driveway on the left in Phoenix Mountains Park and Recreation Area: east on Squaw Peak Drive from Lincoln Drive between 22nd and 24th Streets. For more information on hikes in the preserve, log on to www.phoenix.gov/parks or call (602) 495-5458.</p>
        <p>Noon  5. A Bit of the Old West  Stroll through Old Town (roughly Second Street to Fourth Street, north to south; Scottsdale Road to Drinkwater Boulevard, west to east), where scores of galleries display everything from works of the masters to American Indian jewelry to large contemporary paintings by local artists. There, too, is questionable Western-themed statuary, store names with puns (Coyo-T's) and the obligatory wind chimes and dried chili peppers lilting and listing in the breeze. Of interest nearby is Guidon Books (7117 East Main Street, 480-945-8811; www.guidon.com), which specializes in out-of-print Western Americana and Civil War volumes.</p>
        <p>1 p.m.  6. Then a Taste of the East  While you are in the neighborhood, do as the local residents do and hit Malee's Thai Bistro (7131 East Main Street; 480-947-6042; www.maleesthaibistro.com), a softly lighted room that muffles the sun-drenched action outside. The best bets are the tofu spinach pot stickers ($7.95), evil jungle princess (a pile of chicken doused in coconut cream with mushrooms and fresh mint, $12.25), and the reliable pad Thai ($13.25).</p>
        <p>2:30 p.m.  7. There's Always the Rub  The ways to get pummeled, peeled and rubbed in Scottsdale are endless, and there seems to be an almost Constitutional obligation to do so. From the shoulder rubs at the most commonplace hair salons to the in-room ''ceremonies'' featuring 100 percent freeze-dried seawater (30 minutes, $85) for guests at the gorgeous Sanctuary Spa at the Camelback Mountain Resort and Spa (5700 East McDonald Drive, 480-948-2100; www.sanctuaryoncamelback.com), there is something for every (reasonably generous) budget. Right in the middle is the VH Spa for Vitality and Health at the Hotel Valley Ho (www.hotelvalleyho.com), where the Back, Neck, Shoulders massage was heaven (45 minutes, $95, not counting an automatic 20 percent tip) and the Oh! So Cool Foot Refresher (30 minutes, $65) can literally put you to sleep. The spa even offers treatments for dog guests: a canine massage, 30 minutes for $85.</p>
        <p>5 p.m.  8. Serenity, Inside and Out  Start dinner right at Elements (480-607-2300, www.elementsrestaurant.com), which is at the Sanctuary resort, by angling for just the right seat on the patio at the Jade Bar, where you can watch the sunset while eavesdropping on first-daters as you munch on wasabi-covered peanuts. This moment is best paired with an Asian pear cucumber and ginger martini ($14) or a glass of sparkling rose ($20). Those looking to impress might order the $55 margarita, but we're not sure why. You will want to ask for a window booth inside the restaurant, where the chef, Beau MacMillan, cooks up seasonal fare as you take in Paradise Valley. The view is really the main course, but there are some standout offerings on the changing menu, like grilled salmon ($27), carrot and millet pot stickers ($11) and a diabolical banana Fluffernutter sundae ($10). The Zen-like setting with stone and fireplaces is serene.</p>
        <p>8:30 p.m.  9. Luck Would Be Nice  Somewhere, say, between the glitz of the Venetian casino in Las Vegas and the smoke-choked spots on the Mississippi coast is Casino Arizona 101 &amp; Indian Bend (9700 East Indian Bend Road; 480-850-7777; www.casinoaz.com), a low-key gambling hall run by the Salt River Pima-Maricopa Indians. Try your luck at blackjack (minimum bets range from $5 to $25), or develop a case of repetitive stress injury by yanking on the slots as a cover band oozes the hits of Lionel Richie.</p>
        <p>Sunday</p>
        <p>9:30 a.m.  10. The Architect's Home  Do not miss Taliesin West, the international headquarters for the Frank Lloyd Wright Foundation and the winter campus for the Frank Lloyd Wright School of Architecture (12621 Frank Lloyd Wright Boulevard; 480-860-2700; www.franklloydwright.org). Troubled by poor health, Wright took up half-year residence in this 600-acre ''camp'' in 1937, and the complex was built by apprentices. Take the 90-minute tour, (9 a.m. to 4 p.m. daily on the half-hour for $22.50, children 4 to 12 $15) which takes you through the living quarters, working areas and outdoor spaces that incorporate indigenous materials and organic forms. Then there's all that Asian art.</p>
        <p>Noon  11. Exit Strategy  It's not quite Scottsdale, but just a few exits past the off ramp for the airport on Route 202 is the Phoenix Ranch Market, (1602 East Roosevelt Street, Phoenix; 602-254-6676) a 53,000-square-foot emporium of groceries featuring a food court full of Mexican goodies. One of the best meals around -- and, without a doubt, the best bargain -- is the three tacos for $2.89, with pork or beef or chicken decorated with cheese and cilantro for a tasty goodbye.</p>
        <p>THE BASICS</p>
        <p>Many airlines serve Phoenix Sky Harbor Airport. Carriers with nonstops from from the New York City area include JetBlue, US Airways, Continental and America West. Southwest goes nonstop from Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>The Hotel Valley Ho (6850 East Main Street; 866-882-4484; www.hotelvalleyho.com) is an inviting mid-20th-century hotel made chic by a 2004 renovation. It has a nice, low-key spa, a pool, a Trader Vic's restaurant and the cute Cafe ZuZu. It's within walking distance of Old Town Scottsdale. Rooms start at $259 at this time of year, excluding tax and parking.</p>
        <p>Sanctuary Camelback Mountain Resort and Spa (5700 East McDonald Drive, Paradise Valley; 800-245-2051; www.sanctuaryoncamelback.com) is a former tennis ranch that has become a truly secluded and elegant spot with its infinity pool and serene spa. The rooms are contemporary with Asian accents, wood-burning fireplaces and canopy beds. Rooms start at $495 in high season, excluding tax and parking.</p>
        <p>The 3 Palms Resort Oasis (7707 East McDowell Road; 800-450-8133; www.scottsdale-resort-hotels.com) is a good budget option, with rooms starting at $129 in late January. This contemporary low-rise hotel offers a few things that budget hotels often do not, like views of Camelback Mountain from some rooms, 400-thread-count sheets, down comforters and shuttle service within five miles of the property.  36 HOURS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
