<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CALENDAR</title>
    <meta content="14ctlistingsCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1818708"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE3D71230F937A25752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2225" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CALENDAR</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on in and around Connecticut this week. Items for the guide should be sent at least three weeks in advance to ctcal@nytimes.com, or by mail to Connecticut Weekly, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036-3959.</p>
        <p>Music and Dance</p>
        <p>Fairfield Steve Tyrell, jazz vocalist. Friday at 8 p.m. $35 and $40. Quick Center for the Arts, 1073 North Benson Road. (203) 254-4010.  Greenwich Graham Parker, singer-songwriter. Jan. 14 at 3:30 p.m. Free. Greenwich Library, 101 West Putnam Avenue. (203) 622-7900.  Hartford Beethoven's ''Eroica,'' presented by the Hartford Symphony Orchestra with Vadim Gluzman, violin. Friday and Jan. 20 at 8 p.m. $10 to $62. The Bushnell Center for Performing Arts, 166 Capitol Avenue. (860) 987-5900.  Litchfield Night Sky Music Series: Paul Curreri, singer-songwriter. Jan. 20 at 8 p.m. $10 to $15. Litchfield Community Center, 421 Bantam Road. (860) 567-8302.  New Canaan Notes in Midwinter Concert Series: The Chester Duo, Anthea Kreston, violin, and Jason Duckles, cello. Jan. 14 at 2 p.m. Synchronocity, Garah Landes, piano, and Gregory Landes, percussion. Jan. 21 at 2 p.m. Free. New Canaan Library, 151 Main Street. (203) 594-5000.  New Haven Jazz on the Wharf: Shawnn Monteiro, jazz vocals. Friday at 9 p.m. $15. Long Wharf Theater, 222 Sargent Drive. (203) 787-4282.  New Haven ''Cinderella,'' performed by the State Ballet Theater of Russia. Friday at 8 p.m. $38 to $58. Shubert Theater, 247 College Street. (203) 624-1825.  Ridgefield Garnet Rogers, singer-songwriter. Jan. 14 at 7 p.m. $15 to $20. Temple Shearith Israel, 46 Peaceable Street. (201) 431-6501.  Southport Young Persons' Concert Series: Gleb Ivanov, piano. Jan. 20 at 2 p.m. Free. Pequot Library, 720 Pequot Avenue. (203) 938-3843.  Stamford ''Bravo Beethoven,'' presented by the Stamford Symphony, conducted by Eckart Preu, with Stefan Jackiw, violin. Jan. 20 at 8 p.m. and Jan. 21 at 3 p.m. $17 to $65. Palace Theater, Stamford Center for the Arts, 61 Atlantic Street. (203) 325-4466.  Stamford ''Up Close With the Orchestra Family,'' mini-concert presented by musicians from the Stamford Symphony. Jan. 14 at 2 and 3:30 p.m. Free with museum admission. Stamford Museum and Nature Center, 39 Scofieldtown Road. (203) 322-1646.  Wallingford ''Lord of the Dance.'' Friday at 8 p.m. and Jan. 20 at 2 and 8 p.m. $24 to $74. Chevrolet Theater, 95 South Turnpike Road. (203) 265-1501.  Westport Jimmy LaFave with Antje Duvekot, folk. Friday at 8 p.m. $35; under 18, $5. Seabury Center, 45 Church Lane. (203) 222-7070.  Westport Sandra Murphy and Rita Lapcevic, piano duo. Jan. 14 at 2 p.m. Free. Westport Public Library, 20 Jesup Road. (203) 291-4818.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Darien Neil Simon's ''Biloxi Blues,'' presented by the Darien Players, directed by Frank Gaffney. Through Jan. 27. $20; seniors, $15; children under 12, $5. Darien Arts Center Weatherstone Theater, 2 Renshaw Road. (203) 655-5414.  East Haddam Goodspeed Festival of New Artists: ''Pearl'' by Katie Kring, directed by J. Ranelli. Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. ''Tinyard Hill'' by Mark Allen and Tommy Newman. Thursday at 7:30 p.m. ''The Great American Race'' by Patrick Barry, directed by Nona Lloyd. Friday at 7:30 p.m. Each performance: $10; students, $5; all three performances, $25. Goodspeed Opera House, Route 82. (860) 873-8668.  Hartford ''Fences,'' by August Wilson, directed by Jonathan Wilson. Through Feb. 11. $25 to $45. Hartford Stage, 50 Church Street. (860) 527-5151.  New Britain ''Bat Boy: The Musical'' by Keythe Farley, Brian Flemming and Laurence O'Keefe, directed by Philip D. Vetro. Through Feb. 10. $20. Hole in the Wall Theater, 116 Main Street. (860) 229-3049.  New Haven ''The Cocktail Hour'' by A. R. Gurney, directed by Kim Rubinstein. Through Feb. 4. $30 to $60. Long Wharf Theater, 222 Sargent Drive. (203) 787-4282.  New Haven ''In the Continuum,'' written and performed by Danai Gurira and Nikkole Salter, directed by Robert O'Hara. Through Feb. 10. $20 to $40. Yale Repertory Theater, 1120 Chapel Street. (203) 432-1234.  Stamford ''The Estate'' by Ray Aranha, presented by Prometheus' Fire. Jan. 20 at 7:30 p.m. $20; children under 18, $15. Rich Forum, Stamford Center for the Arts, 307 Atlantic Street. (203) 325-4466.  Torrington ''Steel Magnolias'' by Robert Harling, presented by students of the Warner Theater Center for Arts Education; directed by Isabel Hinman. Jan. 14 at 2 p.m. $10.50. Warner Theater, 68 Main Street. (860) 489-7180.  Waterbury ''Annie'' by Harold Gray, Charles Strouse, Martin Charnin and Thomas Meehan. Jan. 14 at 1:30 and 6:30 p.m. $48.25 to $58.25. Palace Theater of Connecticut, 100 East Main Street. (203) 755-4700.  West Hartford ''Lend Me a Tenor'' by Ken Ludwig, directed by Howard Hirsch. Thursday through Feb. 4. $25; students, $10. Park Road Playhouse, 244 Park Road. (860) 586-8500.  Westport ''Lucky Stiff'' by Lynn Ahrens and Stephen Flaherty, presented by the Music Theater of Connecticut School for the Performing Arts. Jan. 20 at 7:30 p.m. and Jan. 21 at 2 p.m. $15; students and seniors, $12. Long Lots Elementary School, Hyde Lane. (203) 454-3883.</p>
        <p>Film</p>
        <p>Cold Spring Harbor ''The Perfect Storm,'' directed by Wolfgang Petersen. Jan. 14 at 1 p.m. $4; seniors and students, $3; children under 5 and members, free. Whaling Museum, Route 25A. (631) 367-3418.  Hartford ''The Revenge,'' directed by Andrzej Wajda; in Polish with English subtitles. Jan. 21 at 3 p.m. $4.50 to $9. Real Art Ways, 56 Arbor Street. (860) 232-1006.  Stamford ''International Film Day'' with 11 films from around the world. Jan. 21 at 1:30 p.m. Free; refreshments provided. Ferguson Library Main Branch, 1 Public Library Plaza. (203) 964-1000.  Westport ''Glory'' directed by Edward Zwick, followed by discussion with Martin Haas, history professor. Jan. 21 at 2 p.m. Free. Westport Public Library, 20 Jesup Road. (203) 291-4818.</p>
        <p>Outdoors</p>
        <p>Ansonia ''Orienteering for Beginners.'' Learn to use a map and compass. Monday at 1 p.m. $3. Ansonia Nature Center, Deerfield Road. (203) 736-1053.</p>
        <p>Spoken Word</p>
        <p>Greenwich Susan Cheever, author of ''American Bloomsbury.'' Thursday at 7 p.m. Greenwich Library, 101 West Putnam Avenue. (203) 622-7900.  Madison John Sedgwick, author of ''In My Blood: Six Generations of Madness and Desire in an American Family.'' Tuesday at 7 p.m. Bob Drury, author of ''Halsey's Typhoon.'' Thursday at 7 p.m. Both free. R. J. Julia Booksellers, 768 Boston Road. (203) 245-3959.  Stamford Mary-Ann Tirone Smith, author of ''Girls of Tender Age.'' Jan. 20 at 1:30 p.m. Free. Ferguson Library, 115 Vine Road. (203) 964-1000.  Wilton Jack Cavanaugh, author of ''Tunney: Boxing's Brainiest Champ.'' Jan. 14 at 2 p.m. Free; reservations recommended. Wilton Library, 137 Old Ridgefield Road. (203) 762-3950.</p>
        <p>For Children</p>
        <p>Bridgeport ''Oliver Twist,'' a new version of Dickens's classic set to pop music, directed by Bert Bernardi. Through Feb. 18. $13.50. Downtown Cabaret Theater, 263 Golden Hill Street. (203) 576-1636.  Glastonbury ''SuperbOWL.'' Learn about owls, play games and visit with live owls. All ages. Jan. 21 from 2 to 3 p.m. $7; members, $5. The Connecticut Audubon Society Center at Glastonbury, 1361 Main Street. (860) 633-8402.  Mystic ''Winter Animal Homes.'' Look for squirrel dreys, fox dens and other winter wildlife homes. Ages 4 and up. Monday at 9:30 a.m. ''Boisterous Beavers.'' Learn about beavers and search the trails for beaver activity. Ages 6 and up. Friday at 9:30 a.m. $15; members, $12. Denison Pequotsepos Nature Center, 109 Pequotsepos Road. (860) 536-1216.  Pomfret Center Trails for Toddlers, Story and a Stroll: ''Winter Animal Signs,'' stories and nature walk. Thursday at 10 a.m. $5. Connecticut Audubon Society at Pomfret, 189 Pomfret Street. (860) 928-4948.  Stamford ''Bilingual Booktivity with Mrs. Claudia,'' books, songs and art in Spanish and English. Ages 2 to 5. Jan. 20 at 10:30 a.m. Free. Ferguson Library, 34 Woodland Avenue. (203) 964-1000.  West Hartford ''Color Play: The Art and Science of Color and Light.'' Explore light and holographic refraction. Ages 12 and under. Through June 17. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. The Children's Museum, 950 Trout Brook Drive. (860) 231-2824.  Westport ''Captain Louie,'' musical by Stephen Schwartz. Ages 10 and up. Jan. 14 at 1 and 4:30 p.m. $20 to $30. Westport Country Playhouse, 25 Powers Court. (203) 227-4177.  Westport ''Martin Luther King Kids' Activity Program,'' games, outdoor activities and a play. Ages 6 to 10. Jan. 15, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Westport Historical Society, 25 Avery Place. (203) 224-1424.</p>
        <p>Museums and Galleries</p>
        <p>Cornwall ''Book Paintings,'' oil paintings of artist Ken Krug's favorite books. Through Jan. 20. Free. Hours: Tuesday, Thursday and Friday, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Wednesday, noon to 7 p.m., Saturday, 10 a.m. to 2 p.m. Cornwall Free Library, 30 Pine Street. (860) 672-6874.  Greenwich ''Black and White Since 1960,'' 25 large-scale etchings and lithographs from the collection of Reba and Dave Williams, with works by Jasper Johns, Claes Oldenburg and others. Through Feb. 25. ''In Response to Place: Photographs From the Nature Conservancy's Last Great Places,'' photographs by William Wegman, Annie Liebovitz, Lee Friedlander and others. Through Jan. 28. $7; seniors and students, $6; children 5 and under, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Bruce Museum of Arts and Sciences, 1 Museum Drive. (203) 869-0376.  Hartford ''Poza,'' multimedia works by 31 Polish artists. Through Jan. 29. Donation: $3; members, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Thursdays and Sundays, 2 to 10 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays, 2 p.m. to midnight. Real Art Ways, 56 Arbor Street. (860) 232-1006.  Hartford ''Crewel World,'' exhibition of textiles embroidered using the crewel technique. Through Feb. 25. ''Soul Food: African-American Cooking and Creativity,'' art and artifacts exploring Southern cooking and culture; presented by the Amistad Center for Art and Culture. Through April 22. ''Picasso to Pop: Aspects of Modern Art,'' exhibition of the museum's holdings from many 20th-century genres. Through Nov. 18. $3 to $10; members and children 12 and under, free. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; first Thursdays of the month, 11 a.m. to 8 p.m. Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art, 600 Main Street. (860) 838-4058.  Mashantucket ''Booming Out: Mohawk Ironworkers Build New York,'' photographs and sculpture documenting the Mohawk sky-walking construction tradition passed through six generations. Jan. 14 through May 27. $10 to $15; children under 6, free. Hours: Daily, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; last admission, 3 p.m. Mashantucket Pequot Museum and Research Center, 110 Pequot Trail. (800) 411-9671.  New Haven ''Loud,'' juried exhibition with works by artists who are visually or aurally colorful or loud. Monday through Feb. 4. Free. Hours: Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Arts + Literature Laboratory, 319 Peck Street. (203) 671-5175.  New Haven ''To Know the Dark: American Artists' Visions of Night,'' works by Robert Adams, Winslow Homer, Edward Hopper and others. Through Jan. 14. ''Jasper Johns: From Plate to Print.'' Through April 1. ''Making a Mark: Four Contemporary Artists in Print,'' prints by Enrique Chagoya, Carroll Dunham, Jane Hammond and Kiki Smith. Through April 1. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 6 p.m. Yale University Art Gallery, (203) 432-9525.  New London ''femme brut(e),'' works by female artists including May Stevens, Nancy Spero, Barbara Kruger and others. Through Feb. 4. ''Les Santons de Provence,'' exhibition of hand-painted clay figurines. Through Jan. 22. $3 and $4; children 6 and under, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Lyman Allyn Art Museum, 625 Williams Street. (860) 443-2545.  New Milford Michael and Helen Cherney, acrylics, watercolors, oils and pastels. Through Feb. 10. Hours: Mondays, Thursdays and Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Tuesdays and Wednesdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 1 p.m. New Milford Public Library, 24 Main Street. (860) 355-1191.  Old Lyme ''The Freedom Business: Connecticut Landscapes Through the Eyes of Venture Smith,'' poems by Marilyn Nelson paired with paintings from the museum's collection. Through June 24. ''A Collective Endeavor: Three Decades of Acquisitions.'' Through March 25. $4 to $8; under 6, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5. Florence Griswold Museum, 96 Lyme Street. ((860) 434-5542.  Port Chester ''Pollinia,'' sculpture by Leigh Taylor Mickelson. Through Jan. 27. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Clay Art Center, 40 Beech Street. (914) 937-2047.  Ridgefield ''Bitter Fruit,'' photographs by Paul Fusco. Through Feb. 25. ''No Reservations: Native American History and Culture in Contemporary Art.'' Through Feb. 25. $7; seniors and students, $4; members, K-12 teachers and children under 18, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Aldrich Contemporary Art Museum, 258 Main Street. (203) 438-4519.  Storrs ''Intemperate Times: Kathe Kollwitz, 1918-1934.'' Tuesday through May. 6. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 4:30 p.m. William Benton Museum of Art, 245 Glenbrook Road. (860) 486-4520.  West Hartford ''From Theater and Teahouse: Actors and Courtesans in Japanese Woodblock Prints,'' historical works by various artists. Through Jan. 28. Hours: Tuesdays, Wednesdays, Fridays and Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Thursdays, 11 a.m. to 7 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. St. Joseph College Art Gallery, 1678 Asylum Avenue. (860) 231-5399.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on in and around Connecticut this week. Items for the guide should be sent at least three weeks in advance to ctcal@nytimes.com, or by mail to Connecticut Weekly, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036-3959.</p>
        <p>Music and Dance</p>
        <p>Fairfield Steve Tyrell, jazz vocalist. Friday at 8 p.m. $35 and $40. Quick Center for the Arts, 1073 North Benson Road. (203) 254-4010.  Greenwich Graham Parker, singer-songwriter. Jan. 14 at 3:30 p.m. Free. Greenwich Library, 101 West Putnam Avenue. (203) 622-7900.  Hartford Beethoven's ''Eroica,'' presented by the Hartford Symphony Orchestra with Vadim Gluzman, violin. Friday and Jan. 20 at 8 p.m. $10 to $62. The Bushnell Center for Performing Arts, 166 Capitol Avenue. (860) 987-5900.  Litchfield Night Sky Music Series: Paul Curreri, singer-songwriter. Jan. 20 at 8 p.m. $10 to $15. Litchfield Community Center, 421 Bantam Road. (860) 567-8302.  New Canaan Notes in Midwinter Concert Series: The Chester Duo, Anthea Kreston, violin, and Jason Duckles, cello. Jan. 14 at 2 p.m. Synchronocity, Garah Landes, piano, and Gregory Landes, percussion. Jan. 21 at 2 p.m. Free. New Canaan Library, 151 Main Street. (203) 594-5000.  New Haven Jazz on the Wharf: Shawnn Monteiro, jazz vocals. Friday at 9 p.m. $15. Long Wharf Theater, 222 Sargent Drive. (203) 787-4282.  New Haven ''Cinderella,'' performed by the State Ballet Theater of Russia. Friday at 8 p.m. $38 to $58. Shubert Theater, 247 College Street. (203) 624-1825.  Ridgefield Garnet Rogers, singer-songwriter. Jan. 14 at 7 p.m. $15 to $20. Temple Shearith Israel, 46 Peaceable Street. (201) 431-6501.  Southport Young Persons' Concert Series: Gleb Ivanov, piano. Jan. 20 at 2 p.m. Free. Pequot Library, 720 Pequot Avenue. (203) 938-3843.  Stamford ''Bravo Beethoven,'' presented by the Stamford Symphony, conducted by Eckart Preu, with Stefan Jackiw, violin. Jan. 20 at 8 p.m. and Jan. 21 at 3 p.m. $17 to $65. Palace Theater, Stamford Center for the Arts, 61 Atlantic Street. (203) 325-4466.  Stamford ''Up Close With the Orchestra Family,'' mini-concert presented by musicians from the Stamford Symphony. Jan. 14 at 2 and 3:30 p.m. Free with museum admission. Stamford Museum and Nature Center, 39 Scofieldtown Road. (203) 322-1646.  Wallingford ''Lord of the Dance.'' Friday at 8 p.m. and Jan. 20 at 2 and 8 p.m. $24 to $74. Chevrolet Theater, 95 South Turnpike Road. (203) 265-1501.  Westport Jimmy LaFave with Antje Duvekot, folk. Friday at 8 p.m. $35; under 18, $5. Seabury Center, 45 Church Lane. (203) 222-7070.  Westport Sandra Murphy and Rita Lapcevic, piano duo. Jan. 14 at 2 p.m. Free. Westport Public Library, 20 Jesup Road. (203) 291-4818.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Darien Neil Simon's ''Biloxi Blues,'' presented by the Darien Players, directed by Frank Gaffney. Through Jan. 27. $20; seniors, $15; children under 12, $5. Darien Arts Center Weatherstone Theater, 2 Renshaw Road. (203) 655-5414.  East Haddam Goodspeed Festival of New Artists: ''Pearl'' by Katie Kring, directed by J. Ranelli. Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. ''Tinyard Hill'' by Mark Allen and Tommy Newman. Thursday at 7:30 p.m. ''The Great American Race'' by Patrick Barry, directed by Nona Lloyd. Friday at 7:30 p.m. Each performance: $10; students, $5; all three performances, $25. Goodspeed Opera House, Route 82. (860) 873-8668.  Hartford ''Fences,'' by August Wilson, directed by Jonathan Wilson. Through Feb. 11. $25 to $45. Hartford Stage, 50 Church Street. (860) 527-5151.  New Britain ''Bat Boy: The Musical'' by Keythe Farley, Brian Flemming and Laurence O'Keefe, directed by Philip D. Vetro. Through Feb. 10. $20. Hole in the Wall Theater, 116 Main Street. (860) 229-3049.  New Haven ''The Cocktail Hour'' by A. R. Gurney, directed by Kim Rubinstein. Through Feb. 4. $30 to $60. Long Wharf Theater, 222 Sargent Drive. (203) 787-4282.  New Haven ''In the Continuum,'' written and performed by Danai Gurira and Nikkole Salter, directed by Robert O'Hara. Through Feb. 10. $20 to $40. Yale Repertory Theater, 1120 Chapel Street. (203) 432-1234.  Stamford ''The Estate'' by Ray Aranha, presented by Prometheus' Fire. Jan. 20 at 7:30 p.m. $20; children under 18, $15. Rich Forum, Stamford Center for the Arts, 307 Atlantic Street. (203) 325-4466.  Torrington ''Steel Magnolias'' by Robert Harling, presented by students of the Warner Theater Center for Arts Education; directed by Isabel Hinman. Jan. 14 at 2 p.m. $10.50. Warner Theater, 68 Main Street. (860) 489-7180.  Waterbury ''Annie'' by Harold Gray, Charles Strouse, Martin Charnin and Thomas Meehan. Jan. 14 at 1:30 and 6:30 p.m. $48.25 to $58.25. Palace Theater of Connecticut, 100 East Main Street. (203) 755-4700.  West Hartford ''Lend Me a Tenor'' by Ken Ludwig, directed by Howard Hirsch. Thursday through Feb. 4. $25; students, $10. Park Road Playhouse, 244 Park Road. (860) 586-8500.  Westport ''Lucky Stiff'' by Lynn Ahrens and Stephen Flaherty, presented by the Music Theater of Connecticut School for the Performing Arts. Jan. 20 at 7:30 p.m. and Jan. 21 at 2 p.m. $15; students and seniors, $12. Long Lots Elementary School, Hyde Lane. (203) 454-3883.</p>
        <p>Film</p>
        <p>Cold Spring Harbor ''The Perfect Storm,'' directed by Wolfgang Petersen. Jan. 14 at 1 p.m. $4; seniors and students, $3; children under 5 and members, free. Whaling Museum, Route 25A. (631) 367-3418.  Hartford ''The Revenge,'' directed by Andrzej Wajda; in Polish with English subtitles. Jan. 21 at 3 p.m. $4.50 to $9. Real Art Ways, 56 Arbor Street. (860) 232-1006.  Stamford ''International Film Day'' with 11 films from around the world. Jan. 21 at 1:30 p.m. Free; refreshments provided. Ferguson Library Main Branch, 1 Public Library Plaza. (203) 964-1000.  Westport ''Glory'' directed by Edward Zwick, followed by discussion with Martin Haas, history professor. Jan. 21 at 2 p.m. Free. Westport Public Library, 20 Jesup Road. (203) 291-4818.</p>
        <p>Outdoors</p>
        <p>Ansonia ''Orienteering for Beginners.'' Learn to use a map and compass. Monday at 1 p.m. $3. Ansonia Nature Center, Deerfield Road. (203) 736-1053.</p>
        <p>Spoken Word</p>
        <p>Greenwich Susan Cheever, author of ''American Bloomsbury.'' Thursday at 7 p.m. Greenwich Library, 101 West Putnam Avenue. (203) 622-7900.  Madison John Sedgwick, author of ''In My Blood: Six Generations of Madness and Desire in an American Family.'' Tuesday at 7 p.m. Bob Drury, author of ''Halsey's Typhoon.'' Thursday at 7 p.m. Both free. R. J. Julia Booksellers, 768 Boston Road. (203) 245-3959.  Stamford Mary-Ann Tirone Smith, author of ''Girls of Tender Age.'' Jan. 20 at 1:30 p.m. Free. Ferguson Library, 115 Vine Road. (203) 964-1000.  Wilton Jack Cavanaugh, author of ''Tunney: Boxing's Brainiest Champ.'' Jan. 14 at 2 p.m. Free; reservations recommended. Wilton Library, 137 Old Ridgefield Road. (203) 762-3950.</p>
        <p>For Children</p>
        <p>Bridgeport ''Oliver Twist,'' a new version of Dickens's classic set to pop music, directed by Bert Bernardi. Through Feb. 18. $13.50. Downtown Cabaret Theater, 263 Golden Hill Street. (203) 576-1636.  Glastonbury ''SuperbOWL.'' Learn about owls, play games and visit with live owls. All ages. Jan. 21 from 2 to 3 p.m. $7; members, $5. The Connecticut Audubon Society Center at Glastonbury, 1361 Main Street. (860) 633-8402.  Mystic ''Winter Animal Homes.'' Look for squirrel dreys, fox dens and other winter wildlife homes. Ages 4 and up. Monday at 9:30 a.m. ''Boisterous Beavers.'' Learn about beavers and search the trails for beaver activity. Ages 6 and up. Friday at 9:30 a.m. $15; members, $12. Denison Pequotsepos Nature Center, 109 Pequotsepos Road. (860) 536-1216.  Pomfret Center Trails for Toddlers, Story and a Stroll: ''Winter Animal Signs,'' stories and nature walk. Thursday at 10 a.m. $5. Connecticut Audubon Society at Pomfret, 189 Pomfret Street. (860) 928-4948.  Stamford ''Bilingual Booktivity with Mrs. Claudia,'' books, songs and art in Spanish and English. Ages 2 to 5. Jan. 20 at 10:30 a.m. Free. Ferguson Library, 34 Woodland Avenue. (203) 964-1000.  West Hartford ''Color Play: The Art and Science of Color and Light.'' Explore light and holographic refraction. Ages 12 and under. Through June 17. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. The Children's Museum, 950 Trout Brook Drive. (860) 231-2824.  Westport ''Captain Louie,'' musical by Stephen Schwartz. Ages 10 and up. Jan. 14 at 1 and 4:30 p.m. $20 to $30. Westport Country Playhouse, 25 Powers Court. (203) 227-4177.  Westport ''Martin Luther King Kids' Activity Program,'' games, outdoor activities and a play. Ages 6 to 10. Jan. 15, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Westport Historical Society, 25 Avery Place. (203) 224-1424.</p>
        <p>Museums and Galleries</p>
        <p>Cornwall ''Book Paintings,'' oil paintings of artist Ken Krug's favorite books. Through Jan. 20. Free. Hours: Tuesday, Thursday and Friday, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Wednesday, noon to 7 p.m., Saturday, 10 a.m. to 2 p.m. Cornwall Free Library, 30 Pine Street. (860) 672-6874.  Greenwich ''Black and White Since 1960,'' 25 large-scale etchings and lithographs from the collection of Reba and Dave Williams, with works by Jasper Johns, Claes Oldenburg and others. Through Feb. 25. ''In Response to Place: Photographs From the Nature Conservancy's Last Great Places,'' photographs by William Wegman, Annie Liebovitz, Lee Friedlander and others. Through Jan. 28. $7; seniors and students, $6; children 5 and under, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Bruce Museum of Arts and Sciences, 1 Museum Drive. (203) 869-0376.  Hartford ''Poza,'' multimedia works by 31 Polish artists. Through Jan. 29. Donation: $3; members, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Thursdays and Sundays, 2 to 10 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays, 2 p.m. to midnight. Real Art Ways, 56 Arbor Street. (860) 232-1006.  Hartford ''Crewel World,'' exhibition of textiles embroidered using the crewel technique. Through Feb. 25. ''Soul Food: African-American Cooking and Creativity,'' art and artifacts exploring Southern cooking and culture; presented by the Amistad Center for Art and Culture. Through April 22. ''Picasso to Pop: Aspects of Modern Art,'' exhibition of the museum's holdings from many 20th-century genres. Through Nov. 18. $3 to $10; members and children 12 and under, free. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; first Thursdays of the month, 11 a.m. to 8 p.m. Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art, 600 Main Street. (860) 838-4058.  Mashantucket ''Booming Out: Mohawk Ironworkers Build New York,'' photographs and sculpture documenting the Mohawk sky-walking construction tradition passed through six generations. Jan. 14 through May 27. $10 to $15; children under 6, free. Hours: Daily, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; last admission, 3 p.m. Mashantucket Pequot Museum and Research Center, 110 Pequot Trail. (800) 411-9671.  New Haven ''Loud,'' juried exhibition with works by artists who are visually or aurally colorful or loud. Monday through Feb. 4. Free. Hours: Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Arts + Literature Laboratory, 319 Peck Street. (203) 671-5175.  New Haven ''To Know the Dark: American Artists' Visions of Night,'' works by Robert Adams, Winslow Homer, Edward Hopper and others. Through Jan. 14. ''Jasper Johns: From Plate to Print.'' Through April 1. ''Making a Mark: Four Contemporary Artists in Print,'' prints by Enrique Chagoya, Carroll Dunham, Jane Hammond and Kiki Smith. Through April 1. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 6 p.m. Yale University Art Gallery, (203) 432-9525.  New London ''femme brut(e),'' works by female artists including May Stevens, Nancy Spero, Barbara Kruger and others. Through Feb. 4. ''Les Santons de Provence,'' exhibition of hand-painted clay figurines. Through Jan. 22. $3 and $4; children 6 and under, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Lyman Allyn Art Museum, 625 Williams Street. (860) 443-2545.  New Milford Michael and Helen Cherney, acrylics, watercolors, oils and pastels. Through Feb. 10. Hours: Mondays, Thursdays and Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Tuesdays and Wednesdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 1 p.m. New Milford Public Library, 24 Main Street. (860) 355-1191.  Old Lyme ''The Freedom Business: Connecticut Landscapes Through the Eyes of Venture Smith,'' poems by Marilyn Nelson paired with paintings from the museum's collection. Through June 24. ''A Collective Endeavor: Three Decades of Acquisitions.'' Through March 25. $4 to $8; under 6, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5. Florence Griswold Museum, 96 Lyme Street. ((860) 434-5542.  Port Chester ''Pollinia,'' sculpture by Leigh Taylor Mickelson. Through Jan. 27. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Clay Art Center, 40 Beech Street. (914) 937-2047.  Ridgefield ''Bitter Fruit,'' photographs by Paul Fusco. Through Feb. 25. ''No Reservations: Native American History and Culture in Contemporary Art.'' Through Feb. 25. $7; seniors and students, $4; members, K-12 teachers and children under 18, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Aldrich Contemporary Art Museum, 258 Main Street. (203) 438-4519.  Storrs ''Intemperate Times: Kathe Kollwitz, 1918-1934.'' Tuesday through May. 6. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 4:30 p.m. William Benton Museum of Art, 245 Glenbrook Road. (860) 486-4520.  West Hartford ''From Theater and Teahouse: Actors and Courtesans in Japanese Woodblock Prints,'' historical works by various artists. Through Jan. 28. Hours: Tuesdays, Wednesdays, Fridays and Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Thursdays, 11 a.m. to 7 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. St. Joseph College Art Gallery, 1678 Asylum Avenue. (860) 231-5399.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
