<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jordan Chattman, Joseph Shumofsky</title>
    <meta content="14Chattman" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/14/fashion/weddings/14Chattman.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1818799"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chattman, Jordan Deanna (Jordan Deanna Shumofsky)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shumofsky, Joseph Bruce</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E5DB1330F937A25752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="448" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jordan Chattman, Joseph Shumofsky</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Jordan Chattman, Joseph Shumofsky</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jordan Deanna Chattman, a daughter of Renee L. Chattman and Sanders M. Chattman of North Caldwell, N.J., is to be married this evening to Joseph Bruce Shumofsky, a son of Linda Lang Shumofsky and Dr. Edward Shumofsky of New Rochelle, N.Y. Rabbi Norman Patz is to perform the ceremony at Temple Beth Ahm in Springfield, N.J.</p>
        <p>The bride, 31, is the director of donor relations at the Jewish Theological Seminary in Manhattan. She graduated from Tufts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jordan Deanna Chattman, a daughter of Renee L. Chattman and Sanders M. Chattman of North Caldwell, N.J., is to be married this evening to Joseph Bruce Shumofsky, a son of Linda Lang Shumofsky and Dr. Edward Shumofsky of New Rochelle, N.Y. Rabbi Norman Patz is to perform the ceremony at Temple Beth Ahm in Springfield, N.J.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jordan Deanna Chattman, a daughter of Renee L. Chattman and Sanders M. Chattman of North Caldwell, N.J., is to be married this evening to Joseph Bruce Shumofsky, a son of Linda Lang Shumofsky and Dr. Edward Shumofsky of New Rochelle, N.Y. Rabbi Norman Patz is to perform the ceremony at Temple Beth Ahm in Springfield, N.J.</p>
        <p>The bride, 31, is the director of donor relations at the Jewish Theological Seminary in Manhattan. She graduated from Tufts.</p>
        <p>Her father is a partner in Orloff, Lowenbach, Stifelman &amp; Siegel, a law firm in Roseland, N.J.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom, 33, is an associate in the Manhattan office of Dorsey &amp; Whitney, a Minneapolis law firm. He graduated from Cornell and received his law degree from Fordham.</p>
        <p>His father, a general surgeon, has offices in Manhattan and the Bronx, which are managed by the bridegroom's mother.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shumofsky met Ms. Chattman in December 2004 in Manhattan at the Matzo Ball, a party for Jewish singles. About a year later he planned his marriage proposal with the precision of a military operation.</p>
        <p>To keep his intentions from Ms. Chattman, he told her he had in mind a January celebration of both her birthday and Valentine's Day, about two weeks before the events.</p>
        <p>''I knew I wanted drinks at the Top of the Tower at the Beekman Tower hotel first,'' Mr. Shumofsky said.</p>
        <p>He scouted out four-star New York restaurants for dinner and chose Daniel. For the proposal itself, he toured five hotels in search of a room with a view of Central Park and selected one on a high floor of the Carlyle.</p>
        <p>After dinner on the big night, they arrived at the Carlyle, where Champagne and candlelight awaited in the room, with a recording of Andrea Bocelli singing a love song in Italian. Then, as Mr. Shumofsky, recalled: ''I asked her to dance, sang the words in translation to her, got down on my knees and said: 'Will you take care of my heart? I promise to take care of yours.' ''</p>
        <p>The next morning, Meredith Chattman surprised her sister Jordan with a knock on their door. She was carrying two dozen roses. Mr. Shumofsky had flown her in from her home in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Off they went to brunch at the Atlantic Grill, where Mr. Shumofsky had arranged for their families, who had never met, to join them.</p>
        <p>One more surprise was still to come: a trip to Rome and Florence.</p>
        <p>Reflecting on the events, Ms. Chattman said: ''I cry at the drop of a hat, but I was so shocked that no tears could fall. It was so beyond anything I could imagine, the most romantic thing anyone could dream of.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
