<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Having a Drink On the Way Home</title>
    <meta content="l14island-2" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1818990"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EFDE1030F937A25752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="309" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Having a Drink On the Way Home</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The concerns expressed by ''Running Dry on the M.T.A.,'' a Jan. 7 editorial arguing that the Metropolitan Transportation Authority should not be selling alcoholic beverages, add up to unbridled moralism.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The concerns expressed by ''Running Dry on the M.T.A.,'' a Jan. 7 editorial arguing that the Metropolitan Transportation Authority should not be selling alcoholic beverages, add up to unbridled moralism.</p>
        <p>As a Long Island Rail Road passenger, I can verify that rush-hour (by and large ''professional'') travelers who purchase a drink for their home commute are unlikely to disrupt fellow passengers. A far greater threat of disruption exists after Friday and Saturday night binges, when most of the alcohol is consumed far from M.T.A. premises and all platform vendors are shut down.</p>
        <p>I would wager my innocent $2 Budweiser that the push for transit prohibition by the M.T.A. board member Mitch Pally will soon become a reality, in keeping with the maternalistic no-smoking, no-fatty-foods wave that has swept the city. But such a move would unwittingly target moderation while failing to address the truly raucous children of the night, whose decadence falls outside of the M.T.A.'s jurisdiction anyway.</p>
        <p>Chris Wood  Williston Park</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I am 10th-grade student. After reading your editorial about how the Long Island Rail Road and Metro-North are selling alcohol to their passengers, I was completely shocked because I was not aware of this kind of event that has been taking place for many years now.</p>
        <p>I think it is completely unnecessary to sell beer and other alcoholic drinks to passengers whether they are boarding the next train or just getting off the train. The train stations could sell something else rather then supplying people with beer for their ride home. As a rider of the Metropolitan Transportation Authority, I would not appreciate having drunken people sitting next to me or in fact in the same car as me because it is sure to cause a commotion in some form or another.</p>
        <p>Deborah Mui  The Bronx</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
