<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Rematch of Championship, Maryland Is No Match for Duke</title>
    <meta content="14maryland" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1818968"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE BASKETBALL: WOMEN'S ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Maryland</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Duke University</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E2DE1030F937A25752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="695" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Rematch of Championship, Maryland Is No Match for Duke</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIV BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <dateline>DURHAM, N.C., Jan. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Duke University defeats Maryland University, 81-62; other women's basketball results noted (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 2006-7 season began as one long victory parade for the Maryland women's basketball team. After stunning the Duke Blue Devils in the N.C.A.A. championship game last April, the Terrapins have held the No. 1 spot in the national polls since November with an 18-game winning streak.</p>
        <p>No team had challenged Maryland's perch until Saturday afternoon, when the Terrapins showed up at Cameron Indoor Stadium to meet Duke again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The 2006-7 season began as one long victory parade for the Maryland women's basketball team. After stunning the Duke Blue Devils in the N.C.A.A. championship game last April, the Terrapins have held the No. 1 spot in the national polls since November with an 18-game winning streak.</p>
        <p>No team had challenged Maryland's perch until Saturday afternoon, when the Terrapins showed up at Cameron Indoor Stadium to meet Duke again.</p>
        <p>And the rematch was no match. The Blue Devils outplayed Maryland in an 81-62 victory in front of a crowd of 9,314, a rare sellout for a women's game at Cameron.</p>
        <p>''I thought this game we were outworked, outhustled, outplayed, outcoached, you name it,'' Maryland Coach Brenda Frese said.</p>
        <p>Duke guard Lindsey Harding drove the lane at will and finished with 28 points. The 6-foot-7 center Alison Bales had 18 points, 12 rebounds and 7 blocked shots.</p>
        <p>Crystal Langhorne led Maryland (18-1) with 14 points.</p>
        <p>It was the first meeting among the big three of the Atlantic Coast Conference. No. 1 Maryland, No. 2 North Carolina (19-0) and No. 3 Duke (18-0) have spent the season atop the polls and were the only three undefeated teams remaining going into Saturday's play.</p>
        <p>The Terrapins, with all five starters back from last season's championship team, had been averaging 88.8 points a game, second best in the nation. But they faced a Duke defense that was allowing only 45.9 points a game, also second best in the nation. Duke held the Terrapins to 37.8 percent shooting from the field; they were 3 of 18 from 3-point range.</p>
        <p>Maryland had taken an early lead before Duke built a 41-30 halftime advantage, led by Harding's 16 points. The Blue Devils, with three starters back from last season's team, knew better than to sit on that lead. Duke blew a 13-point lead to Maryland in the second half of the championship game before losing in overtime.</p>
        <p>Duke Coach Gail Goestenkors said her halftime message was, ''I don't care about a lead, I have no interest in a lead right now, I don't want to secure a lead or hold onto a lead.''</p>
        <p>Instead, the Blue Devils kept pushing and Maryland dropped behind by as many as 22 in the waning minutes. As the clock ticked down in the final minute, Duke guard Abby Waner allowed a smile to cross her face as she clapped her hands and motioned to the crowd. Goestenkors had ordered a distraught Waner to stay away from basketball for a month after the championship game loss.</p>
        <p>''One thing that Coach said to us yesterday that I think is really important is that with a win today, we don't win last year's national championship, that no matter what happened last year, we can't take it back,'' Waner said. ''So I'm more excited for this year. I think that this was our first big test, and we really proved ourselves, I feel like. But we have a lot farther to go.''</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT 76, SYRACUSE 45 -- The freshman center Tina Charles had 14 points, 19 rebounds and 5 blocks, and No. 7 Connecticut (14-1, 4-0 Big East) defeated visiting Syracuse (8-10, 2-3) in a tuneup before tomorrow's showdown with second-ranked North Carolina.</p>
        <p>It was Charles's fifth double-double of the season, and her 19 rebounds were the most for a Connecticut player since Swin Cash had 20 against West Virginia in 2001. (AP)</p>
        <p>STANFORD 63, WASHINGTON STATE 55 -- The freshman JJ Hones scored a season-high 17 points to help No. 10 Stanford (14-3, 7-0 Pac-10) send visiting Washington State (5-13, 1-7) to its seventh consecutive defeat. (AP)Texas A&amp;M 60, Baylor 52 Takia Starks had 12 points and 11 rebounds, and No. 19 Texas A&amp;M (12-3, 2-1 Big 12) defeated ninth-ranked Baylor (15-3, 2-2), the host Aggies' first victory against a top-10 team in five years. (AP)</p>
        <p>MARQUETTE 76, VILLANOVA 70 -- Krystal Ellis scored 8 of her 21 points down the stretch to help No. 16 Marquette (16-2, 4-1 Big East) hold off visiting Villanova (7-10, 1-3) and bounce back from its loss at Pittsburgh on Tuesday that ended its 14-game winning streak. (AP)</p>
        <p>COLLEGE BASKETBALL: WOMEN'S ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
