<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METROPOLITAN DIARY</title>
    <meta content="15diary" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/15/nyregion/15diary.1.ready.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1819066"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Metropolitan Diary"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metropolitan Diary</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07EFDD1030F936A25752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="746" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METROPOLITAN DIARY</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Dear Diary</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>Walking hand in hand with Jordie, age 7, and Adam, age 5, Grandpa Fred was heard to say:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As I approached the corner, the fire truck made a left turn, and all the firemen called out “HELLO SUSAN” while waving and teasing me.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>Walking hand in hand with Jordie, age 7, and Adam, age 5, Grandpa Fred was heard to say:</p>
        <p>''I'm sorry, boys. I told you, Grandpa doesn't go to see movies where the animals talk.''</p>
        <p>Evelyn Malina</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>The other day I got off the Lexington Avenue subway train at 68th Street, and as I trudged up the steep flight of stairs toward the street exit, a black patent-leather high-heeled shoe tumbled down the steps and came to rest at my feet.</p>
        <p>I looked up to see an attractive young woman hobbling back down the stairs, where she'd obviously come out of her shoe as she was ascending.</p>
        <p>''Just bought them today, and I knew I should have held out for the smaller size,'' she explained, red-faced.</p>
        <p>I kneeled, picked up the shoe, and set it upright on the landing to allow her to slip her foot into it. As she did, I refrained from asking whether it would be a better fit for her wicked stepsisters.</p>
        <p>Instead, I cautioned her, ''Be sure you get home before the clock strikes 12.''</p>
        <p>Richard Curtis</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>When I arrived home and unpacked my purchases from Staples, I realized that an inexpensive calculator was missing from the bag. I immediately called the store and spoke with the manager, who actually located the calculator at the cash register station I had used.</p>
        <p>''I'll put it in a bag with your name on it'' he said. I gave him my name.</p>
        <p>After a moment's silence I heard him say, sotto voce, ''Anybody got a pen? You got something to write with? I need a pen.''</p>
        <p>Barry Levine</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>Exiting the subway at Wall Street, I was a little worried at an overheard conversation between a buttoned-down mom and her 5-ish-looking son:</p>
        <p>Mom: ''not doing well in school? You need to do well in school, so that you can get into a good college''</p>
        <p>Uh-oh, I thought, here comes the guilt trip.</p>
        <p>Mom (continuing): ''so that you can become a professional football player.''</p>
        <p>Oh. Nicely done, Mom.</p>
        <p>Keith Herron</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>As I crossed Broadway above Columbus Circle during the morning rush, with a horde of fellow pedestrians on their way to work, I heard a horn blaring, emanating from an approaching white van.</p>
        <p>The van was forced to stop as the group of commuters flocked across Broadway, paying no attention to the vehicle, which in fact had the right of way.</p>
        <p>The screech of the horn continued for what seemed like an eternity, so I turned around to get a better look at the culprit. On the side of the van was a painted sign advertising the trade of the vehicle's occupant: Soundproof Window Installation.</p>
        <p>Nothing like drumming up a little business whenever the opportunity arises.</p>
        <p>Ian M. Waxman</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>While walking along Columbus Avenue, I had the distinct feeling that I was being followed by a large truck to my right.</p>
        <p>I then heard my name being called, and there on the street was a fire truck with the driver calling out my name: ''Susan!''</p>
        <p>It was a firefighter whom I have known for many years; he plays basketball at the 92nd Street Y, where I work.</p>
        <p>As I approached the corner, the fire truck made a left turn, and all the firemen called out ''HELLO SUSAN'' while waving and teasing me. They all sounded like little girls saying hello!</p>
        <p>It brought a lot of smiles to all the people around me.</p>
        <p>Susan Grucci</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>Car, van and pedestrian traffic through the intersection at 53rd and Lexington during lunch hour is usually very heavy. I was crossing on the south side of the street, heading west.</p>
        <p>As I reached the far corner, I noticed pedestrians watching a biker swing around a van that had just run a red light to take a parking space. He continued onto the sidewalk as the van's youngish driver opened his door and stepped down to the sidewalk.</p>
        <p>The biker said in a surprisingly even voice, ''That was almost a really bad accident.'' The driver stared at the biker and said simply, ''I'm sorry.'' At that, the biker completed his circling of the van and headed north.</p>
        <p>I was stunned. A peaceful exchange that may have made an impact on the van driver, not counting the many bystanders who may have expected a shouting match.</p>
        <p>Good grief, I thought. What has this boisterous city come to?</p>
        <p>Robert Swain</p>
        <p>Metropolitan Diary</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
