<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Neediest Cases; A Mother Dreams of Job Security, and an End to Scraping By</title>
    <meta content="16needy" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1819246"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New York Times Neediest Cases Fund</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Community Service Society of New York</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haskell, Kari</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/The Neediest Cases</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502EEDA1030F935A25752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1200" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Neediest Cases; A Mother Dreams of Job Security, and an End to Scraping By</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KARI HASKELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Haskell, Kari</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Queens (NYC) single mother is overwhelmed by bills, family problems and lack of steady work; is helped by Community Service Society of New York, agency supported by New York Times Neediest Cases Fund; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cassandra Bogen returned to Jamaica, Queens, from North Carolina in 1998 to take care of her dying mother. Being in her childhood home brought back a flood of memories.</p>
        <p>She remembered her sister learning to play the piano. And she remembered that it was at Martin Van Buren High School in Queens Village where she fell in love with her first boyfriend. Though the relationship ended, they had a daughter, Twanysha, now 15.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Cassandra Bogen returned to Jamaica, Queens, from North Carolina in 1998 to take care of her dying mother. Being in her childhood home brought back a flood of memories.</p>
        <p>She remembered her sister learning to play the piano. And she remembered that it was at Martin Van Buren High School in Queens Village where she fell in love with her first boyfriend. Though the relationship ended, they had a daughter, Twanysha, now 15.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bogen said watching her mother, Marie Bogen, slowed down by age and illness was a stark contrast to the happier times they shared when she was younger.</p>
        <p>When Ms. Bogen was a child, the holidays, even on her mother's limited budget as an accounts payable clerk in a grocery store, were always festive. ''No matter what, if you were in my mother's home you talked and enjoyed yourself,'' said Ms. Bogen, now 34, in her living room recently.</p>
        <p>As diabetes eroded her mother's strength, the bills began to pile up. To pay the bills, Ms. Bogen worked as a consumer service representative at Health Insurance Plan of New York, and later at Bell Atlantic, which became Verizon. ''I just worked to support my mom, help with rent, groceries and bills,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bogen also helped her sister, Sonia Fryer, financially. Ms. Fryer has Crohn's disease and was also recovering from radiation treatment for a brain tumor.</p>
        <p>Following her mother's example, Ms. Bogen said she was unequivocal when it came to family matters. ''Family comes first; material things are not important,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In the last year of her mother's life, Ms. Bogen was happy to see her mother spend time with her grandson, Amir, who was born in May 2001. Twanysha was especially close to her grandmother, and insisted on sleeping in her bed. She was in the bedroom when her grandmother died on Nov. 23, 2001.</p>
        <p>After her mother's death, Ms. Bogen took over the expenses and the apartment and was further strained financially. She scraped together $6,000 through a loan, her 401(k) plan, and family and friends to pay for her mother's funeral expenses.</p>
        <p>In 2003, she left Verizon, taking a voluntary severance package, which she used to finish her bachelor's degree in business administration at Metropolitan College of New York. With the degree, she thought she would have a better chance of earning a higher salary. But even after she graduated, she could only find full-time work without benefits.</p>
        <p>By 2005, her rent increased to $940 from $839 a month. She was working on Long Island in the customer service department at Health Care Partners, earning $15 an hour. The commuting and the stress began to wear her down. She was hospitalized in December 2005 for severe migraines, she said.</p>
        <p>In the spring of 2006, her rent was increased again, this time to $1,053.49. It could not have happened at a worse time. She was fired from her job, and her daughter was acting out at school. Twanysha was in therapy for four months to work through severe depression and feelings of abandonment from her father and grandmother. ''All she understands is that people were in her life and now they are not,'' Ms. Bogen said.</p>
        <p>''I felt that I was not doing my job as a parent,'' Ms. Bogen added. ''You are doing so much and your plate is overfull, but you're trying to accommodate their needs.''</p>
        <p>When rent was due in May 2006, Ms. Bogen was short. ''I had to fight to maintain a roof over their head; she needed stability,'' Ms. Bogen said of her daughter. ''I definitely didn't want to go into the shelter.''</p>
        <p>While trying to find work, she received $164 a week from unemployment, which barely covered the cost of food, much less rent. She turned off her cellphone and posted a notice in the laundry room of her building to sell her love seat, sofa and television.</p>
        <p>''Nobody was calling me for jobs, I didn't have food stamps,'' she said. ''I was desperate.'' She sold the furnishings for $1,850, she said, which was about a third of what she had paid for them.</p>
        <p>Trying to head off eviction, she went to a housing court in Queens in July 2006. There she received a number for the Community Service Society of New York, which is one of the seven agencies supported by The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund. Anna Auleley, a caseworker at the agency, returned her call and said she could help as soon as Ms. Bogen found a job, to ensure that she could pay rent the next month.</p>
        <p>By September 2006, she owed $5,485.32. ''My management company would not let me pay a partial amount; I had to pay in full,'' she said. Before time ran out, she found a data entry job in New Jersey making $15 an hour. To pay the outstanding amount, Ms. Auleley drew $1,581.83 from Neediest Cases and received $1,053.49 from FEMA. Ms. Bogen covered the rest with her savings.</p>
        <p>''It was a big load off my shoulders,'' Ms. Bogen said with a sigh of relief.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bogen now works temporarily in data processing for Fidelis Care in Queens, making $13 an hour. And she is sending out résumés, seeking an administrative position.</p>
        <p>Now in her apartment, beside the piano her sister used to play (one of the few things she did not sell), is a worn sofa and love seat given to her by a neighbor.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't going to say no,'' she said, referring to the offer for the furniture. ''For today, this is how we get by.''</p>
        <p>HOW TO HELP</p>
        <p>Checks payable to The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund should be sent to 4 Chase Metrotech Center, 7th Floor East, Lockbox 5193, Brooklyn, N.Y. 11245, or any of these organizations:</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN BUREAU OF COMMUNITY SERVICE  285 Schermerhorn Street  Brooklyn, N.Y. 11217</p>
        <p>CATHOLIC CHARITIES, DIOCESE OF BROOKLYN AND QUEENS  191 Joralemon Street  Brooklyn, N.Y. 11201</p>
        <p>CATHOLIC CHARITIES OF THE ARCHDIOCESE OF NEW YORK  1011 First Avenue  New York, N.Y. 10022</p>
        <p>CHILDREN'S AID SOCIETY  105 East 22nd Street  New York, N.Y. 10010</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY SERVICE SOCIETY OF NEW YORK  105 East 22nd Street  New York, N.Y. 10010</p>
        <p>FEDERATION OF PROTESTANT WELFARE AGENCIES  281 Park Avenue South  New York, N.Y. 10010</p>
        <p>UJA-FEDERATION OF NEW YORK  Church Street Station  P.O. Box 4100  New York, N.Y. 10261-4100</p>
        <p>No agents or solicitors are authorized to seek contributions for The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund.</p>
        <p>Donations may be made with a credit card by phone at (800) 381-0075 or online, courtesy of NYCharities.org, an Internet donations service, at www.nytimes.com/neediest or www.nycharities.org/neediest. For instructions on how to donate stock to the fund, call (212) 556-1137 or fax (212) 556-4450.</p>
        <p>The Times pays the fund's expenses, so all contributions go directly to the charities, which use them to provide services and cash assistance to the poor.</p>
        <p>Contributions to the fund are deductible on federal, state and city income taxes to the extent permitted by law.</p>
        <p>To delay may mean to forget.</p>
        <p>Previously recorded: $6,484,079  Recorded Thursday: 240,690  Total: $6,724,769  Last year to date: $6,285,241</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
