<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seton Hall Starts Big East Play On Right Track, Beating Rutgers</title>
    <meta content="04hoops" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/04/sports/ncaabasketball/04hoops.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1816385"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE BASKETBALL: ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E2D61730F937A35752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1011" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seton Hall Starts Big East Play On Right Track, Beating Rutgers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Seton Hall Starts Big East Play on Right Track, Beating Rutgers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL FINLEY</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Jan. 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For now, Seton Hall looks like the best Big East basketball team from the state of New Jersey. For the Pirates, that may be as good as it gets the rest of this season.</p>
        <p>In front of a small crowd (7,214) at Continental Arena that included an impartial Gov. Jon S. Corzine, Seton Hall defeated interstate rival Rutgers, 77-72, Wednesday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The game kicked off the Big East portion of the schedule for Seton Hall and Rutgers, which figures to mean problems for both teams.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For now, Seton Hall looks like the best Big East basketball team from the state of New Jersey. For the Pirates, that may be as good as it gets the rest of this season.</p>
        <p>In front of a small crowd (7,214) at Continental Arena that included an impartial Gov. Jon S. Corzine, Seton Hall defeated interstate rival Rutgers, 77-72, Wednesday night.</p>
        <p>The game kicked off the Big East portion of the schedule for Seton Hall and Rutgers, which figures to mean problems for both. Neither team fared particularly well in the nonconference portion of their schedules and must now play much tougher opponents.</p>
        <p>Both have first-year coaches and are in a rebuilding mode. Bobby Gonzalez has come over from Manhattan to try to get Seton Hall (9-4, 1-0) back on track. Fred Hill is the new coach at Rutgers (7-7, 0-1).</p>
        <p>So far, it is Gonzalez's team that seems to be on the faster track.</p>
        <p>''We don't know how long we are going to stay undefeated in the league, but the bottom line is that we're 9-4 and we won our first Big East game, and it's a rivalry game,'' Gonzalez said. ''Rivalry games are important. We've got to find ways to win games and scratch and claw. That's what we did. That's what we're going to have to do every game. No games this year are going to be easy for us.''</p>
        <p>The Pirates have a talented freshman, Eugene Harvey, they can build around. A point guard, he had 21 points for Seton Hall on Wednesday. Brian Laing also had 21.</p>
        <p>''Eugene Harvey makes everyone else on the floor better,'' Hill said. ''Everybody gets worried about Eugene's penetration and that opens up the floor for Laing and Jamar Nutter. He's their catalyst and he makes them go. The better Eugene plays and as he continues to develop and grow, they will develop and grow as a team.''</p>
        <p>It appeared early on that Seton Hall was going to run away with the game. The Pirates had a 34-16 lead with 5 minutes 17 seconds to go in the first half.</p>
        <p>But the Scarlet Knights went on a 17-0 run to cut the Pirates' lead to 34-33. Rutgers had its first lead, 54-53, on a hook shot by J. R. Inman with 10:11 to go. Seton Hall then started to take control. When Harvey scored on a driving layup with 4:44 to play, the Pirates had a 68-61 lead.</p>
        <p>Rutgers was not done. When Hamaday N'Diaye dunked with 1:07 left to go, the Seton Hall lead was down to 68-66. Making 9 of 10 free-throw attempts inside the final minute, Seton Hall was able to close out the game.</p>
        <p>Rutgers was led by Inman, who had 18 points and 12 rebounds.</p>
        <p>ST. JOHN'S 64, DEPAUL 53 -- Aaron Spears, playing for the first time since serving a four-game suspension, scored all 6 of his points in the final nine and a half minutes and St. John's won a Big East opener at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>Daryll Hill, who has battled a knee injury all season, had 9 points for the Red Storm (10-4), including a 3-pointer from deep in the corner as the shot clock ran out for a 59-52 lead with 45 seconds to play.</p>
        <p>Wilson Chandler had 15 points for the Blue Demons (9-6).</p>
        <p>Hill, who came in averaging 6.5 points a game, and Spears, who was averaging 2.8, combined to score 12 straight points for the Red Storm in the second half.(AP)</p>
        <p>NOTRE DAME 78, LOUISVILLE 62 -- Tory Jackson, a freshman point guard, tied a career high with 14 points to help 17th-ranked Notre Dame beat visiting Louisville in a Big East opener. Jackson was put in the starting lineup after Kyle McAlarney was arrested on a marijuana possession charge last week and suspended indefinitely.</p>
        <p>Notre Dame (13-1) has won 12 consecutive games for the first time in nearly 33 years. Terrence Williams led Louisville (10-5) with 18 points, but the Cardinals continued to struggle offensively. (AP)</p>
        <p>NORTH CAROLINA 102, PENNSYLVANIA 64 -- Tyler Hansbrough and Reyshawn Terry scored 19 points apiece, and No. 2 North Carolina routed visiting Pennsylvania for its 10th straight victory. Wayne Ellington added 17 points for North Carolina (13-1), which used a 27-4 run late in the first half to take command against the Quakers (6-6). (AP)</p>
        <p>WEST VIRGINIA 67, VILLANOVA 56 -- Frank Young scored a career-high 25 points, including eight 3-pointers, for No. 25 West Virginia (12-1, 2-0) in a Big East game. Curtis Sumpter, conference's second-leading scorer, led visiting Villanova (10-3, 0-1) with 21 points. (AP)</p>
        <p>GEORGE WASHINGTON 70, FORDHAM 59 -- Maureece Rice had 17 points and 6 rebounds to lead George Washington (9-3) past visiting Fordham in the Atlantic 10 opener for both teams. Marcus Stout had 15 points for Fordham (7-6) to give him 1,001 in his career. (AP)</p>
        <p>IN OTHER GAMES -- Dan Nwaelele led a balanced offense with 22 points, and No. 20 Air Force (14-1, 1-0 Mountain West Conference) beat Colorado State, 81-75, for its 10th straight victory.  Cliff Hammonds's layup with three seconds left lifted No. 23 Clemson (15-0) past Florida State, 68-66, in the Atlantic Coast Conference opener for both teams. (AP)</p>
        <p>WOMEN</p>
        <p>MARYLAND 80, NORTH CAROLINA STATE 61 -- Top-ranked Maryland (16-0) opened Atlantic Coast Conference play in the same fashion it handled the nonleague portion of its schedule: with a blowout victory. Laura Harper scored 17 points and Coach Brenda Frese earned her 100th win at Maryland.</p>
        <p>Shay Doron scored 10 points to move into second place on the Terps' career scoring list. Doron, a senior guard, has 1,681 points. (AP)</p>
        <p>DUKE 72, MIAMI 42 -- Carrem Gay had 12 points and 10 rebounds to lead third-ranked Duke (15-0) past Miami in the A.C.C. (AP)</p>
        <p>TENNESSEE 72, ALABAMA 36 -- In a Southeastern Conference opener, Candace Parker scored 15 points and No. 4 Tennessee (13-1) beat visiting Alabama (10-6) for the 31st consecutive time. (AP)</p>
        <p>COLLEGE BASKETBALL: ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
