<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Queens Blackout, Report Finds Some Fault With Regulators</title>
    <meta content="30utility" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/30/nyregion/30utility.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1822638"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blackouts and Brownouts (Electrical)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Monopolies</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Consolidated Edison Co of New York Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Public Service Commission (NYS)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chan, Sewell</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Blackouts and Brownouts (Electrical)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blackouts and Brownouts (Electrical)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monopolies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Public Service Commission</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Consolidated Edison Inc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pataki, George E</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE5D8143FF933A05752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="581" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Queens Blackout, Report Finds Some Fault With Regulators</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Queens Blackout, Report Finds Some Fault With Regulators</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SEWELL CHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chan, Sewell</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Report by New York State Assembly task force on 2006 Queens blackout harshly criticizes Con Edison but says that staff reductions on oversight State Public Service Commission contributed to failure to adequately monitor Con Edison; questions whether Con Edison should have monopoly of 'indefinite duration'; recommends state review of monopoly every 10 years (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The staff size at the New York State Public Service Commission declined by nearly one-third under the Pataki administration, and the reduction contributed to a failure by the agency to adequately monitor Consolidated Edison's performance, according to a report to be released today by a State Assembly task force.</p>
        <p>The 55-page report was in response to the nine-day blackout that crippled western Queens last July. An advance copy of the report was provided to The New York Times by an Assembly member yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A decrease in the size of the staff at the New York State Public Service Commission contributed to a failure to adequately monitor Consolidated Edison’s performance, a report says.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The staff size at the New York State Public Service Commission declined by nearly one-third under the Pataki administration, and the reduction contributed to a failure by the agency to adequately monitor Consolidated Edison's performance, according to a report to be released today by a State Assembly task force.</p>
        <p>The 55-page report was in response to the nine-day blackout that crippled western Queens last July. An advance copy of the report was provided to The New York Times by an Assembly member yesterday.</p>
        <p>The commission, which regulates electric, gas and telecommunications utilities, issued a scathing report of its own on Jan. 17. That report found that Con Edison had failed to adequately maintain and operate its network and that the failure was ''the overriding cause'' of the blackout, which lasted from July 17 to 25 and cut power to 174,000 people.</p>
        <p>Echoing the commission, the Assembly report was highly critical of Con Edison, but it also struck a new theme, taking aim at the commission itself.</p>
        <p>The report quoted a 1932 speech by Franklin D. Roosevelt, then the governor of New York, who said that the Public Service Commission ''was created for the purpose of seeing that the public utilities do two things: first, give people adequate service; second, charge reasonable rates.''</p>
        <p>The task force found that the commission had about 800 employees in 1995, when George E. Pataki began the first of his three terms as governor, and now -- partly due to deregulation -- has about 550. Nearly 40 percent of the staff is 55 or older and is expected to retire within a decade.</p>
        <p>Though the commission is officially bipartisan, some energy experts have asserted that the Pataki administration mainly appointed political supporters to its board. Mr. Pataki named the four current commissioners, including the chairwoman, Patricia L. Acampora. Gov. Eliot Spitzer has nominated Angela M. Sparks-Beddoe to fill a vacancy and become the chairwoman. The task force also recommended that state law be changed to require commissioners to have a background in utilities.</p>
        <p>The task force questioned whether Con Edison should have a monopoly ''of indefinite duration'' and recommended that the state review the monopoly every 10 years. In its draft report, the commission staff recommended a formal proceeding that could result in substantial penalties against Con Edison; the new report agreed with that recommendation.</p>
        <p>Con Edison failed, according to the task force, to compensate residents and businesses for economic damages and to follow the recommendations of a 1999 report by the state attorney general after a blackout in northern Manhattan.</p>
        <p>The task force also recommended that Con Edison spend $20 million over three years to develop a state-of-the-art electrical grid in western Queens that would use energy more efficiently and permit Con Edison to monitor the use of energy better.</p>
        <p>Spokesmen for the Public Service Commission and Con Edison said they could not comment until the report was public.</p>
        <p>The task force included three Democratic Assembly members from Queens -- Michael N. Gianaris, Margaret M. Markey and Catherine T. Nolan -- who represent areas affected by the blackout.</p>
        <p>The other members were Karen S. Burstein, a former member of the Public Service Commission; Francis J. Murray Jr., who was state energy commissioner under Gov. Mario M. Cuomo; Gerald A. Norlander, executive director of the Public Utility Law Project, an advocacy group; Fred Zalcman, executive director of the Energy Project at Pace Law School; and Rae Zimmerman, a professor of planning and public administration at New York University.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
