<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Take a Stand Even if It Means Not Getting a Seat</title>
    <meta content="30flier" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/30/business/30flier.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1822562"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FREQUENT FLIER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Panthea (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mourkogiannis, Nikos</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Christopher</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Frequent Flier</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Business Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E2DA143FF933A05752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="515" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Take a Stand Even if It Means Not Getting a Seat</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Take a Stand Even if It Means Not Getting a Seat</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Nikos Mourkogiannis, as told to Christopher Elliott.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mourkogiannis, Nikos; Elliott, Christopher</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Panthea senior partner Nikos Mourkogiannis, in F2</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NOTHING gives your principles a workout like a business trip. Taking a stand for your beliefs isn't easy when you're outside of your comfort zone, but the rewards can be significant.</p>
        <p>A few years ago, I was flying from Athens to Dallas with my wife, who was several months pregnant. My company had paid for a business-class ticket for me, and my wife purchased her own seat in coach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nothing gives your principles a workout like a business trip. Taking a stand for your beliefs isn’t easy when you’re outside of your comfort zone, but the rewards can be significant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NOTHING gives your principles a workout like a business trip. Taking a stand for your beliefs isn't easy when you're outside of your comfort zone, but the rewards can be significant.</p>
        <p>A few years ago, I was flying from Athens to Dallas with my wife, who was several months pregnant. My company had paid for a business-class ticket for me, and my wife purchased her own seat in coach.</p>
        <p>When we checked in, I asked if we could swap seats.</p>
        <p>''No problem,'' the ticket agent said. ''Just ask the flight attendant once you've boarded.''</p>
        <p>After takeoff, I asked a crew member for permission to switch. The attendant, a short, pale-skinned man with straw-blond hair, said that wasn't allowed -- unless my wife was willing to pay several hundred dollars for an upgrade.</p>
        <p>''My wife is several months pregnant,'' I said, hoping to persuade him to bend the rules.</p>
        <p>He returned a blank expression.</p>
        <p>''But the ticket agent said it wouldn't be a problem,'' I continued. ''It's a terribly long flight. Why don't you just let us change seats?''</p>
        <p>''Sorry,'' he replied icily. ''Rules are rules.''</p>
        <p>It was time to take a stand. I packed up all of my carry-on bags and sat down behind my wife in the closest available seat in the coach cabin. If they weren't going to let her sit in my seat, then I didn't want to sit in it either.</p>
        <p>It took only a minute for the rule-abiding flight attendant to find me.</p>
        <p>''Why are you sitting here?'' he demanded. ''I thought I told you -- no swapping seats!''</p>
        <p>''And I haven't. I moved to coach to be with my wife.''</p>
        <p>''But that is not allowed.''</p>
        <p>Eventually, the captain had to be called to mediate our dispute. And after apologizing profusely, he ordered an upgrade for my spouse.</p>
        <p>The reward for standing up for your principles isn't always immediate. Or even immediately apparent.</p>
        <p>Not long ago, while I waited for my flight to leave from Paris, I was watching TV with several other passengers in the business-class lounge. Without warning, the lounge steward switched the channel on the television to a soccer match.</p>
        <p>The passengers were baffled, but no one said anything. Except me.</p>
        <p>''Why did you change the channel?'' I asked. ''Shouldn't we at least have been consulted?''</p>
        <p>The steward refused to change the channel back, and a heated argument ensued. Soon, the authorities arrived. But this time the outcome was different.</p>
        <p>One of the airline managers ruled in the steward's favor and issued the following ultimatum: either apologize to him or you won't be allowed to board your flight. Given that I had done nothing wrong -- except to question someone's choice in TV programming -- I took yet another stand by refusing. I spent an extra night in Paris and caught the next flight.</p>
        <p>So where's the reward in that? When I told the story to the prospective client I had planned to visit, he not only understood, he also respected my decision to stand firm, and ended up becoming a valuable customer.</p>
        <p>FREQUENT FLIER E-mail: elliott@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: elliott@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
