<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Young Mechanic Improves After Life-Saving Brain Surgery</title>
    <meta content="02brain" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health&amp;Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/02/health/02brain.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1815881"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aneurysms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Laser (Light Amplification by Stimulated Emission of Radiation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Emergency Medical Treatment</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Food and Drug Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grady, Denise</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ratuszny, Chris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Laser (Light Amplification by Stimulated Emission of Radiation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807EED71630F931A35752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="469" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Young Mechanic Improves After Life-Saving Brain Surgery</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Young Mechanic Improves After Life-Saving Brain Surgery</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENISE GRADY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Grady, Denise</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Follow-up article on Chris Ratuszny, who was described in December 19 Science Times article about brain aneurysms; notes that laser surgery used had to be approved by Food and Drug Administration for emergency case, but has been used in Europe; Ratuszny is expected to make full recovery; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chris Ratuszny went home from Roosevelt Hospital in Manhattan on Thursday, 16 days after a brain operation to treat a distended artery deep in his skull that was in danger of bursting and killing him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ratuszny's operation, which involved the experimental use of a laser, was the subject of an article in Science Times on Dec. 19.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chris Ratuszny went home 16 days after an operation to treat a distended artery in his brain that was in danger of bursting and killing him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Chris Ratuszny went home from Roosevelt Hospital in Manhattan on Thursday, 16 days after a brain operation to treat a distended artery deep in his skull that was in danger of bursting and killing him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ratuszny's operation, which involved the experimental use of a laser, was the subject of an article in Science Times on Dec. 19.</p>
        <p>The laser technique, developed in the Netherlands, has not been approved in the United States, but was allowed by the Food and Drug Administration for emergency use in Mr. Ratuszny's case. The laser lets surgeons operate on arteries in the brain without clamping them shut, a necessary step in conventional surgery, but one that can cause a stroke.</p>
        <p>The experimental technique worked. Mr. Ratuszny (ra-TOOSH-nee), 26, emerged intact -- walking, talking, cracking jokes and eager to see his 3-year-old son, Sam, and return to his job as a Lexus mechanic. He was entirely himself, his family said. The operation had begun to relieve the severe headaches and eye pain he had been suffering for two years because of pressure from the bulging artery, known as a giant aneurysm.</p>
        <p>''I don't think he could do much better,'' said his surgeon, Dr. David J. Langer, the director of cerebrovascular neurosurgery at St. Luke's-Roosevelt, Beth Israel and Long Island College Hospital, and an assistant professor at Albert Einstein Medical College.</p>
        <p>But like many people who have major operations, Mr. Ratuszny had suffered some setbacks. Dr. Langer had predicted that he might have transient speech problems, because the surgery involved the left side of his brain, which controls speech. That prediction came true, but the problems were a bit worse than even Dr. Langer had expected. Tests soon after the operation revealed large blood clots where the aneurysm had been, suggesting that it might have bled during the surgery. Doctors expected the speech difficulties to diminish as the clots dissolved and the pressure on the brain eased.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ratuszny began to improve, but another problem developed: a painful, drug-resistant staphylococcus infection that began in his arm, where an intravenous line had been inserted. He needed powerful antibiotics and surgery to drain the infection.</p>
        <p>Then, 10 days after the brain surgery -- just when he was supposed to go home -- Mr. Ratuszny's personality and alertness seemed to sag. Dr. Langer ordered scans and X-rays, and was shocked to find that several major arteries in his brain had gone into spasm, pinching down to only about 20 percent of their normal diameter and restricting the blood supply. The problem, called vasospasm, was most likely a reaction to the blood that had leaked into Mr. Ratuszny's brain from the aneurysm, Dr. Langer said. It responded to treatment and gradually subsided.</p>
        <p>Dr. Langer said he expected Mr. Ratuszny to make a full recovery and lead a normal life.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
