<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Coping With Diabetes on the Job</title>
    <meta content="l02diabetes" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1815926"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diabetes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harris, Rosemary (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Meyers, Deborah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Trent, Tina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sullivan, Reba</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mceniry, Charles</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lesburg, Susan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diabetes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E2D61630F931A35752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="597" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Coping With Diabetes on the Job</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Six letters comment on Dec 26 article about implications of employing diabetics; Dr Rosemary Harris says it has become good business for employers to shun diabetics and others with costly chronic diseases to keep health care costs down; Deborah Meyers calls for rewriting of Americans with Disabilities Act to provide clarity; Tina Trent scores person quoted for minimizing impact of disease on sufferers; Reba Sullivan says diabetics are responsible for managing their disease so it does not affect job performance; Charles McEniry says diabetes is prevelant among groups that are already targets of discrimination; Susan Lesburg says referring to people afflicted with diabetes as 'diabetics' is demeaning and promotes discrimination; drawing</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''Diabetics in the Workplace Confront a Tangle of Laws'' (front page, Dec. 26) details the plight of diabetic Americans -- who will double to 40 million in the next 20 years -- and alludes to the double bind for doctors who must try to keep their patients employed to have health insurance and access to care.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''Diabetics in the Workplace Confront a Tangle of Laws'' (front page, Dec. 26) details the plight of diabetic Americans -- who will double to 40 million in the next 20 years -- and alludes to the double bind for doctors who must try to keep their patients employed to have health insurance and access to care.</p>
        <p>Our current health system is driven by profit for insurance corporations. It is good business for employers to shun diabetics and other patients with costly chronic diseases and keep their insurance costs lower. Until health care in America becomes a right and not a privilege, the chronically ill will find themselves increasingly marginalized in the workplace.</p>
        <p>Rosemary Harris, M.D.  Newtown, Pa., Dec. 27, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The diabetics in your article demonstrate that not every illness or physical condition should be automatically considered a disability. What the article clearly shows is the desperate need to rewrite the Americans With Disabilities Act to provide clarity, even if it means tediously listing what is considered a disability and what is not.</p>
        <p>Go back and review the original purpose for the A.D.A. The previous definition of disability was that it adversely affected at least one or more of the major life activities. The prevailing perception among people today, however, is that a disability is the absence of optimal health. You need only observe those who use disabled parking spaces. People in wheelchairs should not have to compete for parking spaces with people who need no devices whatsoever for their mobility.</p>
        <p>The universal sign for disability has become obsolete.</p>
        <p>Deborah Meyers  Columbia, Md., Dec. 26, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In complaining that too many people who are not disabled demand special favors, William J. Kilberg, a Washington employment lawyer, compares the fact that he wears eyeglasses to the crippling complications experienced by both Type 1 and Type 2 diabetics. ''Why is everybody a victim?'' he muses.</p>
        <p>Indeed, if only organ death, blindness, painful nerve damage, the rigors of testing blood and injecting insulin, the threat of coma, dialysis, transplantation and death were as trivial as Mr. Kilberg perceives them. Perhaps new glasses might help.</p>
        <p>Tina Trent  Atlanta, Dec. 26, 2006</p>
        <p>The writer is a volunteer board member of a dialysis patients' rights group.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Yes, education is the key to better understanding about diabetics. But one aspect of the problem was not discussed. Diabetics need to manage the disease so that it does not affect job performance.</p>
        <p>Having hired and fired a diabetic worker, I found that the diabetic did not manage the illness, and therefore was unable to focus, frequently made severe errors in judgment because of neglect of diet and medication, and had to leave work early and frequently. Thus, performance was often very poor.</p>
        <p>Where, then, does the responsibility lie?</p>
        <p>Reba Sullivan  Dexter, Mich., Dec. 26, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Some groups of people seem more prone to diabetes than the rest of us: the obese, Hispanics, blacks and American Indians. This makes me wonder if diabetes has become yet another way to discriminate against people some are determined not to like.</p>
        <p>Charles McEniry  Stoughton, Wis., Dec. 26, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Thank you for your article. But you do a disservice to all those with diabetes by referring to them as ''diabetics.'' We are not our diseases; we are individuals with lives and families. Such a reference is demeaning and promotes just the discrimination you were reporting.</p>
        <p>Susan Lesburg  Boston, Dec. 26, 2006</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
