<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Checking Out, in Style or in Turmoil</title>
    <meta content="02watc" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/02/arts/television/02watc.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1815905"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE TV WATCH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stanley, Alessandra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hussein, Saddam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ford, Gerald Rudolph Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clark, Dick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seacrest, Ryan</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Dick Clark's New Year's Rockin' Eve (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">ABC Inc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hussein, Saddam</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Clark, Dick</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Seacrest, Ryan</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Ford, Gerald Rudolph Jr</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5D61630F931A35752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="618" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Checking Out, in Style or in Turmoil</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Checking Out, in Style or in Turmoil</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALESSANDRA STANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stanley, Alessandra</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alessandra Stanley TV Watch column on television offerings around New Year; notes that many channels were filled with death, including coverage of execution of Saddam Hussein, funeral of former pres Gerald Ford and tributes to late singer James Brown; holds that most startling image may have been frail Dick Clark as he appeared alongside Ryan Seacrest on Dick Clark's New Year's Rockin' Eve special; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a New Year's weekend bracketed by deaths, it turns out that it was sound, not pictures, that made shocking television.</p>
        <p>The background noise in a camera-cellphone recording of Saddam Hussein's execution -- jostling and sectarian insults -- belied the Iraqi government's portrait of the hasty hanging as a cool, considered meting of justice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the year’s final weekend, death dominates the air.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a New Year's weekend bracketed by deaths, it turns out that it was sound, not pictures, that made shocking television.</p>
        <p>The background noise in a camera-cellphone recording of Saddam Hussein's execution -- jostling and sectarian insults -- belied the Iraqi government's portrait of the hasty hanging as a cool, considered meting of justice.</p>
        <p>The accompanying dark and blurry shot of the Iraqi dictator falling though the gallows' trapdoor -- shown in its two-minute entirety on the Internet but not on most television news programs -- was about as distinct as a sonogram. It was an unsettling sight, but not really all that graphic or gruesome.</p>
        <p>It was more the idea of watching Mr. Hussein die -- a snuff reality show -- that spooked many viewers. It certainly gave news directors pause. But the first images of the execution, filmed by Iraqi officials and shown within hours on Iraqi and American television, came without the ambient sounds that defined his final moments.</p>
        <p>Networks and cable news outlets hesitated briefly about showing the unexpurgated version after it began ricocheting around the Internet on Sunday. But most news programs showed at least some of it. The tape turned out to hold redeeming -- and damning -- news value: it suggested to viewers that the execution that President Bush initially described as ''an important milestone'' in Iraq's advance toward democracy was actually more of a millstone.</p>
        <p>Next to the screams and confusion around the gallows in Baghdad, the slow, stately processions in honor of former President Gerald R. Ford seemed almost on mute. As well-wishers lined up to pass before his flag-covered coffin, lying in state in the Capitol rotunda, the only sound came from marine guards' high-gloss shoes squeaking on the polished marble floor.</p>
        <p>Small wonder CNN kept going back to snippets of ''Get Up (I Feel Like Being a) Sex Machine, Pt. 1,'' sung at the raw, boisterous tribute to James Brown in Augusta, Ga. Michael Jackson stood onstage like a bereaved relative, and the Rev. Al Sharpton stepped up as mourner in chief, giving instructions to St. Peter. ''You need to open up the gates for the Godfather,'' he thundered. Mr. Brown's music was the unofficial soundtrack of the era when Mr. Ford was in office (Mr. Brown sang ''Say It Loud -- I'm Black and I'm Proud'' at President Richard M. Nixon's inaugural festivities in 1969), so those incongruous segues made poetic sense.</p>
        <p>Some of the most startling images of the new year were the ones meant to distract and entertain. As he did last year, a frail Dick Clark, 77, took a seat in ABC's Times Square studio to preside over his signature holiday special, ''Dick Clark's New Year's Rockin' Eve.''</p>
        <p>Ryan Seacrest, a Dick Clark Mini-Me and the host of ''American Idol,'' actually led the show. But despite a 2004 stroke that left him in a wheelchair and his speech impaired, Mr. Clark, wearing a tuxedo jacket with shiny lapels, made brief cameos. His voice was slurred and his face gaunt and waxy, but he smiled gamely as he introduced Christina Aguilera and called out the countdown to midnight.</p>
        <p>Television has little patience with the aging and not much time for stroke victims, so it was both reassuring and painful to see Mr. Clark struggling to still fit into his nickname, ''America's oldest teenager.''</p>
        <p>Anyone who thinks that elderly entertainers can gracefully retire and surrender the limelight don't know anything about show business. As usual, the hardest-working man in it said it best.</p>
        <p>In an interview he gave in 1989 while in prison for, among other things, a PCP-fueled high-speed car chase, Mr. Brown was asked how he was feeling.</p>
        <p>''I'm well rested,'' the singer replied. ''But I miss being tired.''</p>
        <p>THE TV WATCH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
