<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE LISTINGS | JAN. 19 - JAN. 25</title>
    <meta content="19theater" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070130T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1819787"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E7D61130F93AA25752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="16173" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE LISTINGS | JAN. 19 - JAN. 25</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the New York metropolitan region this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'ADRIFT IN MACAO' Previews start on Tuesday. Opens on Feb 13. Primary Stages presents Christopher Durang and Peter Melnick's new musical send-up of the sexy, shadowy world of film noir (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'THE FEVER' In previews; opens on Jan. 29. Wallace Shawn stars in his own play about a man who wakes up in a war-torn country feeling under the weather (1:30). Acorn Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'FRANK'S HOME' In previews; opens on Jan. 30. Richard Nelson's new bio-play about the life and work of Frank Lloyd Wright stars Peter Weller (as Wright) and Harris Yulin (who plays Louis Sullivan) (1:45). Playwrights Horizons Mainstage, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 719-4200.</p>
        <p>'THE GAZILLION BUBBLE SHOW' Performances through Tuesday; returning on Feb. 15. Fan Yan holds the world's record for the largest bubble ever blown, and in an even more amazing feat, he's parlayed this oddball stunt into a bubble-themed, family-friendly show (2:00). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'IN THE HEIGHTS' In previews; opens on Feb. 8. A new Off Broadway musical about two days in the life of Washington Heights, presented from the vantage point of a corner bodega (2:10). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'KIKI AND HERB' On the heels of a Broadway stint, these cabaret hipsters return to their downtown roots (1:30). Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555.</p>
        <p>'THE MERCHANT OF VENICE' In previews; opens on Feb. 4. F. Murray Abraham plays Shylock in this Theater for a New Audience production. Darko Tresnjak directs (2:20). The Duke on 42nd Street, 229 West 42nd Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'A SPANISH PLAY' In previews; opens on Feb. 1. Zoe Caldwell leads an extraordinary cast (Linda Emond, Denis O'Hare, Larry Pine, Katherine Borowitz) in Yasmina Reza's new backstage play, in which real life and fiction blur (1:30). Classic Stage Company, 136 East 13th Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101.</p>
        <p>'TRANSLATIONS' In previews; opens on Thursday. Brian Friel's drama about a British officer in 19th-century rural Ireland deals with themes of language, imperialism and culture clash. Garry Hynes directs (2:15). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE APPLE TREE' The amazing Kristin Chenoweth gives Imax-screen-size life to three curvaceous doodles who by rights shouldn't be any larger than figures in the Sunday funnies. Jerry Bock and Sheldon Harnick's 1966 musical, directed by Gary Griffin, shows its age but is given theatrical verve by Ms. Chenoweth, Brian d'Arcy James and Marc Kudisch (2:30). Studio 54, 254 West 54th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>'A CHORUS LINE' If you want to know why this show was such a big deal when it opened 31 years ago, you need only experience the thrilling first five minutes of this revival. Otherwise, this archivally exact production, directed by Bob Avian, feels like a vintage car that has been taken out of the garage, polished up and sent on the road once again (2:00). Schoenfeld Theater, 236 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE COAST OF UTOPIA' The exhilarating first two installments of Tom Stoppard's trilogy about 19th-century Russian intellectuals dreaming of revolution, these productions pulse with the dizzy, spring-green arrogance and anxiety of a new generation moving as fast as it can toward the future. Jack O'Brien directs a fresh, vigorous and immense cast that includes Brian F. O'Byrne, Jennifer Ehle, Billy Crudup and Ethan Hawke (2:45). Vivian Beaumont Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'COMPANY' Fire, beckoning and dangerous, flickers beneath the frost of John Doyle's elegant, unexpectedly stirring revival of Stephen Sondheim and George Furth's era-defining musical from 1970, starring a compellingly understated Raul Esparza. Like Mr. Doyle's ''Sweeney Todd,'' this production finds new clarity of feeling in Sondheim by melding the roles of performers and musicians (2:20). Barrymore Theater, 243 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE' (Tony Awards, best book of a musical and best original score, 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920s stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, it has theatergoers responding as if they were withering houseplants finally being watered after long neglect. Bob Martin and Sutton Foster are the standouts in the avid, energetic cast (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'GREY GARDENS' Christine Ebersole is absolutely glorious as the middle-aged, time-warped debutante called Little Edie Beale in this uneven musical adaptation of the notorious 1975 documentary of the same title. She and the wonderful Mary Louise Wilson (as her bedridden mother), in the performances of their careers, make ''Grey Gardens'' an experience no passionate theatergoer should miss (2:40). Walter Kerr Theater, 219 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE LITTLE DOG LAUGHED' The comedy of manners, a form widely believed to be extinct in the American theater, has actually resurfaced on Broadway with all its vital signs intact in Douglas Carter Beane's breezy but trenchant satire about truth and illusion, Hollywood style. With the wonderful Julie White as the movie agent you hate to love (but just can't help it) (2:00). Cort Theater, 138 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MARY POPPINS' This handsome, homily-packed, mechanically ingenious and rather tedious musical, adapted from the P. L. Travers stories and the 1964 Disney film, is ultimately less concerned with inexplicable magic than with practical psychology. Ashley Brown, who sings prettily as the family-mending nanny, looks like Joan Crawford trying to be nice and sounds like Dr. Phil. Directed by Richard Eyre and Matthew Bourne (2:30). New Amsterdam Theater, 214 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LES MISÉRABLES' This premature revival, a slightly scaled-down version of the well-groomed behemoth that closed only three years ago, appears to be functioning in a state of mild sedation. Appealingly sung and freshly orchestrated, this fast-moving adaptation of Victor Hugo's novel isn't sloppy or blurry. But its pulse rate stays well below normal (2:55). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' Duncan Sheik and Steven Sater's bold adaptation of the Frank Wedekind play is the freshest and most exciting new musical Broadway has seen in some time. Set in 19th-century Germany but with a ravishing rock score, it exposes the splintered emotional lives of adolescents just discovering the joys and sorrows of sex. Performed with brio by a great cast, with supple direction by Michael Mayer and inventive choreography by Bill T. Jones (2:00). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN' This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a superdeluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE VERTICAL HOUR' David Hare's soggy consideration of the Anglo-American cultural divide stars Julianne Moore (representing the Americans) and Bill Nighy (leading the British), directed by Sam Mendes. The Yanks don't stand a chance. With his irresistibly mannered performance as a laconic doctor, Mr. Nighy mops the floor with Ms. Moore. Actually, he mops the floor with Mr. Hare's play (2:20). Music Box Theater, 239 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'AS YET THOU ART YOUNG AND RASH' An abstract collage of shards of feeling built out of Euripides' ''Suppliant Women,'' this meditation on grief and the death of children in senseless war offers plenty of parallels to current society without doing anything so obvious as explicitly referring to them. The five-member cast, led by three beautiful middle-aged women, is strong; the director, David Herskovits, has helped them shape an evocative piece that might be too nonliteral for some tastes, but is both moving and distinctive (1:10). The Ohio Theater, 66 Wooster Street, SoHo, (212) 352-3101. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>'THE BIG VOICE: GOD OR MERMAN?' Think of two gifted and smart gay men with years of life together deploying their considerable talents from the two pianos you happen to have in your living room. The result is a hilarious and very touching memoir of two decades of love and the funky glories of show business life (2:00). Actors Temple Theater, 339 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Honor Moore)</p>
        <p>*'THE CLEAN HOUSE' Sarah Ruhl's comedy about the painful but beautiful disorder of life has arrived in New York at last in a gorgeous production directed by Bill Rauch. Blair Brown and Jill Clayburgh delight as sisters with different views on the meaning of cleaning, and Vanessa Aspillaga is equally good as the depressed maid with little affection for her work but a deep conviction that a good joke can be a matter of life and death (2:15). Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, Lincoln Center, 150 West 65th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'DAI (ENOUGH)' Iris Bahr's unnerving one-woman show doesn't have much to add to the Middle East debate, but it sure leaves a lasting impression. Ms. Bahr plays an assortment of characters who have the misfortune of being in a Tel Aviv cafe that is about to be visited by the havoc common to such establishments. The attack is rendered in jarring fashion, repeatedly; you watch the play on pins and needles, waiting for the next burst. Gimmicky? Sure. But viscerally effective (1:40). Culture Project, 55 Mercer Street, at Broome Street, SoHo, (212) 253-9983. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'THE FANTASTICKS' A revival -- well, more like a resuscitation -- of the Little Musical That Wouldn't Die. This sweet-as-ever production of Tom Jones and Harvey Schmidt's commedia-dell'arte-style confection is most notable for Mr. Jones's touching performance (under the pseudonym Thomas Bruce) as the Old Actor, a role he created when the show opened in 1960. Mr. Jones also directs (2:05). Snapple Theater Center, 210 West 50th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'GET YOUR WAR ON' Based on the absurdist comic strip of David Rees, this sardonic history lesson of the past six years will delight Bush-haters (1:10). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200. (Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'GUTENBERG! THE MUSICAL' A very funny if not terribly original satire of musical theater features what must be the worst backers' audition of all time. The excellent duo Jeremy Shamos and Christopher Fitzgerald make the pitch (2:05). The Actors' Playhouse, 100 Seventh Avenue South, at Fourth Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 239-6200. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'A JEW GROWS IN BROOKLYN' You don't have to be Jewish or Brooklynish to empathize with Jake Ehrenreich, but in terms of fully appreciating his essentially one-man show, it probably helps. Especially the Catskills jokes (2:05). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 560-8912. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>'MEET ME IN ST. LOUIS' This musical is too big for its stage, but the young turn-of-the-last-century sweethearts have great chemistry, and there are four terrific songs (2:00). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'MY MOTHER'S ITALIAN, MY FATHER'S JEWISH AND I'M IN THERAPY' Steve Solomon does skillful impersonations in his one-man show, but some of his jokes are as old as the hills (1:30). Little Shubert Theater, 422 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'NO CHILD' Teachers will love Nilaja Sun's one-woman show about the challenges of teaching drama at Malcolm X High School (1:10). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, at Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'REGRETS ONLY' Old acquaintance comes under siege in Paul Rudnick's chiffon-thin comedy about the varieties of love and marriage. But no one who sees this latest offering from one of the funniest quipmeisters alive is going to doubt that Christine Baranski is a one-liner's best friend (2:00). City Center Stage I, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RIDDLELIKELOVE (WITH A SIDE OF KETCHUP)' This one-woman show, in which Julie Fitzpatrick tells of her friendship with a deaf woman, is cloying and thin, but the sign-language interpretation provided at each performance gives it an interesting extra dimension, helping to bring the subject to life (1:30). Ensemble Studio Theater, 549 West 52nd Street, Clinton, (212) 352-3101. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'ROOM SERVICE' The Peccadillo Theater Company puts a charge into this comedy from the 1930s, thanks to a brisk pace by the director, Dan Wackerman, and a dozen dandy performances. David Edwards is the would-be producer whose bills threaten to swamp his efforts to put a show on Broadway, and Fred Berman is particularly fine as his director (2:00). SoHo Playhouse, 15 Vandam Street, South Village, (212) 691-1555. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'THE SCENE' Theresa Rebeck's latest is a sharp-witted, sharp-elbowed comedy about the savage economies of sex and show business in Manhattan. Tony Shalhoub plays an out-of-work actor, Charlie, happily married -- but not really -- to Patricia Heaton's frazzled chat show booker. Enter femme fatale Clea, played by the gifted Anna Camp, and goodbye, Charlie (2:00). Second Stage Theater, 307 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 246-4422. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'TOYS IN THE ATTIC' Austin Pendleton's fine revival of Lillian Hellman's last play faithfully attacks the corrosive attachments of family. What good is a family, and thus a society, the play implicitly asks, that can only look in the mirror? (2:30) Pearl Theater, 80 St. Marks Place, East Village, (212) 598-9802. (Ginia Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'25 QUESTIONS FOR A JEWISH MOTHER' This is the comedian Judy Gold's fiercely funny monologue, based on her own life as a single Jewish lesbian mother and interviews with more than 50 other Jewish mothers (1:20). St. Luke's Theater, 308 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Phoebe Hoban)</p>
        <p>* 'THE VIETNAMIZATION OF NEW JERSEY (AN AMERICAN TRAGEDY)' A revival of Christopher Durang's satire of war, family life and Bicentennial fever, on the 30th anniversary of its debut at the Yale Repertory Theater, swishes along at the speed of a Nascar race. Blanche Baker is a gem as an out-of-it 1970s matron who just can't dust off the Eisenhower era. the Beckett Theater, on Theater Row, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>* 'THE VOYSEY INHERITANCE' David Mamet has cleanly and cannily adapted Harley Granville Barker's 1905 play about corruption in the genteel world of Victorian finance. An excellent cast and a sumptuous production bring extra immediacy to a tale of embezzlement and entitlement that feels as fresh as tomorrow's stock options (1:50). Atlantic Theater, 336 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'FLUKE' A meditative collage of enigmatic riffs on ''Moby-Dick'' presented by the rambunctious experimental company Radiohole (1:30). Collapsable Hole, 146 Metropolitan Avenue, at Berry Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 388-2251. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden Theater, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' Singing CliffsNotes for Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' Often more entertaining than the real thing (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS' The biomusical that walks like a man (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT' A singing scrapbook for Monty Python fans (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' ''A Chorus Line'' with pimples (1:45). Circle in the Square, 254 West 50th Street, Manhattan, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'PURITY' The provocateur Thomas Bradshaw's horror show confronts black-on-black racism (1:15). Performance Space 122, 150 First Avenue, at Ninth Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101; closes on Tuesday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'SUDDENLY LAST SUMMER' As the luscious (and lobotomy-threatened) damsel in distress in Tennessee Williams's famously lurid melodrama, Carla Gugino gives a gutsy assurance to a production that otherwise lacks compelling confidence. Mark Brokaw directs a cast that includes Blythe Danner, in a fascinating but misconceived performance as a smothering mother from hell (1:30). Laura Pels Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300; closes on Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'PARTY TIME' This multimedia work by the Talking Band looks great, but it's really just a reworking of the old two-guys-in-a-foxhole plot. Here the foxhole is a tank in a desert war; its two occupants (Will Badgett and Joe Roseto) sing about their lives and fears as they try to find a rendezvous point. It's visceral without being illuminating (1:00). LaMaMa, 74A East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 475-7710; closes on Sunday. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'THE RAPTURE PROJECT' Marionettes of various faiths clash in this confusing modern take on an old brand of Sicilian puppet theater by Great Small Works. A Susan Sontag puppet makes an appearance, as does one that calls to mind a former New York City police commissioner, but more often than not, the musical accompaniment is the liveliest thing about the show (1:30). The Here Arts Center, 145 Avenue of the Americas, at Dominick Street, South Village, (212) 868-4444; closes on Sunday. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'YOU BELONG TO ME: DEATH OF NATIONS, PART V' The fifth, choppily considered installment of the writer and director Josh Fox's millennial play cycle examines the final days of three wars. Should we think about war primarily in terms of the havoc it wreaks on love and sex? He seems to think so (3:00). Performance Space 122, 150 First Avenue, at Ninth Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101; closes on Tuesday. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>* 'ABDUCTION: THE MEGUMI YOKOTA STORY' (No rating, 85 minutes, in Japanese) This documentary about the titular 13-year-old girl -- who vanished on the way home from school in Niigata, Japan, in 1977, and was revealed as a pawn in a North Korean spy-training program -- succeeds as a true crime story, a thumbnail history of a painful recent chapter of Asian history and as a portrait of lives transformed by trauma. Meandering in places, but compassionate and engrossing throughout. (Matt Zoller Seitz)</p>
        <p>'ALPHA DOG' (R, 117 minutes) Based on a true Southern California crime, Nick Cassavetes's entertaining exploitation flick features a lot of attractive, talented young actors shimmying across the screen while embodying the collective parental nightmare. Do you know where your children are? Well, in this film they're getting busy, chilling out, smoking blunts and chugging coolers faster than a toothless wino. Oh, and committing murder. (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>'ARTHUR AND THE INVISIBLES' (PG, 94 minutes) Luc Besson serves up a hybrid of live actors and computer-generated figures to tell a not-endearing-enough story about a boy (Freddie Highmore) who shrinks to microscopic size to find some gems and his missing grandfather. Lots of famous names (Madonna, Robert De Niro, David Bowie, Snoop Dogg) lend their voices to the computerized part of the movie, but only briefly near the end does everything click. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'BABEL' (R, 143 minutes, in English, Spanish, Japanese, Berber, Arabic and sign language) This hugely ambitious movie tells four loosely linked, not quite simultaneous stories set on three different continents, with dialogue in several languages. The themes, to the extent they are decipherable, include loss, fate and the terrible consequences of miscommunication. Written by Guillermo Arriaga and directed by Alejandro Gonzalez Iñárritu, the movie is an intellectual muddle but a visceral tour de force, and the power of the filmmaking almost overcomes the fuzziness of the ideas. Almost. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>'BLOOD DIAMOND' (R, 138 minutes) The makers of this foolish thriller about illegal diamond trafficking in Africa, starring an excellent Leonardo DiCaprio, want you to know there may be blood on your hands, specifically your wedding finger. Too bad they haven't thought through what it means to turn human misery into entertainment. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'BORAT: CULTURAL LEARNINGS OF AMERICA FOR MAKE BENEFIT GLORIOUS NATION OF KAZAKHSTAN' (R, 89 minutes) In this brainy, merciless comedy, a Kazakh journalist named Borat Sagdiyev, a k a the British comic Sacha Baron Cohen, invades America. America laughs, cries, surrenders. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'CHARLOTTE'S WEB' (G, 113 minutes) Gary Winick's adaptation of E. B. White's great children's novel is faithful to the wit and feeling of the source. The celebrity-voiced animals are charming, and Julia Roberts is in fine form as the heroic spider, whose writing ability saves the life of a pig. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'CHILDREN OF MEN' (R, 100 minutes) The end is nigh in this superbly directed political thriller by Alfonso Cuarón about a nervously plausible future. Based on the P. D. James book, the film stars an excellent Clive Owen and features equally sterling support from the actors Michael Caine, Danny Huston and Chiwetel Ejiofior, among others, as well as the great cinematographer Emmanuel Lubezki. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'CODE NAME: THE CLEANER' (PG-13, 91 minutes) Cedric the Entertainer clogs the arteries of what could have been a savvy riff on the ''Bourne'' films with way too much ham, playing a janitor who wakes up with amnesia, a dead man beside him. A missing computer chip fuels the plot, aided by Lucy Liu and Nicollette Sheridan. Though it's all too dumb to amuse grownups, it's harmless fun for tweener types. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'COMEDY OF POWER' (No rating, 110 minutes, in French) Isabelle Huppert is brisk and fierce as a French investigative judge going after corrupt fat cats. The director, Claude Chabrol, is more interested in the forms of ruling-class behavior than in the details of high-level criminality, but his detached, complacent style makes for an interesting contrast with Ms. Huppert's conviction. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'CURSE OF THE GOLDEN FLOWER' (R, 114 minutes, in Mandarin) The Chinese director Zhang Yimou aims for Shakespeare and winds up with Jacqueline Susann in this Tang dynasty melodrama roiling with incest, fraternal rivalry and madness-inducing fungus. As an emperor and empress fighting for control of their three sons, Chow Yun Fat and Gong Li lend the film a core of marital toxicity that's deliciously unstable. Directing with operatic delirium, Mr. Zhang has created a movie in which the line between tragedy and black comedy has been all but erased. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* 'THE DEPARTED' (R, 150 minutes) Martin Scorsese's cubistic entertainment about men divided by power, loyalty and their own selves is at once a success and a relief. Based on the crackling Hong Kong thriller ''Infernal Affairs,'' it features fine twinned performances from Matt Damon and Leonardo DiCaprio, and a showboating Jack Nicholson. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'DREAMGIRLS' (PG-13, 131 minutes) The Broadway musical arrives on the screen, capably directed by Bill Condon, ardently acted and sung by Jamie Foxx, Eddie Murphy, Beyoncé Knowles and (especially) Jennifer Hudson, but undone by mediocre and anachronistic songs. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'FREEDOM WRITERS' (PG-13, 123 minutes) Hilary Swank uses her characteristic neediness to fine effect in a true-to-life story about a teacher making a difference in a Southern California high school. The writer and director Richard LaGravenese provides the smartly laid foundation, but it's the kids who give the film its strong emotional tug. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'GOD GREW TIRED OF US' (PG, 90 minutes) This sober, uplifting documentary, which won two major awards at last year's Sundance Film Festival, follows the resettlement in the United States of three Sudanese young men uprooted as children by the civil war. Handsomely photographed, and inspirational but not cloyingly so, it is the rare contemporary documentary that doesn't leave a residue of cynicism and outrage. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE GOOD GERMAN' (R, 102 minutes) In his adaptation of the Joseph Kanon novel, Steven Soderbergh tries to resurrect the magic of classical Hollywood, principally by sucking out all the air, energy and pleasure from his own filmmaking. It's no wonder George Clooney, who stars alongside a vamping Cate Blanchett, looks confused. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'GURU' (No rating, 166 minutes, in Hindi) The Tamil director Mani Ratnam makes the case for India's growing economic clout with this entertaining epic about the rise and rise of Gurukant Desai, a fictitious Mumbai polyester manufacturer. The actress Aishwarya Rai, as Guru's wife, is a welcome presence, but the picture belongs to Abhishek Bachchan, who gives a rich, varied performance in the title role. (Andy Webster)</p>
        <p>'HAPPILY N'EVER AFTER' (PG, 87 minutes) Like Dreamworks's ''Shrek'' comedies, ''Happily'' is a grab-bag parody set in a fantasyland derived from bedtime stories and Disney films. The adopted chambermaid Ella (voiced by Sarah Michelle Gellar, drawn like Winona Ryder) and the poor dishwasher Rick (Freddie Prinze Jr.) battle Ella's wicked stepmother, Frieda (Sigourney Weaver). Despite self-aware touches, this is another tired kidsploitation product in which a wasp-waisted ingénue and a shallow beau drive the plot and live happily ever after. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>'THE LAST KING OF SCOTLAND' (R, 121 minutes) Kevin Macdonald paints a queasily enjoyable portrait of the Ugandan dictator Idi Amin from inside the palace walls. Forest Whitaker plays the mad king, while James McAvoy plays the fool. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'LETTERS FROM IWO JIMA' (R, 141 minutes, in Japanese) Another masterwork from Clint Eastwood's astonishing late period, and one of the best war movies ever. Ken Watanabe is especially fine as the general commanding Japanese troops in the doomed defense of the island of Iwo Jima. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'LITTLE CHILDREN' (R, 130 minutes) Todd Field's adaptation of Tom Perrotta's novel of suburban adultery is unfailingly intelligent and faultlessly acted. Kate Winslet and Patrick Wilson are superb as the parents of young children who meet at the playground and enact a two-handed variation on ''Madame Bovary'' against a backdrop of social paranoia and middle-class malaise. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'MISS POTTER' (PG, 92 minutes) In ''Miss Potter,'' Renée Zellweger, her face pickled in cheeriness, is Beatrix Potter, the creator of Peter Rabbit, Squirrel Nutkin and Mrs. Tittlemouse, among other beloved characters in children's literature. As portrayed by Ms. Zellweger, Potter is almost as chipper as Julie Andrews's Mary Poppins, a proto-feminist, proto-environmentalist and perfect lady to boot. There was plenty of drama in Potter's life, but the movie turns major conflicts and losses into minor setbacks in a charmed, entirely virtuous life. The movie is far too nice for its own good. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'NIGHT AT THE MUSEUM' (PG, 108 minutes) In this chaotic, overstuffed family comedy, Ben Stiller is a night watchman at the American Museum of Natural History, where the exhibits come to life at night and attack him and one another. This computerized spectacle spares no expense, but the storytelling is weak, and the hit-or-miss jokes miss more than hit. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'NOTES ON A SCANDAL' (R, 92 minutes) Judi Dench and Cate Blanchett play a misogynistic game of cat and mouse from which no one emerges unscathed, including the audience. Adapted by Patrick Marber from a novel by Zoë Heller and directed by Richard Eyre. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'PAN'S LABYRINTH' (R, 119 minutes, in Spanish) Guillermo del Toro's tale of a young girl's ordeal in post-Civil-War fascist Spain is either a fairy tale in the guise of a political allegory or vice versa. In either case it is a moving, enchanting, strange and humane example of popular art at its very best. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE PAINTED VEIL' (PG-13, 125 minutes) Nicely directed by John Curran, this version of the W. Somerset Maugham novel draws you in by turning a distaff bildungsroman into a fine romance with Naomi Watts and Edward Norton. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'PRIMEVAL' (R, 94 minutes) A giant crocodile named Gustave terrorizes Western journalists in war-torn Burundi. Not as much fun as it might have been, but not as terrible either. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE PURSUIT OF HAPPYNESS' (PG-13, 117 minutes) How you respond to this fairy tale in realist drag may depend on whether you find Will Smith's performances so overwhelmingly winning that you buy the idea that poverty is a function of bad luck and bad choices, and success the result of heroic toil and dreams. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'THE QUEEN' (PG-13, 103 minutes) Directed by Stephen Frears from a very smart script by Peter Morgan, and starring a magnificent Helen Mirren in the title role, ''The Queen'' pries open a window in the House of Windsor around the time of the death of Diana, Princess of Wales, blending fact with fiction. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'ROCKY BALBOA' (PG, 102 minutes) Surprisingly, the sixth installment of this franchise is no embarrassment. Like its forerunners, it goes the distance almost in spite of itself. It's all heart and no credibility, except as a raw-boned fable. From the very beginning, Rocky Balboa was about as lifelike a character as Popeye pumped up with spinach. But that may be the point of a series that peddles the notion that if you dream it hard enough, you can live it. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'STOMP THE YARD' (PG-13, 109 minutes) Brotherhood is powerful in this sometimes compelling, sometimes complacent movie about stepping and African-American fraternity life at an Atlanta institution called Truth University. DJ (Columbus Short), a street-style dancer, needs to find his place in a university ruled by Gammas and Thetas and stepping. (Rachel Saltz)</p>
        <p>'TEARS OF THE BLACK TIGER' (No rating, 113 minutes, in Thai) A western weepie from Thailand, filmed in garish color. In spite of the relentless genre pastiche, it has a charming sincerity. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'VENUS' (R, 91 minutes) A modest, diverting, touching tale of a young woman who attracts the interest -- avuncular and also erotic -- of an aging actor, played with effortless aplomb by the great Peter O'Toole. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'VOLVER' (R, 121 minutes, in Spanish) Another keeper from Pedro Almodóvar, with Penélope Cruz -- as a resilient widow -- in her best role to date. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'WE ARE MARSHALL' (PG, 128 minutes) This fact-based story of a West Virginia college town recovering from the death of its entire football team in a 1970 plane crash is a stiff, manipulative dud that gets wrong everything ''Friday Night Lights'' got right. Matthew McConaughey hams it up as the college's goofy new coach, who whips the replacement team into decent shape. (Holden)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>ROBERT ALTMAN REMEMBERED (Tonight through Tuesday) A tribute to the late American filmmaker winds up with several seldom seen Altman films: ''Three Women,'' ''Buffalo Bill and the Indians,'' ''McCabe and Mrs. Miller,'' ''Tanner '88,'' ''Health,'' ''A Wedding,'' ''Secret Honor'' and ''Come Back to the Five and Dime, Jimmy Dean.'' IFC Center, 323 Avenue of the Americas, at West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 924-7771, ifccenter.com; $10.75. (Dave Kehr)</p>
        <p>CRITICS CHOICE: GREAT DOCUMENTARIES (Tomorrow and Sunday) A series of significant documentaries chosen and introduced by members of the New York Film Critics Circle continues this weekend. Matt Zoller Seitz, who contributes to The New York Times and publishes The House Next Door Web site, is joined by the director Albert Maysles tomorrow for a screening of Mr. Maysles's 1968 cinéma-verité study ''Salesman,'' and Stuart Klawans of The Nation on Sunday presents Nora Jacobson's hard look at real estate development in Hoboken, N.J., ''Delivered Vacant.'' (Through Feb. 25.) Museum of the Moving Image, 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, (718) 784-0077, movingimage.us; $10. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>GLOBAL LENS 2007 (Tonight through Thursday) A continuing program of 10 feature films from developing countries, sponsored by the Global Film Initiative. This week's offerings include Li Yu's Chinese film ''Dam Street,'' about the friendship between a washed-up opera singer and a 10-year-old child, which concludes an extended run, with screenings tonight through Monday. On Thursday there's the Kurdistan-French co-production ''Kilometre Zero,'' a story of the ethnic conflict between Kurds and Iraqis set during the Iran-Iraq war of the 1980s, written and directed by Hiner Saleem. (Through Jan. 28.) Museum of Modern Art, Roy and Niuta Titus Theaters, (212) 708-9400, moma.org; $10. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>KEN AND AZAZEL JACOBS (Tonight through Tuesday) Anthology Film Archives is holding the premiere engagements of two new films from the avant-garde eminence Ken Jacobs (whose epic exercise in associative editing, ''Star Spangled to Death,'' has recently been released on DVD) and Azazel Jacobs, a son of Mr. Jacobs who is following in his father's footsteps. ''The Goodtimeskid,'' is by the younger Mr. Jacobs and is a 77-minute color feature that follows two men with the same name and a woman involved with them both over the course of 24 hours in Los Angeles. ''Two Wrenching Departures,'' by the senior Mr. Jacobs, is a black-and-white video piece. First produced as a live performance, it is about two of Mr. Jacobs's friends, the underground filmmakers Jack Smith (''Flaming Creatures'') and Bob Fleischner (''Banners''), who died within a week of each other in October 1989. Anthology Film Archives, 32 Second Avenue, at Second Street, East Village, (212) 505-5181, anthologyfilmarchives.org; $8. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>Pop  Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>* 'THE AMERICAN BEAUTY PROJECT' (Tomorrow and Sunday) The Grateful Dead had its origins in the folk revival, but it took a while for the band to find the right balance between long-form psychedelic jams and small-scale, acoustic country-folk. A diverse group of musicians gathers this weekend to pay tribute to the Dead's two eureka albums from 1970. Performing songs from ''Workingman's Dead'' tomorrow are the Klezmatics, Ollabelle, the Holmes Brothers, Jim Lauderdale, Larry Campbell and Tim O'Reagan of the Jayhawks. Playing from ''American Beauty'' on Sunday are Mark Eitzel, Jay Farrar, Espers, Toshi Reagon, Jorma Kaukonen, Dar Williams, Mr. Lauderdale, Ollabelle and Mr. Campbell. Tony Trischka and Andy Statman play instrumental interludes. At 8 p.m., Winter Garden, World Financial Center, West Street, south of Vesey Street, Lower Manhattan, (212) 945-0505, worldfinancialcenter.com; free. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>ARAMIRÈ (Tonight) This folk ensemble from the Salento region of Italy is dedicated to one of the lesser-known traditions of the country, the Greek-influenced music of the southeast of Italy's ''heel.'' With strings, accordion, flute and lots of tambourine, it pays particular attention to the pizzica, a galloping six-beat dance related to the tarantella and long used as a faith-healing cure for spider bites. At 8:30, Zankel Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7000, carnegiehall.org; $30 to $42. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* CAMERA OBSCURA (Wednesday) Like their fellow Glaswegians Belle and Sebastian, Camera Obscura, led by the expressively plain-voiced Tracyanne Campbell, is in love with wistful 1960s folk-pop and plays a country-leaning variation on it with taste and finesse. With the Essex Green. At 8 p.m., Warsaw, 261 Driggs Avenue, at Eckford Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 387-0505, warsawconcerts.com; $15.50 in advance, $17 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* KRISTIN CHENOWETH (Tonight) This Tony Award-winning treasure plays the Metropolitan Opera House; she's only the third musical-theater person the Met has ever presented in a solo gig. Appearing with a 12-piece orchestra and dancers, she is to add some opera arias to her usual repertory. At 8, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $50 to $200. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>CLIPSE (Wednesday) Comeback stories are rare and sweet in rap. In 2002 this Virginia duo rose all the way to No. 4 with sly rhymes about the criminal life and brutally minimal rhythm tracks by the Neptunes. Since then the Clipse struggled in music-industry purgatory but triumphed with ''Hell Hath No Fury'' (Re-Up Gang/Jive), another cold, lean and virtuosic exercise that was one of the best hip-hop albums of 2006. At 7:30 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; $25 in advance, $30 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>COLD WAR KIDS (Wednesday) The craggy guitars, verge-of-a-breakdown vocals and elliptical songwriting of this band from Austin, Tex., put it at the top of the music-blogger food chain last year. Now comes the hard part: maintaining popularity as the Internet eye roves again. This month the band is bouncing back and forth between New York and Los Angeles each week in a ''bicoastal residency.'' With Illinois and the Virgins. At 8:30 p.m., Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700, mercuryloungenyc.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MARK EITZEL (Tonight) Depression is Mr. Eitzel's element; as leader of the American Music Club and through a solo career, he has anatomized melancholy down to the molecular level. In a weary voice, with tunes that blur folk songs and torch songs in a smoky haze, he looks at estrangement and betrayal, loneliness and separation, and bad luck. At 8, Union Hall, 702 Union Street, at Fifth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 638-4400, unionhallny.com; $12. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>DIAMANDA GALÁS (Sunday) Though she is invariably dressed in black, with her face in witchy streaks of makeup, Ms. Galás needs only her voice to terrify and seduce. She slides from a low, sensual growl to painful yet musically precise shrieks, and has a vast repertory that ranges from Johnny Cash ballads to her own chilling AIDS Masses. At 9:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; $30. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* GLOBALFEST (Sunday) A one-night crash course in some of the best of what is called world music only because there is no other name for it, Globalfest, now in its fourth year, offers a dozen performers from around the planet. Among them, performing on three stages, are the suave Brazilian songwriter Lenine; Dengue Fever, a band from Los Angeles that resurrects the manically eclectic rock of pre-Khmer Rouge Cambodia; Les Primitifs du Futur, a French retro jazz-blues-Gypsy string band; Sara Tavares, a sensuous Cape Verdean singer; Lila Downs, whose take on Mexican rancheras and cumbias can be raucous or reverent; Le Trio Joubran, three oud-playing Palestinian brothers; and Andy Palacio and the Garifuna Collective, from Belize. At 7 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com or globalfest-ny.org; $40. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>GOB IRON (Tonight and tomorrow night) Jay Farrar of Son Volt and Anders Parker of Varnaline have built careers on the idea of ragged, rock-tinged roots music: a little less grungy than Neil Young, a bit more plebeian than Bob Dylan. On ''Death Songs for the Living'' (Transmit Sound/Legacy), their joint album as Gob Iron, they repaint centuries of American music by the Carter Family, Josh White and Stephen Foster in gray, bleak tones; even Clarence Ashley's sprightly ''Coo-Coo Bird'' gets a despondent rewrite. Tonight at 9:30, Maxwell's, 1039 Washington Street, Hoboken, N.J., (201) 653-1703, maxwellsnj.com; tomorrow at 9, Northsix, 66 North Sixth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 599-5103, northsix.com; $15. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PAUL GREEN SCHOOL OF ROCK MUSIC (Tomorrow and Sunday) As seen in the documentary ''Rock School,'' Mr. Green offers an extensive curriculum at his Philadelphia school, teaching youngsters the rock 'n' roll canon, as well as the fundamentals of power chords and budda-budda bass lines. Here his students offer their tribute to Black Sabbath, and if there is any guitar riff especially appropriate for 12-year-olds, it's ''Iron Man.'' At 2:30 p.m., Rebel, 251 West 30th Street, Manhattan, (212) 695-2747, rebelnyc.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>HOLMES BROTHERS AND ALLEN TOUSSAINT (Tuesday) Steeped in blues and gospel, Sherman and Wendell Holmes harmonize and raise the rafters with songs that draw hope from hard times. Their version of gospel is a close neighbor of Southern soul and country. They are joined by Allen Toussaint, the musical statesman from New Orleans, for two sets. At 7 and 9:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; $30. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>JERRY LEE LEWIS (Tonight) People pounded on pianos and hollered about hellfire before Jerry Lee Lewis, but nobody put it together in quite his way, which is the rock 'n' roll way. Now 71, Mr. Lewis recently released his first new album in 11 years, ''Last Man Standing'' (Artist First), which features appearances by the Rolling Stones, Bruce Springsteen and Eric Clapton, all happily overshadowed. With Jack Grace. At 8, B. B. King Blues Club &amp; Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $90. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LIGHTNING BOLT (Sunday) At first it is hard to believe that all the glorious chaos of Lightning Bolt -- a stalwart of the big noise-punk scene in Providence, R.I. -- is being made by only two people. But as the sound comes into focus, a playful give-and-take becomes clear, as the bassist Brian Gibson and the drummer and vocalist Brian Chippendale toss back and forth gigantic metal riffs and giggly high notes, creating rainbows of dissonance. At 9 p.m., Northsix, 66 North Sixth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 599-5103, northsix.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LINCOLN CENTER'S AMERICAN SONGBOOK (Tonight and tomorrow night) Now in its ninth season, this series has greatly expanded from its origins as a home for the midcentury pantheon of Harold Arlen, Richard Rodgers and the like. Tonight the Broadway soprano Judy Kuhn offers songs by Laura Nyro, who, along with Joni Mitchell, established the model for confessional, force-of-nature women's songwriting. Tomorrow Michael Franks plays his own music, including recent Brazilian-inspired works. At 8:30, Allen Room, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Broadway at 60th Street, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LUNA LOUNGE (Tonight and tomorrow night) For a decade beginning in 1995, the Luna Lounge was one of the better rock dives on the Lower East Side, and not just for its foosball table; its tiny back room was host to thousands of bands who played free, including some, like Interpol and the Strokes, who went on to bigger things. A year and a half after losing its lease, the club reopens with roomier digs in Brooklyn, and if the bookings are any indication, the indie tradition will continue even if the no-cover policy will not. The Comas, a band from North Carolina with psychedelic leanings, headlines tonight with Falcon, from Brooklyn. Tomorrow features three appropriately little-known New York bands, Orange Park, the Picture and Motel Creeps. At 8, 361 Metropolitan Avenue, at Havemeyer Street, Williamsburg, lunalounge.com; $10 tonight, $5 tomorrow. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>HUGH MASEKELA, KLEZMATICS (Sunday) The South African flugelhorn player Hugh Masekela has more to offer than his international hit ''Grazing in the Grass.'' For decades he has brought together the three-chord lope of South African pop with the zigzagging possibilities of jazz. The Klezmatics love the laughing, moaning melodies of traditional klezmer music. They also love jazz, rock and downtown improvisation, and they bring all those styles to bear on their music, which can be raucous, hypnotic, reverent and dizzying, sometimes all in one quick-changing piece. At 8 and 10:30 p.m., S.O.B.'s, 204 Varick Street, at Houston Street, South Village, (212) 243-4940, sobs.com; $25 in advance, $30 at the door. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>ERIN McKEOWN (Tuesday and Wednesday) A smiley sprite whose knack for wordplay and light touch on the guitar have sometimes evoked Tin Pan Alley, Ms. McKeown took the plunge in her new album, ''Sing You Sinners'' (Nettwerk), recording 12 nuggets by Harold Arlen, Cole Porter, Fats Waller and others (along with one by herself). If her voice is not quite up to the subtleties of wit the songs demand, her joy of discovery is sincere. With Sean Hayes. Tuesday at 7 p.m., Wednesday at 9:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MEXICAN INSTITUTE OF SOUND (Tomorrow) A one-man mash-up of Mexican and Latin American music of the past and perhaps the future, Camilo Lara, from Mexico City, artfully mingles cumbias and cha-chas with dub and slippery electronica. Like Moby, he spins a dream of groovy eternal life through sounds that retain their kitsch and dance potential forever. With the Gritty Midi Gang. At 8 p.m., Union Hall, 702 Union Street, at Fifth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 638-4400, unionhallny.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* MISSION OF BURMA (Tonight) In the early 1980s this innovative and widely influential Boston band brought sharp, brainy guitar minimalism to American postpunk, and since reuniting in 2002 after almost 20 years, it still plays with passion and smarts. Here the band appears with two worthy descendants: Oneida and Turing Machine, both of Brooklyn. At 8, Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800, irvingplaza.com; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ANDERS PARKER (Wednesday) Mr. Parker, who led the band Varnaline, immerses his songs in the stoic drama of country and folk music, resulting in a melancholy that is sometimes indistinguishable from cynicism. (''The hours I've wasted here I could have wasted anywhere.'') At 9 p.m., Living Room, 154 Ludlow Street, near Stanton Street, Lower East Side, (212) 533-7235, livingroomny.com; $8. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BOB SEGER AND THE SILVER BULLET BAND (Thursday) In the fall Mr. Seger released ''Face the Promise'' (Capitol), his first new album in a decade. It's O.K., but a better illustration of what remains powerful in Mr. Seger's music was his performance of ''America the Beautiful'' at Game 1 of the last World Series: in a tender, soulful rasp, he evoked rock's gospel roots, and made a simple patriotic ode bring a stadium roaring to its feet. At 8 p.m., Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741, thegarden.com; $79.50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* RICKY SKAGGS WITH BRUCE HORNSBY (Sunday) One of the most virtuosic musicians in bluegrass, Ricky Skaggs sends his fingers flying in a blur over mandolin, guitar and fiddle. He performs with Bruce Hornsby, whose years playing with the Grateful Dead made him a more versatile and playful musician. The two of them have a new album, due in March, that looks particularly versatile and playful: they do a version of Rick James's ''Super Freak.'' Sunday's concert also features opening sets by Shawn Colvin and Paul Thorn. At 7:30 p.m., B. B. King Blues Club &amp; Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $55 in advance, $60 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>SUBDUDES (Tomorrow) The Subdudes, from New Orleans, make cozy, mostly unplugged roots-rock: straightforward sentiments in tunes that mix a little country, a little blues, a little soul, a little zydeco and a little swing. The group's original lineup disbanded in 1996, but three founding members have revived the band and since 2004 released two new albums. At 7 p.m., Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800, irvingplaza.com; $22 in advance, $25 at the door. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>ZS (Sunday and Monday) The Zs, one of the most active avant-rock groups in New York, plays kinetic pieces that sputter forth in Morse code dots of percussion and saxophone. On Monday it plays with Dave Longstreth, whose band Dirty Projectors constructs elaborate ''glitch operas'' with precise harmonies and stark pluckings of guitar and strings, all arranged slightly out of whack. Sunday at 9 p.m., Cake Shop, 152 Ludlow Street, between Stanton and Rivington Streets, Lower East Side, (212) 253-0036, cake-shop.com; $7. Monday at 10 p.m., Zebulon, 258 Wythe Avenue, near Metropolitan Avenue, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 218-6934, zebuloncafeconcert.com; no cover. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Jazz  Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>AMPERSAND/KNEEBODY (Tuesday) The guitarist Tim Ziesmer features his own rock-influenced compositions in Ampersand, with Chris Speed on tenor saxophone, Dave Ambrosio on bass and Ted Poor on drums. Kneebody, a collective that includes the keyboardist Adam Benjamin and the trumpeter Shane Endsley, convincingly blends rock, funk and soul in a rugged and exploratory modern fusion. At 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; cover, $12. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>* THE BAD PLUS (Tuesday through Thursday) The pianist Ethan Iverson, the bassist Reid Anderson and the drummer David King constitute the Bad Plus, a delivery system for smartly sweeping original songs as well as wryly affectionate renditions of pop tunes. They caused a stir among jazz purists when they first headlined at the Village Vanguard a few years ago; by now the engagement has become a happy ritual, and the band has nothing to prove but its own continuing vitality. (Through Jan. 28.) At 9 and 11 p.m. (with a 12:30 set on Jan. 27), Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SAM BARDFELD (Tonight) Mr. Bardfeld, a violinist with a wide-ranging résumé, revisits the music from his evocative recent album ''Periodic Trespasses (The Saul Cycle)'' (Fresh Sound New Talent). At 9 p.m., BAMcafé, 30 Lafayette Avenue, between Ashland Place and St. Felix Street, (718) 636-4100, bam.org; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* DON BYRON (Monday) Jazz has many card-carrying eclectics these days, but none more self-assured than the clarinetist Don Byron, who will match wits with two very different pianists: Ursula Oppens, a classical interpreter known for the range of her interests, and Kenny Barron, an improviser with a soulfully sophisticated style. At 8 p.m., Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, (212) 501-3330, kaufman-center.org; $25 in advance, $30 on Monday. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ROBERTO CARCASSES, DAFNIS PRIETO, YOSVANY TERRY AND YUNIOR TERRY (Tomorrow) Cuban folk tradition collides with contemporary jazz protocol in a group featuring Mr. Carcasses on keyboards, Mr. Prieto on drums and the Terry brothers, Yosvany and Yunior, on saxophone and bass respectively. At 10 and 11:30 p.m., Rose Live Music, 345 Grand Street, between Havemeyer and Marcy Streets, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 599-0069, liveatrose.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JIMMY COBB'S MOB (Tuesday and Wednesday) Jimmy Cobb, a masterful hard bop drummer, has served as a mentor to many young musicians through this band; one of them, the tenor saxophonist Eric Alexander, takes the melodic lead here. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE COLEMAN (Tomorrow, Sunday and Thursday) Mr. Coleman, the avant-garde alto saxophonist and composer, programmed this month's schedule at the Stone, leaving a handful of spaces for his own explorations. Tomorrow he convenes a group called Aquarius Ingress consisting of seven reed players, including the saxophonist Miguel Zenón and the clarinetist Chris Speed; on Sunday and Thursday he leads Five Elements, his adventurously funk-focused working band. At 8 and 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TAYLOR EIGSTI AND JULIAN LAGE (Monday) Mr. Eigsti, a pianist, and Mr. Lage, a guitarist, are precociously talented players with a substantive history together, as well as a fruitful affiliation with the Concord label. At 7 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BILL EVANS'S SOULGRASS (Tuesday through Thursday) Virtuosity, the ingredient shared by bluegrass and fusion, will be in copious supply during this summit organized by the saxophonist Bill Evans, featuring Tony Trischka on banjo, Sam Bush on mandolin, Christian Howes on violin, Richard Bona on bass and Dave Weckl on drums. (Through Jan. 28.) At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $35 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DOMINICK FARINACCI (Monday) A sharp and promising young trumpeter, Mr. Farinacci leads a quintet consisting of the vibraphonist Joe Locke, the pianist Danny Grissett, the bassist Vicente Archer and the drummer Ari Hoenig. At 9 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>AYELET ROSE GOTTLIEB (Sunday) Ms. Gottlieb is a commanding vocalist whose most recent album, ''Mayim Rabim'' (Tzadik), features scriptural texts in the original Hebrew. Her high-grade sextet includes Avishai Cohen on trumpet, Loren Stillman on alto saxophone, Anat Fort on piano, Ed Schuller on bass and Take Toriyama on drums. At 8:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEFON HARRIS (Tomorrow and Sunday) ''African Tarantella: Dances With Duke'' (Blue Note), the latest album by the vibraphonist Stefon Harris, features music from two Duke Ellington suites, along with several original themes. As on the album, Mr. Harris augments his working quartet with reeds and strings, and with the trombonist Steve Turre. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set tomorrow only, Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $30. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>VIJAY IYER (Tonight) A pianist-composer given to restive energies and rhythmic conundrums, Mr. Iyer performs in two promising settings: with a trio featuring the attentive bassist Stephan Crump and the supple drummer Marcus Gilmore, and later in a duo with the alto saxophonist Steve Coleman, one of his mentors. At 8 and 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE LEHMAN (Tuesday) Mr. Lehman is a saxophonist who pursues an abstract lyricism informed by myriad traditions. His quintet includes sharp and sympathetic peers like the trumpeter Jonathan Finlayson, the drummer Tyshawn Sorey and the bassist Drew Gress. At 8:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GEORGE LEWIS (Tuesday) Mr. Lewis, a trombonist and pedagogue affiliated with Columbia University and the Association for the Advancement of Creative Musicians, performs two abstract sets: a duo performance with the bassist Reggie Workman, and then a solo improvisation with laptop electronics. At 8 and 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>RAMSEY LEWIS (Monday) A successful crossover artist for more than 40 years, the pianist and broadcaster Ramsey Lewis presents a coolly boppish working trio with Larry Gray on bass and Leon Joyce Jr. on drums. At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $45 at tables, $30 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TONY MALABY, WILLIAM PARKER AND NASHEET WAITS (Sunday) Strenuous free and not-quite-free improvisation, courtesy of several people who know the territory well: Mr. Malaby, tenor saxophonist; Mr. Parker, bassist; and Mr. Waits, drummer. At 7 and 9 p.m., Jimmy's 43 Restaurant, 43 East Seventh Street, East Village, (212) 982-3006, freestylejazz.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MALAMUTE (Tuesday) Though named after a breed of Arctic sled dog, this collective promises something other than steady propulsion; with Jim Black on drums, Kieran Daly on electric mandolin and Nate Wooley on trumpet, it's likely to tumble ahead in fits and starts. At 7 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DONNY McCASLIN (Tonight) As on his recent album ''Soar'' (Sunnyside), Mr. McCaslin applies his extroverted saxophone style to a Latin American-inspired contemporary fusion, benefiting greatly from the contributions of the bassist Scott Colley and the percussionists Antonio Sanchez and Pernell Saturnino. At 10, 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MIKE MORENO (Tonight) A versatile and increasingly prominent guitarist, Mr. Moreno features his own compositions in a post-bop quintet featuring the saxophonist John Ellis and the pianist Aaron Parks. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JOE MORRIS (Wednesday) Mr. Morris has an angular but appealing guitar style, and bright ideas about how to organize timbres. His quintet here includes Michael Winograd on clarinet, Daniel Blacksberg on trombone, Daniel Levin on cello and Michael Evans on drums. At 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* DAVID MURRAY BLACK SAINT QUARTET (Monday through Wednesday) A spirited and often blustery tenor saxophonist, David Murray leads a hard-driving group featuring Lafayette Gilchrist on piano, Ray Drummond on bass and Andrew Cyrille on drums. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>NYC BALKAN GYPSY AND BEYOND (Tonight) A convention of three boisterous groups with similarly folksy inspirations: the Paradox Trio, led by the clarinetist Matt Darriau; Romski Boji, led by the percussionist Seido Salifoski; and Slavic Soul Party, fronted by the percussionist Matt Moran. At 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* NYC WINTER JAZZFEST (Tomorrow) The Knitting Factory commits all three of its floors to jazz during this sprawling one-night festival, which will feature 18 different bands. Among the highlights are groups led by the bassist Henry Grimes, the pianists Marc Cary and Robert Glasper, and the violinist Jenny Scheinman. From 6 p.m. to 1 a.m., 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3132, knittingfactory.com; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JEREMY PELT (Tomorrow) The clarion tone and preternatural poise of Mr. Pelt's trumpet playing have earmarked him as a rising star in the jazz mainstream. His quintet features a frequent foil, the guitarist Mike Moreno. At midnight, Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $10, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BEN RILEY'S MONK LEGACY SEPTET (Wednesday and Thursday) Ben Riley, one of the most buoyant drummers ever to serve under Thelonious Monk's employ, honors the pianist and composer's memory with this rock-solid septet, stocked with players like the trumpeter Don Sickler and the saxophonists Wayne Escoffery and Bruce Williams. (Through Jan. 27.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JEROME SABBAGH (Thursday) Mr. Sabbagh, a coolly composed tenor saxophonist and composer in the postmodern mainstream, leads a sleek ensemble with Ben Monder on guitar, Joe Martin on bass and Ted Poor on drums. At 8 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MATTHEW SHIPP (Tomorrow) Mr. Shipp's pianism is often prickly but rarely off-putting, because even his free improvisations tend to follow a faintly linear path. He performs solo here, as on a thoughtful recent album called ''One'' (Thirsty Ear). At 8 and 9:30 p.m., Tenri Cultural Institute, 43A West 13th Street, between Fifth and Sixth Avenues, Greenwich Village, (212) 645-2800, tenri.org; $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>HELEN SUNG (Tonight and tomorrow) The pianist Helen Sung leads a post-bop quartet featuring the articulate alto saxophonist Steve Wilson. At 8 and 9:45 p.m., Kitano Hotel, 66 Park Avenue, at 38th Street, (212) 885-7119, kitano.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JAMES (BLOOD) ULMER (Wednesday and Thursday) Mr. Ulmer's singing and guitar playing describe an oddly hypnotic combination of influences: Ornette Coleman's polytonality crossed with the psychedelic swagger of Jimi Hendrix. He performs here with a group that includes the keyboardist Amina Claudine Myers and the drummer Aubrey Dale. (Through Jan. 28) At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CEDAR WALTON (Tonight and tomorrow) As a pianist and composer, Mr. Walton pursues an articulate, almost courtly variety of hard bop. His rhythm section here includes the bassist David Williams and the drummer George Fludas. At 8, 10 and 11:30, Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, (212) 864-6662, smokejazz.com; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical  Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>'ACIS AND GALATEA' (Tuesday) Staged opera or home entertainment? Handel's early pastoral opera has been the subject of debate since it was written. Probably first performed for a private group at a country estate, it was later revived as a staged opera by another manager eager to capitalize on Handel's Italian-opera success -- in competition with Handel's own opera company. Now, New York, having experienced the work on an operatic scale in City Opera's 2001 production, can sample it in a more intimate form: presented by the five-member Aulos Ensemble (acclaimed early-music specialists) and four vocal soloists at the Met -- not the opera, but the museum. At 6:30 p.m., Medieval Sculpture Hall, Metropolitan Museum of Art, (212) 570-3949, metmuseum.org; $50. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>'LA BOHÈME' (Wednesday) Franco Zeffirelli's overblown ''Bohème'' returns to the Metropolitan Opera for its first airing of the new year, and the Chilean soprano Cristina Gallardo-Domâs returns to sing Mimì, the role with which she made her house debut in 1996. Her Rodolfo is the excellent tenor Marcello Giordani; they both have the vocal and dramatic chops to make an impact in Zeffirelli's massive sets. Ainhoa Arteta is Musetta, Dwayne Croft is Marcello, and Carlo Rizzi conducts. At 7:30 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $80 tickets remaining. (Vivien Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>'THE FIRST EMPEROR'  (Monday and Thursday) The excitement of a world premiere at the Met, combined with widespread interest among the general public in the composer Tan Dun, who won an Oscar for his film score to ''Crouching Tiger, Hidden Dragon,'' have resulted in a sold-out run for ''The First Emperor.'' Alas, though the story of Qin Shi Huang, the first emperor of China, who unified the country through brutality and conquest, is compelling, Mr. Tan's ponderous score is a huge disappointment. There are gripping moments, especially some propulsive orchestra passages that incorporate Chinese instruments. But the opera's lyrical flights are slow-moving, ponderous and sometimes cloying. Mr. Tan has tried to meld Chinese melody and Italianate lyricism. But his music seems caught in some nowhere land between ''Crouching Tiger'' and Puccini's ''Turandot.'' Even the great Plácido Domingo, bravely taking on the challenging title role, cannot save the show. The colorful production is by the Chinese film director Zhang Yimou (''House of Flying Daggers''). Mr. Tan conducts. There are two more performances. At 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* 'MOSTLY OPERETTA' (Tonight, tomorrow, Monday, Tuesday and Thursday) The Austrian Cultural Forum's innovative festival, which pairs 20th-century operetta in intimate recitals with contemporary visuals in an effort to move the genre into the 21st century, winds up this week with three programs by Viennese singers who specialize in operetta: two programs that pay homage to some composers forced to emigrate by the Nazis, and a selection of Kurt Weill's songs arranged into what the forum's director calls ''a kind of 'Winterreise.' '' At 7 p.m, 11 East 52nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 319-5300, acfny.org; free, but reservations are required. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>* 'IL SIGNOR BRUSCHINO' (Thursday) Mention Rossini and most people come up with ''The Barber of Seville,'' but this work -- in which the composer honed the comic gift that came to the fore in ''Barber'' and other ''opere buffe'' -- hasn't been staged in New York since 1933. The Gotham Chamber Opera has set itself apart among the city's small opera companies with quality performances of less-known operas (with good singers), conducted by the company's founder, Neal Goren: it is opening this frothy piece of fun with a gala performance on Thursday. (The run continues, at normal ticket prices, next week.) At 7:30 p.m., Abrons Arts Center, 466 Grand Street, at Pitt Street, Lower East Side, (212) 279-4200, gothamchamberopera.org; $300. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>'THE TENDER LAND' (Tomorrow and Sunday) In 1976, when the enterprising Bronx Opera Company first presented Copland's ''Tender Land,'' the composer participated in rehearsals and attended productions. For its current production, the company is using the effective chamber version of the orchestral score arranged by Murry Sidlin. Royston Coppenger is the director, and Michael Spierman conducts. At 2 p.m., Heckscher Theater, El Museo del Barrio, 1230 Fifth Avenue, at 104th Street, East Harlem, (718) 960-8833, bronxopera.org; $20 to $35. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* 'LA TRAVIATA' (Tuesday) The admirable soprano Hei-Kyung Hong gives a beautifully sung and deeply felt portrayal of Violetta in the Met revival of Verdi's ''Traviata,'' in Franco Zeffirelli's extravagant 1998 production. The other news is the promising performance of an artist who, like Ms. Hong, is also from South Korea: the tenor Wookyung Kim, singing Alfredo in his Met debut season. As a Verdi tenor, Mr. Kim is a little green. But he has an appealing and robust voice, and at his best, sings with ardor and flair. The baritone Charles Taylor, who was ill on opening night, is scheduled to sing Germont. Carlo Rizzi conducts. At 7:30 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $80 to $175. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>* ALARM WILL SOUND (Tomorrow) This supremely inventive new-music ensemble offers an expansive look at the music of Edgard Varèse in Miller Theater's Composer Portraits series. Among the 10 works on the program are the early ''Grand Sommeil Noir''; ''Ionisation,'' for percussion ensemble; ''Density 21.5,'' for flute; and several orchestral works. The main curiosity, though, is an orchestrated arrangement of the ''Poème Électronique,'' which is normally heard in the electronic tape version that Varèse completed in 1958. At 8 p.m., Miller Theater, Broadway at 116th Street, Morningside Heights, (212) 854-7799, millertheater.com; $25; $15 for students. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>DANIEL BARENBOIM  (Tomorrow and Sunday) In a charming and revealing program note (available on carnegiehall.org), Mr. Barenboim writes of having been reared from his earliest years on Bach's ''Well-Tempered Clavier.'' When he arrived at 12 for his first lesson in Paris with Nadia Boulanger, this formidable teacher opened the score to the Prelude in E minor from Book 1 and told him, ''Play it for me in A minor.'' This weekend Mr. Barenboim, a formidable pianist, will play that prelude (in the original key) in his two-program survey of the complete 48 preludes and fugues from Bach's monumental work. Book 1 tomorrow at 8 p.m., Book 2 on Sunday at 2 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $34 to $108. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>KRISTIAN BEZUIDENHOUT (Thursday) This South African fortepianist gave a fine recital at the Miller Theater in November, and returns with another program, as part of the Boston Early Music Festival's series in the Morgan Library &amp; Museum's intimate new hall. His program includes Mozart's Sonata in F (K. 494) and Variations on ''Unser dummer Pöbel meint'' (K. 455); Benda's Sonata in A minor; and Haydn's Variations in F minor. At 7:30 p.m. (preconcert lecture at 7), Morgan Library &amp; Museum, 225 Madison Avenue, at 36th Street, (212) 685-0008, themorgan.org; $45; $35 for members. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>CHAMBER MUSIC SOCIETY OF LINCOLN CENTER (Sunday and Tuesday) Music for four-hand piano used to be a staple of the repertory, particularly in the days before recordings, when the way most people enjoyed music was to play it themselves. In this program seven pianists (including Charles Wadsworth, a past director of the society, and Wu Han, a current co-director, as well as Gilbert Kalish and Anne-Marie McDermott) take on works for four hands by Mozart, Mendelssohn, Fauré, Stravinsky and Lutoslawski (whose Variations on a Theme of Paganini is the only one to employ two separate pianos). Sunday at 5 p.m., Tuesday at 7:30 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5788, chambermusicsociety.org; $28 to $50. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>* 'DECASIA' (Thursday) The composer Michael Gordon and the filmmaker Bill Morrison have collaborated on this enveloping multimedia work. Mr. Morrison's contribution is a fast-cut montage of antique films, in which bubbles and other signs of decay create patterns as crucial to the work as the images of cowboys, flappers, factory workers, dancers, parachutists and exotic scenes from the Middle East and North Africa. Mr. Gordon's powerful 65-minute score -- played by an orchestra deployed in the balconies -- evolves from a faint, metallic rattle to a barrage of percussion, electric guitars, brass choirs, woodwinds and strings. At 7 and 9:30 p.m., Orensanz Center for the Arts, 172 Norfolk Street, Lower East Side, (212) 352-3101; $25. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* HILLIARD ENSEMBLE (Sunday) In its performance on the Music Before 1800 series, this British vocal ensemble, here in a quartet configuration (David James, Rogers Covey-Crump, Steven Harrold and Gordon Jones), sings the Lassus Requiem, with antiphons and motets by Palestrina interposed between the movements. At 4 p.m., Corpus Christi Church, 529 West 121st Street, Morningside Heights, (212) 666-9266, mb1800.org; $25 to $40; $5 off for students and 62+. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>KIRILL GERSTEIN (Sunday) The Metropolitan Museum presents the third of four young up-and-coming pianists in its Accolades series. This week the spotlight is on the Russian pianist Kirill Gerstein, who won first prize at the 2001 Arthur Rubinstein Piano Competition and was awarded the 2002 Gilmore Young Artist Award. He will perform Haydn's Sonata in D (Hob. XVI:37), Schumann's whimsical ''Humoresque,'' Ligeti's Études, Busoni's Sonatina No. 6 and an arrangement of the Scherzo from Tchaikovsky's Sixth Symphony. At 2:30 p.m., Metropolitan Museum of Art, (212) 570-3949, metmuseum.org; $20. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* MOSCOW SOLOISTS (Thursday) Wu Man, the fleet-fingered and adventurous Chinese pipa player, frequently adds the sound of her exotic instrument to Western ensembles. With the violist Yuri Bashmet and his Moscow Soloists (a group formed in 1992 and made up of young graduates of the Moscow Conservatory), she will perform Tan Dun's Concerto for String Orchestra and Pipa (a pipa is a Chinese lute), a work whose premiere she performed in 2001. The program also includes Toru Takemitsu's ''Nostalgia'' and his Three Film Scores for Strings, and Hikaru Hayashi's Concerto for Viola and Strings, ''Elegie.'' At 7:30 p.m., Zankel Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $28 and $40. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC (Today, tomorrow and Thursday) Riccardo Muti, the exacting Italian maestro, is in town for two weeks to conduct the Philharmonic. This weekend's program offers the brilliant violinist Vadim Repin in Tchaikovsky's Violin Concerto and Scriabin's strangely mystical and musically visionary Symphony No. 3, ''Le Divin Poème.'' On Thursday Mr. Muti presents the first of three performances of an all-Italian program, with ballet music from Verdi's ''Macbeth,'' Respighi's ''Feste Romane'' and a little-known piano concerto from 1885 by Giuseppe Martucci, a work admired by Toscanini, Mahler and, of course, Mr. Muti. Gerhard Oppitz is the soloist. Today at 2 p.m., tomorrow at 8 p.m. and Thursday at 7:30 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nyphil.org; $24 to $96. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>JORGE FEDERICO OSORIO (Monday) This Mexican pianist has recorded everything from Brahms to Ponce (and, most recently, Mozart violin sonatas with Ani Kavafian) but has only infrequently performed in New York. His solo recital juxtaposes works by two Spanish composers, Soler and Albéniz, with preludes by Debussy, showpieces by Liszt and Beethoven's Sonata No. 30. At 8 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $20 to $45. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>* 'REQUIEM FOR DARFUR' (Monday) The Democracy Council, a human-rights advocacy group, is sponsoring this performance of Verdi's magisterial Requiem by musicians from orchestras including the New York and Berlin Philharmonics and the Met and Philadelphia Orchestras. The event, which benefits Unicef and other charities involved in aid work in Darfur, has Mia Farrow as its host, and features as soloists the soprano Alexandra Deshorties, the mezzo-soprano Sarah Heltzel, the tenor Scott Piper and the bass Morris Robinson; George Mathew conducts. At 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $27 to $500. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>RIVERSIDE SYMPHONY (Tomorrow) Even by its own adventurous standards, the Riverside Symphony is offering an offbeat program tomorrow. The most eclectic item is Villa-Lobos's Harmonica Concerto. The harmonica virtuoso Robert Bonfiglio says he has performed the work more than 350 times. I've never heard it. Have you? Here is your chance, on a program that also offers Mozart's ''Haffner'' Symphony and Honegger's Neo-Classical Symphony No. 4 (''Delights of Basel''). George Rothman conducts. At 7:30 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $30 to $50. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>ABBEY SIMON (Tuesday) The Walter W. Naumburg Foundation is offering a retrospective concert series in which it presents former winners of its competition. Mr. Simon, the pianist, won in 1941, and his recordings of the Romantic repertory have always been highly regarded, with Chopin as a particular favorite. At his ''Naumburg Looks Back'' recital, he plays music of Chopin and Schumann. At 8 p.m., Weill Recital Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $20; $10 for students and 65+. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* 'THE SONG CONTINUES' (Tuesday through Thursday) The master classes are going to be a hotter ticket than the recitals at the Marilyn Horne Foundation's annual celebration of the art of song. Leading off at Zankel Hall is the celebrated Barbara Cook; the next night it's the soprano Evelyn Lear; on Thursday it's Ms. Horne herself. The duo recitals by young artists supported by Ms. Horne's foundation, like Joslin Romphf, a soprano, and Lee Poulis, a baritone, on Wednesday; or Hanan Alattar, a soprano, and Timothy Falton, a tenor, on Thursday, have been relegated to the 5:30 time slot at Weill Recital Hall. (The series continues with a gala concert next Friday.) Master classes, Tuesday through Thursday at 7:30 p.m.; recitals, Wednesday and Thursday at 5:30 p.m.; Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $20 for master classes; $5 for recitals; some events sold out. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>TAKACS QUARTET (Tonight) This string quartet has undergone a few personnel changes in recent years, and in the process its sound and focus have improved considerably. A Beethoven cycle at Lincoln Center two years ago showed it to be in remarkable form. This time Takacs offers Debussy's Quartet and Shostakovich's Quartet No. 11, before returning to Beethoven for the Quartet in A minor (Op. 132). At 8, Metropolitan Museum of Art, (212) 570-3949, metmuseum.org; $45. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* TOKYO STRING QUARTET (Tomorrow) This venerable quartet continues its residency at the 92nd Street Y and its commemoration of the 150th anniversary of Schumann's death with a performance of his String Quartet in A minor. The program also includes Schumann's poignant song cycle ''Dichterliebe,'' sung by the fine Canadian lyric baritone Russell Braun, accompanied by the pianist Carolyn Maule. Paul Hecht, an actor, will read poems from Heinrich Heine's ''Lyrisches Intermezzo,'' on which Schumann based these songs. At 8 p.m., 1395 Lexington Avenue, (212) 415-5500, 92y.org; $40. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>Dance  Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>RUTH CANSFIELD DANCE (Tonight through Sunday night) In its first New York performances, this Canadian company will present three dances by Ruth Cansfield, set to music by Debussy, Rachmaninoff and Crumb, that explore characters' hidden stories, movement without artifice and voyages of the soul. At 9, Merce Cunningham Studio, 55 Bethune Street, at Washington Street, West Village, (866) 405-5810, ruthcansfield.com; $17; $13.60 for students and 65+. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>CEDAR LAKE CONTEMPORARY BALLET (Tonight and tomorrow night) The company opens its winter season with a program of dance by Jacopo Godani of Italy, Edgar Zendejas of Mexico and New York's own Benoit-Swan Pouffer, who directs Cedar Lake. (Through Jan. 27.) At 8, Cedar Lake Theater, 547 West 26th Street, Chelsea, (212) 868-4444, smarttix.com; $30; $20 for 65+ and students with ID. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CREATIVE OUTLET DANCE THEATER OF BROOKLYN (Today through Sunday) Jamel Gaines's ''Remembering -- Lest We Forget'' explores historical accounts of the Middle Passage, slavery and emancipation. This vibrant company will also perform two repertory matinees tomorrow, starring Bahiyah Sayyed Gaines, and on Sunday. Tonight and tomorrow at 7:30, Sunday at 3 p.m., Kumble Theater for the Performing Arts, Long Island University Brooklyn Campus, Flatbush and DeKalb Avenues, Brooklyn, (718) 488-1624, creativeoutlet.org; $30; $25 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* DANCE GOTHAM FESTIVAL (Tomorrow and Sunday) Ten modern-dance companies will perform on two different programs, among them Montreal Danse, Johannes Wieland and Keely Garfield (tomorrow) and Kun-Yang Lin/Dancers, Nicolas Andre Dance Theater and Koresh Dance Company (Sunday). Appearing both nights will be Paradigm, the Carolyn Dorfman Dance Company, Keigwin &amp; Company and Battleworks. At 8 p.m., Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, www.symphonyspace.org; $10. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>ANDREA DEL CONTE DANZA ESPANA (Thursday) This program of flamenco dance will feature the dancer Marco De Ana and the fusion band Gazpacho Andalú. (Through Jan. 28.) At 8 p.m., Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, (212) 334-7479, joyce.org; $28; $25 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CHEZ BUSHWICK: 'AMBUSH: A CURE FOR APAP' (Tomorrow) Bless the Bushwickites for this shrug at the phenomenon of the Association of Performing Arts Presenters, which brings dance producers to New York City en masse to assess the talent during a hectic few days -- frustrating to some dance artists -- of conferences and performing. Contributors to the Bushwick program are Matthew Barney, Jonah Bokaer, Foofwa d'Imobilité, Sam Kim, Jennifer Lacey, Antonietta Vicario and Jeremy Wade. At 8 p.m., Brooklyn Fire Proof, 119 Ingraham Street, Brooklyn, (718) 418-4405, www.bam.org/events; $5. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* DIAVOLO (Tomorrow) This Los Angeles-based multimedia company performs ingenious trompe l'oeil spectacles that seamlessly combine dance, gymnastics and cinematic images. Is that a real or a filmed dog racing across the stage? At 8 p.m., Brooklyn Center for the Performing Arts at Brooklyn College, one block from the junction of Flatbush and Nostrand Avenues, Flatbush, (718) 951-4500, brooklyncenteronline.org; $15 to $25. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* JAPANESE CONTEMPORARY DANCE SHOWCASE (Tonight through Sunday) If it's January in New York, it's time for Japanese dance. For this event's 10th anniversary, the Japan Society has relocated to the Joyce. But the eclectic, pop-influenced sampler should be as strange and beguiling as ever. Two programs feature work by Pappa Tarahumara, Kim Itoh &amp; the Glorious Future, Leni-Basso and Noism07. Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 2 and 7:30 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800; $30; $23 for members. (Claudia La Rocco)</p>
        <p>* LOWER LIGHTS COLLECTIVE (Tonight and tomorrow night) Members of this multimedia group have worked with some pretty impressive people in dance. And how can you go wrong with a company that describes its collaborative process as ignoring one another while allowing for the subtle influence of what is seen out of the corner of the eye? In its new ''CRAM,'' the group will pour dance; a ''live horror film''; sound and noise installations; a ''living sculpture'' using potatoes as percussion; and an orchestra of instruments made from architectural salvage into every cranny of this space. At 8, Chocolate Factory, 5-49 49th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (212) 352-3101, chocolatefactorytheater.org; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* SUSAN MARSHALL &amp; COMPANY (Monday, Tuesday and Thursday) Ms. Marshall returns with her Bessie Award-winning ''Cloudless,'' a suite of brief distilled dances. (Through Feb. 3.) At 7:30 p.m., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077, dtw.org; $25. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* MONEY MATTERS (Thursday) Sure does, and it matters a lot that Dixon Place raises funds for a much-needed home on Chrystie Street. Performers in this benefit include Souloworks and Gerald Casel and Jessy Smith. At 7:30 p.m., University Settlement, 184 Eldridge Street, Lower East Side, (212) 219-0736; $10 or more. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* MARK MORRIS DANCE GROUP (Tonight, tomorrow, and Tuesday through Thursday) Welcome 2007 a little late with a celebratory program of dances by Mr. Morris that includes the premiere of ''Italian Concerto,'' set to Bach, and ''The Argument,'' ''Sang-Froid'' and ''Love Song Waltzes.'' (Through Jan. 27.) At 7:30 p.m. (the MMDG Music Ensemble performs tonight at 10), Mark Morris Dance Center, 3 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place (across the street from the Brooklyn Academy of Music), Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (212) 352-3101, mmdg.org; sold out. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* NEW YORK CITY BALLET (Tonight through Sunday, and Tuesday through Thursday) The company will present the first of 10 themed programs, ''Stravinsky and Balanchine: An Eternal Partnership'' (''Agon,'' ''Monumentum/Movements,'' ''Duo Concertant'' and ''Symphony in Three Movements'') tonight, tomorrow afternoon and Thursday. Its second program, ''Tradition and Innovation'' (''Mozartiana,'' ''In Vento'' and Tchaikovsky's Piano Concerto No. 2), will follow on Tuesday. And ''Jerome Robbins: An American Icon'' (''2 &amp; 3 Part Inventions,'' ''A Suite of Dances,'' ''In Memory Of  '' and ''I'm Old Fashioned'') enters the repertory tomorrow night and is repeated on Sunday and Wednesday. (Through Feb. 25.) Tonight and Thursday night at 8, tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 3 p.m., Tuesday and Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 870-5570, wnycballet.com; $20 to 95. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK THEATER BALLET (Tonight and tomorrow night) Choreography by Benoit Swan-Pouffer, Alexandra Damiana, Matthew Neenan, Sallie Wilson and David Parker will be presented in this latest installment of the company's ''Dance on a Shoestring'' series. At 7, Dance Gallery, 30 East 31st Street, Manhattan, (212) 679-0401; $20. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>SANDRA PARKER AND SHELLEY LASICA (Tonight through Sunday) Ms. Parker, who is from Australia, will present a dance about the notions of travel, distance and proximity, and Ms. Lasica has contributed a piece with changing casts and choreography. Ms. Parker, tonight at 8, tomorrow at 7 p.m., Sunday at 4 p.m.; Ms. Lasica, tonight at 10, tomorrow at 5 and 9 p.m., Sunday at 2 p.m. Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, (212) 334-7479; free, but reservations necessary. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* PEAK PERFORMANCES AT MONTCLAIR: TRISHA BROWN (Tonight through Sunday) Ms. Brown, now 70, celebrates her influential career in modern dance with a new work, ''I love my robots,'' that suggests that she is as innovative as ever. A collaboration with the visual artist Kenjiro Okazaki and the performance artist Laurie Anderson, ''robots'' will feature what Mr. Okazaki describes as two interactive ''sculptural apparitions.'' The evening also includes performances of Ms. Brown's 1983 ''Set and Reset'' and her 2005 ''how long does the subject linger on the edge of the volume?'' Tonight and tomorrow night at 7:30, Sunday at 3 p.m., Alexander Kasser Theater, Montclair State University, 1 Normal Avenue, Montclair, N.J., (973) 655-5112, peakperfs.org; $35. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>LAURA PETERSON CHOREOGRAPHY (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ms. Peterson, who has danced with everyone from Risa Jaroslow to Poppo and the GoGo Boys, describes her new ''I Love Dan Flavin'' as a tongue-in-cheek futuristic dance with fluorescent light and pioneering techno music. (Through Jan. 27.) At 8, Dixon Place, 258 Bowery, between Houston and Prince Streets, Lower East Side, (212) 219-0736, Ext. 11, dixonplace.org; $15 or T.D.F. vouchers; $12 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>'TWO: DUETS' (Thursday) Chosen by Nicki Marshall and Helen Styring Tocci, five pairs of dance artists explore the intimacy and colliding energies of the duet form. (Through Jan. 27.) At 8 p.m., WOW Cafe Theater, 59 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 777-4280; $15; $12 for students and artists. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>MIGUEL ÁNGEL ZOTTO'S TANGO X 2 (Wednesday and Thursday) Mr. Zotto, who performed on Broadway in ''Tango Argentino,'' is bringing a company of 16 dancers and 8 musicians to perform ''Su Historia,'' a medley of tango dances and scores, and a tribute to Astor Piazzolla and his lyricist Horacio Ferrer. (Through Jan. 28.) At 8 p.m., City Center, 131 West 55th Street, Manhattan, (212) 581-1212, tangox2.com; $35 to $85. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art  Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* AMERICAN MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY: 'GOLD,' through Aug. 19. This astounding array of art, artifacts and natural samples -- larded with fascinating facts and tales -- ranges from prehistoric times to the present. Stops along the way include pre-Columbian empires, sunken treasure, and the moon landing. It turns out that gold comes from the earth in forms as beautiful as anything man has thought to do with it. Central Park West and 79th Street, (212) 769-5100, amnh.org. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>COOPER-HEWITT NATIONAL DESIGN MUSEUM: 'DESIGN LIFE NOW: NATIONAL DESIGN TRIENNIAL 2006,' through July 29. This ambitious show illuminates the volatile, contradictory and ever-expanding field of design, but fails to call it to order. It covers medical innovation, military hardware, frivolous reiterations of received ideas, sundry Web sites and magazines, haute couture, architecture and recycling. The show coalesces into deliberately orchestrated skirmishes between conflicting principles and entities: corporate and private, decorative and essential. 2 East 91st Street, (212) 849-8400, ndm.si.edu. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'SPANISH PAINTING FROM EL GRECO TO PICASSO, TIME, TRUTH, AND HISTORY' through March 28. This show is carried along on its sheer star power and optical finesse. There are dozens of Goyas and Velázquezes and Zurbaráns and El Grecos and Riberas and Dalís and Picassos, many famous, many not. I can't tell you how often I was stopped by a picture so good or unexpected that it made me do a double take. Velázquez's painting of a dwarf is alone worth crossing a continent to see. 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3500, guggenheim.org. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* THE METROPOLITAN MUSEUM OF ART: 'GLITTER AND DOOM: GERMAN PORTRAITS FROM THE 1920S,' through Feb. 19. The 100 paintings and drawings on display here are by 10 artists, including George Grosz, Christian Schad, and Karl Hubbuch, and most conspicuously the unrelentingly savage Otto Dix and his magnificent other, Max Beckmann. In their works the Weimar Republic's porous worlds reassemble; we look into the faces of museum directors and cabaret performers, society matrons and scarred war veterans, prostitutes and jaded aristocrats who were watching their world slide from one cataclysm to the next. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* THE MET: 'ONE OF A KIND: THE STUDIO CRAFT MOVEMENT,' through Sept. 3. Focusing on the postwar development of artist-craftsmen, this display of furniture, glass, ceramics, metalwork, jewelry and fiber includes funny, quirky, provocative and sometimes gorgeous things. Among its stars are a witty bust by the California funk ceramicist Robert Arneson (1920-92) portraying the mother of the 16th-century painter and printmaker Albrecht Durer; and Bonnie Seeman's fetching ceramic coffeepot and tray, whose mock cabbage leaves and rhubarb stalks evoke the genteel tradition of 18th-century British and continental china, but can also be read as human rather than vegetative tissue. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>* MORGAN LIBRARY &amp; MUSEUM: 'SAUL STEINBERG: ILLUMINATIONS,' through March 4. Saul Steinberg's famous New Yorker cover positioning Manhattan at the center of the world may be his best-known drawing, but he took on everything with visual puns, manic doodles, grandiloquent calligraphy and other inspired artifice. As this show of more than 100 drawings, collages and constructions goes on, Steinberg's progress is evident: from relatively simple cartoons like ''Feet on Chair'' (1946), in which a fellow reading a newspaper parks his feet on the seat of an ornate Victorian monstrosity, to complex comments on the state of the world, like ''Street War (Cadavre Exquisis)'' (about 1972-74), derived from news clips of postcolonial troubles in the Middle East and Africa. The flow of his work amazes. 225 Madison Avenue, at 36th Street, (212) 685-0008, morganlibrary.org. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'MANET AND THE EXECUTION OF MAXIMILIAN,' through Jan. 29. This gripping show reminds us of Modernism's mutinous, myth-scouring origins. And it does so by bringing one of art's great path-cutters, Edouard Manet, onto the scene, wry, politically infuriated and painting like Lucifer. There's not a lot of him here -- eight paintings, three on a single theme: the death by firing squad of the Austrian archduke Ferdinand Maximilian in Mexico in 1867. But it's enough. Manet's images, surrounded by a riveting selection of prints and photographs, are electrifying. (212) 708-9400, www.moma.org. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>* MUSEUM OF THE CITY OF NEW YORK: 'A CITY ON PAPER: SAUL STEINBERG'S NEW YORK,' through March 25. A very lively adjunct to the Morgan show, this display of some 40 drawings focuses on New York. An architect, Steinberg was particularly attracted to edifices like the Chrysler Building, which appears here looming over brownstones and in another incarnation, from a perspective directly below it, looking positively squat. New York people, in Steinberg's eyes, could be monuments, too. You may think you know Steinberg's work, but these shows make it new. 1220 Fifth Avenue at 103rd Street, (212) 534-1672, mcny.org. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>WHITNEY MUSEUM OF AMERICAN ART: 'KIKI SMITH: A GATHERING, 1980-2005,' through Feb. 11. Many things fly and float here: men and women, harpies and angels, birds and beasts, toadstools and stars. And some things fall to earth, or rather to the museum's black stone floors, maybe to rise again, maybe not. The whole show, a midcareer retrospective, suggests a Victorian fairy tale, its tone at once light, grievous and dreamlike. But fanciful as it is, Ms. Smith's art is also deeply, corporeally realistic. It wears moral and mortal seriousness on its sleeve, if not tattooed on its wrist. It is about life and death, the essential things. 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676, whitney.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>* ROBERT IRWIN: 'WHO'S AFRAID OF RED, YELLOW AND BLUE 3' In the past, Robert Irwin has paid homage to Joseph Albers. Now he makes a bow to a different kind of perceptual magician, Barnett Newman, turning Newman's 1966-70 paintings titled ''Who's Afraid of Red, Yellow and Blue'' into a kind of self-reflective architecture. Optical illusionism has long been Mr. Irwin's calling card, but here he has achieved it by bare-bones means, offering quieting visual fare for an overstimulated world. PaceWildenstein, 545 West 22nd Street, (212) 929-7000, pacewildenstein.com, through Feb. 3. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* JAPAN, INC. See this show of work by six painters who are either Japanese or inspired by Japanese culture primarily for Iona Rozeal Brown's dynamic new canvas ''King Kata.'' Through sharpened color and scale and by taking more liberties with her sources, Ms. Brown has markedly increased the visual punch of her characteristic kimono-and-cornrows cross-cultural fusion of cartoons, Japanese woodblock actor prints and gangsta chic. Her contribution underscores the vacuousness of much contemporary realist painting. Kravets Wehby, 521 West 21st Street, (212) 352-2238, through Feb. 17. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Other Galleries</p>
        <p>* 'THE CONSTANT POSSIBILITY OF ERASURE,' through Jan. 29. Organized by Donna Harkavy and Gracie Mansion, this excellent group show is at once witty and elegaic, exploring transience as an existential reality and as a conceptual ploy in late-20th-century art. Robert Rauschenberg's 1953 ''Erased De Kooning'' is an important reference point, present through Mike Bidlo's painstaking recreation. Joseph Beuys, Gary Simmons and Christian Xarec all have chalk pieces on blackboards, while Allan Kaprow preferred drawing, and simultaneously erasing, chalk pictures on the sidewalks or streets. Joanne Stamerra Hendricks uses erasers as a medium, and Jim Dingilian uses smoke. Dorsky Gallery Curatorial Projects, 11-03 45th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 937-6317. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* OLIVER HALSMAN ROSENBERG: 'DADA FOR GRANDMA,' through Jan. 28. Mr. Rosenberg conceived this show of a dozen lovely, small gouache paintings with references to the zodiac, the Kabala and Egyptian and Hindu cosmology as a tribute to his grandmother Yvonne Halsman who died last year. She was the wife of the Dada photographer Phillipe Halsman, and Dada zaniness has its part in the show. The artist has turned the paintings into an ingeniously low-tech ''prayer wheel'' set into motion by the visitor pedaling his grandmother's exercise bicycle. Mr. Rosenberg, a founder of the alternative space Triple Base in San Francisco who is, with Clint Taniguchi, half of the collaborative Crust &amp; Dirt, has other drawings in a box at Triple Candie, worth a look. Little Cakes, 625 East Sixth Street, Apt. 1B, East Village, (646) 342-1056. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'ANNIE LEIBOVITZ: A PHOTOGRAPHER'S LIFE, 1990-2005,' With photographs of her close-knit family and her companion, Susan Sontag; bits of photojournalism; and a pretentious foray into landscape photography, this large exhibition tells you more about Ms. Leibovitz than you probably want to know. Not surprisingly, her celebrity portraits are strongest, and at their best in a re-creation of the large pin-up boards on which she plotted the lavish book that accompanies the show. It reduces these often vivid portrayals to the size of their natural, magazine habitat and allows the viewer to skim for the good ones, as if turning pages. Brooklyn Museum, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, Brooklyn, (718) 638-5000; closes on Sunday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* SOLOMON R. GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'LUCIO FONTANA: VENICE/NEW YORK' If the Italian artist Lucio Fontana (1899-1968) was dazzled by Venice, he was positively awestruck by New York, which he first visited in 1961. For each city he created a group of works that he felt expressed its individual spirit. For Venice, a group of richly sensual oil paintings, with his signature slashes and punctures, sometimes with bits of colored glass scattered over them. For New York he chose shiny metal surfaces that he artfully cut, slashed and pierced to give a semblance of the city's wired energy and architectural vivacity. The two groups are united for the first time in this show, and well attended by works and photographs of works that trace from 1949 the career of an artist seeking to transcend the boundaries of his era. 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3500, guggenheim.org; closes on Sunday. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* THE MET: 'BRUSH AND INK: THE CHINESE ART OF WRITING' If painting and writing can be seen as modes of thinking, and they can, then this exhibition is as much a brainstorming session as an art exhibition, crackling with ideas and arguments every step of the way. It is also a sequence of moods, with impassioned voices calling out from the 80 scrolls and inscribed fans that line the galleries, which include colossal examples of contemporary 21st-century art that both depart from and preserve a tradition, (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org, closes on Sunday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>EL MUSEO DEL BARRIO: 'MERENGUE: VISUAL RHYTHMS' AND 'THIS SKIN I'M IN: CONTEMPORARY DOMINICAN ART FROM EL MUSEO DEL BARRIO'S PERMANENT COLLECTION,' Although ''Merengue,'' the larger of the two shows at El Museo, is made up almost entirely of paintings, it is about music, namely the national popular music of the Dominican Republic. Most of the 40 or so pictures, dating from the 1930s to the 1990s, document the music being performed or danced to; a few seem to be formal responses to its percussive beat. In a second, smaller show, merengue's vaunted joie de vivre gets some critical prodding from artists of Dominican descent living in New York. El Museo Del Barrio, 1230 Fifth Avenue, at 104th Street, East Harlem, (212) 831-7272, elmuseo.org; closes on Sunday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>P.S. 1 CONTEMPORARY ART CENTER: 'ALTERED, STITCHED AND GATHERED' Art by users might be the subtitle here, given that the show's 26 artists operate in the capacious gap between modernist assemblage and postmodern appropriation. Everything from e-mail messages to Wal-Mart plastic hangers and the movie ''Rambo'' are reused, often to comment on history, consumerism and war. Earlier efforts by Yoko Ono, Ben Vautier and Jaques Villeglé provide background. 22-25 Jackson Avenue, at 46th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 784-2084, ps1.org, closes on Tuesday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* THE WHITNEY MUSEUM OF AMERICAN ART: 'ALBERS AND MOHOLY-NAGY: FROM THE BAUHAUS TO THE NEW WORLD' This vigorously multimedia show traces the trajectories of two Modernist pioneers who overlapped as teachers at the Bauhaus in the 1920s and went on, separately, to influence postwar art and design in the United States. Ranging through painting, sculpture, film, design, prints and commercial art, it clarifies the Bauhaus debt to Russian Constructivism and includes works that presage the ''specific objects'' of the 1960s. Given the peregrinations of young artists among multiple art media, the show could not be more pertinent. 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676, whitney.org; closes on Sunday. (Smith)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the New York metropolitan region this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'ADRIFT IN MACAO' Previews start on Tuesday. Opens on Feb 13. Primary Stages presents Christopher Durang and Peter Melnick's new musical send-up of the sexy, shadowy world of film noir (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'THE FEVER' In previews; opens on Jan. 29. Wallace Shawn stars in his own play about a man who wakes up in a war-torn country feeling under the weather (1:30). Acorn Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'FRANK'S HOME' In previews; opens on Jan. 30. Richard Nelson's new bio-play about the life and work of Frank Lloyd Wright stars Peter Weller (as Wright) and Harris Yulin (who plays Louis Sullivan) (1:45). Playwrights Horizons Mainstage, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 719-4200.</p>
        <p>'THE GAZILLION BUBBLE SHOW' Performances through Tuesday; returning on Feb. 15. Fan Yan holds the world's record for the largest bubble ever blown, and in an even more amazing feat, he's parlayed this oddball stunt into a bubble-themed, family-friendly show (2:00). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'IN THE HEIGHTS' In previews; opens on Feb. 8. A new Off Broadway musical about two days in the life of Washington Heights, presented from the vantage point of a corner bodega (2:10). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'KIKI AND HERB' On the heels of a Broadway stint, these cabaret hipsters return to their downtown roots (1:30). Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555.</p>
        <p>'THE MERCHANT OF VENICE' In previews; opens on Feb. 4. F. Murray Abraham plays Shylock in this Theater for a New Audience production. Darko Tresnjak directs (2:20). The Duke on 42nd Street, 229 West 42nd Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'A SPANISH PLAY' In previews; opens on Feb. 1. Zoe Caldwell leads an extraordinary cast (Linda Emond, Denis O'Hare, Larry Pine, Katherine Borowitz) in Yasmina Reza's new backstage play, in which real life and fiction blur (1:30). Classic Stage Company, 136 East 13th Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101.</p>
        <p>'TRANSLATIONS' In previews; opens on Thursday. Brian Friel's drama about a British officer in 19th-century rural Ireland deals with themes of language, imperialism and culture clash. Garry Hynes directs (2:15). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE APPLE TREE' The amazing Kristin Chenoweth gives Imax-screen-size life to three curvaceous doodles who by rights shouldn't be any larger than figures in the Sunday funnies. Jerry Bock and Sheldon Harnick's 1966 musical, directed by Gary Griffin, shows its age but is given theatrical verve by Ms. Chenoweth, Brian d'Arcy James and Marc Kudisch (2:30). Studio 54, 254 West 54th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>'A CHORUS LINE' If you want to know why this show was such a big deal when it opened 31 years ago, you need only experience the thrilling first five minutes of this revival. Otherwise, this archivally exact production, directed by Bob Avian, feels like a vintage car that has been taken out of the garage, polished up and sent on the road once again (2:00). Schoenfeld Theater, 236 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE COAST OF UTOPIA' The exhilarating first two installments of Tom Stoppard's trilogy about 19th-century Russian intellectuals dreaming of revolution, these productions pulse with the dizzy, spring-green arrogance and anxiety of a new generation moving as fast as it can toward the future. Jack O'Brien directs a fresh, vigorous and immense cast that includes Brian F. O'Byrne, Jennifer Ehle, Billy Crudup and Ethan Hawke (2:45). Vivian Beaumont Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'COMPANY' Fire, beckoning and dangerous, flickers beneath the frost of John Doyle's elegant, unexpectedly stirring revival of Stephen Sondheim and George Furth's era-defining musical from 1970, starring a compellingly understated Raul Esparza. Like Mr. Doyle's ''Sweeney Todd,'' this production finds new clarity of feeling in Sondheim by melding the roles of performers and musicians (2:20). Barrymore Theater, 243 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE' (Tony Awards, best book of a musical and best original score, 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920s stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, it has theatergoers responding as if they were withering houseplants finally being watered after long neglect. Bob Martin and Sutton Foster are the standouts in the avid, energetic cast (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'GREY GARDENS' Christine Ebersole is absolutely glorious as the middle-aged, time-warped debutante called Little Edie Beale in this uneven musical adaptation of the notorious 1975 documentary of the same title. She and the wonderful Mary Louise Wilson (as her bedridden mother), in the performances of their careers, make ''Grey Gardens'' an experience no passionate theatergoer should miss (2:40). Walter Kerr Theater, 219 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE LITTLE DOG LAUGHED' The comedy of manners, a form widely believed to be extinct in the American theater, has actually resurfaced on Broadway with all its vital signs intact in Douglas Carter Beane's breezy but trenchant satire about truth and illusion, Hollywood style. With the wonderful Julie White as the movie agent you hate to love (but just can't help it) (2:00). Cort Theater, 138 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MARY POPPINS' This handsome, homily-packed, mechanically ingenious and rather tedious musical, adapted from the P. L. Travers stories and the 1964 Disney film, is ultimately less concerned with inexplicable magic than with practical psychology. Ashley Brown, who sings prettily as the family-mending nanny, looks like Joan Crawford trying to be nice and sounds like Dr. Phil. Directed by Richard Eyre and Matthew Bourne (2:30). New Amsterdam Theater, 214 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LES MISÉRABLES' This premature revival, a slightly scaled-down version of the well-groomed behemoth that closed only three years ago, appears to be functioning in a state of mild sedation. Appealingly sung and freshly orchestrated, this fast-moving adaptation of Victor Hugo's novel isn't sloppy or blurry. But its pulse rate stays well below normal (2:55). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' Duncan Sheik and Steven Sater's bold adaptation of the Frank Wedekind play is the freshest and most exciting new musical Broadway has seen in some time. Set in 19th-century Germany but with a ravishing rock score, it exposes the splintered emotional lives of adolescents just discovering the joys and sorrows of sex. Performed with brio by a great cast, with supple direction by Michael Mayer and inventive choreography by Bill T. Jones (2:00). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN' This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a superdeluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE VERTICAL HOUR' David Hare's soggy consideration of the Anglo-American cultural divide stars Julianne Moore (representing the Americans) and Bill Nighy (leading the British), directed by Sam Mendes. The Yanks don't stand a chance. With his irresistibly mannered performance as a laconic doctor, Mr. Nighy mops the floor with Ms. Moore. Actually, he mops the floor with Mr. Hare's play (2:20). Music Box Theater, 239 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'AS YET THOU ART YOUNG AND RASH' An abstract collage of shards of feeling built out of Euripides' ''Suppliant Women,'' this meditation on grief and the death of children in senseless war offers plenty of parallels to current society without doing anything so obvious as explicitly referring to them. The five-member cast, led by three beautiful middle-aged women, is strong; the director, David Herskovits, has helped them shape an evocative piece that might be too nonliteral for some tastes, but is both moving and distinctive (1:10). The Ohio Theater, 66 Wooster Street, SoHo, (212) 352-3101. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>'THE BIG VOICE: GOD OR MERMAN?' Think of two gifted and smart gay men with years of life together deploying their considerable talents from the two pianos you happen to have in your living room. The result is a hilarious and very touching memoir of two decades of love and the funky glories of show business life (2:00). Actors Temple Theater, 339 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Honor Moore)</p>
        <p>*'THE CLEAN HOUSE' Sarah Ruhl's comedy about the painful but beautiful disorder of life has arrived in New York at last in a gorgeous production directed by Bill Rauch. Blair Brown and Jill Clayburgh delight as sisters with different views on the meaning of cleaning, and Vanessa Aspillaga is equally good as the depressed maid with little affection for her work but a deep conviction that a good joke can be a matter of life and death (2:15). Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, Lincoln Center, 150 West 65th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'DAI (ENOUGH)' Iris Bahr's unnerving one-woman show doesn't have much to add to the Middle East debate, but it sure leaves a lasting impression. Ms. Bahr plays an assortment of characters who have the misfortune of being in a Tel Aviv cafe that is about to be visited by the havoc common to such establishments. The attack is rendered in jarring fashion, repeatedly; you watch the play on pins and needles, waiting for the next burst. Gimmicky? Sure. But viscerally effective (1:40). Culture Project, 55 Mercer Street, at Broome Street, SoHo, (212) 253-9983. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'THE FANTASTICKS' A revival -- well, more like a resuscitation -- of the Little Musical That Wouldn't Die. This sweet-as-ever production of Tom Jones and Harvey Schmidt's commedia-dell'arte-style confection is most notable for Mr. Jones's touching performance (under the pseudonym Thomas Bruce) as the Old Actor, a role he created when the show opened in 1960. Mr. Jones also directs (2:05). Snapple Theater Center, 210 West 50th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'GET YOUR WAR ON' Based on the absurdist comic strip of David Rees, this sardonic history lesson of the past six years will delight Bush-haters (1:10). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200. (Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'GUTENBERG! THE MUSICAL' A very funny if not terribly original satire of musical theater features what must be the worst backers' audition of all time. The excellent duo Jeremy Shamos and Christopher Fitzgerald make the pitch (2:05). The Actors' Playhouse, 100 Seventh Avenue South, at Fourth Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 239-6200. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'A JEW GROWS IN BROOKLYN' You don't have to be Jewish or Brooklynish to empathize with Jake Ehrenreich, but in terms of fully appreciating his essentially one-man show, it probably helps. Especially the Catskills jokes (2:05). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 560-8912. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>'MEET ME IN ST. LOUIS' This musical is too big for its stage, but the young turn-of-the-last-century sweethearts have great chemistry, and there are four terrific songs (2:00). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'MY MOTHER'S ITALIAN, MY FATHER'S JEWISH AND I'M IN THERAPY' Steve Solomon does skillful impersonations in his one-man show, but some of his jokes are as old as the hills (1:30). Little Shubert Theater, 422 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'NO CHILD' Teachers will love Nilaja Sun's one-woman show about the challenges of teaching drama at Malcolm X High School (1:10). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, at Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'REGRETS ONLY' Old acquaintance comes under siege in Paul Rudnick's chiffon-thin comedy about the varieties of love and marriage. But no one who sees this latest offering from one of the funniest quipmeisters alive is going to doubt that Christine Baranski is a one-liner's best friend (2:00). City Center Stage I, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RIDDLELIKELOVE (WITH A SIDE OF KETCHUP)' This one-woman show, in which Julie Fitzpatrick tells of her friendship with a deaf woman, is cloying and thin, but the sign-language interpretation provided at each performance gives it an interesting extra dimension, helping to bring the subject to life (1:30). Ensemble Studio Theater, 549 West 52nd Street, Clinton, (212) 352-3101. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'ROOM SERVICE' The Peccadillo Theater Company puts a charge into this comedy from the 1930s, thanks to a brisk pace by the director, Dan Wackerman, and a dozen dandy performances. David Edwards is the would-be producer whose bills threaten to swamp his efforts to put a show on Broadway, and Fred Berman is particularly fine as his director (2:00). SoHo Playhouse, 15 Vandam Street, South Village, (212) 691-1555. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'THE SCENE' Theresa Rebeck's latest is a sharp-witted, sharp-elbowed comedy about the savage economies of sex and show business in Manhattan. Tony Shalhoub plays an out-of-work actor, Charlie, happily married -- but not really -- to Patricia Heaton's frazzled chat show booker. Enter femme fatale Clea, played by the gifted Anna Camp, and goodbye, Charlie (2:00). Second Stage Theater, 307 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 246-4422. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'TOYS IN THE ATTIC' Austin Pendleton's fine revival of Lillian Hellman's last play faithfully attacks the corrosive attachments of family. What good is a family, and thus a society, the play implicitly asks, that can only look in the mirror? (2:30) Pearl Theater, 80 St. Marks Place, East Village, (212) 598-9802. (Ginia Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'25 QUESTIONS FOR A JEWISH MOTHER' This is the comedian Judy Gold's fiercely funny monologue, based on her own life as a single Jewish lesbian mother and interviews with more than 50 other Jewish mothers (1:20). St. Luke's Theater, 308 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Phoebe Hoban)</p>
        <p>* 'THE VIETNAMIZATION OF NEW JERSEY (AN AMERICAN TRAGEDY)' A revival of Christopher Durang's satire of war, family life and Bicentennial fever, on the 30th anniversary of its debut at the Yale Repertory Theater, swishes along at the speed of a Nascar race. Blanche Baker is a gem as an out-of-it 1970s matron who just can't dust off the Eisenhower era. the Beckett Theater, on Theater Row, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>* 'THE VOYSEY INHERITANCE' David Mamet has cleanly and cannily adapted Harley Granville Barker's 1905 play about corruption in the genteel world of Victorian finance. An excellent cast and a sumptuous production bring extra immediacy to a tale of embezzlement and entitlement that feels as fresh as tomorrow's stock options (1:50). Atlantic Theater, 336 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'FLUKE' A meditative collage of enigmatic riffs on ''Moby-Dick'' presented by the rambunctious experimental company Radiohole (1:30). Collapsable Hole, 146 Metropolitan Avenue, at Berry Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 388-2251. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden Theater, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' Singing CliffsNotes for Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' Often more entertaining than the real thing (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS' The biomusical that walks like a man (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT' A singing scrapbook for Monty Python fans (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' ''A Chorus Line'' with pimples (1:45). Circle in the Square, 254 West 50th Street, Manhattan, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'PURITY' The provocateur Thomas Bradshaw's horror show confronts black-on-black racism (1:15). Performance Space 122, 150 First Avenue, at Ninth Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101; closes on Tuesday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'SUDDENLY LAST SUMMER' As the luscious (and lobotomy-threatened) damsel in distress in Tennessee Williams's famously lurid melodrama, Carla Gugino gives a gutsy assurance to a production that otherwise lacks compelling confidence. Mark Brokaw directs a cast that includes Blythe Danner, in a fascinating but misconceived performance as a smothering mother from hell (1:30). Laura Pels Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300; closes on Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'PARTY TIME' This multimedia work by the Talking Band looks great, but it's really just a reworking of the old two-guys-in-a-foxhole plot. Here the foxhole is a tank in a desert war; its two occupants (Will Badgett and Joe Roseto) sing about their lives and fears as they try to find a rendezvous point. It's visceral without being illuminating (1:00). LaMaMa, 74A East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 475-7710; closes on Sunday. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'THE RAPTURE PROJECT' Marionettes of various faiths clash in this confusing modern take on an old brand of Sicilian puppet theater by Great Small Works. A Susan Sontag puppet makes an appearance, as does one that calls to mind a former New York City police commissioner, but more often than not, the musical accompaniment is the liveliest thing about the show (1:30). The Here Arts Center, 145 Avenue of the Americas, at Dominick Street, South Village, (212) 868-4444; closes on Sunday. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'YOU BELONG TO ME: DEATH OF NATIONS, PART V' The fifth, choppily considered installment of the writer and director Josh Fox's millennial play cycle examines the final days of three wars. Should we think about war primarily in terms of the havoc it wreaks on love and sex? He seems to think so (3:00). Performance Space 122, 150 First Avenue, at Ninth Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101; closes on Tuesday. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>* 'ABDUCTION: THE MEGUMI YOKOTA STORY' (No rating, 85 minutes, in Japanese) This documentary about the titular 13-year-old girl -- who vanished on the way home from school in Niigata, Japan, in 1977, and was revealed as a pawn in a North Korean spy-training program -- succeeds as a true crime story, a thumbnail history of a painful recent chapter of Asian history and as a portrait of lives transformed by trauma. Meandering in places, but compassionate and engrossing throughout. (Matt Zoller Seitz)</p>
        <p>'ALPHA DOG' (R, 117 minutes) Based on a true Southern California crime, Nick Cassavetes's entertaining exploitation flick features a lot of attractive, talented young actors shimmying across the screen while embodying the collective parental nightmare. Do you know where your children are? Well, in this film they're getting busy, chilling out, smoking blunts and chugging coolers faster than a toothless wino. Oh, and committing murder. (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>'ARTHUR AND THE INVISIBLES' (PG, 94 minutes) Luc Besson serves up a hybrid of live actors and computer-generated figures to tell a not-endearing-enough story about a boy (Freddie Highmore) who shrinks to microscopic size to find some gems and his missing grandfather. Lots of famous names (Madonna, Robert De Niro, David Bowie, Snoop Dogg) lend their voices to the computerized part of the movie, but only briefly near the end does everything click. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'BABEL' (R, 143 minutes, in English, Spanish, Japanese, Berber, Arabic and sign language) This hugely ambitious movie tells four loosely linked, not quite simultaneous stories set on three different continents, with dialogue in several languages. The themes, to the extent they are decipherable, include loss, fate and the terrible consequences of miscommunication. Written by Guillermo Arriaga and directed by Alejandro Gonzalez Iñárritu, the movie is an intellectual muddle but a visceral tour de force, and the power of the filmmaking almost overcomes the fuzziness of the ideas. Almost. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>'BLOOD DIAMOND' (R, 138 minutes) The makers of this foolish thriller about illegal diamond trafficking in Africa, starring an excellent Leonardo DiCaprio, want you to know there may be blood on your hands, specifically your wedding finger. Too bad they haven't thought through what it means to turn human misery into entertainment. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'BORAT: CULTURAL LEARNINGS OF AMERICA FOR MAKE BENEFIT GLORIOUS NATION OF KAZAKHSTAN' (R, 89 minutes) In this brainy, merciless comedy, a Kazakh journalist named Borat Sagdiyev, a k a the British comic Sacha Baron Cohen, invades America. America laughs, cries, surrenders. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'CHARLOTTE'S WEB' (G, 113 minutes) Gary Winick's adaptation of E. B. White's great children's novel is faithful to the wit and feeling of the source. The celebrity-voiced animals are charming, and Julia Roberts is in fine form as the heroic spider, whose writing ability saves the life of a pig. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'CHILDREN OF MEN' (R, 100 minutes) The end is nigh in this superbly directed political thriller by Alfonso Cuarón about a nervously plausible future. Based on the P. D. James book, the film stars an excellent Clive Owen and features equally sterling support from the actors Michael Caine, Danny Huston and Chiwetel Ejiofior, among others, as well as the great cinematographer Emmanuel Lubezki. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'CODE NAME: THE CLEANER' (PG-13, 91 minutes) Cedric the Entertainer clogs the arteries of what could have been a savvy riff on the ''Bourne'' films with way too much ham, playing a janitor who wakes up with amnesia, a dead man beside him. A missing computer chip fuels the plot, aided by Lucy Liu and Nicollette Sheridan. Though it's all too dumb to amuse grownups, it's harmless fun for tweener types. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'COMEDY OF POWER' (No rating, 110 minutes, in French) Isabelle Huppert is brisk and fierce as a French investigative judge going after corrupt fat cats. The director, Claude Chabrol, is more interested in the forms of ruling-class behavior than in the details of high-level criminality, but his detached, complacent style makes for an interesting contrast with Ms. Huppert's conviction. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'CURSE OF THE GOLDEN FLOWER' (R, 114 minutes, in Mandarin) The Chinese director Zhang Yimou aims for Shakespeare and winds up with Jacqueline Susann in this Tang dynasty melodrama roiling with incest, fraternal rivalry and madness-inducing fungus. As an emperor and empress fighting for control of their three sons, Chow Yun Fat and Gong Li lend the film a core of marital toxicity that's deliciously unstable. Directing with operatic delirium, Mr. Zhang has created a movie in which the line between tragedy and black comedy has been all but erased. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* 'THE DEPARTED' (R, 150 minutes) Martin Scorsese's cubistic entertainment about men divided by power, loyalty and their own selves is at once a success and a relief. Based on the crackling Hong Kong thriller ''Infernal Affairs,'' it features fine twinned performances from Matt Damon and Leonardo DiCaprio, and a showboating Jack Nicholson. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'DREAMGIRLS' (PG-13, 131 minutes) The Broadway musical arrives on the screen, capably directed by Bill Condon, ardently acted and sung by Jamie Foxx, Eddie Murphy, Beyoncé Knowles and (especially) Jennifer Hudson, but undone by mediocre and anachronistic songs. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'FREEDOM WRITERS' (PG-13, 123 minutes) Hilary Swank uses her characteristic neediness to fine effect in a true-to-life story about a teacher making a difference in a Southern California high school. The writer and director Richard LaGravenese provides the smartly laid foundation, but it's the kids who give the film its strong emotional tug. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'GOD GREW TIRED OF US' (PG, 90 minutes) This sober, uplifting documentary, which won two major awards at last year's Sundance Film Festival, follows the resettlement in the United States of three Sudanese young men uprooted as children by the civil war. Handsomely photographed, and inspirational but not cloyingly so, it is the rare contemporary documentary that doesn't leave a residue of cynicism and outrage. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE GOOD GERMAN' (R, 102 minutes) In his adaptation of the Joseph Kanon novel, Steven Soderbergh tries to resurrect the magic of classical Hollywood, principally by sucking out all the air, energy and pleasure from his own filmmaking. It's no wonder George Clooney, who stars alongside a vamping Cate Blanchett, looks confused. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'GURU' (No rating, 166 minutes, in Hindi) The Tamil director Mani Ratnam makes the case for India's growing economic clout with this entertaining epic about the rise and rise of Gurukant Desai, a fictitious Mumbai polyester manufacturer. The actress Aishwarya Rai, as Guru's wife, is a welcome presence, but the picture belongs to Abhishek Bachchan, who gives a rich, varied performance in the title role. (Andy Webster)</p>
        <p>'HAPPILY N'EVER AFTER' (PG, 87 minutes) Like Dreamworks's ''Shrek'' comedies, ''Happily'' is a grab-bag parody set in a fantasyland derived from bedtime stories and Disney films. The adopted chambermaid Ella (voiced by Sarah Michelle Gellar, drawn like Winona Ryder) and the poor dishwasher Rick (Freddie Prinze Jr.) battle Ella's wicked stepmother, Frieda (Sigourney Weaver). Despite self-aware touches, this is another tired kidsploitation product in which a wasp-waisted ingénue and a shallow beau drive the plot and live happily ever after. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>'THE LAST KING OF SCOTLAND' (R, 121 minutes) Kevin Macdonald paints a queasily enjoyable portrait of the Ugandan dictator Idi Amin from inside the palace walls. Forest Whitaker plays the mad king, while James McAvoy plays the fool. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'LETTERS FROM IWO JIMA' (R, 141 minutes, in Japanese) Another masterwork from Clint Eastwood's astonishing late period, and one of the best war movies ever. Ken Watanabe is especially fine as the general commanding Japanese troops in the doomed defense of the island of Iwo Jima. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'LITTLE CHILDREN' (R, 130 minutes) Todd Field's adaptation of Tom Perrotta's novel of suburban adultery is unfailingly intelligent and faultlessly acted. Kate Winslet and Patrick Wilson are superb as the parents of young children who meet at the playground and enact a two-handed variation on ''Madame Bovary'' against a backdrop of social paranoia and middle-class malaise. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'MISS POTTER' (PG, 92 minutes) In ''Miss Potter,'' Renée Zellweger, her face pickled in cheeriness, is Beatrix Potter, the creator of Peter Rabbit, Squirrel Nutkin and Mrs. Tittlemouse, among other beloved characters in children's literature. As portrayed by Ms. Zellweger, Potter is almost as chipper as Julie Andrews's Mary Poppins, a proto-feminist, proto-environmentalist and perfect lady to boot. There was plenty of drama in Potter's life, but the movie turns major conflicts and losses into minor setbacks in a charmed, entirely virtuous life. The movie is far too nice for its own good. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'NIGHT AT THE MUSEUM' (PG, 108 minutes) In this chaotic, overstuffed family comedy, Ben Stiller is a night watchman at the American Museum of Natural History, where the exhibits come to life at night and attack him and one another. This computerized spectacle spares no expense, but the storytelling is weak, and the hit-or-miss jokes miss more than hit. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'NOTES ON A SCANDAL' (R, 92 minutes) Judi Dench and Cate Blanchett play a misogynistic game of cat and mouse from which no one emerges unscathed, including the audience. Adapted by Patrick Marber from a novel by Zoë Heller and directed by Richard Eyre. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'PAN'S LABYRINTH' (R, 119 minutes, in Spanish) Guillermo del Toro's tale of a young girl's ordeal in post-Civil-War fascist Spain is either a fairy tale in the guise of a political allegory or vice versa. In either case it is a moving, enchanting, strange and humane example of popular art at its very best. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE PAINTED VEIL' (PG-13, 125 minutes) Nicely directed by John Curran, this version of the W. Somerset Maugham novel draws you in by turning a distaff bildungsroman into a fine romance with Naomi Watts and Edward Norton. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'PRIMEVAL' (R, 94 minutes) A giant crocodile named Gustave terrorizes Western journalists in war-torn Burundi. Not as much fun as it might have been, but not as terrible either. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE PURSUIT OF HAPPYNESS' (PG-13, 117 minutes) How you respond to this fairy tale in realist drag may depend on whether you find Will Smith's performances so overwhelmingly winning that you buy the idea that poverty is a function of bad luck and bad choices, and success the result of heroic toil and dreams. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'THE QUEEN' (PG-13, 103 minutes) Directed by Stephen Frears from a very smart script by Peter Morgan, and starring a magnificent Helen Mirren in the title role, ''The Queen'' pries open a window in the House of Windsor around the time of the death of Diana, Princess of Wales, blending fact with fiction. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'ROCKY BALBOA' (PG, 102 minutes) Surprisingly, the sixth installment of this franchise is no embarrassment. Like its forerunners, it goes the distance almost in spite of itself. It's all heart and no credibility, except as a raw-boned fable. From the very beginning, Rocky Balboa was about as lifelike a character as Popeye pumped up with spinach. But that may be the point of a series that peddles the notion that if you dream it hard enough, you can live it. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'STOMP THE YARD' (PG-13, 109 minutes) Brotherhood is powerful in this sometimes compelling, sometimes complacent movie about stepping and African-American fraternity life at an Atlanta institution called Truth University. DJ (Columbus Short), a street-style dancer, needs to find his place in a university ruled by Gammas and Thetas and stepping. (Rachel Saltz)</p>
        <p>'TEARS OF THE BLACK TIGER' (No rating, 113 minutes, in Thai) A western weepie from Thailand, filmed in garish color. In spite of the relentless genre pastiche, it has a charming sincerity. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'VENUS' (R, 91 minutes) A modest, diverting, touching tale of a young woman who attracts the interest -- avuncular and also erotic -- of an aging actor, played with effortless aplomb by the great Peter O'Toole. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'VOLVER' (R, 121 minutes, in Spanish) Another keeper from Pedro Almodóvar, with Penélope Cruz -- as a resilient widow -- in her best role to date. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'WE ARE MARSHALL' (PG, 128 minutes) This fact-based story of a West Virginia college town recovering from the death of its entire football team in a 1970 plane crash is a stiff, manipulative dud that gets wrong everything ''Friday Night Lights'' got right. Matthew McConaughey hams it up as the college's goofy new coach, who whips the replacement team into decent shape. (Holden)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>ROBERT ALTMAN REMEMBERED (Tonight through Tuesday) A tribute to the late American filmmaker winds up with several seldom seen Altman films: ''Three Women,'' ''Buffalo Bill and the Indians,'' ''McCabe and Mrs. Miller,'' ''Tanner '88,'' ''Health,'' ''A Wedding,'' ''Secret Honor'' and ''Come Back to the Five and Dime, Jimmy Dean.'' IFC Center, 323 Avenue of the Americas, at West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 924-7771, ifccenter.com; $10.75. (Dave Kehr)</p>
        <p>CRITICS CHOICE: GREAT DOCUMENTARIES (Tomorrow and Sunday) A series of significant documentaries chosen and introduced by members of the New York Film Critics Circle continues this weekend. Matt Zoller Seitz, who contributes to The New York Times and publishes The House Next Door Web site, is joined by the director Albert Maysles tomorrow for a screening of Mr. Maysles's 1968 cinéma-verité study ''Salesman,'' and Stuart Klawans of The Nation on Sunday presents Nora Jacobson's hard look at real estate development in Hoboken, N.J., ''Delivered Vacant.'' (Through Feb. 25.) Museum of the Moving Image, 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, (718) 784-0077, movingimage.us; $10. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>GLOBAL LENS 2007 (Tonight through Thursday) A continuing program of 10 feature films from developing countries, sponsored by the Global Film Initiative. This week's offerings include Li Yu's Chinese film ''Dam Street,'' about the friendship between a washed-up opera singer and a 10-year-old child, which concludes an extended run, with screenings tonight through Monday. On Thursday there's the Kurdistan-French co-production ''Kilometre Zero,'' a story of the ethnic conflict between Kurds and Iraqis set during the Iran-Iraq war of the 1980s, written and directed by Hiner Saleem. (Through Jan. 28.) Museum of Modern Art, Roy and Niuta Titus Theaters, (212) 708-9400, moma.org; $10. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>KEN AND AZAZEL JACOBS (Tonight through Tuesday) Anthology Film Archives is holding the premiere engagements of two new films from the avant-garde eminence Ken Jacobs (whose epic exercise in associative editing, ''Star Spangled to Death,'' has recently been released on DVD) and Azazel Jacobs, a son of Mr. Jacobs who is following in his father's footsteps. ''The Goodtimeskid,'' is by the younger Mr. Jacobs and is a 77-minute color feature that follows two men with the same name and a woman involved with them both over the course of 24 hours in Los Angeles. ''Two Wrenching Departures,'' by the senior Mr. Jacobs, is a black-and-white video piece. First produced as a live performance, it is about two of Mr. Jacobs's friends, the underground filmmakers Jack Smith (''Flaming Creatures'') and Bob Fleischner (''Banners''), who died within a week of each other in October 1989. Anthology Film Archives, 32 Second Avenue, at Second Street, East Village, (212) 505-5181, anthologyfilmarchives.org; $8. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>Pop  Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>* 'THE AMERICAN BEAUTY PROJECT' (Tomorrow and Sunday) The Grateful Dead had its origins in the folk revival, but it took a while for the band to find the right balance between long-form psychedelic jams and small-scale, acoustic country-folk. A diverse group of musicians gathers this weekend to pay tribute to the Dead's two eureka albums from 1970. Performing songs from ''Workingman's Dead'' tomorrow are the Klezmatics, Ollabelle, the Holmes Brothers, Jim Lauderdale, Larry Campbell and Tim O'Reagan of the Jayhawks. Playing from ''American Beauty'' on Sunday are Mark Eitzel, Jay Farrar, Espers, Toshi Reagon, Jorma Kaukonen, Dar Williams, Mr. Lauderdale, Ollabelle and Mr. Campbell. Tony Trischka and Andy Statman play instrumental interludes. At 8 p.m., Winter Garden, World Financial Center, West Street, south of Vesey Street, Lower Manhattan, (212) 945-0505, worldfinancialcenter.com; free. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>ARAMIRÈ (Tonight) This folk ensemble from the Salento region of Italy is dedicated to one of the lesser-known traditions of the country, the Greek-influenced music of the southeast of Italy's ''heel.'' With strings, accordion, flute and lots of tambourine, it pays particular attention to the pizzica, a galloping six-beat dance related to the tarantella and long used as a faith-healing cure for spider bites. At 8:30, Zankel Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7000, carnegiehall.org; $30 to $42. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* CAMERA OBSCURA (Wednesday) Like their fellow Glaswegians Belle and Sebastian, Camera Obscura, led by the expressively plain-voiced Tracyanne Campbell, is in love with wistful 1960s folk-pop and plays a country-leaning variation on it with taste and finesse. With the Essex Green. At 8 p.m., Warsaw, 261 Driggs Avenue, at Eckford Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 387-0505, warsawconcerts.com; $15.50 in advance, $17 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* KRISTIN CHENOWETH (Tonight) This Tony Award-winning treasure plays the Metropolitan Opera House; she's only the third musical-theater person the Met has ever presented in a solo gig. Appearing with a 12-piece orchestra and dancers, she is to add some opera arias to her usual repertory. At 8, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $50 to $200. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>CLIPSE (Wednesday) Comeback stories are rare and sweet in rap. In 2002 this Virginia duo rose all the way to No. 4 with sly rhymes about the criminal life and brutally minimal rhythm tracks by the Neptunes. Since then the Clipse struggled in music-industry purgatory but triumphed with ''Hell Hath No Fury'' (Re-Up Gang/Jive), another cold, lean and virtuosic exercise that was one of the best hip-hop albums of 2006. At 7:30 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; $25 in advance, $30 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>COLD WAR KIDS (Wednesday) The craggy guitars, verge-of-a-breakdown vocals and elliptical songwriting of this band from Austin, Tex., put it at the top of the music-blogger food chain last year. Now comes the hard part: maintaining popularity as the Internet eye roves again. This month the band is bouncing back and forth between New York and Los Angeles each week in a ''bicoastal residency.'' With Illinois and the Virgins. At 8:30 p.m., Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700, mercuryloungenyc.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MARK EITZEL (Tonight) Depression is Mr. Eitzel's element; as leader of the American Music Club and through a solo career, he has anatomized melancholy down to the molecular level. In a weary voice, with tunes that blur folk songs and torch songs in a smoky haze, he looks at estrangement and betrayal, loneliness and separation, and bad luck. At 8, Union Hall, 702 Union Street, at Fifth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 638-4400, unionhallny.com; $12. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>DIAMANDA GALÁS (Sunday) Though she is invariably dressed in black, with her face in witchy streaks of makeup, Ms. Galás needs only her voice to terrify and seduce. She slides from a low, sensual growl to painful yet musically precise shrieks, and has a vast repertory that ranges from Johnny Cash ballads to her own chilling AIDS Masses. At 9:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; $30. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* GLOBALFEST (Sunday) A one-night crash course in some of the best of what is called world music only because there is no other name for it, Globalfest, now in its fourth year, offers a dozen performers from around the planet. Among them, performing on three stages, are the suave Brazilian songwriter Lenine; Dengue Fever, a band from Los Angeles that resurrects the manically eclectic rock of pre-Khmer Rouge Cambodia; Les Primitifs du Futur, a French retro jazz-blues-Gypsy string band; Sara Tavares, a sensuous Cape Verdean singer; Lila Downs, whose take on Mexican rancheras and cumbias can be raucous or reverent; Le Trio Joubran, three oud-playing Palestinian brothers; and Andy Palacio and the Garifuna Collective, from Belize. At 7 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com or globalfest-ny.org; $40. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>GOB IRON (Tonight and tomorrow night) Jay Farrar of Son Volt and Anders Parker of Varnaline have built careers on the idea of ragged, rock-tinged roots music: a little less grungy than Neil Young, a bit more plebeian than Bob Dylan. On ''Death Songs for the Living'' (Transmit Sound/Legacy), their joint album as Gob Iron, they repaint centuries of American music by the Carter Family, Josh White and Stephen Foster in gray, bleak tones; even Clarence Ashley's sprightly ''Coo-Coo Bird'' gets a despondent rewrite. Tonight at 9:30, Maxwell's, 1039 Washington Street, Hoboken, N.J., (201) 653-1703, maxwellsnj.com; tomorrow at 9, Northsix, 66 North Sixth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 599-5103, northsix.com; $15. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PAUL GREEN SCHOOL OF ROCK MUSIC (Tomorrow and Sunday) As seen in the documentary ''Rock School,'' Mr. Green offers an extensive curriculum at his Philadelphia school, teaching youngsters the rock 'n' roll canon, as well as the fundamentals of power chords and budda-budda bass lines. Here his students offer their tribute to Black Sabbath, and if there is any guitar riff especially appropriate for 12-year-olds, it's ''Iron Man.'' At 2:30 p.m., Rebel, 251 West 30th Street, Manhattan, (212) 695-2747, rebelnyc.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>HOLMES BROTHERS AND ALLEN TOUSSAINT (Tuesday) Steeped in blues and gospel, Sherman and Wendell Holmes harmonize and raise the rafters with songs that draw hope from hard times. Their version of gospel is a close neighbor of Southern soul and country. They are joined by Allen Toussaint, the musical statesman from New Orleans, for two sets. At 7 and 9:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; $30. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>JERRY LEE LEWIS (Tonight) People pounded on pianos and hollered about hellfire before Jerry Lee Lewis, but nobody put it together in quite his way, which is the rock 'n' roll way. Now 71, Mr. Lewis recently released his first new album in 11 years, ''Last Man Standing'' (Artist First), which features appearances by the Rolling Stones, Bruce Springsteen and Eric Clapton, all happily overshadowed. With Jack Grace. At 8, B. B. King Blues Club &amp; Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $90. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LIGHTNING BOLT (Sunday) At first it is hard to believe that all the glorious chaos of Lightning Bolt -- a stalwart of the big noise-punk scene in Providence, R.I. -- is being made by only two people. But as the sound comes into focus, a playful give-and-take becomes clear, as the bassist Brian Gibson and the drummer and vocalist Brian Chippendale toss back and forth gigantic metal riffs and giggly high notes, creating rainbows of dissonance. At 9 p.m., Northsix, 66 North Sixth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 599-5103, northsix.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LINCOLN CENTER'S AMERICAN SONGBOOK (Tonight and tomorrow night) Now in its ninth season, this series has greatly expanded from its origins as a home for the midcentury pantheon of Harold Arlen, Richard Rodgers and the like. Tonight the Broadway soprano Judy Kuhn offers songs by Laura Nyro, who, along with Joni Mitchell, established the model for confessional, force-of-nature women's songwriting. Tomorrow Michael Franks plays his own music, including recent Brazilian-inspired works. At 8:30, Allen Room, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Broadway at 60th Street, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LUNA LOUNGE (Tonight and tomorrow night) For a decade beginning in 1995, the Luna Lounge was one of the better rock dives on the Lower East Side, and not just for its foosball table; its tiny back room was host to thousands of bands who played free, including some, like Interpol and the Strokes, who went on to bigger things. A year and a half after losing its lease, the club reopens with roomier digs in Brooklyn, and if the bookings are any indication, the indie tradition will continue even if the no-cover policy will not. The Comas, a band from North Carolina with psychedelic leanings, headlines tonight with Falcon, from Brooklyn. Tomorrow features three appropriately little-known New York bands, Orange Park, the Picture and Motel Creeps. At 8, 361 Metropolitan Avenue, at Havemeyer Street, Williamsburg, lunalounge.com; $10 tonight, $5 tomorrow. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>HUGH MASEKELA, KLEZMATICS (Sunday) The South African flugelhorn player Hugh Masekela has more to offer than his international hit ''Grazing in the Grass.'' For decades he has brought together the three-chord lope of South African pop with the zigzagging possibilities of jazz. The Klezmatics love the laughing, moaning melodies of traditional klezmer music. They also love jazz, rock and downtown improvisation, and they bring all those styles to bear on their music, which can be raucous, hypnotic, reverent and dizzying, sometimes all in one quick-changing piece. At 8 and 10:30 p.m., S.O.B.'s, 204 Varick Street, at Houston Street, South Village, (212) 243-4940, sobs.com; $25 in advance, $30 at the door. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>ERIN McKEOWN (Tuesday and Wednesday) A smiley sprite whose knack for wordplay and light touch on the guitar have sometimes evoked Tin Pan Alley, Ms. McKeown took the plunge in her new album, ''Sing You Sinners'' (Nettwerk), recording 12 nuggets by Harold Arlen, Cole Porter, Fats Waller and others (along with one by herself). If her voice is not quite up to the subtleties of wit the songs demand, her joy of discovery is sincere. With Sean Hayes. Tuesday at 7 p.m., Wednesday at 9:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MEXICAN INSTITUTE OF SOUND (Tomorrow) A one-man mash-up of Mexican and Latin American music of the past and perhaps the future, Camilo Lara, from Mexico City, artfully mingles cumbias and cha-chas with dub and slippery electronica. Like Moby, he spins a dream of groovy eternal life through sounds that retain their kitsch and dance potential forever. With the Gritty Midi Gang. At 8 p.m., Union Hall, 702 Union Street, at Fifth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 638-4400, unionhallny.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* MISSION OF BURMA (Tonight) In the early 1980s this innovative and widely influential Boston band brought sharp, brainy guitar minimalism to American postpunk, and since reuniting in 2002 after almost 20 years, it still plays with passion and smarts. Here the band appears with two worthy descendants: Oneida and Turing Machine, both of Brooklyn. At 8, Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800, irvingplaza.com; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ANDERS PARKER (Wednesday) Mr. Parker, who led the band Varnaline, immerses his songs in the stoic drama of country and folk music, resulting in a melancholy that is sometimes indistinguishable from cynicism. (''The hours I've wasted here I could have wasted anywhere.'') At 9 p.m., Living Room, 154 Ludlow Street, near Stanton Street, Lower East Side, (212) 533-7235, livingroomny.com; $8. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BOB SEGER AND THE SILVER BULLET BAND (Thursday) In the fall Mr. Seger released ''Face the Promise'' (Capitol), his first new album in a decade. It's O.K., but a better illustration of what remains powerful in Mr. Seger's music was his performance of ''America the Beautiful'' at Game 1 of the last World Series: in a tender, soulful rasp, he evoked rock's gospel roots, and made a simple patriotic ode bring a stadium roaring to its feet. At 8 p.m., Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741, thegarden.com; $79.50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* RICKY SKAGGS WITH BRUCE HORNSBY (Sunday) One of the most virtuosic musicians in bluegrass, Ricky Skaggs sends his fingers flying in a blur over mandolin, guitar and fiddle. He performs with Bruce Hornsby, whose years playing with the Grateful Dead made him a more versatile and playful musician. The two of them have a new album, due in March, that looks particularly versatile and playful: they do a version of Rick James's ''Super Freak.'' Sunday's concert also features opening sets by Shawn Colvin and Paul Thorn. At 7:30 p.m., B. B. King Blues Club &amp; Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $55 in advance, $60 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>SUBDUDES (Tomorrow) The Subdudes, from New Orleans, make cozy, mostly unplugged roots-rock: straightforward sentiments in tunes that mix a little country, a little blues, a little soul, a little zydeco and a little swing. The group's original lineup disbanded in 1996, but three founding members have revived the band and since 2004 released two new albums. At 7 p.m., Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800, irvingplaza.com; $22 in advance, $25 at the door. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>ZS (Sunday and Monday) The Zs, one of the most active avant-rock groups in New York, plays kinetic pieces that sputter forth in Morse code dots of percussion and saxophone. On Monday it plays with Dave Longstreth, whose band Dirty Projectors constructs elaborate ''glitch operas'' with precise harmonies and stark pluckings of guitar and strings, all arranged slightly out of whack. Sunday at 9 p.m., Cake Shop, 152 Ludlow Street, between Stanton and Rivington Streets, Lower East Side, (212) 253-0036, cake-shop.com; $7. Monday at 10 p.m., Zebulon, 258 Wythe Avenue, near Metropolitan Avenue, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 218-6934, zebuloncafeconcert.com; no cover. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Jazz  Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>AMPERSAND/KNEEBODY (Tuesday) The guitarist Tim Ziesmer features his own rock-influenced compositions in Ampersand, with Chris Speed on tenor saxophone, Dave Ambrosio on bass and Ted Poor on drums. Kneebody, a collective that includes the keyboardist Adam Benjamin and the trumpeter Shane Endsley, convincingly blends rock, funk and soul in a rugged and exploratory modern fusion. At 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; cover, $12. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>* THE BAD PLUS (Tuesday through Thursday) The pianist Ethan Iverson, the bassist Reid Anderson and the drummer David King constitute the Bad Plus, a delivery system for smartly sweeping original songs as well as wryly affectionate renditions of pop tunes. They caused a stir among jazz purists when they first headlined at the Village Vanguard a few years ago; by now the engagement has become a happy ritual, and the band has nothing to prove but its own continuing vitality. (Through Jan. 28.) At 9 and 11 p.m. (with a 12:30 set on Jan. 27), Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SAM BARDFELD (Tonight) Mr. Bardfeld, a violinist with a wide-ranging résumé, revisits the music from his evocative recent album ''Periodic Trespasses (The Saul Cycle)'' (Fresh Sound New Talent). At 9 p.m., BAMcafé, 30 Lafayette Avenue, between Ashland Place and St. Felix Street, (718) 636-4100, bam.org; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* DON BYRON (Monday) Jazz has many card-carrying eclectics these days, but none more self-assured than the clarinetist Don Byron, who will match wits with two very different pianists: Ursula Oppens, a classical interpreter known for the range of her interests, and Kenny Barron, an improviser with a soulfully sophisticated style. At 8 p.m., Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, (212) 501-3330, kaufman-center.org; $25 in advance, $30 on Monday. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ROBERTO CARCASSES, DAFNIS PRIETO, YOSVANY TERRY AND YUNIOR TERRY (Tomorrow) Cuban folk tradition collides with contemporary jazz protocol in a group featuring Mr. Carcasses on keyboards, Mr. Prieto on drums and the Terry brothers, Yosvany and Yunior, on saxophone and bass respectively. At 10 and 11:30 p.m., Rose Live Music, 345 Grand Street, between Havemeyer and Marcy Streets, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 599-0069, liveatrose.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JIMMY COBB'S MOB (Tuesday and Wednesday) Jimmy Cobb, a masterful hard bop drummer, has served as a mentor to many young musicians through this band; one of them, the tenor saxophonist Eric Alexander, takes the melodic lead here. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE COLEMAN (Tomorrow, Sunday and Thursday) Mr. Coleman, the avant-garde alto saxophonist and composer, programmed this month's schedule at the Stone, leaving a handful of spaces for his own explorations. Tomorrow he convenes a group called Aquarius Ingress consisting of seven reed players, including the saxophonist Miguel Zenón and the clarinetist Chris Speed; on Sunday and Thursday he leads Five Elements, his adventurously funk-focused working band. At 8 and 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TAYLOR EIGSTI AND JULIAN LAGE (Monday) Mr. Eigsti, a pianist, and Mr. Lage, a guitarist, are precociously talented players with a substantive history together, as well as a fruitful affiliation with the Concord label. At 7 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BILL EVANS'S SOULGRASS (Tuesday through Thursday) Virtuosity, the ingredient shared by bluegrass and fusion, will be in copious supply during this summit organized by the saxophonist Bill Evans, featuring Tony Trischka on banjo, Sam Bush on mandolin, Christian Howes on violin, Richard Bona on bass and Dave Weckl on drums. (Through Jan. 28.) At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $35 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DOMINICK FARINACCI (Monday) A sharp and promising young trumpeter, Mr. Farinacci leads a quintet consisting of the vibraphonist Joe Locke, the pianist Danny Grissett, the bassist Vicente Archer and the drummer Ari Hoenig. At 9 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>AYELET ROSE GOTTLIEB (Sunday) Ms. Gottlieb is a commanding vocalist whose most recent album, ''Mayim Rabim'' (Tzadik), features scriptural texts in the original Hebrew. Her high-grade sextet includes Avishai Cohen on trumpet, Loren Stillman on alto saxophone, Anat Fort on piano, Ed Schuller on bass and Take Toriyama on drums. At 8:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEFON HARRIS (Tomorrow and Sunday) ''African Tarantella: Dances With Duke'' (Blue Note), the latest album by the vibraphonist Stefon Harris, features music from two Duke Ellington suites, along with several original themes. As on the album, Mr. Harris augments his working quartet with reeds and strings, and with the trombonist Steve Turre. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set tomorrow only, Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $30. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>VIJAY IYER (Tonight) A pianist-composer given to restive energies and rhythmic conundrums, Mr. Iyer performs in two promising settings: with a trio featuring the attentive bassist Stephan Crump and the supple drummer Marcus Gilmore, and later in a duo with the alto saxophonist Steve Coleman, one of his mentors. At 8 and 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE LEHMAN (Tuesday) Mr. Lehman is a saxophonist who pursues an abstract lyricism informed by myriad traditions. His quintet includes sharp and sympathetic peers like the trumpeter Jonathan Finlayson, the drummer Tyshawn Sorey and the bassist Drew Gress. At 8:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GEORGE LEWIS (Tuesday) Mr. Lewis, a trombonist and pedagogue affiliated with Columbia University and the Association for the Advancement of Creative Musicians, performs two abstract sets: a duo performance with the bassist Reggie Workman, and then a solo improvisation with laptop electronics. At 8 and 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>RAMSEY LEWIS (Monday) A successful crossover artist for more than 40 years, the pianist and broadcaster Ramsey Lewis presents a coolly boppish working trio with Larry Gray on bass and Leon Joyce Jr. on drums. At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $45 at tables, $30 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TONY MALABY, WILLIAM PARKER AND NASHEET WAITS (Sunday) Strenuous free and not-quite-free improvisation, courtesy of several people who know the territory well: Mr. Malaby, tenor saxophonist; Mr. Parker, bassist; and Mr. Waits, drummer. At 7 and 9 p.m., Jimmy's 43 Restaurant, 43 East Seventh Street, East Village, (212) 982-3006, freestylejazz.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MALAMUTE (Tuesday) Though named after a breed of Arctic sled dog, this collective promises something other than steady propulsion; with Jim Black on drums, Kieran Daly on electric mandolin and Nate Wooley on trumpet, it's likely to tumble ahead in fits and starts. At 7 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DONNY McCASLIN (Tonight) As on his recent album ''Soar'' (Sunnyside), Mr. McCaslin applies his extroverted saxophone style to a Latin American-inspired contemporary fusion, benefiting greatly from the contributions of the bassist Scott Colley and the percussionists Antonio Sanchez and Pernell Saturnino. At 10, 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MIKE MORENO (Tonight) A versatile and increasingly prominent guitarist, Mr. Moreno features his own compositions in a post-bop quintet featuring the saxophonist John Ellis and the pianist Aaron Parks. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JOE MORRIS (Wednesday) Mr. Morris has an angular but appealing guitar style, and bright ideas about how to organize timbres. His quintet here includes Michael Winograd on clarinet, Daniel Blacksberg on trombone, Daniel Levin on cello and Michael Evans on drums. At 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* DAVID MURRAY BLACK SAINT QUARTET (Monday through Wednesday) A spirited and often blustery tenor saxophonist, David Murray leads a hard-driving group featuring Lafayette Gilchrist on piano, Ray Drummond on bass and Andrew Cyrille on drums. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>NYC BALKAN GYPSY AND BEYOND (Tonight) A convention of three boisterous groups with similarly folksy inspirations: the Paradox Trio, led by the clarinetist Matt Darriau; Romski Boji, led by the percussionist Seido Salifoski; and Slavic Soul Party, fronted by the percussionist Matt Moran. At 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* NYC WINTER JAZZFEST (Tomorrow) The Knitting Factory commits all three of its floors to jazz during this sprawling one-night festival, which will feature 18 different bands. Among the highlights are groups led by the bassist Henry Grimes, the pianists Marc Cary and Robert Glasper, and the violinist Jenny Scheinman. From 6 p.m. to 1 a.m., 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3132, knittingfactory.com; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JEREMY PELT (Tomorrow) The clarion tone and preternatural poise of Mr. Pelt's trumpet playing have earmarked him as a rising star in the jazz mainstream. His quintet features a frequent foil, the guitarist Mike Moreno. At midnight, Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $10, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BEN RILEY'S MONK LEGACY SEPTET (Wednesday and Thursday) Ben Riley, one of the most buoyant drummers ever to serve under Thelonious Monk's employ, honors the pianist and composer's memory with this rock-solid septet, stocked with players like the trumpeter Don Sickler and the saxophonists Wayne Escoffery and Bruce Williams. (Through Jan. 27.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JEROME SABBAGH (Thursday) Mr. Sabbagh, a coolly composed tenor saxophonist and composer in the postmodern mainstream, leads a sleek ensemble with Ben Monder on guitar, Joe Martin on bass and Ted Poor on drums. At 8 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MATTHEW SHIPP (Tomorrow) Mr. Shipp's pianism is often prickly but rarely off-putting, because even his free improvisations tend to follow a faintly linear path. He performs solo here, as on a thoughtful recent album called ''One'' (Thirsty Ear). At 8 and 9:30 p.m., Tenri Cultural Institute, 43A West 13th Street, between Fifth and Sixth Avenues, Greenwich Village, (212) 645-2800, tenri.org; $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>HELEN SUNG (Tonight and tomorrow) The pianist Helen Sung leads a post-bop quartet featuring the articulate alto saxophonist Steve Wilson. At 8 and 9:45 p.m., Kitano Hotel, 66 Park Avenue, at 38th Street, (212) 885-7119, kitano.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JAMES (BLOOD) ULMER (Wednesday and Thursday) Mr. Ulmer's singing and guitar playing describe an oddly hypnotic combination of influences: Ornette Coleman's polytonality crossed with the psychedelic swagger of Jimi Hendrix. He performs here with a group that includes the keyboardist Amina Claudine Myers and the drummer Aubrey Dale. (Through Jan. 28) At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CEDAR WALTON (Tonight and tomorrow) As a pianist and composer, Mr. Walton pursues an articulate, almost courtly variety of hard bop. His rhythm section here includes the bassist David Williams and the drummer George Fludas. At 8, 10 and 11:30, Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, (212) 864-6662, smokejazz.com; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical  Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>'ACIS AND GALATEA' (Tuesday) Staged opera or home entertainment? Handel's early pastoral opera has been the subject of debate since it was written. Probably first performed for a private group at a country estate, it was later revived as a staged opera by another manager eager to capitalize on Handel's Italian-opera success -- in competition with Handel's own opera company. Now, New York, having experienced the work on an operatic scale in City Opera's 2001 production, can sample it in a more intimate form: presented by the five-member Aulos Ensemble (acclaimed early-music specialists) and four vocal soloists at the Met -- not the opera, but the museum. At 6:30 p.m., Medieval Sculpture Hall, Metropolitan Museum of Art, (212) 570-3949, metmuseum.org; $50. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>'LA BOHÈME' (Wednesday) Franco Zeffirelli's overblown ''Bohème'' returns to the Metropolitan Opera for its first airing of the new year, and the Chilean soprano Cristina Gallardo-Domâs returns to sing Mimì, the role with which she made her house debut in 1996. Her Rodolfo is the excellent tenor Marcello Giordani; they both have the vocal and dramatic chops to make an impact in Zeffirelli's massive sets. Ainhoa Arteta is Musetta, Dwayne Croft is Marcello, and Carlo Rizzi conducts. At 7:30 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $80 tickets remaining. (Vivien Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>'THE FIRST EMPEROR'  (Monday and Thursday) The excitement of a world premiere at the Met, combined with widespread interest among the general public in the composer Tan Dun, who won an Oscar for his film score to ''Crouching Tiger, Hidden Dragon,'' have resulted in a sold-out run for ''The First Emperor.'' Alas, though the story of Qin Shi Huang, the first emperor of China, who unified the country through brutality and conquest, is compelling, Mr. Tan's ponderous score is a huge disappointment. There are gripping moments, especially some propulsive orchestra passages that incorporate Chinese instruments. But the opera's lyrical flights are slow-moving, ponderous and sometimes cloying. Mr. Tan has tried to meld Chinese melody and Italianate lyricism. But his music seems caught in some nowhere land between ''Crouching Tiger'' and Puccini's ''Turandot.'' Even the great Plácido Domingo, bravely taking on the challenging title role, cannot save the show. The colorful production is by the Chinese film director Zhang Yimou (''House of Flying Daggers''). Mr. Tan conducts. There are two more performances. At 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* 'MOSTLY OPERETTA' (Tonight, tomorrow, Monday, Tuesday and Thursday) The Austrian Cultural Forum's innovative festival, which pairs 20th-century operetta in intimate recitals with contemporary visuals in an effort to move the genre into the 21st century, winds up this week with three programs by Viennese singers who specialize in operetta: two programs that pay homage to some composers forced to emigrate by the Nazis, and a selection of Kurt Weill's songs arranged into what the forum's director calls ''a kind of 'Winterreise.' '' At 7 p.m, 11 East 52nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 319-5300, acfny.org; free, but reservations are required. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>* 'IL SIGNOR BRUSCHINO' (Thursday) Mention Rossini and most people come up with ''The Barber of Seville,'' but this work -- in which the composer honed the comic gift that came to the fore in ''Barber'' and other ''opere buffe'' -- hasn't been staged in New York since 1933. The Gotham Chamber Opera has set itself apart among the city's small opera companies with quality performances of less-known operas (with good singers), conducted by the company's founder, Neal Goren: it is opening this frothy piece of fun with a gala performance on Thursday. (The run continues, at normal ticket prices, next week.) At 7:30 p.m., Abrons Arts Center, 466 Grand Street, at Pitt Street, Lower East Side, (212) 279-4200, gothamchamberopera.org; $300. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>'THE TENDER LAND' (Tomorrow and Sunday) In 1976, when the enterprising Bronx Opera Company first presented Copland's ''Tender Land,'' the composer participated in rehearsals and attended productions. For its current production, the company is using the effective chamber version of the orchestral score arranged by Murry Sidlin. Royston Coppenger is the director, and Michael Spierman conducts. At 2 p.m., Heckscher Theater, El Museo del Barrio, 1230 Fifth Avenue, at 104th Street, East Harlem, (718) 960-8833, bronxopera.org; $20 to $35. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* 'LA TRAVIATA' (Tuesday) The admirable soprano Hei-Kyung Hong gives a beautifully sung and deeply felt portrayal of Violetta in the Met revival of Verdi's ''Traviata,'' in Franco Zeffirelli's extravagant 1998 production. The other news is the promising performance of an artist who, like Ms. Hong, is also from South Korea: the tenor Wookyung Kim, singing Alfredo in his Met debut season. As a Verdi tenor, Mr. Kim is a little green. But he has an appealing and robust voice, and at his best, sings with ardor and flair. The baritone Charles Taylor, who was ill on opening night, is scheduled to sing Germont. Carlo Rizzi conducts. At 7:30 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $80 to $175. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>* ALARM WILL SOUND (Tomorrow) This supremely inventive new-music ensemble offers an expansive look at the music of Edgard Varèse in Miller Theater's Composer Portraits series. Among the 10 works on the program are the early ''Grand Sommeil Noir''; ''Ionisation,'' for percussion ensemble; ''Density 21.5,'' for flute; and several orchestral works. The main curiosity, though, is an orchestrated arrangement of the ''Poème Électronique,'' which is normally heard in the electronic tape version that Varèse completed in 1958. At 8 p.m., Miller Theater, Broadway at 116th Street, Morningside Heights, (212) 854-7799, millertheater.com; $25; $15 for students. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>DANIEL BARENBOIM  (Tomorrow and Sunday) In a charming and revealing program note (available on carnegiehall.org), Mr. Barenboim writes of having been reared from his earliest years on Bach's ''Well-Tempered Clavier.'' When he arrived at 12 for his first lesson in Paris with Nadia Boulanger, this formidable teacher opened the score to the Prelude in E minor from Book 1 and told him, ''Play it for me in A minor.'' This weekend Mr. Barenboim, a formidable pianist, will play that prelude (in the original key) in his two-program survey of the complete 48 preludes and fugues from Bach's monumental work. Book 1 tomorrow at 8 p.m., Book 2 on Sunday at 2 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $34 to $108. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>KRISTIAN BEZUIDENHOUT (Thursday) This South African fortepianist gave a fine recital at the Miller Theater in November, and returns with another program, as part of the Boston Early Music Festival's series in the Morgan Library &amp; Museum's intimate new hall. His program includes Mozart's Sonata in F (K. 494) and Variations on ''Unser dummer Pöbel meint'' (K. 455); Benda's Sonata in A minor; and Haydn's Variations in F minor. At 7:30 p.m. (preconcert lecture at 7), Morgan Library &amp; Museum, 225 Madison Avenue, at 36th Street, (212) 685-0008, themorgan.org; $45; $35 for members. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>CHAMBER MUSIC SOCIETY OF LINCOLN CENTER (Sunday and Tuesday) Music for four-hand piano used to be a staple of the repertory, particularly in the days before recordings, when the way most people enjoyed music was to play it themselves. In this program seven pianists (including Charles Wadsworth, a past director of the society, and Wu Han, a current co-director, as well as Gilbert Kalish and Anne-Marie McDermott) take on works for four hands by Mozart, Mendelssohn, Fauré, Stravinsky and Lutoslawski (whose Variations on a Theme of Paganini is the only one to employ two separate pianos). Sunday at 5 p.m., Tuesday at 7:30 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5788, chambermusicsociety.org; $28 to $50. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>* 'DECASIA' (Thursday) The composer Michael Gordon and the filmmaker Bill Morrison have collaborated on this enveloping multimedia work. Mr. Morrison's contribution is a fast-cut montage of antique films, in which bubbles and other signs of decay create patterns as crucial to the work as the images of cowboys, flappers, factory workers, dancers, parachutists and exotic scenes from the Middle East and North Africa. Mr. Gordon's powerful 65-minute score -- played by an orchestra deployed in the balconies -- evolves from a faint, metallic rattle to a barrage of percussion, electric guitars, brass choirs, woodwinds and strings. At 7 and 9:30 p.m., Orensanz Center for the Arts, 172 Norfolk Street, Lower East Side, (212) 352-3101; $25. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* HILLIARD ENSEMBLE (Sunday) In its performance on the Music Before 1800 series, this British vocal ensemble, here in a quartet configuration (David James, Rogers Covey-Crump, Steven Harrold and Gordon Jones), sings the Lassus Requiem, with antiphons and motets by Palestrina interposed between the movements. At 4 p.m., Corpus Christi Church, 529 West 121st Street, Morningside Heights, (212) 666-9266, mb1800.org; $25 to $40; $5 off for students and 62+. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>KIRILL GERSTEIN (Sunday) The Metropolitan Museum presents the third of four young up-and-coming pianists in its Accolades series. This week the spotlight is on the Russian pianist Kirill Gerstein, who won first prize at the 2001 Arthur Rubinstein Piano Competition and was awarded the 2002 Gilmore Young Artist Award. He will perform Haydn's Sonata in D (Hob. XVI:37), Schumann's whimsical ''Humoresque,'' Ligeti's Études, Busoni's Sonatina No. 6 and an arrangement of the Scherzo from Tchaikovsky's Sixth Symphony. At 2:30 p.m., Metropolitan Museum of Art, (212) 570-3949, metmuseum.org; $20. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* MOSCOW SOLOISTS (Thursday) Wu Man, the fleet-fingered and adventurous Chinese pipa player, frequently adds the sound of her exotic instrument to Western ensembles. With the violist Yuri Bashmet and his Moscow Soloists (a group formed in 1992 and made up of young graduates of the Moscow Conservatory), she will perform Tan Dun's Concerto for String Orchestra and Pipa (a pipa is a Chinese lute), a work whose premiere she performed in 2001. The program also includes Toru Takemitsu's ''Nostalgia'' and his Three Film Scores for Strings, and Hikaru Hayashi's Concerto for Viola and Strings, ''Elegie.'' At 7:30 p.m., Zankel Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $28 and $40. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC (Today, tomorrow and Thursday) Riccardo Muti, the exacting Italian maestro, is in town for two weeks to conduct the Philharmonic. This weekend's program offers the brilliant violinist Vadim Repin in Tchaikovsky's Violin Concerto and Scriabin's strangely mystical and musically visionary Symphony No. 3, ''Le Divin Poème.'' On Thursday Mr. Muti presents the first of three performances of an all-Italian program, with ballet music from Verdi's ''Macbeth,'' Respighi's ''Feste Romane'' and a little-known piano concerto from 1885 by Giuseppe Martucci, a work admired by Toscanini, Mahler and, of course, Mr. Muti. Gerhard Oppitz is the soloist. Today at 2 p.m., tomorrow at 8 p.m. and Thursday at 7:30 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nyphil.org; $24 to $96. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>JORGE FEDERICO OSORIO (Monday) This Mexican pianist has recorded everything from Brahms to Ponce (and, most recently, Mozart violin sonatas with Ani Kavafian) but has only infrequently performed in New York. His solo recital juxtaposes works by two Spanish composers, Soler and Albéniz, with preludes by Debussy, showpieces by Liszt and Beethoven's Sonata No. 30. At 8 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $20 to $45. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>* 'REQUIEM FOR DARFUR' (Monday) The Democracy Council, a human-rights advocacy group, is sponsoring this performance of Verdi's magisterial Requiem by musicians from orchestras including the New York and Berlin Philharmonics and the Met and Philadelphia Orchestras. The event, which benefits Unicef and other charities involved in aid work in Darfur, has Mia Farrow as its host, and features as soloists the soprano Alexandra Deshorties, the mezzo-soprano Sarah Heltzel, the tenor Scott Piper and the bass Morris Robinson; George Mathew conducts. At 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $27 to $500. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>RIVERSIDE SYMPHONY (Tomorrow) Even by its own adventurous standards, the Riverside Symphony is offering an offbeat program tomorrow. The most eclectic item is Villa-Lobos's Harmonica Concerto. The harmonica virtuoso Robert Bonfiglio says he has performed the work more than 350 times. I've never heard it. Have you? Here is your chance, on a program that also offers Mozart's ''Haffner'' Symphony and Honegger's Neo-Classical Symphony No. 4 (''Delights of Basel''). George Rothman conducts. At 7:30 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $30 to $50. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>ABBEY SIMON (Tuesday) The Walter W. Naumburg Foundation is offering a retrospective concert series in which it presents former winners of its competition. Mr. Simon, the pianist, won in 1941, and his recordings of the Romantic repertory have always been highly regarded, with Chopin as a particular favorite. At his ''Naumburg Looks Back'' recital, he plays music of Chopin and Schumann. At 8 p.m., Weill Recital Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $20; $10 for students and 65+. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* 'THE SONG CONTINUES' (Tuesday through Thursday) The master classes are going to be a hotter ticket than the recitals at the Marilyn Horne Foundation's annual celebration of the art of song. Leading off at Zankel Hall is the celebrated Barbara Cook; the next night it's the soprano Evelyn Lear; on Thursday it's Ms. Horne herself. The duo recitals by young artists supported by Ms. Horne's foundation, like Joslin Romphf, a soprano, and Lee Poulis, a baritone, on Wednesday; or Hanan Alattar, a soprano, and Timothy Falton, a tenor, on Thursday, have been relegated to the 5:30 time slot at Weill Recital Hall. (The series continues with a gala concert next Friday.) Master classes, Tuesday through Thursday at 7:30 p.m.; recitals, Wednesday and Thursday at 5:30 p.m.; Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $20 for master classes; $5 for recitals; some events sold out. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>TAKACS QUARTET (Tonight) This string quartet has undergone a few personnel changes in recent years, and in the process its sound and focus have improved considerably. A Beethoven cycle at Lincoln Center two years ago showed it to be in remarkable form. This time Takacs offers Debussy's Quartet and Shostakovich's Quartet No. 11, before returning to Beethoven for the Quartet in A minor (Op. 132). At 8, Metropolitan Museum of Art, (212) 570-3949, metmuseum.org; $45. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* TOKYO STRING QUARTET (Tomorrow) This venerable quartet continues its residency at the 92nd Street Y and its commemoration of the 150th anniversary of Schumann's death with a performance of his String Quartet in A minor. The program also includes Schumann's poignant song cycle ''Dichterliebe,'' sung by the fine Canadian lyric baritone Russell Braun, accompanied by the pianist Carolyn Maule. Paul Hecht, an actor, will read poems from Heinrich Heine's ''Lyrisches Intermezzo,'' on which Schumann based these songs. At 8 p.m., 1395 Lexington Avenue, (212) 415-5500, 92y.org; $40. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>Dance  Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>RUTH CANSFIELD DANCE (Tonight through Sunday night) In its first New York performances, this Canadian company will present three dances by Ruth Cansfield, set to music by Debussy, Rachmaninoff and Crumb, that explore characters' hidden stories, movement without artifice and voyages of the soul. At 9, Merce Cunningham Studio, 55 Bethune Street, at Washington Street, West Village, (866) 405-5810, ruthcansfield.com; $17; $13.60 for students and 65+. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>CEDAR LAKE CONTEMPORARY BALLET (Tonight and tomorrow night) The company opens its winter season with a program of dance by Jacopo Godani of Italy, Edgar Zendejas of Mexico and New York's own Benoit-Swan Pouffer, who directs Cedar Lake. (Through Jan. 27.) At 8, Cedar Lake Theater, 547 West 26th Street, Chelsea, (212) 868-4444, smarttix.com; $30; $20 for 65+ and students with ID. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CREATIVE OUTLET DANCE THEATER OF BROOKLYN (Today through Sunday) Jamel Gaines's ''Remembering -- Lest We Forget'' explores historical accounts of the Middle Passage, slavery and emancipation. This vibrant company will also perform two repertory matinees tomorrow, starring Bahiyah Sayyed Gaines, and on Sunday. Tonight and tomorrow at 7:30, Sunday at 3 p.m., Kumble Theater for the Performing Arts, Long Island University Brooklyn Campus, Flatbush and DeKalb Avenues, Brooklyn, (718) 488-1624, creativeoutlet.org; $30; $25 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* DANCE GOTHAM FESTIVAL (Tomorrow and Sunday) Ten modern-dance companies will perform on two different programs, among them Montreal Danse, Johannes Wieland and Keely Garfield (tomorrow) and Kun-Yang Lin/Dancers, Nicolas Andre Dance Theater and Koresh Dance Company (Sunday). Appearing both nights will be Paradigm, the Carolyn Dorfman Dance Company, Keigwin &amp; Company and Battleworks. At 8 p.m., Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, www.symphonyspace.org; $10. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>ANDREA DEL CONTE DANZA ESPANA (Thursday) This program of flamenco dance will feature the dancer Marco De Ana and the fusion band Gazpacho Andalú. (Through Jan. 28.) At 8 p.m., Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, (212) 334-7479, joyce.org; $28; $25 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CHEZ BUSHWICK: 'AMBUSH: A CURE FOR APAP' (Tomorrow) Bless the Bushwickites for this shrug at the phenomenon of the Association of Performing Arts Presenters, which brings dance producers to New York City en masse to assess the talent during a hectic few days -- frustrating to some dance artists -- of conferences and performing. Contributors to the Bushwick program are Matthew Barney, Jonah Bokaer, Foofwa d'Imobilité, Sam Kim, Jennifer Lacey, Antonietta Vicario and Jeremy Wade. At 8 p.m., Brooklyn Fire Proof, 119 Ingraham Street, Brooklyn, (718) 418-4405, www.bam.org/events; $5. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* DIAVOLO (Tomorrow) This Los Angeles-based multimedia company performs ingenious trompe l'oeil spectacles that seamlessly combine dance, gymnastics and cinematic images. Is that a real or a filmed dog racing across the stage? At 8 p.m., Brooklyn Center for the Performing Arts at Brooklyn College, one block from the junction of Flatbush and Nostrand Avenues, Flatbush, (718) 951-4500, brooklyncenteronline.org; $15 to $25. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* JAPANESE CONTEMPORARY DANCE SHOWCASE (Tonight through Sunday) If it's January in New York, it's time for Japanese dance. For this event's 10th anniversary, the Japan Society has relocated to the Joyce. But the eclectic, pop-influenced sampler should be as strange and beguiling as ever. Two programs feature work by Pappa Tarahumara, Kim Itoh &amp; the Glorious Future, Leni-Basso and Noism07. Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 2 and 7:30 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800; $30; $23 for members. (Claudia La Rocco)</p>
        <p>* LOWER LIGHTS COLLECTIVE (Tonight and tomorrow night) Members of this multimedia group have worked with some pretty impressive people in dance. And how can you go wrong with a company that describes its collaborative process as ignoring one another while allowing for the subtle influence of what is seen out of the corner of the eye? In its new ''CRAM,'' the group will pour dance; a ''live horror film''; sound and noise installations; a ''living sculpture'' using potatoes as percussion; and an orchestra of instruments made from architectural salvage into every cranny of this space. At 8, Chocolate Factory, 5-49 49th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (212) 352-3101, chocolatefactorytheater.org; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* SUSAN MARSHALL &amp; COMPANY (Monday, Tuesday and Thursday) Ms. Marshall returns with her Bessie Award-winning ''Cloudless,'' a suite of brief distilled dances. (Through Feb. 3.) At 7:30 p.m., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077, dtw.org; $25. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* MONEY MATTERS (Thursday) Sure does, and it matters a lot that Dixon Place raises funds for a much-needed home on Chrystie Street. Performers in this benefit include Souloworks and Gerald Casel and Jessy Smith. At 7:30 p.m., University Settlement, 184 Eldridge Street, Lower East Side, (212) 219-0736; $10 or more. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* MARK MORRIS DANCE GROUP (Tonight, tomorrow, and Tuesday through Thursday) Welcome 2007 a little late with a celebratory program of dances by Mr. Morris that includes the premiere of ''Italian Concerto,'' set to Bach, and ''The Argument,'' ''Sang-Froid'' and ''Love Song Waltzes.'' (Through Jan. 27.) At 7:30 p.m. (the MMDG Music Ensemble performs tonight at 10), Mark Morris Dance Center, 3 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place (across the street from the Brooklyn Academy of Music), Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (212) 352-3101, mmdg.org; sold out. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* NEW YORK CITY BALLET (Tonight through Sunday, and Tuesday through Thursday) The company will present the first of 10 themed programs, ''Stravinsky and Balanchine: An Eternal Partnership'' (''Agon,'' ''Monumentum/Movements,'' ''Duo Concertant'' and ''Symphony in Three Movements'') tonight, tomorrow afternoon and Thursday. Its second program, ''Tradition and Innovation'' (''Mozartiana,'' ''In Vento'' and Tchaikovsky's Piano Concerto No. 2), will follow on Tuesday. And ''Jerome Robbins: An American Icon'' (''2 &amp; 3 Part Inventions,'' ''A Suite of Dances,'' ''In Memory Of  '' and ''I'm Old Fashioned'') enters the repertory tomorrow night and is repeated on Sunday and Wednesday. (Through Feb. 25.) Tonight and Thursday night at 8, tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 3 p.m., Tuesday and Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 870-5570, wnycballet.com; $20 to 95. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK THEATER BALLET (Tonight and tomorrow night) Choreography by Benoit Swan-Pouffer, Alexandra Damiana, Matthew Neenan, Sallie Wilson and David Parker will be presented in this latest installment of the company's ''Dance on a Shoestring'' series. At 7, Dance Gallery, 30 East 31st Street, Manhattan, (212) 679-0401; $20. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>SANDRA PARKER AND SHELLEY LASICA (Tonight through Sunday) Ms. Parker, who is from Australia, will present a dance about the notions of travel, distance and proximity, and Ms. Lasica has contributed a piece with changing casts and choreography. Ms. Parker, tonight at 8, tomorrow at 7 p.m., Sunday at 4 p.m.; Ms. Lasica, tonight at 10, tomorrow at 5 and 9 p.m., Sunday at 2 p.m. Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, (212) 334-7479; free, but reservations necessary. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* PEAK PERFORMANCES AT MONTCLAIR: TRISHA BROWN (Tonight through Sunday) Ms. Brown, now 70, celebrates her influential career in modern dance with a new work, ''I love my robots,'' that suggests that she is as innovative as ever. A collaboration with the visual artist Kenjiro Okazaki and the performance artist Laurie Anderson, ''robots'' will feature what Mr. Okazaki describes as two interactive ''sculptural apparitions.'' The evening also includes performances of Ms. Brown's 1983 ''Set and Reset'' and her 2005 ''how long does the subject linger on the edge of the volume?'' Tonight and tomorrow night at 7:30, Sunday at 3 p.m., Alexander Kasser Theater, Montclair State University, 1 Normal Avenue, Montclair, N.J., (973) 655-5112, peakperfs.org; $35. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>LAURA PETERSON CHOREOGRAPHY (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ms. Peterson, who has danced with everyone from Risa Jaroslow to Poppo and the GoGo Boys, describes her new ''I Love Dan Flavin'' as a tongue-in-cheek futuristic dance with fluorescent light and pioneering techno music. (Through Jan. 27.) At 8, Dixon Place, 258 Bowery, between Houston and Prince Streets, Lower East Side, (212) 219-0736, Ext. 11, dixonplace.org; $15 or T.D.F. vouchers; $12 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>'TWO: DUETS' (Thursday) Chosen by Nicki Marshall and Helen Styring Tocci, five pairs of dance artists explore the intimacy and colliding energies of the duet form. (Through Jan. 27.) At 8 p.m., WOW Cafe Theater, 59 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 777-4280; $15; $12 for students and artists. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>MIGUEL ÁNGEL ZOTTO'S TANGO X 2 (Wednesday and Thursday) Mr. Zotto, who performed on Broadway in ''Tango Argentino,'' is bringing a company of 16 dancers and 8 musicians to perform ''Su Historia,'' a medley of tango dances and scores, and a tribute to Astor Piazzolla and his lyricist Horacio Ferrer. (Through Jan. 28.) At 8 p.m., City Center, 131 West 55th Street, Manhattan, (212) 581-1212, tangox2.com; $35 to $85. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art  Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* AMERICAN MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY: 'GOLD,' through Aug. 19. This astounding array of art, artifacts and natural samples -- larded with fascinating facts and tales -- ranges from prehistoric times to the present. Stops along the way include pre-Columbian empires, sunken treasure, and the moon landing. It turns out that gold comes from the earth in forms as beautiful as anything man has thought to do with it. Central Park West and 79th Street, (212) 769-5100, amnh.org. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>COOPER-HEWITT NATIONAL DESIGN MUSEUM: 'DESIGN LIFE NOW: NATIONAL DESIGN TRIENNIAL 2006,' through July 29. This ambitious show illuminates the volatile, contradictory and ever-expanding field of design, but fails to call it to order. It covers medical innovation, military hardware, frivolous reiterations of received ideas, sundry Web sites and magazines, haute couture, architecture and recycling. The show coalesces into deliberately orchestrated skirmishes between conflicting principles and entities: corporate and private, decorative and essential. 2 East 91st Street, (212) 849-8400, ndm.si.edu. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'SPANISH PAINTING FROM EL GRECO TO PICASSO, TIME, TRUTH, AND HISTORY' through March 28. This show is carried along on its sheer star power and optical finesse. There are dozens of Goyas and Velázquezes and Zurbaráns and El Grecos and Riberas and Dalís and Picassos, many famous, many not. I can't tell you how often I was stopped by a picture so good or unexpected that it made me do a double take. Velázquez's painting of a dwarf is alone worth crossing a continent to see. 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3500, guggenheim.org. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* THE METROPOLITAN MUSEUM OF ART: 'GLITTER AND DOOM: GERMAN PORTRAITS FROM THE 1920S,' through Feb. 19. The 100 paintings and drawings on display here are by 10 artists, including George Grosz, Christian Schad, and Karl Hubbuch, and most conspicuously the unrelentingly savage Otto Dix and his magnificent other, Max Beckmann. In their works the Weimar Republic's porous worlds reassemble; we look into the faces of museum directors and cabaret performers, society matrons and scarred war veterans, prostitutes and jaded aristocrats who were watching their world slide from one cataclysm to the next. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* THE MET: 'ONE OF A KIND: THE STUDIO CRAFT MOVEMENT,' through Sept. 3. Focusing on the postwar development of artist-craftsmen, this display of furniture, glass, ceramics, metalwork, jewelry and fiber includes funny, quirky, provocative and sometimes gorgeous things. Among its stars are a witty bust by the California funk ceramicist Robert Arneson (1920-92) portraying the mother of the 16th-century painter and printmaker Albrecht Durer; and Bonnie Seeman's fetching ceramic coffeepot and tray, whose mock cabbage leaves and rhubarb stalks evoke the genteel tradition of 18th-century British and continental china, but can also be read as human rather than vegetative tissue. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>* MORGAN LIBRARY &amp; MUSEUM: 'SAUL STEINBERG: ILLUMINATIONS,' through March 4. Saul Steinberg's famous New Yorker cover positioning Manhattan at the center of the world may be his best-known drawing, but he took on everything with visual puns, manic doodles, grandiloquent calligraphy and other inspired artifice. As this show of more than 100 drawings, collages and constructions goes on, Steinberg's progress is evident: from relatively simple cartoons like ''Feet on Chair'' (1946), in which a fellow reading a newspaper parks his feet on the seat of an ornate Victorian monstrosity, to complex comments on the state of the world, like ''Street War (Cadavre Exquisis)'' (about 1972-74), derived from news clips of postcolonial troubles in the Middle East and Africa. The flow of his work amazes. 225 Madison Avenue, at 36th Street, (212) 685-0008, morganlibrary.org. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'MANET AND THE EXECUTION OF MAXIMILIAN,' through Jan. 29. This gripping show reminds us of Modernism's mutinous, myth-scouring origins. And it does so by bringing one of art's great path-cutters, Edouard Manet, onto the scene, wry, politically infuriated and painting like Lucifer. There's not a lot of him here -- eight paintings, three on a single theme: the death by firing squad of the Austrian archduke Ferdinand Maximilian in Mexico in 1867. But it's enough. Manet's images, surrounded by a riveting selection of prints and photographs, are electrifying. (212) 708-9400, www.moma.org. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>* MUSEUM OF THE CITY OF NEW YORK: 'A CITY ON PAPER: SAUL STEINBERG'S NEW YORK,' through March 25. A very lively adjunct to the Morgan show, this display of some 40 drawings focuses on New York. An architect, Steinberg was particularly attracted to edifices like the Chrysler Building, which appears here looming over brownstones and in another incarnation, from a perspective directly below it, looking positively squat. New York people, in Steinberg's eyes, could be monuments, too. You may think you know Steinberg's work, but these shows make it new. 1220 Fifth Avenue at 103rd Street, (212) 534-1672, mcny.org. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>WHITNEY MUSEUM OF AMERICAN ART: 'KIKI SMITH: A GATHERING, 1980-2005,' through Feb. 11. Many things fly and float here: men and women, harpies and angels, birds and beasts, toadstools and stars. And some things fall to earth, or rather to the museum's black stone floors, maybe to rise again, maybe not. The whole show, a midcareer retrospective, suggests a Victorian fairy tale, its tone at once light, grievous and dreamlike. But fanciful as it is, Ms. Smith's art is also deeply, corporeally realistic. It wears moral and mortal seriousness on its sleeve, if not tattooed on its wrist. It is about life and death, the essential things. 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676, whitney.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>* ROBERT IRWIN: 'WHO'S AFRAID OF RED, YELLOW AND BLUE 3' In the past, Robert Irwin has paid homage to Joseph Albers. Now he makes a bow to a different kind of perceptual magician, Barnett Newman, turning Newman's 1966-70 paintings titled ''Who's Afraid of Red, Yellow and Blue'' into a kind of self-reflective architecture. Optical illusionism has long been Mr. Irwin's calling card, but here he has achieved it by bare-bones means, offering quieting visual fare for an overstimulated world. PaceWildenstein, 545 West 22nd Street, (212) 929-7000, pacewildenstein.com, through Feb. 3. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* JAPAN, INC. See this show of work by six painters who are either Japanese or inspired by Japanese culture primarily for Iona Rozeal Brown's dynamic new canvas ''King Kata.'' Through sharpened color and scale and by taking more liberties with her sources, Ms. Brown has markedly increased the visual punch of her characteristic kimono-and-cornrows cross-cultural fusion of cartoons, Japanese woodblock actor prints and gangsta chic. Her contribution underscores the vacuousness of much contemporary realist painting. Kravets Wehby, 521 West 21st Street, (212) 352-2238, through Feb. 17. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Other Galleries</p>
        <p>* 'THE CONSTANT POSSIBILITY OF ERASURE,' through Jan. 29. Organized by Donna Harkavy and Gracie Mansion, this excellent group show is at once witty and elegaic, exploring transience as an existential reality and as a conceptual ploy in late-20th-century art. Robert Rauschenberg's 1953 ''Erased De Kooning'' is an important reference point, present through Mike Bidlo's painstaking recreation. Joseph Beuys, Gary Simmons and Christian Xarec all have chalk pieces on blackboards, while Allan Kaprow preferred drawing, and simultaneously erasing, chalk pictures on the sidewalks or streets. Joanne Stamerra Hendricks uses erasers as a medium, and Jim Dingilian uses smoke. Dorsky Gallery Curatorial Projects, 11-03 45th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 937-6317. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* OLIVER HALSMAN ROSENBERG: 'DADA FOR GRANDMA,' through Jan. 28. Mr. Rosenberg conceived this show of a dozen lovely, small gouache paintings with references to the zodiac, the Kabala and Egyptian and Hindu cosmology as a tribute to his grandmother Yvonne Halsman who died last year. She was the wife of the Dada photographer Phillipe Halsman, and Dada zaniness has its part in the show. The artist has turned the paintings into an ingeniously low-tech ''prayer wheel'' set into motion by the visitor pedaling his grandmother's exercise bicycle. Mr. Rosenberg, a founder of the alternative space Triple Base in San Francisco who is, with Clint Taniguchi, half of the collaborative Crust &amp; Dirt, has other drawings in a box at Triple Candie, worth a look. Little Cakes, 625 East Sixth Street, Apt. 1B, East Village, (646) 342-1056. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'ANNIE LEIBOVITZ: A PHOTOGRAPHER'S LIFE, 1990-2005,' With photographs of her close-knit family and her companion, Susan Sontag; bits of photojournalism; and a pretentious foray into landscape photography, this large exhibition tells you more about Ms. Leibovitz than you probably want to know. Not surprisingly, her celebrity portraits are strongest, and at their best in a re-creation of the large pin-up boards on which she plotted the lavish book that accompanies the show. It reduces these often vivid portrayals to the size of their natural, magazine habitat and allows the viewer to skim for the good ones, as if turning pages. Brooklyn Museum, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, Brooklyn, (718) 638-5000; closes on Sunday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* SOLOMON R. GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'LUCIO FONTANA: VENICE/NEW YORK' If the Italian artist Lucio Fontana (1899-1968) was dazzled by Venice, he was positively awestruck by New York, which he first visited in 1961. For each city he created a group of works that he felt expressed its individual spirit. For Venice, a group of richly sensual oil paintings, with his signature slashes and punctures, sometimes with bits of colored glass scattered over them. For New York he chose shiny metal surfaces that he artfully cut, slashed and pierced to give a semblance of the city's wired energy and architectural vivacity. The two groups are united for the first time in this show, and well attended by works and photographs of works that trace from 1949 the career of an artist seeking to transcend the boundaries of his era. 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3500, guggenheim.org; closes on Sunday. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* THE MET: 'BRUSH AND INK: THE CHINESE ART OF WRITING' If painting and writing can be seen as modes of thinking, and they can, then this exhibition is as much a brainstorming session as an art exhibition, crackling with ideas and arguments every step of the way. It is also a sequence of moods, with impassioned voices calling out from the 80 scrolls and inscribed fans that line the galleries, which include colossal examples of contemporary 21st-century art that both depart from and preserve a tradition, (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org, closes on Sunday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>EL MUSEO DEL BARRIO: 'MERENGUE: VISUAL RHYTHMS' AND 'THIS SKIN I'M IN: CONTEMPORARY DOMINICAN ART FROM EL MUSEO DEL BARRIO'S PERMANENT COLLECTION,' Although ''Merengue,'' the larger of the two shows at El Museo, is made up almost entirely of paintings, it is about music, namely the national popular music of the Dominican Republic. Most of the 40 or so pictures, dating from the 1930s to the 1990s, document the music being performed or danced to; a few seem to be formal responses to its percussive beat. In a second, smaller show, merengue's vaunted joie de vivre gets some critical prodding from artists of Dominican descent living in New York. El Museo Del Barrio, 1230 Fifth Avenue, at 104th Street, East Harlem, (212) 831-7272, elmuseo.org; closes on Sunday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>P.S. 1 CONTEMPORARY ART CENTER: 'ALTERED, STITCHED AND GATHERED' Art by users might be the subtitle here, given that the show's 26 artists operate in the capacious gap between modernist assemblage and postmodern appropriation. Everything from e-mail messages to Wal-Mart plastic hangers and the movie ''Rambo'' are reused, often to comment on history, consumerism and war. Earlier efforts by Yoko Ono, Ben Vautier and Jaques Villeglé provide background. 22-25 Jackson Avenue, at 46th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 784-2084, ps1.org, closes on Tuesday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* THE WHITNEY MUSEUM OF AMERICAN ART: 'ALBERS AND MOHOLY-NAGY: FROM THE BAUHAUS TO THE NEW WORLD' This vigorously multimedia show traces the trajectories of two Modernist pioneers who overlapped as teachers at the Bauhaus in the 1920s and went on, separately, to influence postwar art and design in the United States. Ranging through painting, sculpture, film, design, prints and commercial art, it clarifies the Bauhaus debt to Russian Constructivism and includes works that presage the ''specific objects'' of the 1960s. Given the peregrinations of young artists among multiple art media, the show could not be more pertinent. 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676, whitney.org; closes on Sunday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Correction:  January 30, 2007, Tuesday  A classical music entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on Jan. 19 misstated the history of the performance in New York of ''Il Signor Bruschino,'' by Rossini, which the Gotham Chamber Orchestra is performing through Saturday. The Gotham Chamber Orchestra's production is the first professional staging of the work in New York since 1933, not the first staging since then. (The error was repeated in a Week Ahead entry in Arts &amp; Leisure on Jan. 21, in the Listings pages of Weekend on Friday and in a review of a performance on Saturday.)</p>
        <p>Correction:  February 1, 2007, Thursday  A classical music entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on Jan. 19 misstated the history of the performance in New York of ''Il Signor Bruschino,'' by Rossini, which is being performed in New York through Saturday. The current production is the first professional staging of the work in New York since 1933, not the first staging since then. (The error was repeated in a Week Ahead entry in Arts &amp; Leisure on Jan. 21, in the Listings pages of Weekend on Friday and in a review of a performance on Saturday.) A correction in this space on Tuesday misstated the name of the group that is currently presenting the work, at the Abrons Arts Center on the Lower East Side. It is the Gotham Chamber Opera, not Orchestra.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: January 30, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A classical music entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on Jan. 19 misstated the history of the performance in New York of ''Il Signor Bruschino,'' by Rossini, which the Gotham Chamber Orchestra is performing through Saturday. The Gotham Chamber Orchestra's production is the first professional staging of the work in New York since 1933, not the first staging since then. (The error was repeated in a Week Ahead entry in Arts &amp; Leisure on Jan. 21, in the Listings pages of Weekend on Friday and in a review of a performance on Saturday.)</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>Correction: February 1, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>A classical music entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on Jan. 19 misstated the history of the performance in New York of ''Il Signor Bruschino,'' by Rossini, which is being performed in New York through Saturday. The current production is the first professional staging of the work in New York since 1933, not the first staging since then. (The error was repeated in a Week Ahead entry in Arts &amp; Leisure on Jan. 21, in the Listings pages of Weekend on Friday and in a review of a performance on Saturday.) A correction in this space on Tuesday misstated the name of the group that is currently presenting the work, at the Abrons Arts Center on the Lower East Side. It is the Gotham Chamber Opera, not Orchestra.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
