<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After 20 Seasons in the N.F.L., Testaverde Has a Shot at Reaching His First Super Bowl</title>
    <meta content="19playoffs-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1819961"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL: ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New England Patriots</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indianapolis Colts</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Clifton</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Testaverde, Vinny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Indianapolis Colts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New England Patriots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806EEDC1E30F93AA25752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="724" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After 20 Seasons in the N.F.L., Testaverde Has a Shot at Reaching His First Super Bowl</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
      <dateline>FOXBOROUGH, Mass., Jan. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New England Patriots and backup quarterback Vinny Testaverde prepare to face Indianapolis Colts in playoffs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If the New England Patriots beat the Indianapolis Colts and advance to the Super Bowl, it will be a milestone for their 43-year-old backup quarterback, Vinny Testaverde, who has never reached the Super Bowl in 20 N.F.L. seasons.</p>
        <p>''Every year I watch it, I think, 'Got away from me again,' '' Testaverde said. ''Hopefully, this year will be a little different.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If the New England Patriots beat the Indianapolis Colts and advance to the Super Bowl, it will be a milestone for their 43-year-old backup quarterback, Vinny Testaverde, who has never reached the Super Bowl in 20 N.F.L. seasons.</p>
        <p>''Every year I watch it, I think, 'Got away from me again,' '' Testaverde said. ''Hopefully, this year will be a little different.''</p>
        <p>The chance to win the Super Bowl, and another chance to play for Bill Belichick, lured Testaverde out of a brief retirement when he signed with the Patriots on Nov. 14 as a backup to Tom Brady. Testaverde's main role is to offer advice and encouragement as a stable presence in a locker room already loaded with experience.</p>
        <p>The quarterback duel between Brady and Peyton Manning will be a dominant theme during Sunday's American Football Conference championship game, and Brady has the upper hand, with three Super Bowl titles and two playoff victories over Manning.</p>
        <p>Because of those losses, and his failure to reach the Super Bowl, Manning has been targeted for criticism despite a brilliant career. But Testaverde finds it hard to fathom that Manning does not have the makeup to lead a team to a championship,</p>
        <p>''I don't know Peyton personally as well as I do Tom, but I think from what I've seen, he has a lot of the same instincts and ability as Tom does,'' Testaverde said. ''He's obviously one of the best. A lot of people don't give him as much credit as he deserves, because he hasn't won the big game yet. It's more than one player when it comes to winning in this sport. A guy as good as he is, sooner or later, he's going to get one, he's going to get a ring.''</p>
        <p>Though Testaverde barely played this season, a personal high point occurred Dec. 31, when he threw a touchdown pass to Troy Brown during the Patriots' 40-23 victory over Tennessee. The pass was completed with less than two minutes left in the game, and some Titans were not happy. But Belichick wanted Testaverde to become the first N.F.L. player to throw touchdown passes in 20 consecutive seasons, and Testaverde appreciated the opportunity.</p>
        <p>''I didn't expect to go in the game at that point, and then when I did, I really didn't think we were going to be throwing the football,'' Testaverde said. ''That situation shows that he does have a sense of history. He lets the team know the accomplishments of certain guys, because guys are proud to be a part of it, too.''</p>
        <p>Even if the Patriots win the Super Bowl, Testaverde did not guarantee that he would retire -- again.</p>
        <p>''This is what I love to do,'' he said. ''I can't think of anything better, and this is a great situation.''</p>
        <p>FOUR PATRIOTS ARE AILING -- At least four Patriots had flu symptoms Thursday, three days before New England takes on Indianapolis in the A.F.C. championship game.</p>
        <p>Receiver Troy Brown, linebacker Tedy Bruschi, offensive tackle Ryan O'Callaghan and defensive tackle Mike Wright were ailing, but all were expected to be available for Sunday's game.</p>
        <p>The hard-hitting safety Rodney Harrison, one of New England's key defensive players, was on the field at the beginning of Thursday's practice, although he missed the previous two playoff games with a knee injury. His status for Sunday was uncertain. Only the beginning of practice was open to the news media, so it was not known how much Harrison participated.</p>
        <p>VICK'S WATER BOTTLE SEIZED -- Atlanta Falcons quarterback Michael Vick reluctantly surrendered a water bottle that smelled like marijuana and contained a substance in a hidden compartment to security at Miami International Airport, the Miami police said Thursday.</p>
        <p>Vick was not arrested and was allowed to board a flight that landed in Atlanta Wednesday morning.</p>
        <p>The police said Thursday that it could be weeks before a decision is made on whether to file charges against Vick, a three-time Pro Bowl player, who this season became the first quarterback in N.F.L. history to rush for 1,000 yards.</p>
        <p>The N.F.L.'s substance abuse policy states any team can decide that a player's ''behavior, including but not limited to an arrest,'' can warrant a physical exam from its medical director. A league spokesman, Greg Aiello, said that no decision had been made in Vick's case. (AP)</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL: ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
