<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LIVING HERE | Pied-à-terres; Small but Sufficient</title>
    <meta content="19live" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1819912"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Charleston (Sc)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gundrum-Cooper, Wyndi</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gunderson, Amy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Havens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Living Here</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/South Carolina/Charleston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/South Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E6DC1E30F93AA25752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="920" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LIVING HERE | Pied-à-terres; Small but Sufficient</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">As told to Amy Gunderson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gunderson, Amy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Wyndi Gundrum-Cooper, who comments on her studio condominium in Charleston, SC; photos and brief descriptions of other pied-a-terres available around country (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHO -- Wyndi Gundrum-Cooper, 47, a real estate agent from Ocean Isle Beach, N.C.  WHAT -- Studio condominium  WHERE -- Charleston, S.C.</p>
        <p>I've been visiting Charleston for 15 years, I even honeymooned here, and it's a place where I've always wanted to own a home. I looked for years, but of course the closer I got to the city center, the higher the cost. I discovered this little gem about a year ago. It's 320 square feet with a 100-square-foot courtyard. When I bought it, it needed work. I redid the bathroom, since the only thing holding it up was the tile, and turned the full kitchen into a kitchenette.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHO -- Wyndi Gundrum-Cooper, 47, a real estate agent from Ocean Isle Beach, N.C.  WHAT -- Studio condominium  WHERE -- Charleston, S.C.</p>
        <p>I've been visiting Charleston for 15 years, I even honeymooned here, and it's a place where I've always wanted to own a home. I looked for years, but of course the closer I got to the city center, the higher the cost. I discovered this little gem about a year ago. It's 320 square feet with a 100-square-foot courtyard. When I bought it, it needed work. I redid the bathroom, since the only thing holding it up was the tile, and turned the full kitchen into a kitchenette.</p>
        <p>The biggest thing in the apartment is the fireplace. It's 84 inches, while the kitchenette is only 54 inches across. But a big fireplace is part of the historic nature of this 200-year-old building. It's only two rooms but proved to be the hardest two rooms I've ever had to decorate. Though it's the smallest unit in the building, I wouldn't think about giving up my courtyard for a bigger space.</p>
        <p>I live at the beach, so when I want to get away, I come here. We're two and a half hours away and make it here about twice a month. Generally my husband, Ron Cooper, and I will arrive late on a Friday night. We park the car out front and don't move it again until we leave at the end of the weekend. The condo is right on Queen Street, so we can walk to shopping on King Street and to restaurants. Charleston has a growing gallery district, and we are right in the heart of it. But when I first arrive, I just love to spend time in our home.</p>
        <p>I never say I have a place in Charleston. I don't want people to think that I have a mansion in the city or one of the newer, grand apartments, so instead, I always say that I have ''a space'' in Charleston.</p>
        <p>As told to Amy Gunderson</p>
        <p>Information on properties were supplied by the owners or the listing companies</p>
        <p>WHERE -- San Francisco  WHAT -- 1-bedroom condominium  HOW MUCH -- $549,000</p>
        <p>Built in 2001, this Pacific Heights condo is 500 square feet and has Brazilian cherry wood floors, cherry cabinets and built-in bookcases that separate the living area from the open bedroom. There are stainless-steel appliances, granite counters, a washer and dryer, one bathroom and one parking space. The building is a long walk or a short drive from the Fisherman's Wharf area. Monthly fees are $481. Agents: Kevin Kearney and Brendon Kearney, Coldwell Banker Northern California, (415) 338-0209; www.kearneyandkearney.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Washington  WHAT -- 1-bedroom condominium  HOW MUCH -- $350,000</p>
        <p>This first-floor, 510-square-foot condo is in a renovated 12-unit building that dates to 1910. The unit has stainless-steel appliances, bamboo floors, a private patio and one bathroom. It is in the Capitol Hill neighborhood, within walking distance of the Capitol, the Mall and the Metro. Monthly fees are $226. Agent: Federico P. Glucksmann, Coldwell Banker Residential Brokerage, (202) 746-9336; www.cbmove.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Boston  WHAT -- Studio condominium  HOW MUCH -- $369,000</p>
        <p>This 553-square-foot condo is on Commercial Street adjacent to the waterfront and the North End neighborhood. It is within walking distance of Faneuil Hall. The unit has harbor views, 10-foot ceilings, hardwood floors, one bathroom, a full kitchen and a washer and dryer. It is on the seventh floor in a 105-unit complex that was converted to condos in 1984. The complex has a roof deck. Monthly fees are $357. Parking is available for $350 a month. Agent: Carmela Laurella, Otis &amp; Ahearn, (617) 227-6070, www.carmelalaurella.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- New York  WHAT -- 1-bedroom condominium  HOW MUCH -- $725,000</p>
        <p>A half-block from Carnegie Hall and a short walk from Central Park, this Midtown condo is 501 square feet, with south-facing windows on the 46th floor offering expansive views of Manhattan. It has hardwood floors, stainless-steel appliances, one bathroom and a dressing area. The unit has central air-conditioning, and the building has a doorman, a laundry room, a gym, a swimming pool, a conference room and a roof deck. Parking is available. Monthly fees are $385. Agent: Milena Miglietta, Bellmarc, (212) 252-1900; www.bellmarc.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Portland, Ore.  WHAT -- 1-bedroom condominium  HOW MUCH -- $315,000</p>
        <p>This 778-square-foot, sixth-floor loft is in Portland's Pearl District, a hub of art galleries, restaurants and shops. The building dates back to 1910 and was formerly a warehouse. The loft has a separate bedroom space, a kitchen with cherry cabinets and slate countertops, one bathroom and covered parking. The unit overlooks a landscaped open-air atrium that has a fountain and benches. Monthly fees are $181. Agents: Beverly and Doug Moser, Windermere Cronin &amp; Caplan Realty Group, (503) 789-5417; www.beverlymoser.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Seattle  WHAT -- 1-bedroom condominium  HOW MUCH -- $325,000</p>
        <p>This 16th-floor condo is a block from the Seattle Art Museum and a few blocks from the Seattle waterfront and shopping for produce, fish and other goods at Pike Place Market. It is also close to Benaroya Hall, home to the Seattle Symphony. The unit is 510 square feet and has one bathroom, city views and one parking space. The building has an indoor swimming pool, a hot tub, a sauna, a fitness center and a business center. Monthly fees are $303. Agent: Mark Anderson, John L. Scott Real Estate, (206) 931-9807; www.mark-anderson.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
