<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SPARE TIMES | JAN. 19 - JAN. 25</title>
    <meta content="19spar" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/19/arts/19spar.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1819797"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE4D61130F93AA25752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2141" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SPARE TIMES | JAN. 19 - JAN. 25</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Spare Times</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Around Town</p>
        <p>Museums and Sites</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY, Central Park West and 79th Street. Through Aug. 19, ''Gold,'' with coins, jewelry and other artifacts. Sunday, 2 to 4 p.m., ''Living in America: The Gold Rush,'' the second of three events in conjunction with the ''Gold'' exhibition, featuring performances by the Tagish Nation Singers and Dancers and Paseo Taino: Travesia Taina, a Puerto Rican music ensemble; a screening of the film ''Keish: The Real Story of the Yukon Gold Rush''; and a lecture by Hans Koning, the author of a book about Christopher Columbus and his travels in pursuit of gold. Through Feb. 18, ''Yellowstone to Yukon,'' an exhibition of more than 40 photographs by 11 photographers documenting the animals, vegetation and geology of the regions affected by one of the world's largest wildlife conservation initiatives. Through May 28, ''The Butterfly Conservatory: Tropical Butterflies Alive in Winter,'' a display with hundreds of butterflies in a re-creation of their natural habitat. In the Imax theater, ''Roving Mars,'' a film about NASA's Mars Rover. Timed tickets to ''Gold'' and ''The Butterfly Conservatory,'' which include museum admission, are $21; $16 for students and 60+; $12 for 12 and younger. Imax tickets, which include museum admission, are $21; $16 for students and 60+; $12 for children under 12. Suggested museum admission: $14; $10.50 for students and 60+; children, $8. Combination tickets, including museum and Rose Center admission and the Hayden Planetarium space show (''Cosmic Collisions''): $22; $16.50 for students and 60+; $13 for 12 and younger; under 2, free; admission that includes all activities: $30; $23 for students and 60+; $19 for 12 and younger. Museum hours: daily, 10 a.m. to 5:45 p.m. (to 8:45 p.m. on Fridays). (212) 769-5100 or (212) 769-5200; amnh.org.</p>
        <p>HISTORIC RICHMOND TOWN, Staten Island Historical Society, 441 Clarke Avenue, Richmond Town. Tomorrow night at 7:30 and 9, the first in the Tavern Concert series, featuring the group String Fever; $15 ($12 for members); a lecture about tavern culture by Angelo T. Angelis, a history professor, will precede the concert at 6 p.m.; $5 ($4 for students and 62+). Through April 1, ''Out of Fire and Valor: Staten Island War Memorials,'' photographs by Cal Snyder, a Marine Corps veteran. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. $5; $4 for 62+; $3.50 for students and 5 to 17; free for children under 5 and members; (718) 351-1611.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF THE CITY OF NEW YORK, Fifth Avenue at 103rd Street. Through Jan. 28, ''It's in the Bag,'' more than 100 purses from the museum's costume collection, some dating to the 18th century. Wednesday at 7 p.m., a panel discussion on the music of Harlem over the last 30 years with scholars, musicians, and arts and community activists, and a performance by the group TriHarLenium; $9; $5 for members, students and 62+. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Suggested admission: $9; $5 for students and 62+; free for children under 12; $20 for families; free on Sundays, 10 a.m. to noon. (212) 534-1672, mcny.org.</p>
        <p>NEW-YORK HISTORICAL SOCIETY, 2 West 77th Street, Manhattan. Tuesday at 6:30 p.m., a talk with Peter Vallone Sr., author of ''Learning to Govern: My Life in New York Politics, From Hell Gate to City Hall''; $15; $10 for students, educators and 65+; $8 for members. Thursday at 6:30 p.m., a discussion with the author E. L. Doctorow; $18; $12 for students, educators and 65+; $10 for members. Through Sept. 3, ''New York Divided: Slavery and the Civil War,'' a display of historical documents, photographs, political cartoons and other items. Through July 1, ''Elegy in the Dust: Sep. 11 and the Chelsea Jeans Memorial,'' a glass-encased time capsule of items from that retail store at the time of the terrorist attacks of 9/11, along with photographs from the society's collection that document events that day. Through Feb. 25, ''Nature and the American Vision: The Hudson River School at the New-York Historical Society,'' an exhibition of 100 paintings and watercolors from the society's permanent collection, including works by Thomas Cole, Frederic Edwin Church and Jasper Francis Cropsey. Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; to 8 p.m. on Fridays. $10; $7 for educators and 65+; $6 for students; free for those under 12. (212) 873-3400; nyhistory.org.</p>
        <p>Gardens</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN BOTANIC GARDEN, 1000 Washington Avenue, Crown Heights. Beginning tomorrow and running through Feb. 25, the 2007 Student and Teacher Art Exhibition and Sale, featuring artwork in all media. Tuesday, 9 a.m. to 4 p.m., the 11th Annual Plant-O-Rama, with unusual varieties for sale as well as lectures and panel discussions. Tuesdays through Fridays, 8 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Saturdays, Sundays and holidays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m. $5; $3 for students and 65+; free for children under 16. Through Feb. 28, free admission Tuesdays through Fridays and Saturdays from 10 a.m. to noon. (718) 623-7200; bbg.org.</p>
        <p>WAVE HILL, Independence Avenue and West 249th Street, Riverdale, the Bronx. Sunday at 2 p.m., a performance classical and contemporary works by the Children's Orchestra Society; $18; members, $15. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 9 a.m. to 4:30 p.m. Free admission through February. (718) 549-3200.</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>'FLOODWALL,' World Financial Center, Liberty Street Bridge, Lower Manhattan. An art installation reflective of post-Katrina New Orleans, by Jana Napoli. Daily, 7 a.m. to 11 p.m. through Feb. 9. Free. (212) 945-0505; worldfinancialcenter.com.</p>
        <p>'I'LL TAKE MANHATTAN,' Manhattan borough president's office, 1 Centre Street, 19th floor, Lower Manhattan. Through January, a photography display featuring works by members of the Pictorial Photographers of America. Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. Free; photo ID required; ppa-photoclub.org.</p>
        <p>'MAESTRO'S SECRET MUSIC; THE ARTWORK COLLECTED BY ARTURO TOSCANINI,' Avery Fisher Hall, Grand Promenade and First Tier, Lincoln Center. Commemorates the 50th anniversary of his death. Open to the public Thursdays, 2 to 6 p.m. and during concerts for Philharmonic ticket holders. Through March 31. (212) 875-5930.</p>
        <p>SOUTH STREET SEAPORT MUSEUM, 12 Fulton Street, Lower Manhattan. Today, 5 to 9 p.m., ''Free Fridays!: Maritime Crafts &amp; Skills,'' free admission to gallery exhibits and workshops. (212) 748-8600.</p>
        <p>WATSON ADVENTURES Tomorrow at 2 p.m., ''MoMA Mania Scavenger Hunt,'' through the galleries of the Museum of Modern Art. $38, including admission. Reservations and meeting place: (877) 946-4868.</p>
        <p>MUSIC SCHOOL OPEN HOUSE, 92nd Street Y, 1395 Lexington Avenue. Sunday, 1 to 4 p.m., classroom tours and demonstrations by faculty members. Free. (212) 415-5500.</p>
        <p>THIRD ANNUAL BROOKLYN ISRAEL FILM FESTIVAL, Kane Street Synagogue, 236 Kane Street, Cobble Hill, Brooklyn. Thursday night at 8, opening of the three-day festival with the documentary ''The Ashkenazi,'' followed by a post-screening discussion. $25 in advance for the series or $10 per screening at the door. (718) 875-1550.</p>
        <p>'HOT OFF THE PRESS': PRINTS OF 2006 FROM NEW YORK PRINTSHOPS, Grolier Club of New York, 47 East 60th Street, Manhattan. An exhibition that illustrates the collaboration of 50 artists with master printers in the area. Through Feb. 3. Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Free. (212) 838-6690.</p>
        <p>'GREENBELT NATURALLY,' Arsenal Gallery, Central Park, 830 Fifth Avenue, at 64th Street. Today and Monday through Wednesday, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m., photographs of the Staten Island Greenbelt, taken by New York City schoolchildren.</p>
        <p>Spoken Word</p>
        <p>'MARIO CUOMO: A LOOK BACK AND A LOOK FORWARD,' 92nd Street Y, Poetry Center, 1395 Lexington Avenue. Sunday night at 7:30, a talk with the former governor. $25. (212) 415-5500.</p>
        <p>'CONTEMPLATING THE BLACK DIASPORA,' Barnard College, Barnard Hall, Broadway and West 117th Street, Morningside Heights. Monday at 7 p.m., a discussion with Yvette Christiansë, poet and author of ''Unconfessed,'' and Saidiya Hartman, a scholar and author. Free. (212) 854-9850.</p>
        <p>SELECTED SHORTS: A CELEBRATION OF THE SHORT STORY, Symphony Space, Broadway and 95th Street. Wednesday night at 6:30, readings of stories from ''New Sudden Fiction,'' a new anthology, by the actors James Naughton, B. D. Wong and Marian Seldes; the host will be Isaiah Sheffer, artistic director of Symphony Space. $21 to $30. (212) 864-5400.</p>
        <p>'HIDDEN CHILD; AN EVENING WITH EVI BLAIKIE,' Hungarian Cultural Center, 447 Broadway, at Grand Street, SoHo. Thursday at 7 p.m., a discussion with Ms. Blaikie, author of ''Magda's Daughter: A Hidden Child's Journey Home,'' who escaped Nazi-occupied Paris as a child and spent her childhood in exile in Hungary. Free. (212) 750-4450.</p>
        <p>'FREEDOMLAND -- BEFORE CO-OP CITY, THE GRAND AMUSEMENT PARK IN THE BRONX,' Bartow-Pell Mansion, 895 Shore Road, Pelham Bay Park, the Bronx. Sunday at 4 p.m., a lecture by Thomas X. Casey, a collector of vintage postcards. Suggested donation, $8. Pre-registration requested, (718) 885-1461; bartowpellmansionmuseum.org.</p>
        <p>'KEEP THE ARTS IN WILLIAMSBURG,' Galapagos Art Space, 70 North Sixth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn. Tonight at 7, a symposium on the economic development and displacement of artists in the area with artists, arts administrators and elected officials; dance and comedy performances will follow. Free. galapagosartspace.com.</p>
        <p>INSTITUTE OF CLASSICAL ARCHITECTURE &amp; CLASSICAL AMERICA, 20 West 44th Street. Thursday at 7 p.m., a panel discussion about the architectural firm Carrère and Hastings, with the authors Mark Alan Hewitt, Kate Lemos, William Morrison and Charles D. Warren, who have written a two-volume set about the noted partnership. Also sponsored by the General Society of Mechanics and Tradesmen. $10; free for members of the Institute and Society. Reservations: (212) 730-9646, Ext. 109.</p>
        <p>Walking Tours</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS CLUB  Tomorrow at 10:30 a.m., an 11-mile walk along the beach and boardwalk in Queens, from 116th Street and Rockaway Park to Fort Tilden and Breezy Point; meeting place is at the token booth of the Rockaway Park/Beach 116th Street stop on the A train. (Participants should take the Rockaway Park shuttle train from the Broad Channel stop.) $3. (212) 242-5384.</p>
        <p>MUNICIPAL ART SOCIETY Tomorrow at 11 a.m., a free tour of waterfront development in Lower Manhattan, meeting at the top of the stairs in the Winter Garden at the World Financial Center. (212) 935-3960.</p>
        <p>'BETWEEN THE LIONS: THEN &amp; NOW,' Sunday at 11 a.m., a historical look at the main branch of New York Public Library and the land on which it was built, meeting on the southeast corner of Broadway and 41st Street. Sponsored by Bonnie's Lost New York Walks and Talks. $15. (212) 594-8039.</p>
        <p>BIG ONION WALKING TOURS Tomorrow at 1 p.m., ''SoHo and NoLIta,'' meeting on the southeast corner of Spring and Lafayette Streets. $15 each; $12 for 63+; $10 for students and New-York Historical Society members. (212) 439-1090.</p>
        <p>SHOREWALKERS Sunday at 11 a.m., a three-to-four mile walk from the World Trade Center to Brooklyn Heights via the Brooklyn Bridge, meeting in the lobby of the Millennium Hilton Hotel in Lower Manhattan. $3. (932) 724-2542. $3.</p>
        <p>STREET SMARTS N.Y. Tomorrow at 2 p.m., ''Dandies, Dudes and Shady Ladies'' visits lowlife haunts of old New York, for adults; meeting at the subway kiosk at Astor Place in the East Village. $10. (212) 969-8262. $10. (212) 969-8262.</p>
        <p>TIMELINE TOURING: 'A LIVING HISTORY TOUR OF THE LOWER EAST SIDE,' Sunday at 1:15 p.m. $38; $32 for children. Meeting place and reservations: (212) 209-3370 or timelinetouring.com.</p>
        <p>ADVENTURE ON A SHOESTRING Tomorrow at 2:30 p.m., ''Marilyn Monroe's Manhattan,'' stopping by her favorite nightclub and a movie location, meeting on the northeast corner of 57th Street and First Avenue. $5. (212) 265-2663.</p>
        <p>'MANSIONS, MILLIONS AND MAGNIFICENCE,' Sunday at 1 p.m., a walking tour of Fifth Avenue, meeting at the statue of General Sherman, Fifth Avenue and 59th Street. Sponsored by I'll Take Manhattan Tours. $15; (732) 270-5559.</p>
        <p>HARLEM, YOUR WAY! Sunday at 10:15 a.m., ''Experience the Beauty of Harlem Gospel'' combines a historical walk through the neighborhood with a stop at an art gallery and a gospel church service, meeting at 129 West 130th Street. $25. An optional meal follows. (212) 690-1687.</p>
        <p>CENTRAL PARK CONSERVANCY Free weekend tours of Central Park. Tomorrow at 11 a.m., ''Let the Games Begin: History of Sports in the Park,'' meeting at the Dairy, midpark at 65th Street. Sunday at 1 p.m., a ''Cross-Park Promenade'' meets at the statue of Samuel F. B. Morse, at Fifth Avenue and 72nd Street. centralparknyc.org.</p>
        <p>METRO TOUR SERVICE Today and tomorrow at 2 p.m., Brooklyn Heights, Fort Greene and Clinton Hill, Brooklyn. Sunday at 3 p.m., a gospel tour. Both meet in front of the Marriott Hotel, Adams and Tillary Streets, downtown Brooklyn. $25. (718) 789-0430.</p>
        <p>Recreation</p>
        <p>NEW YORK ROAD RUNNERS CLUB Sunday at 8:30 a.m., the Half-Marathon Grand Prix, a 13.1-mile run, in Central Park, beginning on the East Drive and 84th Street. Advance registration: $25; $17 for members; $13 for members 18 and younger and 62+. Race-day registration: $35; $25 for members; $15 for members 18 and younger and 62+. (212) 860-4455; nyrrc.org.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>AROUND TOWN.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Around Town</p>
        <p>Museums and Sites</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY, Central Park West and 79th Street. Through Aug. 19, ''Gold,'' with coins, jewelry and other artifacts. Sunday, 2 to 4 p.m., ''Living in America: The Gold Rush,'' the second of three events in conjunction with the ''Gold'' exhibition, featuring performances by the Tagish Nation Singers and Dancers and Paseo Taino: Travesia Taina, a Puerto Rican music ensemble; a screening of the film ''Keish: The Real Story of the Yukon Gold Rush''; and a lecture by Hans Koning, the author of a book about Christopher Columbus and his travels in pursuit of gold. Through Feb. 18, ''Yellowstone to Yukon,'' an exhibition of more than 40 photographs by 11 photographers documenting the animals, vegetation and geology of the regions affected by one of the world's largest wildlife conservation initiatives. Through May 28, ''The Butterfly Conservatory: Tropical Butterflies Alive in Winter,'' a display with hundreds of butterflies in a re-creation of their natural habitat. In the Imax theater, ''Roving Mars,'' a film about NASA's Mars Rover. Timed tickets to ''Gold'' and ''The Butterfly Conservatory,'' which include museum admission, are $21; $16 for students and 60+; $12 for 12 and younger. Imax tickets, which include museum admission, are $21; $16 for students and 60+; $12 for children under 12. Suggested museum admission: $14; $10.50 for students and 60+; children, $8. Combination tickets, including museum and Rose Center admission and the Hayden Planetarium space show (''Cosmic Collisions''): $22; $16.50 for students and 60+; $13 for 12 and younger; under 2, free; admission that includes all activities: $30; $23 for students and 60+; $19 for 12 and younger. Museum hours: daily, 10 a.m. to 5:45 p.m. (to 8:45 p.m. on Fridays). (212) 769-5100 or (212) 769-5200; amnh.org.</p>
        <p>HISTORIC RICHMOND TOWN, Staten Island Historical Society, 441 Clarke Avenue, Richmond Town. Tomorrow night at 7:30 and 9, the first in the Tavern Concert series, featuring the group String Fever; $15 ($12 for members); a lecture about tavern culture by Angelo T. Angelis, a history professor, will precede the concert at 6 p.m.; $5 ($4 for students and 62+). Through April 1, ''Out of Fire and Valor: Staten Island War Memorials,'' photographs by Cal Snyder, a Marine Corps veteran. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. $5; $4 for 62+; $3.50 for students and 5 to 17; free for children under 5 and members; (718) 351-1611.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF THE CITY OF NEW YORK, Fifth Avenue at 103rd Street. Through Jan. 28, ''It's in the Bag,'' more than 100 purses from the museum's costume collection, some dating to the 18th century. Wednesday at 7 p.m., a panel discussion on the music of Harlem over the last 30 years with scholars, musicians, and arts and community activists, and a performance by the group TriHarLenium; $9; $5 for members, students and 62+. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Suggested admission: $9; $5 for students and 62+; free for children under 12; $20 for families; free on Sundays, 10 a.m. to noon. (212) 534-1672, mcny.org.</p>
        <p>NEW-YORK HISTORICAL SOCIETY, 2 West 77th Street, Manhattan. Tuesday at 6:30 p.m., a talk with Peter Vallone Sr., author of ''Learning to Govern: My Life in New York Politics, From Hell Gate to City Hall''; $15; $10 for students, educators and 65+; $8 for members. Thursday at 6:30 p.m., a discussion with the author E. L. Doctorow; $18; $12 for students, educators and 65+; $10 for members. Through Sept. 3, ''New York Divided: Slavery and the Civil War,'' a display of historical documents, photographs, political cartoons and other items. Through July 1, ''Elegy in the Dust: Sep. 11 and the Chelsea Jeans Memorial,'' a glass-encased time capsule of items from that retail store at the time of the terrorist attacks of 9/11, along with photographs from the society's collection that document events that day. Through Feb. 25, ''Nature and the American Vision: The Hudson River School at the New-York Historical Society,'' an exhibition of 100 paintings and watercolors from the society's permanent collection, including works by Thomas Cole, Frederic Edwin Church and Jasper Francis Cropsey. Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; to 8 p.m. on Fridays. $10; $7 for educators and 65+; $6 for students; free for those under 12. (212) 873-3400; nyhistory.org.</p>
        <p>Gardens</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN BOTANIC GARDEN, 1000 Washington Avenue, Crown Heights. Beginning tomorrow and running through Feb. 25, the 2007 Student and Teacher Art Exhibition and Sale, featuring artwork in all media. Tuesday, 9 a.m. to 4 p.m., the 11th Annual Plant-O-Rama, with unusual varieties for sale as well as lectures and panel discussions. Tuesdays through Fridays, 8 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Saturdays, Sundays and holidays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m. $5; $3 for students and 65+; free for children under 16. Through Feb. 28, free admission Tuesdays through Fridays and Saturdays from 10 a.m. to noon. (718) 623-7200; bbg.org.</p>
        <p>WAVE HILL, Independence Avenue and West 249th Street, Riverdale, the Bronx. Sunday at 2 p.m., a performance classical and contemporary works by the Children's Orchestra Society; $18; members, $15. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 9 a.m. to 4:30 p.m. Free admission through February. (718) 549-3200.</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>'FLOODWALL,' World Financial Center, Liberty Street Bridge, Lower Manhattan. An art installation reflective of post-Katrina New Orleans, by Jana Napoli. Daily, 7 a.m. to 11 p.m. through Feb. 9. Free. (212) 945-0505; worldfinancialcenter.com.</p>
        <p>'I'LL TAKE MANHATTAN,' Manhattan borough president's office, 1 Centre Street, 19th floor, Lower Manhattan. Through January, a photography display featuring works by members of the Pictorial Photographers of America. Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. Free; photo ID required; ppa-photoclub.org.</p>
        <p>'MAESTRO'S SECRET MUSIC; THE ARTWORK COLLECTED BY ARTURO TOSCANINI,' Avery Fisher Hall, Grand Promenade and First Tier, Lincoln Center. Commemorates the 50th anniversary of his death. Open to the public Thursdays, 2 to 6 p.m. and during concerts for Philharmonic ticket holders. Through March 31. (212) 875-5930.</p>
        <p>SOUTH STREET SEAPORT MUSEUM, 12 Fulton Street, Lower Manhattan. Today, 5 to 9 p.m., ''Free Fridays!: Maritime Crafts &amp; Skills,'' free admission to gallery exhibits and workshops. (212) 748-8600.</p>
        <p>WATSON ADVENTURES Tomorrow at 2 p.m., ''MoMA Mania Scavenger Hunt,'' through the galleries of the Museum of Modern Art. $38, including admission. Reservations and meeting place: (877) 946-4868.</p>
        <p>MUSIC SCHOOL OPEN HOUSE, 92nd Street Y, 1395 Lexington Avenue. Sunday, 1 to 4 p.m., classroom tours and demonstrations by faculty members. Free. (212) 415-5500.</p>
        <p>THIRD ANNUAL BROOKLYN ISRAEL FILM FESTIVAL, Kane Street Synagogue, 236 Kane Street, Cobble Hill, Brooklyn. Thursday night at 8, opening of the three-day festival with the documentary ''The Ashkenazi,'' followed by a post-screening discussion. $25 in advance for the series or $10 per screening at the door. (718) 875-1550.</p>
        <p>'HOT OFF THE PRESS': PRINTS OF 2006 FROM NEW YORK PRINTSHOPS, Grolier Club of New York, 47 East 60th Street, Manhattan. An exhibition that illustrates the collaboration of 50 artists with master printers in the area. Through Feb. 3. Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Free. (212) 838-6690.</p>
        <p>'GREENBELT NATURALLY,' Arsenal Gallery, Central Park, 830 Fifth Avenue, at 64th Street. Today and Monday through Wednesday, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m., photographs of the Staten Island Greenbelt, taken by New York City schoolchildren.</p>
        <p>Spoken Word</p>
        <p>'MARIO CUOMO: A LOOK BACK AND A LOOK FORWARD,' 92nd Street Y, Poetry Center, 1395 Lexington Avenue. Sunday night at 7:30, a talk with the former governor. $25. (212) 415-5500.</p>
        <p>'CONTEMPLATING THE BLACK DIASPORA,' Barnard College, Barnard Hall, Broadway and West 117th Street, Morningside Heights. Monday at 7 p.m., a discussion with Yvette Christiansë, poet and author of ''Unconfessed,'' and Saidiya Hartman, a scholar and author. Free. (212) 854-9850.</p>
        <p>SELECTED SHORTS: A CELEBRATION OF THE SHORT STORY, Symphony Space, Broadway and 95th Street. Wednesday night at 6:30, readings of stories from ''New Sudden Fiction,'' a new anthology, by the actors James Naughton, B. D. Wong and Marian Seldes; the host will be Isaiah Sheffer, artistic director of Symphony Space. $21 to $30. (212) 864-5400.</p>
        <p>'HIDDEN CHILD; AN EVENING WITH EVI BLAIKIE,' Hungarian Cultural Center, 447 Broadway, at Grand Street, SoHo. Thursday at 7 p.m., a discussion with Ms. Blaikie, author of ''Magda's Daughter: A Hidden Child's Journey Home,'' who escaped Nazi-occupied Paris as a child and spent her childhood in exile in Hungary. Free. (212) 750-4450.</p>
        <p>'FREEDOMLAND -- BEFORE CO-OP CITY, THE GRAND AMUSEMENT PARK IN THE BRONX,' Bartow-Pell Mansion, 895 Shore Road, Pelham Bay Park, the Bronx. Sunday at 4 p.m., a lecture by Thomas X. Casey, a collector of vintage postcards. Suggested donation, $8. Pre-registration requested, (718) 885-1461; bartowpellmansionmuseum.org.</p>
        <p>'KEEP THE ARTS IN WILLIAMSBURG,' Galapagos Art Space, 70 North Sixth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn. Tonight at 7, a symposium on the economic development and displacement of artists in the area with artists, arts administrators and elected officials; dance and comedy performances will follow. Free. galapagosartspace.com.</p>
        <p>INSTITUTE OF CLASSICAL ARCHITECTURE &amp; CLASSICAL AMERICA, 20 West 44th Street. Thursday at 7 p.m., a panel discussion about the architectural firm Carrère and Hastings, with the authors Mark Alan Hewitt, Kate Lemos, William Morrison and Charles D. Warren, who have written a two-volume set about the noted partnership. Also sponsored by the General Society of Mechanics and Tradesmen. $10; free for members of the Institute and Society. Reservations: (212) 730-9646, Ext. 109.</p>
        <p>Walking Tours</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS CLUB  Tomorrow at 10:30 a.m., an 11-mile walk along the beach and boardwalk in Queens, from 116th Street and Rockaway Park to Fort Tilden and Breezy Point; meeting place is at the token booth of the Rockaway Park/Beach 116th Street stop on the A train. (Participants should take the Rockaway Park shuttle train from the Broad Channel stop.) $3. (212) 242-5384.</p>
        <p>MUNICIPAL ART SOCIETY Tomorrow at 11 a.m., a free tour of waterfront development in Lower Manhattan, meeting at the top of the stairs in the Winter Garden at the World Financial Center. (212) 935-3960.</p>
        <p>'BETWEEN THE LIONS: THEN &amp; NOW,' Sunday at 11 a.m., a historical look at the main branch of New York Public Library and the land on which it was built, meeting on the southeast corner of Broadway and 41st Street. Sponsored by Bonnie's Lost New York Walks and Talks. $15. (212) 594-8039.</p>
        <p>BIG ONION WALKING TOURS Tomorrow at 1 p.m., ''SoHo and NoLIta,'' meeting on the southeast corner of Spring and Lafayette Streets. $15 each; $12 for 63+; $10 for students and New-York Historical Society members. (212) 439-1090.</p>
        <p>SHOREWALKERS Sunday at 11 a.m., a three-to-four mile walk from the World Trade Center to Brooklyn Heights via the Brooklyn Bridge, meeting in the lobby of the Millennium Hilton Hotel in Lower Manhattan. $3. (932) 724-2542. $3.</p>
        <p>STREET SMARTS N.Y. Tomorrow at 2 p.m., ''Dandies, Dudes and Shady Ladies'' visits lowlife haunts of old New York, for adults; meeting at the subway kiosk at Astor Place in the East Village. $10. (212) 969-8262. $10. (212) 969-8262.</p>
        <p>TIMELINE TOURING: 'A LIVING HISTORY TOUR OF THE LOWER EAST SIDE,' Sunday at 1:15 p.m. $38; $32 for children. Meeting place and reservations: (212) 209-3370 or timelinetouring.com.</p>
        <p>ADVENTURE ON A SHOESTRING Tomorrow at 2:30 p.m., ''Marilyn Monroe's Manhattan,'' stopping by her favorite nightclub and a movie location, meeting on the northeast corner of 57th Street and First Avenue. $5. (212) 265-2663.</p>
        <p>'MANSIONS, MILLIONS AND MAGNIFICENCE,' Sunday at 1 p.m., a walking tour of Fifth Avenue, meeting at the statue of General Sherman, Fifth Avenue and 59th Street. Sponsored by I'll Take Manhattan Tours. $15; (732) 270-5559.</p>
        <p>HARLEM, YOUR WAY! Sunday at 10:15 a.m., ''Experience the Beauty of Harlem Gospel'' combines a historical walk through the neighborhood with a stop at an art gallery and a gospel church service, meeting at 129 West 130th Street. $25. An optional meal follows. (212) 690-1687.</p>
        <p>CENTRAL PARK CONSERVANCY Free weekend tours of Central Park. Tomorrow at 11 a.m., ''Let the Games Begin: History of Sports in the Park,'' meeting at the Dairy, midpark at 65th Street. Sunday at 1 p.m., a ''Cross-Park Promenade'' meets at the statue of Samuel F. B. Morse, at Fifth Avenue and 72nd Street. centralparknyc.org.</p>
        <p>METRO TOUR SERVICE Today and tomorrow at 2 p.m., Brooklyn Heights, Fort Greene and Clinton Hill, Brooklyn. Sunday at 3 p.m., a gospel tour. Both meet in front of the Marriott Hotel, Adams and Tillary Streets, downtown Brooklyn. $25. (718) 789-0430.</p>
        <p>Recreation</p>
        <p>NEW YORK ROAD RUNNERS CLUB Sunday at 8:30 a.m., the Half-Marathon Grand Prix, a 13.1-mile run, in Central Park, beginning on the East Drive and 84th Street. Advance registration: $25; $17 for members; $13 for members 18 and younger and 62+. Race-day registration: $35; $25 for members; $15 for members 18 and younger and 62+. (212) 860-4455; nyrrc.org.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
