<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PROPERTY VALUES: What You Get for ... $3.9 Million</title>
    <meta content="31GH-what" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1822871"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Property Values</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070131T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E7DD153FF932A05752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="458" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PROPERTY VALUES: What You Get for ... $3.9 Million</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA BAHNEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Portsmouth, R.I.</p>
        <p>WHAT: Five-bedroom house</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Portsmouth, R.I.</p>
        <p>WHAT: Five-bedroom house</p>
        <p>HOW MUCH: $3,995,000</p>
        <p>PER SQUARE FOOT: $644.35</p>
        <p>This 6,200-square-foot Cape Cod-style house was built in 2006 on the Narragansett Bay, with views of the water and the Newport Pell Bridge. About six miles from Newport, the house is in the Carnegie Abbey Club, which offers tennis courts, yacht slips, two restaurants, a clubhouse, swimming pools, a spa, a golf course and access to 10 club horses for riding. The house, called High Tide, has a 20-foot-high stone fireplace in the double-height great room and a professional-grade kitchen. There is a putting green just off the patio, which has a gas grill and fire pit. The house has six full baths, one half bath, three stone fireplaces and a two-car garage. The estimated taxes are $25,000 a year, the estimated homeowners' association fee $600 a month. The Carnegie Abbey Club charges a mandatory initiation fee. The house can be bought fully furnished for $4.395 million. Maureen Fraser, Carnegie Abbey Private Estates, (888) 373-9819; www.thecarnegieabbeyclub.com</p>
        <p>Edwards, Colo.</p>
        <p>WHAT: Five-bedroom house with guest house</p>
        <p>HOW MUCH: $3,950,000</p>
        <p>PER SQUARE FOOT: $569.82</p>
        <p>This 6,932-square-foot log home in the Vail Valley comes with 15 acres. It includes a barn, a horse stable, and guest or caretaker's house. The house is in Pilgrim Downs, a private gated subdivision with a residence ranch manager, private fishing pond, and horse trails with access to national forest land. It is also within 20 miles of skiing and golf in Vail or Beaver Creek. Built in 1991, the house has a double-height great room with a river-rock fireplace and log posts and beams. It has four full baths, one half bath, three fireplaces and a three-car garage. The one-bedroom, two-bath, two-story guest or caretaker's house has a two-car garage and a fireplace. The taxes are $11,336.30 a year, the homeowners' association fee $6,200 a year. At the closing, the owners will offer a $250,000 credit for remodeling. Doug Ketchum, Prudential Colorado Properties, (970) 926-8440, ext. 12; www.prudentialcoloradoproperties.com</p>
        <p>Napa, Calif.</p>
        <p>WHAT: Two-bedroom house with guest house</p>
        <p>HOW MUCH: $3,995,000</p>
        <p>PER SQUARE FOOT: $887.77</p>
        <p>This 20-acre estate, la Casa del Cielo, has views of Napa Valley vineyards and Yountville. The Mediterranean-style house was built in 1991, with the main living areas and the guest house adjacent to a wraparound deck providing mountain and valley views. A patio surrounds an infinity pool. The formal dining room opens to the living room. The house has two full baths, one half bath, four fireplaces, a wine cave with space for 478 bottles and a two-car garage. The guest house has two bedrooms, one bath and an art studio. Estimated taxes are $49,937 a year. Ginger Martin and Carol Sebastiani, Sotheby's International Realty, (707) 935-2277; www.sothebysrealty.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
