<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In a Yale Dining Hall, Independent Study at the Microwave</title>
    <meta content="31yale" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/31/dining/31yale.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1822706"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Yale University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Yale Daily News</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, Bryan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marks, Zach</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Microwaves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Microwaves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Yale University</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Yale Daily News</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070131T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E7D7143FF932A05752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1160" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In a Yale Dining Hall, Independent Study at the Microwave</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In a Yale Dining Hall, Independent Study at the Microwave</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRYAN MILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Miller, Bryan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Zach Marks, student at Yale University, uses microwave in dining hall and items from buffet to create gastronomic treats; he has gained some celebrity around campus for his culinary skill, whch he often shares with fellow students in column in Yale Daily News; sample of tips offered in his column; recipe; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS students streamed into a towering Gothic dining hall at Yale University last week, appraising the plats du jour on a cafeteria buffet, one of their classmates was concocting his own sauce from peanut butter and a dark liquid.</p>
        <p>''You have to be careful with the sesame oil,'' cautioned the student, Zach Marks, a self-described dining hall gastronome. ''Too much of this and the texture gets watery.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A monthly column in the Yale Daily News offers tips for gourmet cooking with items from the dining room buffet, a few condiments and a microwave oven.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS students streamed into a towering Gothic dining hall at Yale University last week, appraising the plats du jour on a cafeteria buffet, one of their classmates was concocting his own sauce from peanut butter and a dark liquid.</p>
        <p>''You have to be careful with the sesame oil,'' cautioned the student, Zach Marks, a self-described dining hall gastronome. ''Too much of this and the texture gets watery.''</p>
        <p>After mixing in some soy sauce, Mr. Marks, a sophomore from Philadelphia, reached for curry powder and swirled in a pinch, followed by a little dried ginger and dried coriander.</p>
        <p>''Hey Zach, what's that you're making tonight?'' asked Marvin Cunningham, a kitchen worker.</p>
        <p>''Appetizers of chicken satay, and some tikka masala,'' Mr. Marks replied, never diverting his eyes from the oeuvre in progress.</p>
        <p>''Ooohthat sounds good to me,'' Mr. Cunningham said with a grin.</p>
        <p>Mr. Marks transferred the peanut mixture to a microwave oven for about 30 seconds, ''until it bubbles and has a nice smooth texture.'' He wanted fresh limes, but they were not on the buffet that evening, so he settled for lemon to add a little bite to the sauce. (The spices were also a twist on his basic recipe.)</p>
        <p>Next stop: the giant steel milk dispenser. ''This makes it creamy,'' he said, letting go with two short squirts.</p>
        <p>A gregarious and athletic 20-year-old, Mr. Marks prepares what he describes as ''gourmet treats'' by employing items from the dining room buffet, a well-stocked condiment bar and occasional borrowing from the kitchen.</p>
        <p>Mr. Marks has garnered no small degree of celebrity around campus for his culinary legerdemain, which he often shares with fellow students in a monthly column in the Yale Daily News.</p>
        <p>''I'm not saying that Yale food isn't good -- it is good, especially compared to most colleges,'' Mr. Marks said. ''But I've learned that by playing around you can make your own excellent meals.''</p>
        <p>Turning back to matters at hand, he fetched a grilled chicken breast and hacked it into bite-size pieces. For ease of dipping he decided to skewer the meat -- ''Hey Marvin! You have any toothpicks?''</p>
        <p>''If food tastes good it should look good,'' he opined, sprinkling the sauce with black and white sesame seeds and garnishing it with fresh cilantro.</p>
        <p>''Here we go!'' Mr. Marks beamed. ''Chicken satay!'' Though dry, it was tasty enough. The dish was the amuse-gueule of a two-course tasting menu that also featured a free-wheeling interpretation of tikka masala fashioned from yogurt, coriander, curry and garlic. Broccoli florets were set out for dipping.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Marks started his column last spring, his first effort was a culinary call to arms for fellow Yalies.</p>
        <p>''Do not regard the condiment bar as a humble home for ketchup and mustard,'' he wrote. ''Think of it as an arsenal of ingredients to whip up savory sauces -- you'll find the possibilities are limitless.''</p>
        <p>A column for Valentine's Day suggested chocolate fondue with chocolate chips, cream from the coffee station, sugar and eggs (brought over from his dorm room). The fondue served as a sauce for Cocobanana, a truly original twist on the banana split confected with crushed cornflakes, peanuts and shredded coconut.</p>
        <p>The column carries practical tips like these for dining hall denizens:</p>
        <p>All dining halls have microwave ovens; learn to use them. Steam all kinds of vegetables in a little water. Carrots and broccoli actually turn out better this way. Or place onion slices (or garlic cloves) in a pool of olive oil and cook until soft. Not only do you have flavorful onions and garlic, but the olive oil takes on some of their flavor.</p>
        <p>Don't be discouraged if you can't find a certain ingredient. If there's no more cream cheese, try sour cream. If you want to make amandine sauce but all they have is cashews, go for it.</p>
        <p>When microwaving anything with bread, put a napkin underneath to keep it from getting soggy. (This is especially helpful with Reubens and garlic bread.)</p>
        <p>''My column is not so much about the recipes,'' Mr. Marks said as he plunged a piece of broccoli into the masala sauce. ''It's about empowering students to use their creativity not just in the classroom but in the dining hall, too.''</p>
        <p>His message may find a national following. He said he had been approached by a publisher to write a students' guide to dining hall food.</p>
        <p>Mr. Marks said he is largely a self-taught cook, having learned the basics from his father, whom he calls ''pretty serious'' when it comes to food.</p>
        <p>He has no aspirations to become a chef, though. ''I don't want to have to stand for 14 hours a day and be abused all day.'' Having grown up in central Philadelphia, he is interested in city issues and hopes to become an urban planner.</p>
        <p>Even without the column or his position as secretary of the Yale College Council, Mr. Marks would have commanded a high profile on campus because of a pig roast he staged last year on the freshman quad.</p>
        <p>''It was finals week and everybody was studying and miserable, so I thought we'd have a little fun,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Marks and a companion drove to a pig farm and brought back a freshly slaughtered 120-pound specimen -- snout to curly tail. Undeterred by ignorance of pig preparation, they carried the pig up five flights of stairs to Mr. Marks's dormitory room and placed it on ice from a vending machine in the hall.</p>
        <p>When the ice melted, they hauled the pig to the dining hall, hacked it into six pieces and placed it in a refrigerator.</p>
        <p>''That's where my dining hall contacts came in handy,'' Mr. Marks said.</p>
        <p>The following afternoon they fired up an ancient wood-frame charcoal grill and laid on the pig, suffusing the quad with the sweet waftings of barbecue -- that is, until the grill caught fire and collapsed.</p>
        <p>''After the fire went out we roasted it inside,'' Mr. Marks said. ''When we brought it back about 200 Yale students descended on us, with everybody taking pictures and having a great time. What a party!''</p>
        <p>He paused, reveling in the smoky memory, then added:</p>
        <p>''That was the weekend my girlfriend became a vegetarian.''</p>
        <p>Thai Chicken Satay  Time: 5 minutes</p>
        <p>For the sauce:  1/4 cup crunchy peanut butter (preferably natural, unsweetened)  2 tablespoons sesame oil  1 tablespoon soy sauce  1 tablespoon honey  1 teaspoon milk</p>
        <p>For the satay:  1 cooked chicken breast  2 tablespoons soy sauce  2 tablespoons honey  1 teaspoon sesame seeds.</p>
        <p>1. For sauce: mix peanut butter, sesame oil, soy sauce, honey and milk in a small microwaveable bowl. Microwave until thoroughly heated, about 30 seconds (be careful not to overcook), then mix until smooth.  2. For satay: Cut chicken into 1-inch-thick strips. Mix soy sauce and honey in small bowl. Coat chicken with mixture, discarding any excess. Microwave for 15 seconds. Sprinkle with sesame seeds, and serve with sauce.</p>
        <p>Yield: 1 serving.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
