<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Highly Paid Chief Is Paid $210 Million to Go Away</title>
    <meta content="06five" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/06/business/06five.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1816714"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FIVE DAYS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Home Depot Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Reserve System</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Toyota Motor Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Daimler-Chrysler Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boeing Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Airbus Industrie</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ubs Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Stanford University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nardelli, Robert L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stein, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Home Depot Inc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Toyota Motor Corp</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Boeing Co</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Nardelli, Robert L</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Galvin, William F</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E3D71430F935A35752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1084" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Highly Paid Chief Is Paid $210 Million to Go Away</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Highly Paid Chief Is Paid $210 Million to Go Away</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK A. STEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stein, Mark</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mark A Stein Five Days column; Home Depot chief executive Robert L Nardelli left company with severance package worth $210 million after abruptly resigning amid mounting criticism over his pay; Federal Reserve policy makers said worries about housing market being drag on economy have led to decision to hold interest rates steady; General Motors and Ford said they sold 13 percent fewer cars in December than in December 2005; Toyota met sales record in 2006, passing Daimler-Chrysler as third place automaker in American market; Boeing reported record 1,044 orders for commercial airplanes thanks to strong demand for its 737 narrow-body jet and its new fuel-efficient 787 Dreamliner; is likely to surpass Airbus in sales for first time since 2000; investigation began into whether UBS is using cheap office space to entice hedge funds to do business with firm, possible at expense of investors; Stanford University reported that securities fraud class-action lawsuits fell last year to lowest numbers in decade; decline 38 percent, to just 110 filing, compared with 178 in 2005; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE new year began with a series of surprises, not all of them pleasant.</p>
        <p>There was a blowup over excessive pay for corporate executives, worrying signs of a slowing economy, accelerating troubles for major manufacturers and new accusations of wrongdoing on Wall Street.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The new year began with a series of surprises, not all of them pleasant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE new year began with a series of surprises, not all of them pleasant.</p>
        <p>There was a blowup over excessive pay for corporate executives, worrying signs of a slowing economy, accelerating troubles for major manufacturers and new accusations of wrongdoing on Wall Street.</p>
        <p>There was good news, too. Boeing said its order book was bulging, and the number of securities fraud class-action lawsuits fell last year to the lowest level in a decade.</p>
        <p>PAY FIGHT -- After enduring six years of mounting criticism over his pay package, an imperious management style and a listless stock price, Robert L. Nardelli, the chief executive of Home Depot, resigned abruptly. He left with a severance package worth $210 million. Over six years as chief executive, he had taken home $64 million and was on track to earn hundreds of millions more.</p>
        <p>In a statement, Home Depot said the former chief executive and the company's board ''mutually agreed that Nardelli would leave his position.'' It added that Frank Blake, its vice chairman and one of Mr. Nardelli's lieutenants, would succeed him.</p>
        <p>The $210 million in compensation for Mr. Nardelli will include deferred compensation, pensions and other benefits to which he was already entitled. It also included an extra $20 million cash payment that the company was not legally obliged to pay.</p>
        <p>The developments reignited public debate about executive pay, just as the Securities and Exchange Commission is moving to modify disclosure rules. The changes will mask the true value of what senior executives are paid, critics say.</p>
        <p>Representative Barney Frank of Massachusetts, chairman of the House Financial Services Committee in the Democratic-controlled Congress, has said he will pursue legislation to curb executive salaries.</p>
        <p>WEAK ECONOMY -- Federal Reserve policy makers shed light on why they have held interest rates steady even though inflation is rising faster than their target rate: they are worried that the housing market slump may be a drag on the economy.</p>
        <p>That came out when the Fed released minutes of the December meeting of its Open Market Committee.</p>
        <p>The Fed's wary outlook surfaced as retailers said sales in December were disappointing, even after many had scaled back their fourth-quarter profit expectations. Some retailers also reduced forecasts for 2007.</p>
        <p>Retailers blamed mild weather that depressed winter clothing sales, but the flagging housing market and rising energy prices also had a big effect.</p>
        <p>Economists generally expect the Fed to hold rates steady at its next meeting, at the end of the month, followed by possible reductions in rates later in the year.</p>
        <p>HEARING FOOTSTEPS -- General Motors and Ford Motor said they ended a year of slumping sales with an accelerating slide in December, when they sold about 13 percent fewer cars than in December 2005.</p>
        <p>With consumers turning away from pickups and big sport utility vehicles, mainstays of both company's lineups, their share of the American market slid to just 53.7 percent for the year -- and just 51.5 percent for the month. Both are their lowest collective shares ever.</p>
        <p>Toyota, meanwhile, set a sales record in 2006 and passed DaimlerChrysler to take third place in the American car market. Toyota is now bearing down on Ford, which it is expected to unseat this year to take second place in the United States, and may overtake G.M. as the largest carmaker in the world.</p>
        <p>Toyota will soon decide whether to build two more plants in the United States, even as industry analysts forecast a slight decline in total sales for all makers in 2007. G.M. and Ford are closing factories.</p>
        <p>BOEING'S BACK -- Strong demand for its workhorse 737 narrow-body jet and robust sales of its new fuel-efficient 787 Dreamliner helped Boeing report a record 1,044 orders for commercial airplanes at the end of last year. That should be more than enough to surpass Airbus for the first time since 2000.</p>
        <p>Airbus, which has not yet reported December sales, said it had 687 firm orders as of the end of November.</p>
        <p>Measured by actual deliveries, however, Airbus remains ahead. It was on pace to deliver about 425 commercial aircraft last year, while Boeing delivered 398. Airlines and leasing companies order planes years in advance, and sometimes increase, decrease or cancel those orders before the planes are delivered.</p>
        <p>Airbus is scheduled to announce its 2006 order total on Jan. 17.</p>
        <p>HEDGE INQUIRY -- William F. Galvin, the secretary of the commonwealth of Massachusetts, has asked UBS for information to determine whether it is using cheap office space to entice hedge funds to do business with the firm, possibly at the expense of the funds' investors.</p>
        <p>UBS leases space to hedge funds and provides them with office help at a tower in Boston, said Brian McNiff, a spokesman for Mr. Galvin. Investigators suspect that UBS expected the hedge funds to execute their trades through the bank, paying higher fees in return for the space.</p>
        <p>Other banks may also come in for scrutiny. Bear Stearns, for example, also offers space in so-called hedge fund hotels in New York, Boston, San Francisco and Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>FEWER SUITS -- Just days after Wall Street began a campaign to curb what it said was a surge in shareholder lawsuits encouraged by a 2002 corporate-disclosure reform law, Stanford University reported that securities fraud class-action lawsuits fell last year to the lowest number in a decade.</p>
        <p>The study, from the Stanford Law School Securities Class Action Clearinghouse, said the number of class actions declined 38 percent, to just 110 filings, compared with 178 in 2005. Last year's total was 43 percent below the 10-year historical average.</p>
        <p>The clearinghouse is run jointly by the Stanford Law School and Cornerstone Research, which provides advice to lawyers in commercial lawsuits.</p>
        <p>Excluding suits over stock option backdating, which has embroiled 130 companies so far, the decline is even bigger, researchers said.</p>
        <p>The number of suits is likely to fall further because regulations adopted after recent scandals have discouraged fraud, encouraged good practices and energized law enforcement, said Joseph A. Grundfest, the professor who runs the clearinghouse.</p>
        <p>MOST POPULAR -- Following are the most-popular business news articles on nytimes.com from Dec. 30 through Jan. 5:</p>
        <p>1. Wal-Mart Puts Some Muscle Behind Power-Sipping Bulbs  2. Google Answer to Filling Jobs Is an Algorithm  3. Young Turn to Web Sites Without Rules  4. Fewer Excuses for Not Doing a PC Backup  5. In Silicon Valley, the Race Is On to Trump Google</p>
        <p>Links are at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>FIVE DAYS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
