<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Status Quo Secretary General</title>
    <meta content="06sat3" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/06/opinion/06sat3.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1816667"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Editorial"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ban Ki-Moon (Sec Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bolton, John R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Khalilzad, Zalmay (Amb)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">United Nations</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Ban Ki-moon</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Barcena Ibarra, Alicia</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Khalilzad, Zalmay</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E7D81430F935A35752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="361" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Status Quo Secretary General</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Status Quo Secretary General</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial holds that big powers in UN Security Council chose Ban Ki-moon as secretary general because they wanted low-key bureaucrat who would not rock boat; maintains that judging by his early moves, world has gotten exactly that; says on one crucial front, outlook may be brightening; contends that under Pres Bush, relations between Washington and UN were driven to their lowest point ever, following twin blows of Iraq war and destructive presence of former ambassador, John Bolton; says White House reportedly plans to nominate new ambassador, Zalmay Khalilzad, current ambassador in Iraq, who actually believes in diplomacy</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The big powers in the United Nations Security Council chose Ban Ki-moon as secretary general because they wanted a low-key bureaucrat who wouldn't rock the boat. Judging by Mr. Ban's early moves, the world has gotten exactly that.</p>
        <p>Expect no Kofi Annan-style exhortations to live up to the values of the U.N. charter. In commenting on the sordid execution of Saddam Hussein, Mr. Ban even managed to forget that the U.N. opposes the death penalty on principle. Expect no shift from patronage to selection based on merit for key staff positions. The top jobs in peacekeeping, political affairs and humanitarian relief are already being doled out to the favored candidates of London, Paris and Washington (three of Mr. Ban's backers).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United Nations Security Council chose Ban Ki-moon as secretary general because they wanted a low-key bureaucrat who wouldn’t rock the boat, and the world has gotten exactly that.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The big powers in the United Nations Security Council chose Ban Ki-moon as secretary general because they wanted a low-key bureaucrat who wouldn't rock the boat. Judging by Mr. Ban's early moves, the world has gotten exactly that.</p>
        <p>Expect no Kofi Annan-style exhortations to live up to the values of the U.N. charter. In commenting on the sordid execution of Saddam Hussein, Mr. Ban even managed to forget that the U.N. opposes the death penalty on principle. Expect no shift from patronage to selection based on merit for key staff positions. The top jobs in peacekeeping, political affairs and humanitarian relief are already being doled out to the favored candidates of London, Paris and Washington (three of Mr. Ban's backers).</p>
        <p>And expect no serious drive for much-needed administrative reform. The top management job, previously held by a reform-minded American, has now been given to a long-serving insider, Alicia Bárcena Ibarra of Mexico.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ban takes over at a difficult time. The secretariat's reputation for integrity has been battered by the oil-for-food scandal, and the Security Council's claim to influence has been battered by its failure to halt the genocide in Darfur or the nuclear ambitions of Iran and North Korea.</p>
        <p>On one crucial front, though, the outlook may be brightening. Under President Bush, relations between Washington and the U.N. were driven to their lowest point ever, following the twin blows of the Iraq war and the destructive presence of the former ambassador, John Bolton. The White House reportedly plans to nominate a new ambassador, Zalmay Khalilzad, who actually believes in diplomacy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Khalilzad is currently the ambassador in Baghdad, where he is one of the few American officials to try to reach out to Sunni Muslims and curb the divisively sectarian policies of Prime Minister Nuri Kamal al-Maliki. Unfortunately, the White House -- desperate to make Mr. Maliki look like a leader -- decided it did not want such an activist ambassador. We hope that choosing Mr. Khalilzad for the United Nations is at least a sign that Mr. Bush is learning the importance of diplomacy and cooperation, if not the importance of a powerful U.N. leader or a strong-minded ambassador in Baghdad.</p>
        <p>Editorial</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
