<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rooting Around Grandma's Basement in Cyberspace</title>
    <meta content="18Online" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Thursday Styles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/18/fashion/18Online.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1819578"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ONLINE SHOPPER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Handicrafts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gifts</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slatalla, Michelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Thursday Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gifts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Blogs and Blogging (Internet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicrafts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blogs and Blogging (Internet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gifts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EFDC1130F93BA25752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1047" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rooting Around Grandma's Basement in Cyberspace</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rooting Around Grandma’s Basement in Cyberspace</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michelle Slatalla</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Slatalla, Michelle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michelle Slatalla on shopping online for handmade one-of-a-kind things with crafty tinge, which she says is perfect gift for people who have given you something; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOME years I receive nothing.</p>
        <p>The holiday season passes peacefully. I dismantle the tree. And the only nagging social obligation I feel guilty about is not managing to mail out a family greeting card. So I sweep up the pine needles and tell myself everyone will be thrilled to receive the annual photo of my children on Valentine's Day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For gifts that say, “I like you,” but certainly not, “This is payback.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOME years I receive nothing.</p>
        <p>The holiday season passes peacefully. I dismantle the tree. And the only nagging social obligation I feel guilty about is not managing to mail out a family greeting card. So I sweep up the pine needles and tell myself everyone will be thrilled to receive the annual photo of my children on Valentine's Day.</p>
        <p>This year was different.</p>
        <p>One day last month I found a festively wrapped bottle of wine on the porch. (Thanks, Dawn and Bill.)</p>
        <p>It was the start of a trend. The unexpected gift tipped the scales of heaven in my direction. The next day a friend delivered a plate of homemade cookies. (Thanks, Lisa). Another dropped off a holiday wreath to hang on the door. (Thanks, Stephanie.) By the end of December I was the delighted recipient of a sleighful of iced sugar cookies, bottles of Champagne and tiny Christmas tree ornaments (the one shaped like a bird was a regift, but still adorable).</p>
        <p>This sort of situation creates a crisis in January.</p>
        <p>I call it the response gift syndrome. I know that someday -- maybe not today, maybe not tomorrow, but soon -- I will have to reciprocate. The best way to thank my friends for a gift is with a gift in return.</p>
        <p>But what? The last thing I want them to know is that it's a response gift because I don't want them to think I'm keeping score (although I am). I don't want them to think that I think they won't like me unless I show my gratitude with a gift (although that is my secret fear).</p>
        <p>Most important, I don't want to become locked in a terrible cycle. I envision an escalating round of gift-giving, starting innocently enough with that box of mail-order pears but potentially leading to buying Porsches and diamond necklaces for the neighbors, instead of saving all our money to pay for college tuition.</p>
        <p>And I really want my children to go to college.</p>
        <p>The solution is a stealth response gift. This is one that seems thoughtful but in an offhand way, a casual sort of token that says, ''I like you and gave you this for no reason, certainly not because you gave me something.''</p>
        <p>The solution does not come from the mall. It is a handmade one-of-a-kind thing, perhaps with a crafty tinge to it.</p>
        <p>In the old days I used to wander the stalls at weekend fairs. But now such objects are available at a growing number of Internet sites that operate like online crafts shows. At sites like Cutxpaste.com, dozens of do-it-yourselfers sell handmade wares, ranging from letterpress notepads ($8 each, from DeLuce Design) to crocheted pompom hats ($42 each, from Purldrop.com).</p>
        <p>At Handmadecatalog.com a painted beehive birdhouse made from a gourd is $21.95. And at Artsefest.com shoppers can click on ''Shop by Crafter'' to link directly to more than 500 sites that sell merchandise like handmade journals bound with a ribbon made of tree bark ($35 to $65, depending on size).</p>
        <p>But the site with the widest selection, about 300,000 items, is Etsy.com, which describes itself as a ''a place to buy &amp; sell all things handmade.''</p>
        <p>''We know a lot of people who sell things on our site sell at crafts fairs, too,'' said Rob Kalin, a founder of the site. ''We're trying to serve a class of artisans who are making things in quantities not large enough to stock a store, but maybe enough to take out a booth at a crafts fair.''</p>
        <p>Etsy.com is a mishmash of merchandise, organized in categories like knitting, housewares, furniture and toys. If it evokes your grandma's basement, that's no accident.</p>
        <p>''When I was a kid, one compensation for visiting my grandmother in Buffalo after an eight-hour trip was that I got to root around in her basement,'' Mr. Kalin said.</p>
        <p>Navigating the site, which Mr. Kalin created with two college friends in 2005, is like going on a weird treasure hunt. It is hard to predict what you will stumble across: curiosities like a pair of clay earrings in the shape of salmon roe sushi ($8, from Stitcherx) or a velvet pillow decorated with an anatomy-book illustration of a skull ($35, from Crows Cloth).</p>
        <p>There's a handcrafted feel to the site's design, thanks in part to its search features. On the home page, for example, shoppers can click on ''Time Machine'' to view a swirling display of the most recently listed wares for sale. Or you can click on ''Colors'' to unleash a rainbow flurry of colored bubbles. A click on one of them links to items of the same hue.</p>
        <p>While these features are amusing, I prefer a more old-fashioned and efficient approach to shopping. Last week I conducted a keyword search on the site for a tea towel --who doesn't need a nice new one? -- and came up with a number of choices that qualify as useful response gifts.</p>
        <p>A flour-sack tea towel embroidered with an apple ($5, from Heatherhalesdesigns) would please anyone with a vintage kitchen. A set of two white-on-white hemstitched towels (which you can order with a monogram, $20, from Trndesigns) would fit any décor.</p>
        <p>The only drawback to shopping on Etsy.com is that it's as time-consuming as digging through all those boxes in the basement. To find the perfect response gift you have to root through a lot of idiosyncratic stuff -- like a pink quilted purse that looks like a brain (''It's a must to complete any zombie or mad scientist type ensemble,'' $65, from Bakingwithmedusa) -- before you stumble across something you think you want.</p>
        <p>I bought a set of four beaded wineglass tags with painted charms shaped like flip-flops. They were a one-a-one-of-a-kind set, but you're not missing anything -- they arrived in a little fabric bag that smelled so heavily of cigarettes that I can't give them to anyone.</p>
        <p>But luckily I also bought 10 adorable envelopes that were handmade from atlas pages (with note cards, $2.25, from time2cre8). So at least I have the proper stationery to attach to response gifts.</p>
        <p>Smug about making progress in the response-gift department, I rewarded myself with a trip to the grocery store. On the way out the door, I tripped over a New Year's gift addressed to me. (Thanks, Amy.)</p>
        <p>ONLINE SHOPPER E-mail: slatalla@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: slatalla@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
