<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>St.-Émilions, Ripe From the Heat of 2003</title>
    <meta content="10wine" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/10/dining/reviews/10wine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1817742"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WINES OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Asimov, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Wines of the Times</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Wine Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E7DF1230F933A25752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1400" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>St.-Émilions, Ripe From the Heat of 2003</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">St.-Émilions, Ripe From the Heat of 2003</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC ASIMOV</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Asimov, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ratings of St-Emilion wines from 2003 vintage noted; bottles included in tastings were all less than $100; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE 2003 vintage in Europe has been characterized as bordering on the bizarre. The weather was extreme, particularly in France, where a long, deadly August heat wave challenged winemakers.</p>
        <p>Problems caused by the heat are most evident in white wines. Accelerated ripening meant acidity was lost, and because of this the whites lack their characteristic freshness and vivacity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The tasting panel savors St.-Émilions from the 2003 vintage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE 2003 vintage in Europe has been characterized as bordering on the bizarre. The weather was extreme, particularly in France, where a long, deadly August heat wave challenged winemakers.</p>
        <p>Problems caused by the heat are most evident in white wines. Accelerated ripening meant acidity was lost, and because of this the whites lack their characteristic freshness and vivacity.</p>
        <p>But red wines are another story.</p>
        <p>From almost every part of France, I've found the 2003 reds to be remarkably successful. They aren't great, except maybe some from Touraine and isolated other cases. But the wines are full of pleasure and are accessible, without the extra aging that a great vintage would require.</p>
        <p>A case in point is St.-Émilion, the Bordeaux commune on the Right Bank of the Gironde River where cabernet franc and merlot grapes are far more prominent than cabernet sauvignon. That makes for a softer, easier style than the more austere wines of the Médoc, across the river. The wine panel recently tasted 25 St.-Émilions from the '03 vintage and we found them to be greatly enjoyable.</p>
        <p>The best were juicy and rich, bordering on jammy but never quite crossing over into baked or raisiny flavors. The heat of the vintage was evident in the dark power of the wines and in the abundance of ripe fruit, but the best wines were balanced and surprisingly fresh.</p>
        <p>For the tasting, Florence Fabricant and I were joined by Jean-Luc Le Dû, owner of Le Dû's Wines in the West Village, and Jamie Ritchie, senior vice president of Sotheby's North American wine department.</p>
        <p>We focused on St.-Émilion because it has been the most dynamic of Bordeaux's leading communes, diverse in style and home both to established producers and rebels. Indeed, more so in St.-Émilion than anywhere else in Bordeaux, a new wave of producers has gone head-to-head against old-line chateaux, receiving the high ratings and stratospheric prices that were once the property only of hallowed old names.</p>
        <p>St.-Émilion produces a lot of wine, so we decided to limit ourselves to bottles under $100, which effectively eliminated the most renowned estates like Ausone and Cheval Blanc, along with other leading lights like Angélus, Valandraud and La Mondotte. We made one exception to the price limit. Motivated by curiosity, we spent $210 for a bottle of Château Pavie, a wine that has been the subject of controversy. More on the Pavie later.</p>
        <p>We easily accumulated wines from some of St.-Émilion's best producers, which made our top wine all the more surprising. It was from Château Destieux, a little-known estate that has never received much appreciation but maybe now has earned a little love.</p>
        <p>This wine might have been easy to overlook at first sniff. I found it dark, sweet and oaky to begin with, but after it had some time to open up its underlying fruit emerged, showing concentration, complexity and intensity without heaviness. The wine is tannic, but not unpleasantly so, and even though many of the 2003's are not destined for long aging, the Destieux will benefit from at least another year in the bottle.</p>
        <p>At $33, the Destieux was our best value. It was also one of a cluster of relatively inexpensive bottles that were among our top wines. They included Fonroque at $21, tannic yet balanced with complexity already evident; Chauvin at $27, dense and energetic, and Lusseau at $31, concentrated and full of fruit, but with an underlying elegance.</p>
        <p>On the other end of the scale, we had the Pavie. This wine has been the subject of much sniping as critics either lauded Pavie as one of the great current St.-Émilion producers or lambasted it for making essentially a satire of a wine.</p>
        <p>Frankly, in our blind tasting, we could not see what all the fuss had been about. The wine is dark and juicy, full of lush fruit aromas, and very rich in the mouth. It appealed especially to Jean-Luc and Jamie, less so to Florence and me. I found it somewhat exaggerated compared with other rich wines in the tasting, and I also found little structure, that skeletal quality derived from tannins and acidity that gives shape and definition to a wine. Was that a function of this hot vintage? I'll have to find a bottle from another year.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, we all agreed that the quality was high enough to make our list of top wines, and though it didn't fit our price limit, we included it anyway, which is why we have listed our top 11 this week instead of the usual top 10.</p>
        <p>That said, we found less outsize versions of the style at a third the price. Our No. 2 wine, Canon-la-Gaffelière, was full of ripe fruit aromas and flavors, yet it had an earthiness to it as well and a tannic definition that gave it focus. So too did the Péby Faugères, which had the baked fruit-and-toasty oak aroma of a California wine but also had a balance and energy to it that kept me intrigued.</p>
        <p>Wines that we found balanced were rated higher than those that were powerful without a sense of proportion. That's why Clos de Sarpe and Tertre Roteboeuf are further down the list. Both are big, jammy, enjoyable wines, but without the delineation of those we liked better.</p>
        <p>The last of our top 11, the Monbousquet (like Pavie, it's owned by Gérard Perse), and the Beauséjour (Duffau-Lagarrosse), both had a surprising lightness to them. They were easy to enjoy but without the intensity of the wines rated higher.</p>
        <p>In any tasting like this, others could take our list of top wines, juggle the order and defend their results. In the end, the specifics don't matter so much as the bigger picture of the 2003 vintage. Ripe? Indeed. But very good.</p>
        <p>Tasting Report: Dark, Complex Flavors, Baked by the Sun</p>
        <p>BEST VALUE</p>
        <p>Château Destieux: $33 *** 1/2 [Rating: Three and a Half Stars]  Dark and oaky, yet with plenty of underlying complex fruit and herbal aromas; intense but not heavy. (Importer: Diageo Chateau &amp; Estates, New York)</p>
        <p>Château Canon-la-Gaffelière: $65 *** [Rating: Three Stars]  Dark, with flavors of earth, spice and baked fruit. You can taste the heat of the vintage in the ripeness of the fruit. (Le Reine, New York)</p>
        <p>Château Péby Faugères: $75 *** [Rating: Three Stars]  Silky yet structured with chewy tannins and aromas of dark fruit and compote. (Le Reine, New York)</p>
        <p>Château Fonroque: $21 *** [Rating: Three Stars]  Balanced and elegant with taut tannins and complex aromas of fruits and herbs. (Fruit of the Vine, New York)</p>
        <p>Château Chauvin: $27 *** [Rating: Three Stars]  Balanced herbal and fruit aromas; breezy and uplifting. (Fruit of the Vine, New York)</p>
        <p>Château Lusseau: $31 *** [Rating: Three Stars]  Rich texture and concentrated fruit, yet well balanced, even elegant. (Le Reine, New York)</p>
        <p>Château Pavie: $210 ** 1/2 [Rating: Two and a Half Stars]  Dark, juicy and ultra-rich with pretty aromas, lingering flavors but little sense of structure. (Le Reine, New York)</p>
        <p>Château Clos de Sarpe: $75 ** 1/2 [Rating: Two and a Half Stars]  Plum jammy; big, concentrated and a little thick. (Imperial Importing, New York)</p>
        <p>Château Monbousquet: $50 ** 1/2 [Rating: Two and a Half Stars]  Well balanced with a sense of lightness; lingering flavors of spice, herbs and fruit. (Vintage Trading, New York)</p>
        <p>Château Beauséjour (Duffau-Lagarrosse): $55 ** 1/2 [Rating: Two and a Half Stars]  Opulent aromas of cranberry and anise; easy and pleasing. (Le Reine, New York)</p>
        <p>Château Tertre Roteboeuf: $95 ** 1/2 [Rating: Two and a Half Stars]  Rich, ripe and plummy and a creamy, soft texture; on the sweet side. (Le Reine, New York)</p>
        <p>WHAT THE STARS MEAN:</p>
        <p>(None) Pass It By</p>
        <p>* Passable  ** Good  *** Excellent  **** Extraordinary</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the panel's reaction to wines, which were tasted with names and vintages concealed. The panelists this week are Eric Asimov; Florence Fabricant; Jean-Luc Le Dû, owner of Le Dû's Wines; and Jamie Ritchie, senior vice president of Sotheby's North American wine department. The tasted wines represent a selection generally available in good retail shops and restaurants. Prices are those paid in liquor shops in the New York region.</p>
        <p>Tasting Coordinator: Bernard Kirsch</p>
        <p>nytimes.com  Recent wine columns from The New York Times are online: nytimes.com/wine. This week, members of the panel discuss their favorite 2003 St.-Émilions.</p>
        <p>WINES OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
