<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ruling Seen as Giving an Edge to Challengers of Patents</title>
    <meta content="10scotus" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/10/washington/10scotus.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1817804"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Respiratory Diseases</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Synagis (Drug)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Medimmune Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Genentech Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhouse, Linda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Respiratory Diseases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Respiratory Diseases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Supreme Court</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E1DE1230F933A25752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="590" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ruling Seen as Giving an Edge to Challengers of Patents</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ruling Seen as Giving an Edge to Challengers of Patents</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenhouse, Linda</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Supreme Court, 8 to 1, overturns ruling by US Court of Appeals for Federal Circuit that barred category of patent lawsuits; decision, in case involving biotechology companies MedImmune and Genentech, will probably shift power in courtroom from bigger patent-owning companies to smaller start-up ones that rely on obtaining licenses for patented technology; case grew out of license agreement involving genetically engineered drug Synagis used to prevent a respiratory disease in infants (M</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Supreme Court opened the door Tuesday to a category of patent lawsuits that a lower court had barred, issuing a decision that will probably shift power in the courtroom from bigger patent-owning companies to smaller start-up companies that rely on obtaining licenses for patented technology.</p>
        <p>The court's 8-to-1 decision held that the holder of a patent license can sue to challenge the patent's validity without first refusing to pay royalties and putting itself in breach of the license agreement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Supreme Court held that the holder of a patent license can sue to challenge the patent’s validity without first refusing to pay royalties and putting itself in breach of the license agreement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Supreme Court opened the door Tuesday to a category of patent lawsuits that a lower court had barred, issuing a decision that will probably shift power in the courtroom from bigger patent-owning companies to smaller start-up companies that rely on obtaining licenses for patented technology.</p>
        <p>The court's 8-to-1 decision held that the holder of a patent license can sue to challenge the patent's validity without first refusing to pay royalties and putting itself in breach of the license agreement.</p>
        <p>This seemingly technical question, in a dispute by two biotechnology companies, MedImmune and Genentech, has considerable practical importance. A license holder is much less likely to sue if it must first stop paying royalties and thereby risk becoming the target of a patent infringement suit, with the potential for triple damages and the loss of the right to continue selling its product.</p>
        <p>In making its decision, the Supreme Court overturned a ruling by the specialized appeals court that hears all patent appeals. That court, the United States Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit, had adopted a rule in a previous case that required a party to breach its license agreement before suing to declare a patent invalid.</p>
        <p>As long as royalties were being paid, the Federal Circuit had reasoned, there was no actual controversy between the parties and such a lawsuit would therefore not meet the requirement of Article III of the Constitution, which limits the jurisdiction of the federal courts to resolving actual ''cases'' or ''controversies.''</p>
        <p>The Declaratory Judgment Act, the federal law that MedImmune invoked when it went to the federal District Court in Los Angeles for a determination of the validity of Genentech's patent, likewise requires the existence of an ''actual controversy'' before a court can act.</p>
        <p>But the dispute between MedImmune and Genentech was indeed a controversy that met the jurisdictional requirements of the statute and the Constitution, Justice Antonin Scalia wrote for the majority in overturning the Federal Circuit's dismissal of the case, MedImmune Inc. v. Genentech Inc., No. 05-608.</p>
        <p>Justice Scalia said the rule that a plaintiff must ''bet the farm, or (as here) risk treble damages and the loss of 80 percent of its business before seeking a declaration of its actively contested legal rights finds no support in Article III.''</p>
        <p>The decision did not resolve the underlying dispute, instead reinstating MedImmune's lawsuit and sending the case back to the lower courts.</p>
        <p>The case grew out of a license agreement the two companies reached in 1997 as MedImmune, then a new company, was working on a genetically engineered drug, Synagis, used to prevent a respiratory disease in infants. While MedImmune later came to public attention as the maker of the FluMist influenza vaccine, Synagis has been the company's main product, accounting for 80 percent of its sales since 1999.</p>
        <p>The license authorized MedImmune to use the technology developed by Genentech and its research partner, the City of Hope National Medical Center in Duarte, Calif. City of Hope is also a party in the case.</p>
        <p>The agreement obliged MedImmune to pay royalties for the use of patents ''which have neither expired nor been held invalid.''</p>
        <p>The specific patent at issue in the case was not granted to Genentech until 2001, at which point Genentech wrote to MedImmune demanding royalties. MedImmune paid under protest, while filing its lawsuit to have the patent declared invalid.</p>
        <p>Justice Clarence Thomas was the lone dissenter from the ruling. He said there was ''no Article III jurisdiction over MedImmune's claim,'' which he called ''hypothetical or conjectural.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
