<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How to Fix a Honking Honda</title>
    <meta content="21MOTOR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/21/automobiles/21MOTOR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1820384"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">alldatapro.com</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sturgis, Scott</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Guarantees and Warranties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03EFDF1E30F932A15752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="691" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How to Fix a Honking Honda</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">How to Fix a Honking Honda</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SCOTT STURGIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sturgis, Scott</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Technical service bulletins issued by automakers offer guidance on car problems and repairs, and they are available online at alldatapro.com; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF YOUR Honda honks unexpectedly or your BMW's acceleration doesn't leave you beaming, recent technical service bulletins, or T.S.B.'s, may offer some guidance for repairs.</p>
        <p>T.S.B.'s, available at alldatapro.com, offer automakers' insights into some recurring problems with various models. The bulletins are not recalls; they include information from manufacturers to their dealers' service departments and mechanics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If your Honda honks unexpectedly or your BMW’s acceleration doesn’t leave you beaming, recent technical service bulletins may offer some guidance for repairs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF YOUR Honda honks unexpectedly or your BMW's acceleration doesn't leave you beaming, recent technical service bulletins, or T.S.B.'s, may offer some guidance for repairs.</p>
        <p>T.S.B.'s, available at alldatapro.com, offer automakers' insights into some recurring problems with various models. The bulletins are not recalls; they include information from manufacturers to their dealers' service departments and mechanics.</p>
        <p>Alldata.com provides less expensive reports intended to help owners learn about their vehicles. Here are recent examples:</p>
        <p>HONDA AND ACURA Some 2003 and 2004 Acura MDX and Honda Pilot sport utility wagons may sound the horn when turning or hitting bumps. In T.S.B.'s 06-045 and 06-081 issued on Nov. 10, Honda says replacing the horn button springs should quiet things down.</p>
        <p>Some 2003-07 Accords may experience a front brake judder when the brakes are applied normally. In T.S.B. 06-087 issued on Dec. 6, Honda says the front brake pads may have worn the discs unevenly. Refinishing the rotors and installing new brake pads should fix the problem.</p>
        <p>Honda mentions that it might pay the cost of all work performed outside the warranty period, at the district manager's discretion.</p>
        <p>All 2003-4 Elements now have a six-year or 60,000-mile warranty for their windshields as a result of a class-action suit. In T.S.B. 06-084 issued on Nov. 22, Honda noted the extension after some Elements were delivered with cracks in the lower corners of windshields.</p>
        <p>In T.S.B.'s 06-085 and 06-050 issued on Nov. 21, Honda says some 2002-7 Acuras and Hondas could get a 5 percent extension on the mileage portion of their vehicle warranties after the final settlement of a class-action suit, scheduled for May 30. Dealers have been told not to extend warranties until the final settlement is completed.</p>
        <p>BMW Some 2006 3 Series models may be bucking under slight acceleration from a standing start when the engine is still cold. In T.S.B. 124606 issued on Nov. 1, BMW says recalibrating the digital motor electronics module should smooth the ride. No word on coverage outside the warranty.</p>
        <p>FORD Some 2004-7 Ford Freestar minivans may be hampered by momentary activation of the traction control. In T.S.B. 6-21-8 issued on Oct. 30, Ford says a new steering-wheel-angle sensor and tone ring, which detects motion, should control the AdvanceTrac system. No word on coverage outside the warranty.</p>
        <p>ISUZU Some 2003-6 Ascender S.U.V.'s may leak oil from the engine's rear cover assembly area. In T.S.B. SB06-01-S003 issued on Nov. 1, Isuzu says engine block porosity may be the culprit. Replacing the rear cover gasket and covering the block pores with silicone sealer should halt the leak, Isuzu says. No word on coverage outside the warranty period.</p>
        <p>TOYOTA AND LEXUS Drivers of some 2006 Lexus LX 400h sport wagons and 2006 Toyota Highlander Hybrids may feel a rocking sensation at 40 miles an hour. Toyota says the problem, described in Toyota T.S.B. EG057-06 issued on Oct. 18 and Lexus T.S.B. EG020R-06 issued on Dec. 15, can be fixed by reprogramming the hybrid vehicle engine control module. Neither T.S.B. mentions coverage outside of the warranty.</p>
        <p>MERCEDES-BENZ Owners of some 2006 GL-Class models with Airmatic suspension may notice a knocking, thumping or cracking noise from the front end on heavy acceleration. In T.S.B. T-32-22-45 issued on Nov. 27, Mercedes says the damping effect of the suspension's quiet mode may cause the noise because of extra pressure from hard acceleration. Reprogramming the Airmatic control module should keep things quiet, Mercedes says. No word on coverage outside the warranty.</p>
        <p>VOLKSWAGEN Some 2006 Passats could have transmission fluid seeping from the transmission cooler. In T.S.B. 3706-03 issued on Nov. 9, Volkswagen says O-rings on its H-block fastener may need to be realigned to fix the problem. No word on coverage after the warranty is up.</p>
        <p>1998-99 Passats and Passat wagons with automatic transmissions may have shifting problems, like upshifting too fast, shaking when downshifting into first and sudden high revs in fifth gear. In T.S.B. 3706-05 issued on Nov. 17, VW says replacing the transmission control module should solve the problem. No word on coverage outside of the warranty.</p>
        <p>SCOTT STURGIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
