<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CALENDAR</title>
    <meta content="21welistingsWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1820332"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E2D71130F932A15752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2447" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CALENDAR</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on in and around Westchester and Putnam Counties this week. Items for the guide should be sent at least three weeks in advance to westweek@nytimes.com, or by mail to Westchester Cultural Calendar, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036-3959.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>Chappaqua New Castle Community Television's short video and film festival awards ceremony and showcase. Jan. 27 at 7:30 p.m. Free. Chappaqua Library, 195 South Greeley Avenue. (914) 238-4779.</p>
        <p>Mount Kisco ''An Inconvenient Truth,'' documentary by Al Gore. Thursday at 7 p.m. Free. Mount Kisco Public Library, 100 East Main Street. (914) 666-8041.</p>
        <p>Nyack ''Half Nelson,'' directed by Ryan Fleck. Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. $6 and $8. Riverspace, 119 Main Street. (845) 348-0741.</p>
        <p>Pleasantville ''50 Years of Janus Films,'' a series showcasing films by Bergman, Truffaut, Fellini, Kurosawa and others. Through Feb. 28. $6 to $13 per film; some films are followed by question-and-answer sessions. Schedule and information: burnsfilmcenter.org. FrameWorks: Art on Film Series: ''The Collector,'' documentary by Olympia Stone about her father, Allan, a Purchase gallery owner and collector who died in December; a question-and-answer session with Ms. Stone follows the screening. Wednesday at 7:15 p.m; sold out. Jacob Burns Film Center, 364 Manville Road. (914) 773-7663.</p>
        <p>Poughkeepsie ''Monty Python and the Holy Grail.'' Friday at 7 p.m. $5. Bardavon 1869 Opera House, 35 Market Street. (845) 473-2072.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>Croton-on-Hudson Circus Sisters, circus demonstrations, comedy and music. Friday at 7:30 p.m. Young People's Concert with the Artemis String Quartet; works by Mozart, Gershwin, Dvorak and others. Jan. 28 at 2 p.m. Free. Croton Free Library, 171 Cleveland Drive. (914) 271-6612.  Montrose Parent and child crochet workshop. Ages 8 and up. Mondays through Feb. 26 at 6:45 p.m. $10; includes yarn, hook and instructional booklet. Hendrick Hudson Free Library, 185 Kings Ferry Road. (914) 739-5654.</p>
        <p>Rye ''Emily Dickinson: Feathers Sometimes Soar on the Breath of God,'' by Ward James Riley, by M and M Productions with YCP TheaterWorks. Jan. 28 at 4 p.m. Free. Rye Free Reading Room, 1061 Boston Post Road. (914) 967-0480.</p>
        <p>Scarsdale ''Snowflakes Galore,'' an exploration of the world of snowflakes. Jan. 21 at 2 p.m. $2 and $5. Greenburgh Nature Center, 99 Dromore Road. (914) 723-3470.</p>
        <p>Tarrytown JellyBean children's concert. For ages 2 to 5. Jan. 21 at 2:15 p.m. Free. JCC on the Hudson, 371 South Broadway. (914) 366-7898.</p>
        <p>Valhalla Dance concert for children, presented by Danceworks, with audience participation. Jan. 28 at 3 p.m. $7. Fine Arts Gallery, 75 Grasslands Road. (914) 606-7867.</p>
        <p>White Plains David Grover and the Big Bear Band, family concert. Jan. 21 at 1:30 p.m. $15 to $20. Congregation Kol Ami, 252 Soundview Avenue. (914) 949-4717 ext. 103.</p>
        <p>White Plains Kids on Central: The Big Bang, percussion with Matt Gold and Matt Ward of the Westchester Philharmonic. For ages 5 and up. Jan. 27 at 2 p.m. $10. Music Conservatory of Westchester, 216 Central Avenue. (914) 761-3900.</p>
        <p>Yonkers ''Music and Merriment,'' children's program. For ages 1 1/2 to 5. Through June 20. Yonkers Crestwood Library, 16 Thompson Street. (914) 337-1500 x360.</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE</p>
        <p>Bronx Philadanco. Jan. 28 at 3 p.m. $20 to $35. Lehman Center for the Performing Arts, 250 Bedford Park Boulevard West. (718) 960-8833.</p>
        <p>Bronx Yeou-Cheng Ma, violist, and Children's Orchestra Society; works by Mozart, Brahms and Turina. Jan. 21 at 2 p.m. $15 and $18. Wave Hill, 675 West 252nd Street. (718) 549-3200.</p>
        <p>Dobbs Ferry Jennifer Tao, pianist. Monday at 1 p.m. $15. Hudson Valley Music Club, 54 Clinton Avenue. (914) 693-0616.</p>
        <p>Hastings-on-Hudson Electric Junkyard Gamelan, original music on invented instruments. Jan. 27 at 7:30 p.m. $10 to $15. First Unitarian Society of Westchester, 25 Jackson Avenue. (914) 478-2710.</p>
        <p>Irvington Works by Scarlatti, Mozart and Faure, and music for celtic harp; Emily Mitchell, harpist, and Margaret Swinchoski, flutist. Jan. 21 at 4 p.m. Free. Irvington Public Library, 12 South Astor Street. (914) 591-7840.</p>
        <p>Irvington Music of Joe Henderson and the Messengers, performed by the Westchester Jazz Orchestra. Jan. 27 at 8 p.m. $25 and $30. Irvington Town Hall, 85 Main Street. (914) 591-6602.</p>
        <p>Nyack Jazz in the Cafe, with Erik Lawrence, saxaphonist. Jan. 21, 4 to 7 p.m. $4 and $8. MusicWorks annual benefit concert for the Nyack Schools music program; with Vaneese Thomas and Nine Men's Morris, pop. Jan. 27 at 8 p.m. $15 and $25. Riverspace, 119 Main Street. (845) 348-0741.</p>
        <p>Ossining Somebody Scream Cajun and Zydeco Dance Series: Captain Squeeze and the Zydeco Moshers. Jan. 27, 7 to 11:30 p.m. $18. Zydeco Hall, 7 Old Albany Post Road. (914) 528-7612.</p>
        <p>Pleasantville ''Best of Broadway,'' presented by Be Mused Productions. Jan. 28 at 2 p.m. Free. Mount Pleasant Public Library, 350 Bedford Road. (914) 769-0548.</p>
        <p>Pleasantville ''Robert Stallman and Friends,'' sonatas by Bach, presented by the Pleasantville Chamber Music Society. Jan. 21 at 3 p.m. Free. Presbyterian Church, 400 Bedford Road. (914) 769-1782.</p>
        <p>Poughkeepsie ''Modfest,'' festival of music, dance and art. Friday through Feb. 4. Free. Vassar College, (845) 437-7294.</p>
        <p>Purchase Martha Graham Dance Company. Jan. 27 at 8 p.m. $45 to $65. Performing Arts Center, 735 Anderson Hill Road. (914) 251-6200.</p>
        <p>Scarsdale Artist Recital Series: Richard Carrick, pianist and composer. Friday at 8 p.m. Hoff-Barthelson Music School, 25 School Lane. (914) 723-1169.</p>
        <p>Scarsdale Hoff-Barthelson Artist Series: Jenny Hayden, soprano, and David Oei, pianist. Jan. 21 at 4 p.m. $11 to $13. Scarsdale Community Baptist Church, Popham and Autenrieth Roads. (914) 723-1169.</p>
        <p>Tarrytown ''Hooray for Hollywood: A Ballroom Dancing Extravaganza,'' with professional and amateur dancers. Jan. 27 at 7 p.m. $33. Tarrytown Music Hall, 13 Main Street. (914) 631-3390.</p>
        <p>Valhalla Saint Petersburg Classic Ballet. Jan. 21 at 3 p.m. $10 to $20. Fine Arts Gallery, 75 Grasslands Road. (914) 606-6262.</p>
        <p>White Plains Prokofiev's ''Peter and the Wolf,'' with narration, presented with the Eastchester Arts Council. Jan. 28 at 3 p.m. $10 to $20. Arts Exchange, 31 Mamaroneck Avenue. (914) 428-4220, extension 273.</p>
        <p>White Plains The Damocles Trio; works by Mozart, Salvador Brotons and Villa-Lobos. Jan. 28 at 3 p.m. $10 and $15. Community Unitarian Church, 468 Rosedale Avenue. (914) 232-3394.</p>
        <p>White Plains Works by Ellington, Gershwin and Harold Arlen, Glenda Davenport, vocalist; Hiroshi Yamazaki, pianist; and Ryan Berg, bassist. Wednesday at 12:10 p.m. Free. Grace Church, 33 Church Street. (914) 949-2478.</p>
        <p>White Plains Annual dance benefit for African children, presented by the White Plains and Westchester County Youth Bureaus, in support of Esther's Aid for Needy and Abandoned Children, Philadelphia Dance Conservatory, Steffi Nossen Dance Group and others. Jan. 27 at 7 p.m. $25 and $50. White Plains Performing Arts Center, 11 City Place. (914) 328-1600.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>Sleepy Hollow Reading by Patrica Smith and other performance poets. Jan. 21 at 4:30 p.m. Free. Hudson Valley Writers' Center, 300 Riverside Drive. (914) 332-5953.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>Chappaqua ''Cinderella,'' musical presented by the students of Amadeus Conservatory of Music. Jan. 21 at 1:30 and 3 p.m. $5 and $7. Chappaqua Library, 195 South Greeley Avenue. (914) 238-0388.</p>
        <p>Mamaroneck ''Murder on the Nile,'' an adaptation of Agatha Christie's novel; a question-and-answer session follows the performances on Feb. 1 and 8. Thursday through Feb. 11. $26 to $35. Emelin Theater, 153 Library Lane. (914) 698-0098.</p>
        <p>Mohegan Lake ''The Little Foxes,'' by Lillian Hellman, presented by YCP TheaterWorks. Friday through Feb. 4. $10 and $15. Van Cortlandtville School, Route 6. (914) 528-4145.</p>
        <p>Pawling ''The Heidi Chronicles,'' comedy by Wendy Wasserstein; the Pawling Theater Company. Through Jan. 27. $11 to $15. Pawling High School, Reservoir Road. (845) 855-1965.</p>
        <p>Suffern ''The Snow Queen,'' musical adaptation of the Hans Christian Andersen tale; Hudson Vagabond Puppets. Jan. 21 at 2:30 p.m. $10 and $12. Cultural Arts Theater, 145 College Road. (845) 732-8186.</p>
        <p>Tarrytown ''The Wizard of Oz,'' presented by Music in Chappaqua and the Saw Mill Summer Theater. Through Jan. 21. $15 and $18. Tarrytown Music Hall, 13 Main Street. (914) 631-3390.</p>
        <p>White Plains ''From the Wings,'' collection of one-act plays and scenes by the Fort Hill Players. Friday through Jan. 27 at 8 p.m. $10. Rochambeau School for Adult and Continuing Education, 228 Fisher Avenue. (914) 761-7463.</p>
        <p>White Plains ''The Secret Garden,'' musical adapted from the Frances Hodgson Burnett novel; book and lyrics by Marsha Norman, music by Lucy Simon, presented by the Play Group Theater. Through Jan. 21. $15. White Plains Performing Arts Center, 11 City Place. (914) 946-4433.</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>Armonk ''Winter Solstice V: Expressions of Our Time and Place,'' group show. Through Jan. 28. Hours: Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. The Studio: An Alternative Space for Contemporary Art, 2 Maryland Avenue. (914) 273-1452.</p>
        <p>Beacon ''bau 25: bau NOW,'' group exhibition featuring sculpture, painting and mixed media. Through Feb. 4. Gallery talk by Norton Batkin, director of the Center for Curatorial Studies, Bard College, on Jan. 27 at 1 p.m. Hours: Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 6 p.m. Beacon Artists Union (bau), 161 Main Street. (845) 440-7584.</p>
        <p>Beacon ''New Hudson 3, Contemporary Art of the Hudson Valley,'' group show. Through Feb. 26. Hours: daily, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Van Brunt Gallery, 460 Main Street. (845) 838-2995.</p>
        <p>Briarcliff Manor Watercolor and oil paintings by Julie Anello. Through Jan. 27. Hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Images Art Gallery, 1157 Pleasantville Road. (914) 762-3000.</p>
        <p>Bronx ''South Bronx Contemporary,'' group show. Through March 10. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. Longwood Art Gallery at Hostos, 450 Grand Concourse, C-190. (718) 518-6728.</p>
        <p>Greenburgh Watercolors by students of Brigitte Loritz. Through Jan. 31. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. Madeleine Gutman Gallery, 177 Hillside Avenue. (914) 682-1574.</p>
        <p>Harrison ''A few of my favorite things,'' watercolors by Caty Kendall. Through Friday. Hours: Mondays and Wednesdays, 9:30 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Tuesdays, Thursdays and Fridays, to 5:30 p.m.; Saturdays, to 12:30 p.m. Harrison Public Library, Bruce Avenue. (914) 835-0324.</p>
        <p>Hartsdale DeSanti Plaza Sculpture Project: ''Tinted Reflections II,'' sculpture by Anthony Krauss. Through March 1. DeSanti Plaza, across from Metro-North. (914) 478-4630.</p>
        <p>Hudson ''In Our Name: Iraqi Children in War,'' paintings by Christine Heller. Jan. 27 through Feb. 25. Reception: Jan. 27, 6 to 8 p.m. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, noon to 5 p.m. Hudson Opera House, 327 Warren Street. (518) 822-1438.</p>
        <p>Katonah Sculpture by Michael Steiner. Through April 22. ''Michael Krondl: Rising Water, Falling Water,'' photographic mural. Through March 8. ''The Way Things Go,'' video documenting a mad science experiment. ''Tools As Art: The Hechinger Collection,'' curated by Sarah Tanguy. Through April 8. Admission: $3 and $5. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Katonah Museum of Art, Route 22 at Jay Street. (914) 232-9555.</p>
        <p>Larchmont ''Just a Moment,'' photography by Sid Hecker. Through Jan. 30. Hours: Mondays and Thursdays, 9 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Tuesdays and Wednesdays, 9 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Larchmont Public Library, 121 Larchmont Avenue. (914) 834-2281.</p>
        <p>New Rochelle ''Racing on a Broken Road,'' exhibit on the Underground Railroad. Through March 4. Hours: Tuesdays and Wednesdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Thursdays and Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Castle Gallery, 29 Castle Place. (914) 654-5423.</p>
        <p>New Rochelle ''Remembering the New York-Westchester-Boston Railway in New Rochelle,'' with artifacts, maps and photographs. Hours: Mondays, Tuesdays and Thursdays 9 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Wednesdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Fridays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. New Rochelle Public Library, Lawton Street. (914) 632-7878.</p>
        <p>Newburgh Decorative works curated by Elizabeth Oliver. Through Feb. 25. Yellow Bird Gallery, 19 Front Street. (845) 561-7204.</p>
        <p>Port Chester ''Pollinia,'' ceramic sculpture by Leigh Taylor Mickelson. Through Jan. 27. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Clay Art Center, 40 Beech Street. (914) 937-2047.</p>
        <p>Poughkeepsie ''For the People: American Mural Drawings of the 1930s and 1940s,'' group show. Through March 11. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Vassar College, Frances Lehman Loeb Art Center. (845) 437-5632.</p>
        <p>Purchase ''Crossing the Boulevard: Strangers, Neighbors, Aliens in a New America.'' Through Jan. 27. $3 to $5; members and children 12 and under, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Neuberger Museum of Art, 735 Anderson Hill Road. (914) 251-6100.</p>
        <p>Rockville Centre ''Poor Art Student ... Strike 3!'' mixed-media group show of student artwork, curated by Cristina Pugliese. Through Wednesday. Free. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Molloy College Art Gallery, 1000 Hempstead Avenue. (516) 678-5000.</p>
        <p>Rye ''Cutting Across Cultures: The Art of Papercutting, Then and Now,'' works by traditional and contemporary paper-cutting artists. Through Feb. 17. Rye Arts Center, 51 Milton Road. (914) 967-0700.</p>
        <p>Rye ''The Image Makers,'' works by members of the Westchester Photographic Society. Through Feb. 16. Rye Free Reading Room, 1061 Boston Post Road. (914) 967-0480.</p>
        <p>Rye ''Shells and Trees,'' works by Elasah Schaff. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Rye Nature Center, 873 Boston Post Road. (914) 967-5150.</p>
        <p>Valhalla ''Looser, Smoother, Faster,'' works by Eric Hongisto, Shoji Kato and Matt King. Through Feb. 24. Reception: Thursday, 4 to 6 p.m. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 3 p.m.; Thursdays, 6 to 8 p.m. Fine Arts Gallery, 75 Grasslands Road. (914) 606-7867.</p>
        <p>West Point ''The Color of Loyalty: A Tribute to Dr. J. Robert Oppenheimer,'' works of Linda Jean Fisher. Through Feb. 11. Hours: daily, 9 a.m. to 4 p.m. 1929 Gallery, Eisenhower Hall, United States Military Academy. (845) 938-2782.</p>
        <p>White Plains ''Once Upon a Time  the Art of Children's Book Illustration,'' work of Howard Fine, Yumi Heo and Mary O'Keefe Young. Through Feb. 28. Free. White Plains Public Library, 100 Martine Avenue. (914) 422-1480.</p>
        <p>Woodstock ''Nature Without Glass,'' pinhole photographs by Mark Stetler. Through Feb. 12. Hours: Thursdays through Mondays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Gallery B.M.G., 12 Tannery Brook Road. (845) 679-0027.</p>
        <p>Woodstock ''Exhibit A,'' group show. Through Feb. 4. Hours: Thursdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Varga Gallery, 130 Tinker Street. (845) 679-4005.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on in and around Westchester and Putnam Counties this week. Items for the guide should be sent at least three weeks in advance to westweek@nytimes.com, or by mail to Westchester Cultural Calendar, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036-3959.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>Chappaqua New Castle Community Television's short video and film festival awards ceremony and showcase. Jan. 27 at 7:30 p.m. Free. Chappaqua Library, 195 South Greeley Avenue. (914) 238-4779.</p>
        <p>Mount Kisco ''An Inconvenient Truth,'' documentary by Al Gore. Thursday at 7 p.m. Free. Mount Kisco Public Library, 100 East Main Street. (914) 666-8041.</p>
        <p>Nyack ''Half Nelson,'' directed by Ryan Fleck. Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. $6 and $8. Riverspace, 119 Main Street. (845) 348-0741.</p>
        <p>Pleasantville ''50 Years of Janus Films,'' a series showcasing films by Bergman, Truffaut, Fellini, Kurosawa and others. Through Feb. 28. $6 to $13 per film; some films are followed by question-and-answer sessions. Schedule and information: burnsfilmcenter.org. FrameWorks: Art on Film Series: ''The Collector,'' documentary by Olympia Stone about her father, Allan, a Purchase gallery owner and collector who died in December; a question-and-answer session with Ms. Stone follows the screening. Wednesday at 7:15 p.m; sold out. Jacob Burns Film Center, 364 Manville Road. (914) 773-7663.</p>
        <p>Poughkeepsie ''Monty Python and the Holy Grail.'' Friday at 7 p.m. $5. Bardavon 1869 Opera House, 35 Market Street. (845) 473-2072.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>Croton-on-Hudson Circus Sisters, circus demonstrations, comedy and music. Friday at 7:30 p.m. Young People's Concert with the Artemis String Quartet; works by Mozart, Gershwin, Dvorak and others. Jan. 28 at 2 p.m. Free. Croton Free Library, 171 Cleveland Drive. (914) 271-6612.  Montrose Parent and child crochet workshop. Ages 8 and up. Mondays through Feb. 26 at 6:45 p.m. $10; includes yarn, hook and instructional booklet. Hendrick Hudson Free Library, 185 Kings Ferry Road. (914) 739-5654.</p>
        <p>Rye ''Emily Dickinson: Feathers Sometimes Soar on the Breath of God,'' by Ward James Riley, by M and M Productions with YCP TheaterWorks. Jan. 28 at 4 p.m. Free. Rye Free Reading Room, 1061 Boston Post Road. (914) 967-0480.</p>
        <p>Scarsdale ''Snowflakes Galore,'' an exploration of the world of snowflakes. Jan. 21 at 2 p.m. $2 and $5. Greenburgh Nature Center, 99 Dromore Road. (914) 723-3470.</p>
        <p>Tarrytown JellyBean children's concert. For ages 2 to 5. Jan. 21 at 2:15 p.m. Free. JCC on the Hudson, 371 South Broadway. (914) 366-7898.</p>
        <p>Valhalla Dance concert for children, presented by Danceworks, with audience participation. Jan. 28 at 3 p.m. $7. Fine Arts Gallery, 75 Grasslands Road. (914) 606-7867.</p>
        <p>White Plains David Grover and the Big Bear Band, family concert. Jan. 21 at 1:30 p.m. $15 to $20. Congregation Kol Ami, 252 Soundview Avenue. (914) 949-4717 ext. 103.</p>
        <p>White Plains Kids on Central: The Big Bang, percussion with Matt Gold and Matt Ward of the Westchester Philharmonic. For ages 5 and up. Jan. 27 at 2 p.m. $10. Music Conservatory of Westchester, 216 Central Avenue. (914) 761-3900.</p>
        <p>Yonkers ''Music and Merriment,'' children's program. For ages 1 1/2 to 5. Through June 20. Yonkers Crestwood Library, 16 Thompson Street. (914) 337-1500 x360.</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE</p>
        <p>Bronx Philadanco. Jan. 28 at 3 p.m. $20 to $35. Lehman Center for the Performing Arts, 250 Bedford Park Boulevard West. (718) 960-8833.</p>
        <p>Bronx Yeou-Cheng Ma, violist, and Children's Orchestra Society; works by Mozart, Brahms and Turina. Jan. 21 at 2 p.m. $15 and $18. Wave Hill, 675 West 252nd Street. (718) 549-3200.</p>
        <p>Dobbs Ferry Jennifer Tao, pianist. Monday at 1 p.m. $15. Hudson Valley Music Club, 54 Clinton Avenue. (914) 693-0616.</p>
        <p>Hastings-on-Hudson Electric Junkyard Gamelan, original music on invented instruments. Jan. 27 at 7:30 p.m. $10 to $15. First Unitarian Society of Westchester, 25 Jackson Avenue. (914) 478-2710.</p>
        <p>Irvington Works by Scarlatti, Mozart and Faure, and music for celtic harp; Emily Mitchell, harpist, and Margaret Swinchoski, flutist. Jan. 21 at 4 p.m. Free. Irvington Public Library, 12 South Astor Street. (914) 591-7840.</p>
        <p>Irvington Music of Joe Henderson and the Messengers, performed by the Westchester Jazz Orchestra. Jan. 27 at 8 p.m. $25 and $30. Irvington Town Hall, 85 Main Street. (914) 591-6602.</p>
        <p>Nyack Jazz in the Cafe, with Erik Lawrence, saxaphonist. Jan. 21, 4 to 7 p.m. $4 and $8. MusicWorks annual benefit concert for the Nyack Schools music program; with Vaneese Thomas and Nine Men's Morris, pop. Jan. 27 at 8 p.m. $15 and $25. Riverspace, 119 Main Street. (845) 348-0741.</p>
        <p>Ossining Somebody Scream Cajun and Zydeco Dance Series: Captain Squeeze and the Zydeco Moshers. Jan. 27, 7 to 11:30 p.m. $18. Zydeco Hall, 7 Old Albany Post Road. (914) 528-7612.</p>
        <p>Pleasantville ''Best of Broadway,'' presented by Be Mused Productions. Jan. 28 at 2 p.m. Free. Mount Pleasant Public Library, 350 Bedford Road. (914) 769-0548.</p>
        <p>Pleasantville ''Robert Stallman and Friends,'' sonatas by Bach, presented by the Pleasantville Chamber Music Society. Jan. 21 at 3 p.m. Free. Presbyterian Church, 400 Bedford Road. (914) 769-1782.</p>
        <p>Poughkeepsie ''Modfest,'' festival of music, dance and art. Friday through Feb. 4. Free. Vassar College, (845) 437-7294.</p>
        <p>Purchase Martha Graham Dance Company. Jan. 27 at 8 p.m. $45 to $65. Performing Arts Center, 735 Anderson Hill Road. (914) 251-6200.</p>
        <p>Scarsdale Artist Recital Series: Richard Carrick, pianist and composer. Friday at 8 p.m. Hoff-Barthelson Music School, 25 School Lane. (914) 723-1169.</p>
        <p>Scarsdale Hoff-Barthelson Artist Series: Jenny Hayden, soprano, and David Oei, pianist. Jan. 21 at 4 p.m. $11 to $13. Scarsdale Community Baptist Church, Popham and Autenrieth Roads. (914) 723-1169.</p>
        <p>Tarrytown ''Hooray for Hollywood: A Ballroom Dancing Extravaganza,'' with professional and amateur dancers. Jan. 27 at 7 p.m. $33. Tarrytown Music Hall, 13 Main Street. (914) 631-3390.</p>
        <p>Valhalla Saint Petersburg Classic Ballet. Jan. 21 at 3 p.m. $10 to $20. Fine Arts Gallery, 75 Grasslands Road. (914) 606-6262.</p>
        <p>White Plains Prokofiev's ''Peter and the Wolf,'' with narration, presented with the Eastchester Arts Council. Jan. 28 at 3 p.m. $10 to $20. Arts Exchange, 31 Mamaroneck Avenue. (914) 428-4220, extension 273.</p>
        <p>White Plains The Damocles Trio; works by Mozart, Salvador Brotons and Villa-Lobos. Jan. 28 at 3 p.m. $10 and $15. Community Unitarian Church, 468 Rosedale Avenue. (914) 232-3394.</p>
        <p>White Plains Works by Ellington, Gershwin and Harold Arlen, Glenda Davenport, vocalist; Hiroshi Yamazaki, pianist; and Ryan Berg, bassist. Wednesday at 12:10 p.m. Free. Grace Church, 33 Church Street. (914) 949-2478.</p>
        <p>White Plains Annual dance benefit for African children, presented by the White Plains and Westchester County Youth Bureaus, in support of Esther's Aid for Needy and Abandoned Children, Philadelphia Dance Conservatory, Steffi Nossen Dance Group and others. Jan. 27 at 7 p.m. $25 and $50. White Plains Performing Arts Center, 11 City Place. (914) 328-1600.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>Sleepy Hollow Reading by Patrica Smith and other performance poets. Jan. 21 at 4:30 p.m. Free. Hudson Valley Writers' Center, 300 Riverside Drive. (914) 332-5953.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>Chappaqua ''Cinderella,'' musical presented by the students of Amadeus Conservatory of Music. Jan. 21 at 1:30 and 3 p.m. $5 and $7. Chappaqua Library, 195 South Greeley Avenue. (914) 238-0388.</p>
        <p>Mamaroneck ''Murder on the Nile,'' an adaptation of Agatha Christie's novel; a question-and-answer session follows the performances on Feb. 1 and 8. Thursday through Feb. 11. $26 to $35. Emelin Theater, 153 Library Lane. (914) 698-0098.</p>
        <p>Mohegan Lake ''The Little Foxes,'' by Lillian Hellman, presented by YCP TheaterWorks. Friday through Feb. 4. $10 and $15. Van Cortlandtville School, Route 6. (914) 528-4145.</p>
        <p>Pawling ''The Heidi Chronicles,'' comedy by Wendy Wasserstein; the Pawling Theater Company. Through Jan. 27. $11 to $15. Pawling High School, Reservoir Road. (845) 855-1965.</p>
        <p>Suffern ''The Snow Queen,'' musical adaptation of the Hans Christian Andersen tale; Hudson Vagabond Puppets. Jan. 21 at 2:30 p.m. $10 and $12. Cultural Arts Theater, 145 College Road. (845) 732-8186.</p>
        <p>Tarrytown ''The Wizard of Oz,'' presented by Music in Chappaqua and the Saw Mill Summer Theater. Through Jan. 21. $15 and $18. Tarrytown Music Hall, 13 Main Street. (914) 631-3390.</p>
        <p>White Plains ''From the Wings,'' collection of one-act plays and scenes by the Fort Hill Players. Friday through Jan. 27 at 8 p.m. $10. Rochambeau School for Adult and Continuing Education, 228 Fisher Avenue. (914) 761-7463.</p>
        <p>White Plains ''The Secret Garden,'' musical adapted from the Frances Hodgson Burnett novel; book and lyrics by Marsha Norman, music by Lucy Simon, presented by the Play Group Theater. Through Jan. 21. $15. White Plains Performing Arts Center, 11 City Place. (914) 946-4433.</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>Armonk ''Winter Solstice V: Expressions of Our Time and Place,'' group show. Through Jan. 28. Hours: Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. The Studio: An Alternative Space for Contemporary Art, 2 Maryland Avenue. (914) 273-1452.</p>
        <p>Beacon ''bau 25: bau NOW,'' group exhibition featuring sculpture, painting and mixed media. Through Feb. 4. Gallery talk by Norton Batkin, director of the Center for Curatorial Studies, Bard College, on Jan. 27 at 1 p.m. Hours: Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 6 p.m. Beacon Artists Union (bau), 161 Main Street. (845) 440-7584.</p>
        <p>Beacon ''New Hudson 3, Contemporary Art of the Hudson Valley,'' group show. Through Feb. 26. Hours: daily, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Van Brunt Gallery, 460 Main Street. (845) 838-2995.</p>
        <p>Briarcliff Manor Watercolor and oil paintings by Julie Anello. Through Jan. 27. Hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Images Art Gallery, 1157 Pleasantville Road. (914) 762-3000.</p>
        <p>Bronx ''South Bronx Contemporary,'' group show. Through March 10. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. Longwood Art Gallery at Hostos, 450 Grand Concourse, C-190. (718) 518-6728.</p>
        <p>Greenburgh Watercolors by students of Brigitte Loritz. Through Jan. 31. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. Madeleine Gutman Gallery, 177 Hillside Avenue. (914) 682-1574.</p>
        <p>Harrison ''A few of my favorite things,'' watercolors by Caty Kendall. Through Friday. Hours: Mondays and Wednesdays, 9:30 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Tuesdays, Thursdays and Fridays, to 5:30 p.m.; Saturdays, to 12:30 p.m. Harrison Public Library, Bruce Avenue. (914) 835-0324.</p>
        <p>Hartsdale DeSanti Plaza Sculpture Project: ''Tinted Reflections II,'' sculpture by Anthony Krauss. Through March 1. DeSanti Plaza, across from Metro-North. (914) 478-4630.</p>
        <p>Hudson ''In Our Name: Iraqi Children in War,'' paintings by Christine Heller. Jan. 27 through Feb. 25. Reception: Jan. 27, 6 to 8 p.m. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, noon to 5 p.m. Hudson Opera House, 327 Warren Street. (518) 822-1438.</p>
        <p>Katonah Sculpture by Michael Steiner. Through April 22. ''Michael Krondl: Rising Water, Falling Water,'' photographic mural. Through March 8. ''The Way Things Go,'' video documenting a mad science experiment. ''Tools As Art: The Hechinger Collection,'' curated by Sarah Tanguy. Through April 8. Admission: $3 and $5. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Katonah Museum of Art, Route 22 at Jay Street. (914) 232-9555.</p>
        <p>Larchmont ''Just a Moment,'' photography by Sid Hecker. Through Jan. 30. Hours: Mondays and Thursdays, 9 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Tuesdays and Wednesdays, 9 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Larchmont Public Library, 121 Larchmont Avenue. (914) 834-2281.</p>
        <p>New Rochelle ''Racing on a Broken Road,'' exhibit on the Underground Railroad. Through March 4. Hours: Tuesdays and Wednesdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Thursdays and Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Castle Gallery, 29 Castle Place. (914) 654-5423.</p>
        <p>New Rochelle ''Remembering the New York-Westchester-Boston Railway in New Rochelle,'' with artifacts, maps and photographs. Hours: Mondays, Tuesdays and Thursdays 9 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Wednesdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Fridays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. New Rochelle Public Library, Lawton Street. (914) 632-7878.</p>
        <p>Newburgh Decorative works curated by Elizabeth Oliver. Through Feb. 25. Yellow Bird Gallery, 19 Front Street. (845) 561-7204.</p>
        <p>Port Chester ''Pollinia,'' ceramic sculpture by Leigh Taylor Mickelson. Through Jan. 27. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Clay Art Center, 40 Beech Street. (914) 937-2047.</p>
        <p>Poughkeepsie ''For the People: American Mural Drawings of the 1930s and 1940s,'' group show. Through March 11. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Vassar College, Frances Lehman Loeb Art Center. (845) 437-5632.</p>
        <p>Purchase ''Crossing the Boulevard: Strangers, Neighbors, Aliens in a New America.'' Through Jan. 27. $3 to $5; members and children 12 and under, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Neuberger Museum of Art, 735 Anderson Hill Road. (914) 251-6100.</p>
        <p>Rockville Centre ''Poor Art Student ... Strike 3!'' mixed-media group show of student artwork, curated by Cristina Pugliese. Through Wednesday. Free. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Molloy College Art Gallery, 1000 Hempstead Avenue. (516) 678-5000.</p>
        <p>Rye ''Cutting Across Cultures: The Art of Papercutting, Then and Now,'' works by traditional and contemporary paper-cutting artists. Through Feb. 17. Rye Arts Center, 51 Milton Road. (914) 967-0700.</p>
        <p>Rye ''The Image Makers,'' works by members of the Westchester Photographic Society. Through Feb. 16. Rye Free Reading Room, 1061 Boston Post Road. (914) 967-0480.</p>
        <p>Rye ''Shells and Trees,'' works by Elasah Schaff. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Rye Nature Center, 873 Boston Post Road. (914) 967-5150.</p>
        <p>Valhalla ''Looser, Smoother, Faster,'' works by Eric Hongisto, Shoji Kato and Matt King. Through Feb. 24. Reception: Thursday, 4 to 6 p.m. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 3 p.m.; Thursdays, 6 to 8 p.m. Fine Arts Gallery, 75 Grasslands Road. (914) 606-7867.</p>
        <p>West Point ''The Color of Loyalty: A Tribute to Dr. J. Robert Oppenheimer,'' works of Linda Jean Fisher. Through Feb. 11. Hours: daily, 9 a.m. to 4 p.m. 1929 Gallery, Eisenhower Hall, United States Military Academy. (845) 938-2782.</p>
        <p>White Plains ''Once Upon a Time  the Art of Children's Book Illustration,'' work of Howard Fine, Yumi Heo and Mary O'Keefe Young. Through Feb. 28. Free. White Plains Public Library, 100 Martine Avenue. (914) 422-1480.</p>
        <p>Woodstock ''Nature Without Glass,'' pinhole photographs by Mark Stetler. Through Feb. 12. Hours: Thursdays through Mondays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Gallery B.M.G., 12 Tannery Brook Road. (845) 679-0027.</p>
        <p>Woodstock ''Exhibit A,'' group show. Through Feb. 4. Hours: Thursdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Varga Gallery, 130 Tinker Street. (845) 679-4005.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
