<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gun Making as an Art as Well as a Business</title>
    <meta content="21ctcoltCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/21/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/21ctcolt.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1820302"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wadsworth Atheneum (Hartford, Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Genocchio, Benjamin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Colt, Samuel (1814-62)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Colt, Samuel</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE6D71130F932A15752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="602" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gun Making as an Art as Well as a Business</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Gun Making as an Art as Well as a Business</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BENJAMIN GENOCCHIO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Genocchio, Benjamin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Benjamin Genocchio reviews exhibition Samuel Colt: Arms, Art and Invention at Wadsworth Atheneum in Hartford, Conn; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An engrossing exhibition at the Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art is the first show to document the colorful life and business career of Samuel Colt, the firearms manufacturer and shameless self-promoter.</p>
        <p>As expected, the extensive Colt firearms collections, donated to the museum by his widow, Elizabeth Hart Jarvis Colt, in 1905, draws the eye, but there is much else of interest here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A show at the Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art is the first show to document the colorful life and business career of Samuel Colt, the firearms maker.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An engrossing exhibition at the Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art is the first show to document the colorful life and business career of Samuel Colt, the firearms manufacturer and shameless self-promoter.</p>
        <p>As expected, the extensive Colt firearms collections, donated to the museum by his widow, Elizabeth Hart Jarvis Colt, in 1905, draws the eye, but there is much else of interest here.</p>
        <p>Colt (1814-1862) was a canny promoter of his products. In the 1850s he commissioned the frontier artist George Catlin to paint a series of pictures that showed people hunting with Colt guns -- several of these paintings are on view. There is also information about Colt's achievements as a technological innovator and industrial entrepreneur, including gun-design schematics.</p>
        <p>Arranged loosely into nine themes, the exhibition opens with a display on the development of the revolving firearm by Colt in the early 1830s. Like many scientific and technological breakthroughs, it happened by accident: after Colt dropped out of school, he was packed off by his parents, at age 16, to work as a crew member on a Boston brig, where, the story goes, he observed that the locking mechanism of the ship's wheel might also be used to house multiple, revolving barrels of a pistol. Colt quickly whittled a wooden model. This was the germ of the revolutionary idea for the famous Colt revolver.</p>
        <p>When Colt returned to Hartford the following year, he hired Anson Chase, a gunmaker, to create a prototype. The result was, as an exhibition label says, ''the first multishot weapon to automatically rotate its cylinder with the action of its hammer -- the spring mechanism that strikes off the powder charge.'' To finance his early prototypes, Colt worked as a traveling salesmen demonstrating the uses and applications of nitrous oxide, or laughing gas.</p>
        <p>The exhibition charts Colt's efforts to perfect his new revolver design and cost-efficient manufacturing techniques. He took several years to get it right, initially going bankrupt. But once perfected, Colt's guns became a market leader.</p>
        <p>To keep up with demand, he built an arms factory in Hartford, with state-of-the-art machines and dedicated production lines; back then it was one of the most technologically advanced factories in the world. He even built an area called Coltsville, which had housing for employees, a library and a community center.</p>
        <p>Colt's pistols are beautiful pieces of machinery and, for their time, the world's most efficient weapons, combining a functional simplicity with a formal elegance. Colt liked to juxtapose materials, colors and finishes to heighten visual appeal. Some of the revolvers have expertly carved or inlaid handles and gun barrels with a seductive black-blue tinge.</p>
        <p>Colt was apparently indifferent to the uses of his products; he sold arms to whoever would pay. Buyers included Czar Alexander II of Russia, the Japanese shogun Tokugawa Yoshinobu and Sultan Abd al-Majid of Turkey.</p>
        <p>Colt even sold guns to opposing forces -- during the Crimean war (1853-56), he supplied guns to both the British and the Russians. To him, it was just business.</p>
        <p>In gratitude, his customers often gave him lavish gifts, several of which are on view, including enormous diamond rings, medals, vases, swords and other trinkets.</p>
        <p>One of the most astonishing gifts on display here is a gold and diamond snuffbox given to Colt by the czar and fitted at its center with a blue enamel plaque bearing the czar's monogram in diamonds beneath a diamond-studded crown. Not bad for a school dropout.</p>
        <p>''Samuel Colt: Arms, Art and Invention,'' Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art, 600 Main Street, Hartford, through March 4. Information can be found at (860) 278-2670 or www.wadsworthatheneum.org.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
