<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Funny Girl</title>
    <meta content="21WWLN--Q4.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/21/magazine/21WWLN_Q4.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1820227"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 1-21-07: QUESTIONS FOR SARAH SILVERMAN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Comedy and Humor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Silverman, Sarah</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Solomon, Deborah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Comedy and Humor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Comedy and Humor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Comedy Central</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Silverman, Sarah</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E2DB1030F932A15752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="656" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Funny Girl</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Funny Girl</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SOLOMON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Solomon, Deborah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Deborah Solomon interview with comedian Sarah Silverman; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q: The opening credits of your new television sitcom, ''The Sarah Silverman Program,'' include a scenic glimpse of a cemetery plot, as your voice explains that your parents are both deceased. Is that actually true? No. They're both pretty retired.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The comedian talks about her new sitcom, shock comedy, her adolescent depression and the significance of ‘‘Borat.’’</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q: The opening credits of your new television sitcom, ''The Sarah Silverman Program,'' include a scenic glimpse of a cemetery plot, as your voice explains that your parents are both deceased. Is that actually true? No. They're both pretty retired.</p>
        <p>How do they feel about being knocked off in your show, which makes its debut on Comedy Central on Feb. 1? They're fine with it. It was a way to bring a little bit of pathos to a self-centered character. It's like Mr. Rogers said, There isn't anyone you couldn't love if you knew their whole story, and I figured if I added dead parents --</p>
        <p>Even so, the show's protagonist, who is named Sarah Silverman, is not exactly Mr. Rogers's type. A model of political incorrectness, she becomes enraged when she is forced to watch a commercial for a humanitarian-aid group. Whom is she based on? I would describe her as ignorant and arrogant. The character is a lot of myself and a lot of my mother.</p>
        <p>Much like Sacha Baron Cohen, you specialize in a kind of shock comedy that seems designed to give offense. What do you think of him? ''Borat'' was the most retarded yet most important movie I've seen in many years.</p>
        <p>In the documentary ''The Aristocrats,'' you set a new record for outrageousness by claiming, with a straight face, ''Joe Franklin raped me,'' referring to the elderly television host. I heard that he threatened to sue you. I'm pretty sure he wasn't really mad. I think he was just milking the extra publicity.</p>
        <p>Do you see your work as social commentary? I don't see it as anything. I try not to look at it. Deconstruction is a comedy killer.</p>
        <p>How are things going with your comedic other, Jimmy Kimmel? Excellently! All my friends are comics, but I don't know that you would know them -- Mark Cohen, Doug Benson, Todd Glass, Todd Barry.</p>
        <p>Why don't you have any female friends? Tig Notaro, she's a woman. She's probably one of my best friends. She's a comedian.</p>
        <p>Tell us about your childhood in Bedford, N.H., where you were the youngest of four daughters. Isn't your oldest sister a rabbi? She got into it on her own, after grad school, even. We grew up in a place with very few Jews. I didn't look like the other kids. I had hairy legs, hairy arms, hair everywhere. I looked like a little monkey.</p>
        <p>This doesn't sound like a description of an idyllic childhood. I wouldn't want to do it again. I had a lot of depression as a kid.</p>
        <p>During adolescence, you mean? From 13 to 16. I didn't go to school for months. It was so awful. I didn't know how to express what it was. I remember trying to explain it to my stepdad and saying, ''I feel like that terrible homesick feeling, but I'm home.''</p>
        <p>Were you treated at the time for depression? I had very bad experiences with doctors. I got sent to a psychiatrist who put me on Xanax when I was 13. I went back for my next visit, and he had killed himself.</p>
        <p>That's a pretty good story, but is it true? I swear to God. I had to wait for the rest of the hour for my mom to pick me up.</p>
        <p>You eventually wound up at New York University, where you dropped out after a year to work in comedy clubs. I didn't really drop out. I just didn't go back.</p>
        <p>Do you wish your new show were appearing on HBO, if only because Comedy Central bleeps out the swear words? No, I spent two years developing shows at HBO, right before this. I wrote two pilots with Larry Charles. Neither of them was even shot. They're so good too.</p>
        <p>And then you were rescued by Comedy Central. Yes, I'm one of those lucky people who's attracted to people who like me.</p>
        <p>DEBORAH SOLOMON</p>
        <p>THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 1-21-07: QUESTIONS FOR SARAH SILVERMAN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
