<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Governor Brokers Truce For Darfur</title>
    <meta content="11darfur" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/11/world/africa/11darfur.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1818003"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sudan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Darfur (Sudan)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Save Darfur Coalition</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Polgreen, Lydia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richardson, Bill (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bashir, Omar Hassan Al- (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sudan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Sudan</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Darfur (Sudan)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Sudan</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Richardson, Bill</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bashir, Omar Hassan Al-</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070111T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E5DA1230F932A25752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="357" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Governor Brokers Truce For Darfur</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. Governor Brokers Truce for Darfur</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYDIA POLGREEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Polgreen, Lydia</byline>
      <dateline>DAKAR, Senegal, Jan. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Omar Hassan al-Bashir of Sudan and leaders of several rebel factions in Darfur agree to 60-day cease-fire; truce is brokered by Gov Bill Richardson of New Mexico, who is in Sudan on behalf of Save Darfur Coalition, groups trying to stem violence there; peace agreement signed last May between government and one rebel faction has foundered, and Bashir's government has repeatedly rejected United Nations peacekeeping force; Bashir claims non-African peacekeepers would be seen as 'colonialists'; Richardson says cease-fire is first step in political process that would lead to UN force; notes that leaders of two rebel factions that did not sign earlier agreement have agreed to new cease-fire (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Omar Hassan al-Bashir of Sudan and leaders of several rebel factions in Darfur, the western Sudanese region, agreed Wednesday to a 60-day cease-fire in separate meetings with Gov. Bill Richardson of New Mexico, a former American ambassador to the United Nations, according to a statement by Mr. Richardson and Mr. Bashir.</p>
        <p>Mr. Richardson went to Sudan on behalf of the Save Darfur Coalition of groups trying to stem the violence in Darfur, to try to break the deadlock over who will police the region.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sudan’s president and leaders of rebel factions agreed to a 60-day cease-fire in meetings with Gov. Bill Richardson of New Mexico.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Omar Hassan al-Bashir of Sudan and leaders of several rebel factions in Darfur, the western Sudanese region, agreed Wednesday to a 60-day cease-fire in separate meetings with Gov. Bill Richardson of New Mexico, a former American ambassador to the United Nations, according to a statement by Mr. Richardson and Mr. Bashir.</p>
        <p>Mr. Richardson went to Sudan on behalf of the Save Darfur Coalition of groups trying to stem the violence in Darfur, to try to break the deadlock over who will police the region.</p>
        <p>A peace agreement signed last May between the government and one rebel faction has foundered, and the government has repeatedly rejected a United Nations peacekeeping force.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bashir reiterated his opposition to such a force on Wednesday, telling The Associated Press that non-African peacekeepers would be seen as ''colonialists.'' But the Bashir-Richardson statement said he had agreed to halt military operations to allow time for a political settlement to the crisis to emerge.</p>
        <p>''What is lacking is a political process that leads to a U.N. force,'' Mr. Richardson said by telephone from Khartoum, the capital. ''I think this 60-day cease-fire is at least a step.''</p>
        <p>He said the leaders of two rebel factions that did not sign the May agreement, the Justice and Equality Movement and a splinter group of the Sudan Liberation Army, had also agreed to the new cease-fire. But it is not clear if they represent all dissident factions, because the rebel groups have fractured and realigned several times in the past year.</p>
        <p>The Darfur crisis, a conflict over land, identity and self-determination that has killed at least 200,000 people and driven 2.5 million from their homes, has deepened in the past year despite the peace agreement. Recently, escalating violence in Sudan has forced aid agencies to curtail operations and has destabilized Chad and the Central African Republic.</p>
        <p>Mr. Richardson, who last year helped negotiate the release of an American journalist charged with espionage in Sudan, has known Mr. Bashir for a decade and has international contacts made as ambassador in the Clinton administration. He is expected to seek the Democratic nomination for president next year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
