<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Green Is the Color of Coaches' Parachutes</title>
    <meta content="11coaches" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/11/sports/ncaafootball/11coaches.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1818060"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Florida</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Meyer, Urban</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070111T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E7D81230F932A25752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="848" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Green Is the Color of Coaches' Parachutes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Green Is the Color of Coaches’ Parachutes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Sandomir Sports Business column discusses kinds of bonuses college football coaches receive above and beyond base salaries; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If Florida Coach Urban Meyer is the type of fellow to watch his money roll in, then he has had plenty to admire since he took the job in 2004, and even more since his Gators won the national championship Monday.</p>
        <p>Like most top coaches, Meyer is paid a base salary ($231,750) that is less than a third of what the university's president makes, and one that would not overwhelm critics of how academics are subverted to big-time sports at major universities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like most top coaches, Florida's Urban Meyer is paid a base salary, but is guaranteed much more through news-media payments, apparel deals and incentives based on his team’s performance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If Florida Coach Urban Meyer is the type of fellow to watch his money roll in, then he has had plenty to admire since he took the job in 2004, and even more since his Gators won the national championship Monday.</p>
        <p>Like most top coaches, Meyer is paid a base salary ($231,750) that is less than a third of what the university's president makes, and one that would not overwhelm critics of how academics are subverted to big-time sports at major universities.</p>
        <p>But like many football coaches at elite Division I-A programs, Meyer is guaranteed much more through news-media payments, apparel deals and other mostly private sources, as well as through incentives based on his team's performance.</p>
        <p>Upon signing his seven-year contract, Meyer received a $500,000 signing bonus. The contract, available online with many other coaches' deals on USAToday.com, shows that he receives $300,000 annually to appear on his local TV show, participate in Web site chats, make promotional appearances and sign helmets and footballs. He receives $500,000 through Florida's apparel deal and $200,000 to speak 20 times a year to Gator Clubs.</p>
        <p>Yes, there is more. A $60,000 expense account. Two cars, with the insurance paid. A $100,000 deposit into whatever investment he chooses. Another $100,000 for the education of his son and two daughters.</p>
        <p>And a longevity payment (a bonus for not breaking a contract) of $250,000 this year, which is part of a larger pool of cash that will add up to $2.1 million if Meyer stays at Florida until the end of the 2011 season.</p>
        <p>If all this were not enough to make him stay longer than Larry Brown, then he has incentives to perk him up. For beating Arkansas in the Southeastern Conference title game, he got $75,000. For beating Ohio State in the Bowl Championship Series title game, he got $250,000. For finishing No. 1 in the Associated Press poll, he will get $50,000.</p>
        <p>If not for Jim Grobe of Wake Forest being the A.P. national coach of the year and Houston Nutt of Arkansas being voted coach of the year in the SEC, Meyer would have collected another $75,000.</p>
        <p>But no one can vote away his 12 free seats at Ben Hill Griffin Stadium.</p>
        <p>Colleges, their boosters and others who love their varsity programs can be mighty sweet to winning coaches. On Aug. 27, 2004, in his seventh year as the coach at Texas -- but 17 months before winning a national title -- Mack Brown received a one-time $1.6 million birthday gift. That is in addition to the university's annual $300,000 deposit into a special Mack Brown account.</p>
        <p>Jim Tressel of Ohio State, whose Buckeyes lost to the Gators on Monday night, is paid nearly as well as Meyer. His $366,000 base salary in 2006 was augmented by $524,000 for TV and radio appearances; $429,000 from the Buckeyes' Nike deal; and $5,000 to help run summer youth football camps on the Columbus campus. His postseason football incentive plan is simpler than Meyer's: $200,000 for playing in the national championship game.</p>
        <p>But Tressel can earn another $190,000 to $325,000 based on the academic performance of his players, like their yearly graduation rates, the percentage of players with grade point averages above 3.0 at the end of each quarter and the percentage of players with annual G.P.A. increases.</p>
        <p>Dennis R. Howard, a business professor at the Warsaw Sports Marketing Center at the University of Oregon, analyzes coaches' contracts and wonders why academic incentives are such minor elements of the agreements.</p>
        <p>''I'd like to see coaches made accountable for G.P.A.s and graduation rates,'' Howard said during an interview. ''Perhaps football-related bonuses would be activated only when coaches meet the academic standards. Then the school's first responsibility would be to make the players graduate.''</p>
        <p>Howard and three colleagues looked at the available contracts of coaches in bowl games played from Jan. 1 to Jan. 8 and found, not surprisingly, that the maximum academic bonus averaged 2.7 percent of a coach's maximum compensation, while football performance bonuses averaged 13.3 percent.</p>
        <p>''You're incentivized to win,'' said Paul Swangard, the Warsaw Center's managing director. ''Why is that the priority? Coaches' salaries have grown to amazing levels. It's time to say time out and reflect on what's happening.''</p>
        <p>On Swangard and Howard's campus is an example of enlightened capitalism, if not attention to the notion of graduating student-athletes. Mike Bellotti, the Oregon football coach, has a clause in his contract that gives him 8 percent of gross season-ticket revenues, if season tickets exceed 40,000. For 2006, Swangard and Howard said, Bellotti has earned at least $700,000 by encouraging the act of spectating.</p>
        <p>Bobby Petrino's leave-taking from Louisville after winning the Orange Bowl to the Atlanta Falcons required that he pay the university $1 million because he left after the first season of a 10-year contract. Had Petrino remained with the Cardinals through 2016, his guaranteed compensation would have risen to $2.6 million, and he would have been eligible for $1 million bonuses midway through 2007, 2010 and 2013, and a final one for $2 million in 2015.</p>
        <p>SPORTS BUSINESS E-mail: sportsbiz@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: sportsbiz@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
