<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spitzer Orders Sharp Cuts In Cost of Prisoner Phone Calls</title>
    <meta content="09calls" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/09/nyregion/09calls.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1817591"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Verizon Communications</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Confessore, Nicholas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spitzer, Eliot (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E3D71530F93AA35752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="598" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spitzer Orders Sharp Cuts In Cost of Prisoner Phone Calls</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Spitzer Orders Sharp Cuts in Cost of Prisoner Phone Calls</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS CONFESSORE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Confessore, Nicholas</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, Jan. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Gov Eliot Spitzer reduces charges that relatives and friends of inmates incur on collect calls from prison; reverses policy of predecessor George E Pataki under which inmates were charged far higher fees than public for same calls; telephone provider Verizon must return more than half of profits from prison calls; policy will end state's sharing of revenue from phone calls (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer struck an early blow at the policies of his predecessor on Monday, sharply reducing steep Pataki-era charges that relatives and friends of inmates in New York State's prisons have had to pay on collect telephone calls from them.</p>
        <p>The governor's move, effective April 1, came one day before state lawyers were to appear before the state's highest court to defend the old policy, under which inmates were charged far higher fees than the public would be for the same calls.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer sharply reduced steep Pataki-era charges that relatives and friends of inmates in New York State’s prisons have had to pay on collect telephone calls from them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer struck an early blow at the policies of his predecessor on Monday, sharply reducing steep Pataki-era charges that relatives and friends of inmates in New York State's prisons have had to pay on collect telephone calls from them.</p>
        <p>The governor's move, effective April 1, came one day before state lawyers were to appear before the state's highest court to defend the old policy, under which inmates were charged far higher fees than the public would be for the same calls.</p>
        <p>''In light of assuring that as much information is available to the court and plaintiffs as possible, we decided to announce it today,'' said Paul Larrabee, a spokesman for Mr. Spitzer.</p>
        <p>Since 1996, the telephone company that provides calling services to state inmates, currently Verizon, has been required to return more than half its profits to the state. The arrangement earned the state $16 million in 2005. The phone companies passed along those charges to people accepting inmates' collect calls, in some cases tripling the price of those calls, according to prisoners' rights groups.</p>
        <p>The Pataki administration had aggressively defended the charges, arguing that they helped pay for services to inmates and extra security features to prevent prison phones from being used to commit fraud or other crimes.</p>
        <p>But nonprofit groups have long described the practice as exploitative and counterproductive, saying that both prisoners and the public benefited when inmates could readily stay in touch with their wives, husbands and parents. They also argued that the practice essentially charged families for their relatives' incarceration.</p>
        <p>''They were taking advantage of the high price to cover the cost of programs and services that the prison system should be providing in any case,'' said Robert Gangi, the executive director of the Correctional Association of New York, a nonprofit group that monitors conditions in state prisons.</p>
        <p>Legislation to end the high charges had passed the Democratic-controlled State Assembly several times in recent years but had stalled in the Senate. Mr. Spitzer, however, signaled during last year's gubernatorial campaign that he would change the policy if elected. Yesterday, he was warmly praised by advocates who had pressed for the change.</p>
        <p>''This is a victory for all New Yorkers because increased contact with family members is proven to reduce recidivism rates after release,'' said Annette Dickerson, coordinator of the New York Campaign for Telephone Justice, which pushed for the change. Ms. Dickerson is also the director of education at the Center for Constitutional Rights, which filed suit two years ago on behalf of prisoners' families to end the charges.</p>
        <p>Most states still charge their prison inmates higher rates for telephone calls than are paid by the public, often through direct surcharges or commissions. Mr. Spitzer's move makes New York one of only a few that have ended the practice.</p>
        <p>Under the arrangement that will take effect April 1, the state will not share in any revenue from the phone calls. Mr. Larrabee said that the cost of a 20-minute call would fall to about $3, from about $6.20. Inmates in New York prisons are allowed to make only collect calls.</p>
        <p>Prisoner advocates also praised Mr. Spitzer for abolishing the high charges without abolishing any of the prison programs for which the fees helped pay. Those programs -- including AIDS medications and family reunion programs -- must now be paid for out of general revenues, another reason why Mr. Spitzer, who will soon present next year's budget, made the announcement on Monday.</p>
        <p>''We are preparing the state budget,'' Mr. Larrabee said. ''And we're no longer going to have that revenue stream.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
