<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Critic's Choice: New DVDs</title>
    <meta content="09dvd" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/09/movies/homevideo/09dvd.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1817511"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Critics Choice"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Disney, Walt, Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kehr, Dave</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/DVD and Video</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">DVD (Digital Versatile Disk)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Animated Films</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cartoons and Cartoonists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animated Films</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DVD (Digital Versatile Disk)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cartoons and Cartoonists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Disney, Walt, Co</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Kehr, Dave</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Maltin, Leonard</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E7D91530F93AA35752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1123" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Critic's Choice: New DVDs</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New DVDs: Walt Disney Treasures</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dave Kehr</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kehr, Dave</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dave Kehr reviews new DVD collection Disney Treasures; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Walt Disney Treasures</p>
        <p>The critic Leonard Maltin has been rooting through the Disney archives again, and a result is four more double-disc sets in the limited-edition ''Walt Disney Treasures'' series.</p>
        <p>The ''Treasures'' collections, which come packed in tin boxes and usually contain a brochure and a souvenir postcard or two, are aimed at adult consumers who grew up with Walt Disney on television, or those with a deeper interest in animation and the history of Walt Disney Productions. Now that the older Disney cartoons, particularly those in black and white, have largely disappeared from circulation, the ''Treasures'' represent a rare opportunity to see the formative shorts that led up to the features and were testing grounds for experimental animation techniques and new narrative approaches.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Four new double-disc sets are added to the limited edition "Walt Disney Treasures" collection.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Walt Disney Treasures</p>
        <p>The critic Leonard Maltin has been rooting through the Disney archives again, and a result is four more double-disc sets in the limited-edition ''Walt Disney Treasures'' series.</p>
        <p>The ''Treasures'' collections, which come packed in tin boxes and usually contain a brochure and a souvenir postcard or two, are aimed at adult consumers who grew up with Walt Disney on television, or those with a deeper interest in animation and the history of Walt Disney Productions. Now that the older Disney cartoons, particularly those in black and white, have largely disappeared from circulation, the ''Treasures'' represent a rare opportunity to see the formative shorts that led up to the features and were testing grounds for experimental animation techniques and new narrative approaches.</p>
        <p>There are four sets in the new batch. ''The Mickey Mouse Club Featuring the Hardy Boys'' collects episodes from the long-running serial originally broadcast in the late 1950s and is strictly of nostalgic interest. ''The Complete Pluto, Volume Two'' takes Mickey's oddly disadvantaged animal companion (why is Pluto the only resident of Disneyland who isn't able to speak?) from 1947 to 1951, and represents Disney product at its least distinguished, most industrial level.</p>
        <p>Far more intriguing are ''Your Host, Walt Disney'' -- five episodes from Disney's weekly television show, all with Uncle Walt -- and, supremely, ''More Silly Symphonies, Volume Two,'' a gathering of work from 1929 to 1938, most of it very seldom seen.</p>
        <p>Disney began producing the ''Silly Symphonies'' in 1929 to complement his immensely popular Mickey Mouse cartoons. These shorts have no recurring characters and little if any dialogue; rather, they feature Busby Berkeley-like chorus lines of rubber-limbed figures going through their paces to a synchronized musical score.</p>
        <p>The scores were cobbled together by Carl Stalling, the former theater organist Disney had met back in Kansas City, Mo., when he was first starting out, and the animation was largely the work of Ub Iwerks, an eccentric loner, also an associate from the Kansas City days, who had become Disney's leading artist. (Mr. Stalling would gain his greatest fame when he moved to Warner Brothers to create the unforgettable, free-form soundtracks of the ''Merrie Melodies'' series.)</p>
        <p>The first ''Silly Symphony,'' based on an idea by Mr. Stalling, was ''Skeleton Dance'' (featured in the first ''Treasures'' volume of ''Silly Symphonies'') with a cast of tap-dancing cadavers and low-flying bats. Though theater owners feared that audiences would be horrified by the macabre imagery, ''Skeleton Dance'' became an enormous success and helped to draw serious critical attention to the fledgling studio. Included in the new collection is ''Hell's Bells,'' the immediate follow-up to ''Skeleton Dance'' and an even more impressive piece, featuring a jazz band of demons who play snippets from ''Funeral March of a Marionette'' in perfect synchronization.</p>
        <p>''Hell's Bells'' is looser and funnier than ''Skeleton Dance,'' and it reveals the strong influence of the Fleischer school: a hipper, more urban style than Disney's. The Fleischer brothers, Dave and Max, were big-city boys, whose cartoons were full of sex (the garter-snapping flapper Betty Boop was their leading character by that time) and often scored by leading jazz musicians, including Louis Armstrong and Cab Calloway. Disney, by comparison, was Guy Lombardo, piping sweet tunes to a public yearning for the pastoral.</p>
        <p>It's hard today to reconstruct the enormous enthusiasm that greeted the first Disney shorts. Compared with the work of his (then) better-known East Coast competitors, the Fleischers, Disney's early efforts seem conspicuously lacking in draftsmanship and imagination; the Fleischers' ''Ko-Ko's Earth Control,'' from 1928, displays a sophistication in its humor and a polish in its execution miles beyond what Disney was capable of at the time.</p>
        <p>But Disney, as Neal Gabler documents in his new biography, ''Walt Disney'' (Knopf), had a vision and drive that the Fleischers did not. Where Fleischer films were animated as silent works and then synchronized to what often sounds like an improvised music and effects track, Disney films exploited an ingenious method that allowed animators to time their work to prerecorded scores and spoken dialogue. The results were much more natural and created the convincing illusion that voices were issuing from the drawn figures.</p>
        <p>Disney trumped the Fleischers again when he signed an agreement with the Technicolor Corporation that gave him exclusive use of a dramatically improved three-color process for a period of two years. Vastly superior to any other color process on the market, three-color Technicolor gave Disney's films a visual pop unlike that of any others in the field. The color, draftsmanship and expressivity of movement seem to grow dramatically from film to film in the early 30s, as the shaded outlines and depth effects of ''Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs'' (1937), the first Disney feature, begin to emerge in films like ''The Goddess of Spring'' (1934) and ''Three Blind Mouseketeers'' (1936).</p>
        <p>Mr. Gabler's book portrays Disney as a driven perfectionist, often unhappy with the quality of his product, particularly after World War II, as the industry started to change and the money available to him began to shrink. That persistent dissatisfaction was not allowed to surface in ''Uncle Walt,'' the carefully constructed television personality that Disney displayed in his weekly appearances. In his television incarnation, wonderfully delineated in the five specials that Mr. Maltin has chosen for the ''Your Host, Walt Disney'' set, Disney seemed to become America's favorite uncle, presiding over the 1950s with an optimism and a faith in steady technological advancement, seeming to summarize the decade more than anyone else.</p>
        <p>If Dwight Eisenhower was president of the American people, Walt Disney was president of the American imagination, gently urging the country toward greater technological feats (and, as a reward, bigger and better toys). It is a position that has not been occupied since Disney's death in 1966, despite strong campaigns by Steven Spielberg, George Lucas and others. Applications for the post are still being accepted, but it seems unlikely to be filled any time soon. Walt Disney Video, $32.99 each; all G, except ''Your Host, Walt Disney,'' which is not rated.</p>
        <p>Also Out Today</p>
        <p>THE ILLUSIONIST -- A magician (Edward Norton) is drawn into the court intrigue of 19th-century Vienna. With Jessica Biel and Paul Giamatti; Neil Burger directed. 20th Century Fox, $29.99, PG-13.</p>
        <p>EXTRAS: THE COMPLETE FIRST SEASON -- Ricky Gervais's follow-up to ''The Office,'' centered on a lowly extra with great ambitions. Stephen Merchant and Mr. Gervais directed. HBO Home Video, $29.98, not rated.</p>
        <p>IDIOCRACY -- Mike Judge's ''Office Space'' flopped in theaters but became a cult favorite on DVD; maybe this new feature, with Luke Wilson as an ''average American'' projected 500 years into the future, will do the same. 20th Century Fox, $27.98, R.</p>
        <p>Critics Choice</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
