<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Accord Falls Far From the Tree</title>
    <meta content="08NUGGETaccord" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="0" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1817693"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E1DD1130F93AA35752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="236" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Accord Falls Far From the Tree</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE ULRICH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Introduced on Monday:Honda Accord Coupe Concept</p>
        <p>Is it real? Some automakers' concepts are nothing but car teases; Honda, bless them, moves its concepts swiftly to showrooms with few changes. Expect the 2008 Accord coupe to strongly resemble this sweet-looking machine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Introduced on Monday:Honda Accord Coupe Concept</p>
        <p>Is it real? Some automakers' concepts are nothing but car teases; Honda, bless them, moves its concepts swiftly to showrooms with few changes. Expect the 2008 Accord coupe to strongly resemble this sweet-looking machine.</p>
        <p>What's the point? Coupes are staging a comeback, and Honda wants its two-door Accord to lure a good chunk of under-30 buyers. Vastly more extroverted than the previous Accord coupe, the new model harvests styling cues from several of its two-door competitors -- including Nissan and Infiniti.</p>
        <p>What they said: Honda executives extolled the Accord's three decades of excellence, but the press conferences' choice of musical accompaniment may have summed up the new model best: ''I'll Bet You Look Good on the Dance Floor,'' by the Arctic Monkeys.</p>
        <p>What they didn't say: Compelling new coupes like this Accord, and its competitors from Ford, Scion and Nissan, will solidify the Toyota Solara's position as the segment's maiden aunt. The pressure will be on Toyota to swap Solara's flannel-petticoat exterior for something more silken and sexy.</p>
        <p>What makes it tick? Honda is being coy on particulars, but the eighth-generation Accord coupe and sedan will certainly continue to offer four- and six-cylinder engines.</p>
        <p>How much, how soon? The Accord coupe and sedan go on sale in the fall, probably starting below $20,000 and topping $30,000 for loaded versions.</p>
        <p>How's it look? Finally, not like the Accord sedan.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
