<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mazda's Chapter Two Rakes the Garden</title>
    <meta content="08NUGGETmazda" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="0" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1817694"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E1DD1130F93AA35752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="278" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mazda's Chapter Two Rakes the Garden</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM DIEM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Introduced on Monday: Mazda Ryuga design study</p>
        <p>Is it real? The Ryuga is concept No. 2 in a four-part series that began at the Los Angeles auto show last fall with a car named the Nagare, which means flow in Japanese. Ryuga is ''gracious flow.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Introduced on Monday: Mazda Ryuga design study</p>
        <p>Is it real? The Ryuga is concept No. 2 in a four-part series that began at the Los Angeles auto show last fall with a car named the Nagare, which means flow in Japanese. Ryuga is ''gracious flow.''</p>
        <p>What's the point? The idea is to build interest in a new look coming to Mazda through a series of design proposals revealed at the Los Angeles, Detroit, Geneva (in March) and Tokyo (October) auto shows.</p>
        <p>What they said: This series of concepts ''will ultimately sow the seeds for a completely new generation of Mazda vehicles,'' said Laurens van den Acker, general manager of Mazda's design division. It is ''an exploration -- inspired by nature -- into how we can capture its motion, energy and beauty and translate it into powerful and exciting automobiles.''</p>
        <p>What they didn't say: The year-long ''flow'' journey gives Mazda something to talk about that is more interesting than a facelift of the Tribute S.U.V.</p>
        <p>What makes it tick? A 2.5-liter Flex Fuel engine is coupled to a six-speed automatic transmission. E85 is the marketing solution to make red hot cars green.</p>
        <p>How much, how soon? We'll never see this exact shape on the road, but we might see a two-door four-passenger sports car one day.</p>
        <p>How's it look? The company's designers and language specialists have stretched their definitions of ''inspired by nature'' to the breaking point. The parallel scratch marks on the side may well be inspired by raked Japanese rock gardens, but the high belt line and low roof line are more likely inspired by the strong market response to those features on the Chrysler 300.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
