<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BMW 3 Series Flips Its Lid, the Hard Way</title>
    <meta content="07NUGGETbmw" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="0" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1817689"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E3DD1130F93AA35752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="266" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BMW 3 Series Flips Its Lid, the Hard Way</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM McCRAW</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Introduced on Sunday: 2007 BMW 3 Series convertible</p>
        <p>Is it real? Real, indeed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Introduced on Sunday: 2007 BMW 3 Series convertible</p>
        <p>Is it real? Real, indeed.</p>
        <p>What's the point? The 3 Series convertible with the traditional fabric top has been out of production for some time and the new one, with its folding and disappearing steel top, will fill the void in the lineup.</p>
        <p>What they said: ''BMW has over 70 years of experience in producing dynamic convertibles'' Michael Ganal, BMW board member, said of the new droptop. ''Our expertise and our innovative spirit are reflected in this fourth-generation BMW 3 Series convertible.''</p>
        <p>What they didn't say: That it's a poke in the eye of the Mercedes-Benz CLK Cabriolet. We can see ourselves flying up the Pacific Coast Highway in this car -- top down, speed up, mood mellow.</p>
        <p>What makes it tick? The new 3 Series convertible will come in four versions: a four-cylinder 320i and three in-line six cylinder versions, 325i, 328i and 335i, with power ranging from 170 to 300 horsepower.</p>
        <p>How much, how soon? BMW officials confided that the steel-top convertible will start showing up in dealerships at the end of March, just in time for the summer selling season. The price will be about 5 percent higher than the outgoing fabric-top convertible, topping out at just under $50,000 for the max-performance 335i version.</p>
        <p>How's it look? We will defer to the car designer Fabrizio Giugiaro, who was on the BMW stand when it was introduced, along with his famous father, Giorgetto Giugiaro, the founder of ItalDesign. The younger Guigiaro pronounced it an unqualified success, and said he especially liked the rear-end treatment.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
