<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When 510 Horsepower Just Isn't Enough, Go For 600!</title>
    <meta content="09NUGGETviper" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="0" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1817697"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <person class="indexing_service">Montoya, Juan Pablo</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E0DD1130F93AA35752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="274" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When 510 Horsepower Just Isn't Enough, Go For 600!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM McCRAW</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Introduced on Tuesday: 2008 Dodge Viper SRT10</p>
        <p>Is it real? Real enough to make Ford GT (550 horsepower) and Corvette Z06 (500 horsepower) owners deflate into a puddle of power envy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Introduced on Tuesday: 2008 Dodge Viper SRT10</p>
        <p>Is it real? Real enough to make Ford GT (550 horsepower) and Corvette Z06 (500 horsepower) owners deflate into a puddle of power envy.</p>
        <p>What's the point? In the small-volume premium sports car market segment, it's all about numbers, and this baby has numbers: 0-to-60 miles an hour in 3.7 seconds; 0-to-100 miles an hour and back to 0 again in just over 12 seconds flat; and 60-to-0 braking in less than 100 feet.</p>
        <p>What they said: Between introductions of Juan Pablo Montoya, Elliott Sadler and Kurt Busch, Dodge's star drivers, Chrysler Group's chief operating officer, Eric Ridenour, waxed poetic about the new Viper, quoting the numbers referenced above.</p>
        <p>What they didn't say: Dear crosstown rivals: See you on Woodward Avenue. Don't forget to bring your pinks!</p>
        <p>What makes it tick? The Chrysler Street &amp; Racing Technology (SRT) group has given the Viper coupe and convertible (which was not shown) a completely new 8.4-liter V-10 engine with variable valve timing and other mechanical tweaks that bump the output to 600 horsepower at 6,100 rpm. It's coupled to an improved, slicker-shifting 6-speed manual transmission.</p>
        <p>How much, how soon? The new Viper will go into production late in the spring and arrive at Dodge dealerships by midsummer. Pricing is expected to close in on $90,000 -- the hand-building process can only produce 3,000 Vipers a year running flat-out. Exclusivity has its price.</p>
        <p>How's it look? It looks even more menacing and angry than before. The long hood, with a new intake snorkel and six air extractors, will be your best clue that it's the powered-up 2008 version.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
