<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Menu Item at the Road Kill Cafe</title>
    <meta content="08NUGGETtrail" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="0" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1817695"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E1DD1130F93AA35752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="222" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Menu Item at the Road Kill Cafe</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERRY GARRETT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Introduced on Monday: Jeep Trailhawk design study</p>
        <p>Is it real? Let's hope not. As far as anyone can tell, this is just an old sketch that somehow came to life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Introduced on Monday: Jeep Trailhawk design study</p>
        <p>Is it real? Let's hope not. As far as anyone can tell, this is just an old sketch that somehow came to life.</p>
        <p>What's the point? Jeep is still trying to find a way to constructively fill showrooms. The Trailhawk would be an answer if the goal was merely to load up dealers' lots with more Jeeps like the Patriot and the Compass that won't sell.</p>
        <p>What they said: ''The Trailhawk's headlights give it the look of a bird of prey,'' said Trevor Creed, Chrysler Group's design chief. ''Or what might have resulted after a Wrangler and a Grand Cherokee had been parked alone together too long.''</p>
        <p>What they didn't say: The engine is the only thing worth remembering from this vehicle. It's a Bluetec diesel. Future Jeeps are likely to get them. That will please Jeep fanatics immensely, in particular those disenfranchised when the Liberty diesel was discontinued.</p>
        <p>What makes it tick? A 3.0-liter V-6 Bluetec common rail diesel engine that makes ''only'' 215 horsepower, but it's got enough torque -- 376 pounds-feet -- to crawl up a face on Mt. Rushmore.</p>
        <p>How much, how soon? Bluetec diesels should start appearing in DaimlerChrysler's new models next year. With any luck, the Trailhawk will never be seen again.</p>
        <p>How's it look? Like road kill.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
