<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cross-Check Brings Orr Five-Game Suspension</title>
    <meta content="01rangers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/01/sports/hockey/01rangers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1815800"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Washington Capitals</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caldwell, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ovechkin, Alexander</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Orr, Colton</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Washington Capitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E2D81630F932A35752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="559" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cross-Check Brings Orr Five-Game Suspension</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cross-Check Brings Orr Five-Game Suspension</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Rangers player Colton Orr is suspended five games for cross-checking Washington Capitals player Alexander Ovechkin in the head; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The National Hockey League suspended Rangers right wing Colton Orr for five games yesterday for cross-checking the Washington Capitals star Alexander Ovechkin in the head late in the Rangers' 4-1 victory Saturday night at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>Orr was involved in two fights, the second of which followed his hit of Ovechkin with 4 minutes 20 seconds left. Ovechkin, tied with Martin St. Louis of Tampa Bay for the league lead with 25 goals through Saturday, was not hurt.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The N.H.L. suspended Rangers right wing Colton Orr for five games Sunday for cross-checking the Washington Capitals star Alexander Ovechkin in the head late in the Rangers’ 4-1 victory Saturday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The National Hockey League suspended Rangers right wing Colton Orr for five games yesterday for cross-checking the Washington Capitals star Alexander Ovechkin in the head late in the Rangers' 4-1 victory Saturday night at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>Orr was involved in two fights, the second of which followed his hit of Ovechkin with 4 minutes 20 seconds left. Ovechkin, tied with Martin St. Louis of Tampa Bay for the league lead with 25 goals through Saturday, was not hurt.</p>
        <p>''The Rangers player's actions with his stick were reckless and dangerous,'' Colin Campbell, the N.H.L.'s senior executive vice president for hockey operations, said in a statement released by the league. ''Although no injury resulted, the action is unacceptable.''</p>
        <p>The league also suspended Washington left wing Donald Brashear for one game for punching Rangers defenseman Aaron Ward after Brashear fought left wing Brendan Shanahan with 12:21 left.</p>
        <p>Brashear, a notorious enforcer, was ejected for attempting to cause a deliberate injury. Ward later acknowledged that he might have provoked Brashear by asking what he called an obvious question -- perhaps why Brashear was fighting Shanahan, who is not known as a fighter.</p>
        <p>Except for a scrape on his chin, Shanahan escaped unharmed. And although he absorbed a beating from Brashear, he made a point.</p>
        <p>''When your leaders do things like that, clearly it demonstrates that they're willing to pay any price to win,'' Rangers Coach Tom Renney said after the Rangers ended a seven-game losing streak. ''That's how badly he wanted us to get out of what we'd been through seven times.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers had three major penalties for fighting, their highest total since Feb. 26, 2004, when they had three in a 6-3 victory against the Islanders.</p>
        <p>Fighting is practically passé in the post-lockout N.H.L. But the Rangers wanted to prove to their opponents -- and probably to themselves -- that they were not going to be passive, especially in the third period after blowing late leads to Florida and Tampa Bay in consecutive games during the losing streak.</p>
        <p>Renney noted that the brutish Brashear matched shifts with Jagr, the Rangers' highest-paid and most valuable player. Shanahan picked a fight with Brashear after he elbowed Jaromir Jagr in the face after a face-off.</p>
        <p>Jagr, the Rangers' captain, said of Shanahan, ''He is not only about big goals, but he protects his players.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers (19-17-4), who face the Devils on Tuesday in East Rutherford, N.J., played with intensity from the start Saturday.</p>
        <p>Defenseman Darius Kasparaitis drove Ovechkin to the ice with a hard check two minutes into the game. The collision led to a goal seconds later by Petr Prucha. The Rangers led, 3-0, after two periods.</p>
        <p>''The game was about us coming out with the first period the way we did, and the things that happened in the third period are secondary.'' Shanahan said.</p>
        <p>Orr challenged Brashear to a fight 12 minutes into the game, even throwing down his gloves, but Brashear left the ice in a line change after a face-off.</p>
        <p>Orr finally squared off with Brashear with less than a minute left in the second period, and Brashear slammed him to the ice. Although he had not been in a fight since March 30, Shanahan soon took his turn.</p>
        <p>''I am a little out of practice, but it is still fun when you are in them,'' Shanahan said.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
