<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Judge Rebuffs U.S. Scientist In Lawsuit Against Times</title>
    <meta content="13hatfill" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/13/us/13hatfill.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1818480"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Anthrax</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Libel and Slander</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Times</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Neil A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hilton, Claude M (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hatfill, Steven J (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Libel and Slander</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Libel and Slander</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anthrax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Times</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Kristof, Nicholas D</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E0D81330F930A25752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="639" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Judge Rebuffs U.S. Scientist In Lawsuit Against Times</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Judge Rejects Defamation Suit Against The Times</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL A. LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewis, Neil A</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Judge Claude M Hilton dismisses suit against New York Times by Dr Steven J Hatfill, former government scientist who says he was defamed by series of columns about deadly anthrax mailings in 2001; Hilton grants motion by Times to dismiss suit but does not provide explanation; he is expected to file detailed written opinion in coming days; Hatfill photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A federal judge on Friday dismissed a suit against The New York Times by a former government scientist who said he was defamed by a series of columns about the deadly anthrax mailings in 2001.</p>
        <p>The judge, Claude M. Hilton of Federal District Court in Alexandria, Va., granted a motion by The Times to dismiss the suit but did not provide an immediate explanation. He is expected to file a detailed written opinion in coming days.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dr. Stephen J. Hatfill had said in his suit that the columns by Nicholas D. Kristof about the anthrax mailings had defamed him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A federal judge on Friday dismissed a suit against The New York Times by a former government scientist who said he was defamed by a series of columns about the deadly anthrax mailings in 2001.</p>
        <p>The judge, Claude M. Hilton of Federal District Court in Alexandria, Va., granted a motion by The Times to dismiss the suit but did not provide an immediate explanation. He is expected to file a detailed written opinion in coming days.</p>
        <p>It was the latest and, perhaps, final chapter in a suit that has gone to the Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>The scientist, Dr. Stephen J. Hatfill, a specialist in biological weapons, had said in his suit that the columns by Nicholas D. Kristof about the anthrax mailings had defamed him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kristof wrote about a government scientist whom he initially identified as Mr. Z, saying he had become the overwhelming focus of the investigation. In August 2002, Mr. Kristof wrote that Dr. Hatfill, a former scientist at the Army bioweapons center at Fort Detrick, Md., had come forward and identified himself as Mr. Z and said the news media had treated him unfairly.</p>
        <p>Five people died in the anthrax attacks. Although federal authorities identified Dr. Hatfill as a ''person of interest,'' he was never charged with any crime, and the attacks remain unsolved.</p>
        <p>The Times argued in its dismissal motion that Dr. Hatfill was a public figure, at least for the purposes of the suit, in that he had thrust himself into the public debate about preparedness for a biological attack. That would present him with a far greater burden in showing that he was defamed and could, as the newspaper argued, prevent such a judgment.</p>
        <p>The Times also argued that the columns did not blame Dr. Hatfill for the attacks, as he said in his suit. Instead, the paper's lawyers said, the columns were aimed at pressing the Federal Bureau of Investigation to move more swiftly and either charge or clear Dr. Hatfill as a suspect.</p>
        <p>Judge Hilton had dismissed the suit earlier, saying that no defamation had occurred. A three-judge appeals panel voted, 2 to 1, to reinstate the suit, saying a jury should decide whether the columns were defamatory.</p>
        <p>The full appeals court, based in Richmond, Va., split, and the Supreme Court refused to intervene.</p>
        <p>Judge Hilton's latest dismissal, when his opinion is published, is expected to rest on a fuller argument than the last time and could thus be less vulnerable to being overturned. It is likely to deal with the issues raised in The Times's dismissal motion and Dr. Hatfill's response, including the question of whether he is a public figure for the purposes of defamation law.</p>
        <p>Whether there is any leeway for Dr. Hatfill to mount an appeal as he did before would depend on how Judge Hilton fashions his ruling.</p>
        <p>A lawyer for Dr. Hatfill, Mark A. Grannis, said, ''Obviously we can't make any statements as to what we'll do until we see the ruling.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Grannis said he did not believe that the case was over.</p>
        <p>''It has always been our position,'' he said, ''that the evidence of defamation was extremely strong and Mr. Kristof fabricated parts of his column to falsely implicate Dr. Hatfill in the anthrax attacks.''</p>
        <p>David E. McCraw, a lawyer for The Times, said in a statement: ''We are gratified by the judge's ruling today. In making our summary judgment motion, we believed that the plaintiff had failed to come up with the evidence necessary to bring this case to trial, and we are pleased that the court agreed.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McCraw said the case had required a significant investment of time and money on the part of the newspaper, ''but in the end, the law of defamation worked the way it was supposed to, by protecting aggressive, important journalism.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
