<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Martin D. Kruskal Dies; Mathematician Was 81</title>
    <meta content="13kruskal" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Obituaries" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/13/obituaries/13kruskal.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1818404"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Martin D. Kruskal</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kruskal, Martin D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pearce, Jeremy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Obituary (Obit)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Obituaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mathematics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mathematics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E2DA1330F930A25752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="487" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Martin D. Kruskal Dies; Mathematician Was 81</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Martin D. Kruskal Dies; Mathematician Was 81</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEREMY PEARCE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pearce, Jeremy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Martin D Kruskal, mathematician whose wide-ranging research touched on astrophysics, nuclear fusion and soliton, unique form of wave that he helped describe in 1960s, dies at age 81; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Martin D. Kruskal, a mathematician whose wide-ranging research touched on astrophysics, nuclear fusion and the soliton, a unique form of wave that he helped describe in the 1960s, died Dec. 26 in Princeton, N.J. He was 81.</p>
        <p>The cause was a stroke, his family said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Martin D. Kruskal was a mathematician whose wide-ranging research touched on astrophysics, nuclear fusion and the soliton, a unique form of wave that he helped describe in the 1960s.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Martin D. Kruskal, a mathematician whose wide-ranging research touched on astrophysics, nuclear fusion and the soliton, a unique form of wave that he helped describe in the 1960s, died Dec. 26 in Princeton, N.J. He was 81.</p>
        <p>The cause was a stroke, his family said.</p>
        <p>Working on a phenomenon that had been observed in the 19th century, Dr. Kruskal and a fellow researcher, Norman J. Zabusky, studied the behavior of a nonlinear wave that is able to pass through an opposing wave of the same type without affecting the energy or direction of either wave. They coined the term ''soliton.''</p>
        <p>Such waves have been found traveling in water, gases and other matter. Scientists in subsequent studies have found that solitons pass through fiber-optic cables and have important applications in telecommunications.</p>
        <p>Robert M. Miura, a professor of mathematical sciences at the New Jersey Institute of Technology, said Dr. Kruskal and Dr. Zabusky helped explain a ''striking phenomenon'' by formulating numerical simulations and putting them on a computer, ''to find the waves actually do go through each other unchanged.''</p>
        <p>Earlier, Dr. Kruskal, who was affiliated with Princeton University from 1951 to 1989, worked on a classified project to develop a process for controlled nuclear fusion in a Princeton laboratory. He applied theoretical mathematics to aspects of science and, with George Szekeres, developed a system for describing black holes in space, known as Kruskal-Szekeres coordinates.</p>
        <p>Late in his career, Dr. Kruskal became interested in surreal numbers -- a concept that includes numbers infinitely large or correspondingly small -- and helped extend the work of the originator of the concept, the British mathematician John Conway.</p>
        <p>In a less formal but no less serious pursuit, Dr. Kruskal developed a card trick in which he used probability to find a reliable way of identifying a playing card picked at random from a given deck. The result often baffled audiences, and the trick has been adopted by performers, who named it the Kruskal Count.</p>
        <p>Martin David Kruskal was born in New York City. He attended the University of Chicago and received his doctorate in mathematics from New York University in 1952.</p>
        <p>At Princeton, Dr. Kruskal was named a professor of astrophysical sciences in 1961. He was a former chairman of the university's program in applied mathematics and retired as a professor of mathematics in 1989. He then moved to Rutgers, where he was appointed a professor of mathematics and continued to work until his death.</p>
        <p>For his work on solitons, Dr. Kruskal received the National Medal of Science in 1993.</p>
        <p>Dr. Kruskal is survived by his wife of 56 years, the former Laura Lashinsky. The couple lived in Princeton.</p>
        <p>He is also survived by a daughter, Karen of Brookline, Mass.; two sons, Kerry, of Taos, N.M., and Clyde, a computer scientist, of University Park, Md.; a brother, Joseph Kruskal, a mathematician, of Maplewood, N.J.; a sister, Rosaly Evnine of Jerusalem; and five grandchildren.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
