<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CALENDAR</title>
    <meta content="28lilistingsLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1821926"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02EFDC163FF93BA15752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2326" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CALENDAR</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on in and around Nassau and Suffolk Counties this week. Items for the guide should be sent at least three weeks in advance to lical@nytimes.com, or by mail to Long Island Weekly, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036-3959.</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE</p>
        <p>Bay Shore Kevin Covais, vocalist. Friday at 8 p.m. $25. Boulton Center for the Performing Arts, 37 West Main Street. (631) 969-1101.</p>
        <p>Brookville ''An Evening of Jazz,'' presented by Nassau-Suffolk Performing Arts Jazz Band, Jazz Ensemble and Vocal Jazz Ensemble. Friday at 8 p.m. $37 to $65. Tony DeSare, vocalist. Feb. 3 at 8 and 10 p.m. $30 to $40. The Nassau Performing Arts Concert Band and Wind Symphony. Feb. 4 at 2 p.m. $10 to $20. Tilles Center for the Performing Arts, 720 Northern Boulevard, C.W. Post Campus, Long Island University. (516) 299-3100.</p>
        <p>Farmingdale Thursday, with Fear Before the March of Flames, Murder By Death, and Heavy Heavy Low Low, hard rock. Thursday at 6 p.m. $18 to $20. Crazy Donkey, 1058 Route 110. (631) 753-1975.</p>
        <p>Garden City Works by Mozart, Bloch and others presented by the Mineola Choral Society. Jan. 28 at 4 p.m. $15; seniors and students, $10. Cathedral of the Incarnation, 50 Cathedral Avenue. (631) 293-2222.</p>
        <p>Great River Daniel Lippel, classical guitar. Jan. 28 at 2 p.m. Soyeon Lee, piano. Feb. 4 at 2 p.m. Both free. Bayard Cutting Arboretum State Park, 440 Montauk Highway. (631) 224-5420.</p>
        <p>Holbrook The Devotions, pop. Jan. 28 at 2 p.m. Free. Sachem Public Library, 150 Holbrook Library. (631) 588-5024.</p>
        <p>Huntington Keb' Mo', blues. Feb. 2 at 7 and 9:30 p.m. $45; members, $34. Buckwheat Zydeco. Feb. 3 at 8 p.m. $37.50; members, $28.50. Inter-Media Art Center, 370 New York Avenue. (631) 549-2787.</p>
        <p>Long Beach ''An Afternoon of Classical Piano Music,'' performed by Matthew Weissman. Feb. 4 at 2 p.m. Both free. Long Beach Public Library, 111 West Park Avenue. (516) 432-7201.</p>
        <p>Patchogue Live in the Lobby: Millers Crossing, rock. Thursday at 7:30 p.m. $5. Quartet New Generation, recorder chamber ensemble. Feb. 4 at 3 p.m. $15; seniors and students, $12. Patchogue Theater for the Performing Arts, 71 East Main Street. (631) 207-1313.</p>
        <p>Port Washington Odetta with the Shepherd's Singers, gospel. Feb. 3 at 8 p.m. $17 to $23. Jeanne Rimsky Theater at the Landmark on Main Street, 232 Main Street. (516) 767-6444.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook The New Century Saxophone Quartet. Jan. 28 at 3 p.m. $32. Staller Center for the Arts, Stony Brook University. (631) 632-2787.</p>
        <p>Tony Brook Fred Eaglesmith, singer-songwriter. Feb. 4 at 2 p.m. $15 to $20. University Cafe, Stony Brook Union Building, Stony Brook University. (631) 632-6027.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook ''A Concert of Chamber Music,'' presented by the North Shore Pro Musica. Jan. 28 at 5 p.m. $15; students, $10. Ward Melville Heritage Educational and Cultural Center, Main Street. (631) 473-5220.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>Bohemia ''Godspell'' by Stephen Schwartz and John-Michael Tebelak. Through Jan. 28. $14 to $20. Airport Playhouse, 218 Knickerbocker Avenue. (631) 589-7588.</p>
        <p>Bridgehampton Eve Ensler's ''The Vagina Monologues,'' presented by the River Theater Company, directed by Toni Munna. Feb. 3 at 8 p.m. and Feb. 4 at 2 p.m. $25. Unitarian Universalist Congregation of the South Fork, 997 Bridgehampton-Sag Harbor Turnpike. (631) 259-3399.</p>
        <p>East Farmingdale ''Happy Birthday Bridgit,'' comedy by Marc Camoletti. Through Feb. 4. $18 to $22. Arena Players Second Stage Theater, 294 Route 109. (516) 293-0674.</p>
        <p>East Hampton Eve Ensler's ''The Vagina Monologues,'' presented by the Retreat, a domestic violence shelter. Friday and Feb. 3 at 8 p.m. $25. Ross School, 18 Goodfriend Drive. (631) 329-4398.</p>
        <p>East Hills ''Annie Get Your Gun'' by Irving Berlin, Herbert Fields, Dorothy Fields and Peter Stone, presented by the Sid Jacobson Adult Theater Company. Through Feb. 4. $18; members, seniors and students, $15. Sid Jacobson Jewish Community Center, 300 Forest Drive. (516) 484-1545.</p>
        <p>Hempstead ''Quartet'' by Ronald Harwood, directed by Bob Spiotto. Through Jan. 28. $18; seniors and students, $16. Emily and Jerry Spiegel Theater, Hofstra University, South Campus. (516) 463-6644.</p>
        <p>Lynbrook ''Gilbert and Sullivan From A to Z,'' presented by the Gilbert and Sullivan Light Opera Company. Feb. 4 at 3 p.m. $8; seniors, $6. Lynbrook Library, Eldert Street and Carpenter Avenue. (516) 599-8630.</p>
        <p>Quogue Edward Albee's ''Everything in the Garden,'' presented by the Hampton Theater Company, directed by Sarah Hunnewell. Through Jan. 28. $10 to $20. Quogue Community Hall, 126 Jessup Avenue. (631) 653-8955.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>Bay Shore ''Dead End,'' directed by William Wyler, followed by book signing with Leonard Getz, author of ''From Broadway to the Bowery.'' Jan. 28 at 2 p.m. $8. ''Some Like It Hot,'' directed by Billy Wilder. Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. $5. Boulton Center for the Performing Arts, 37 West Main Street. (631) 969-1101.</p>
        <p>East Hampton ''Day Break,'' directed by Hamid Rahmanian; in Persian with English subtitles. Jan. 28 at 7 p.m. Free. Guild Hall, 158 Main Street. (631) 324-4050.</p>
        <p>Great Neck Furman Film Series: ''Starter for Ten,'' directed by Tom Vaughan. Thursday at 7:30 p.m. $15; series subscription; $75. Clearview Squire Cinema, 115 Middle Neck Road. (516) 829-2570.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''Buffalo Bill and the Indians, or Sitting Bull's History Lesson,'' directed by Robert Altman. Jan. 28 at 11 a.m.; bagel breakfast at 10 a.m. $13; members, $10; reservations recommended. ''Absolute Wilson,'' documentary about Robert Wilson, directed by Katharina Otto. Tuesday at 7:30 p.m. $12; members, $8; reservations recommended; includes reception with guests from the film. Theater of the Wild: ''Tears of the Black Tiger,'' directed by Wisit Sasanatieng; with English subtitles. Wednesday at 7 and 9 p.m. $4.50 to $9. Cinema Arts Center, 423 Park Avenue. (631) 423-7611.</p>
        <p>Sag Harbor ''Sweet Liberty,'' directed by Alan Alda; post-screening discussion with Mr. Alda. Feb. 3 at 8 p.m. $50. Bay Street Theater, Main and Bay Streets. (631) 725-9500.</p>
        <p>Wading River Lunfest: Festival of nine films directed by women plus belly dance and self-defense workshops. Feb. 4 at 1 p.m. $35. Inn at East Wind, 5720 Route 25A. (631) 846-2313.</p>
        <p>Westhampton Beach Finest in World Cinema Series: ''The Painted Veil,'' directed by John Curran. Jan. 28 at 1 and 4 p.m. ''Sweet Land,'' directed by Ali Selim. Friday and Feb. 3 at 7:30 p.m.; Feb. 4 at 1 and 4 p.m. $3 to $10. Westhampton Beach Performing Arts Center, 76 Main Street. (631) 288-1500.</p>
        <p>Outdoors</p>
        <p>Captree Island ''Evening Lighthouse Tower Tour.'' Friday at 4:30 p.m. $10; reservations required. Fire Island Lighthouse Preservation Society, 4640 Captree Island. (631) 661-4876.</p>
        <p>Long Beach Nature Center Seal Walks, introductory program and walk to view wintering seals. Feb. 4 at 10:30 a.m. $3; children under 3, free. Theodore Roosevelt Nature Center, Ocean Parkway. (516) 679-7254.</p>
        <p>Smithtown ''Early Birds,'' adult nature program to observe birds; bring binoculars. Feb. 4 at 9 a.m. $3; reservations required. Caleb Smith State  Park Preserve, Jericho Turnpike. (631) 265-1054.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>Huntington Jay Jii, author of ''Solar Tapestry: A Collection of Poetry, Prose and Art.'' Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. Book Revue, 313 New York Avenue. (631) 271-1442.</p>
        <p>Montauk Clem Healy, author of ''North Fork Cemeteries'' and ''South Fork Cemeteries.'' Jan. 28 at 2:30 p.m. Free. Montauk Library, 871 Montauk Highway. (631) 668-3377.</p>
        <p>For Children</p>
        <p>Bay Shore The Russian American Kids Circus, presented by child performers trained by the Moscow Circus. Feb. 3 at 7 p.m. $12. Boulton Center for the Performing Arts, 37 West Main Street. (631) 969-1101.</p>
        <p>Brookville Fred Garbo Inflatable Theater Company. All ages. Feb. 3  at 2 p.m. $15 to $25. Tilles Center for the Performing Arts, 720 Northern Boulevard, C.W. Post Campus, Long Island University. (516) 299-3100.</p>
        <p>Dix Hills ''Peter Pan'' by James M. Barrie, Mark Charlap and Carolyn Leigh, directed by Tony Frangipane and performed by fifth-grade students. Jan. 28 at 1 p.m. $10; seniors and students, $5. Eugene Orloff Auditorium, East High School, 50 Vanderbilt Parkway. (631) 592-3185.</p>
        <p>Garden City Kids First! Film Club: ''The Journey of Henry (Box) Brown,'' selection of short animated films. Ages 3 and up. Friday at 4:30 p.m. ''Unlock My Heart.'' Learn about and decorate Welsh love spoons. Ages 3 and up. Feb. 3 at 12:30 and 2:30 p.m. Bari Koral Family Rock Band. Ages 3 and up. Feb. 3 at 1 and 3 p.m. ''Portuguese Traditional Dances,'' Juventude dance workshop. Ages 3 to 12. Feb. 4 at 11 a.m. $5; $3 with museum admission. Long Island Children's Museum, 11 Davis Avenue. (516) 224-5800.</p>
        <p>Islip ''Peter Pan and Wendy,'' presented by BroadHollow Theater; followed by a princess tea party. Through Feb. 3. $8; $20 for show and tea party. BayWay Arts Center, 265 East Main Street. (631) 581-2700.</p>
        <p>Lindenhurst ''Wizard of Oz,'' presented by BroadHollow Theater; followed by a princess tea party. Feb. 3 through 24. $8; $20 for show and tea party. Studio Theater, 141 South Wellwood Avenue. (631) 581-2700.</p>
        <p>Assapequa Special Youth Concert, presented by the Massapequa Philharmonic Orchestra, with Greta Hayes, cello. Jan. 28 at 2 p.m. Free. Berner Middle School, Carmans Mill Road. (516) 795-4071.</p>
        <p>Oakdale ''Animal Tracking,'' learn to track animals. Ages 5 and up. Feb. 3 at 9:30 a.m. $3; children, $2; reservations required. Connetquot River State Park, Sunrise Highway. (631) 581-1005.</p>
        <p>Oakdale ''High School Musical,'' children's musical adapted from the film by Kenny Ortega. Through Jan. 28. $12. CM Performing Arts Center, 931 Montauk Highway. (631) 218-2810.</p>
        <p>Riverhead ''Pinwheels and Parachutes,'' make parachutes by testing a variety of materials. Jan. 28, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m. ''Feed the Birds.'' Learn to identify birds and their nests and create a birdfeeder. Feb. 4, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m. $2; children, $5. Long Island Science Center, 11 West Main Street. (631) 208-8000.</p>
        <p>Smithtown ''Candle Making 101,'' family program to make drip candles; bring empty soup can. All ages. Jan. 28 at 1:30 p.m. $3; children, $2; reservations required. Caleb Smith State Park Preserve, Jericho Turnpike. (631) 265-1054.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook ''11th Annual Chinese New Year Celebration,'' crafts, dance performances and taiko drumming concert. Feb. 4 at 1:30 p.m. $10; seniors and children under 12, $8; advance tickets required. Ward Melville Heritage Educational and Cultural Center, Main Street. (631) 473-</p>
        <p>5220.</p>
        <p>Westbury ''Third Annual Winterfest,'' magic show, wild animal visits, food, gardening and craft activities. All ages. Jan. 28 from 9 a.m. to 4 p.m. Free. Hicks Nurseries, 100 Jericho Turnpike. (516) 334-0066.</p>
        <p>Museums and Galleries</p>
        <p>Cold Spring Harbor ''What If? Long Island That Might Have Been,'' exhibition featuring unrealized design plans for Long Island. Through Jan. 28. $1. Hours: Daily, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Society for the Preservation of Long Island Antiquities, 1 Shore Road. (631) 692-4664.</p>
        <p>Cold Spring Harbor ''Toys, Kids and Boats,'' exhibition of children's toys from the whaling era. Through August. $4; seniors and students, $3; children under 5, free. Whaling Museum, Route 25A. (631) 367-3418.</p>
        <p>East Islip ''Animal House,'' works by various artists who portray animals to comment on contemporary society. Through Jan. 28. Donation: $3. Hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Islip Art Museum, 50 Irish Lane. (631) 224-5402.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''East Coast/West Coast and Beyond: Colin Campbell Cooper, American Impressionist.'' Through Jan. 28. ''Picturing Long Island: Abstract, Figurative and Historical,'' works by various Long Island artists. Feb. 3 through March 25. $5; seniors, $3; children ages 5 to 12, $1; under 5, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Fridays, 10 a.m. to 8:30 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 8:30 p.m. The  Heckscher Museum of Art, 2 Prime Avenue. (631) 351-3250.</p>
        <p>Oakdale ''Inventory Control,'' multimedia works by Elise Engler, Chris Bors and others. Through Feb. 25. Hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Anthony Giordano Gallery, Dowling College, Idle Hour Boulevard. (631) 244-3016.</p>
        <p>Riverhead ''Between Mobility and Immobility,'' works by Hideaki Ariizumi, Christopher Chambers and Mark Hage. Feb. 3 through March 11. Hours: Thursdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Art Sites, 651 West Main Street. (631) 323-1426.</p>
        <p>Riverhead ''Ice Age: Revisited,'' exhibition featuring animals that lived during the ice age. Through March 18. $11; seniors and children 12 to 18, $9; children 3 to 11, $8; children 2 and under, free. Hours: Daily, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Dinosaur Walk Museum, 221 East Main Street. (631) 369-6556.</p>
        <p>Riverhead Caroline M. Bell and the Peconic Bay Impressionists. Through April 30. Suffolk County Historical Society, 300 West Main Street. (631) 727-2881.</p>
        <p>Rockville Centre Exhibition of work by the Long Island Black Artist Association. Through March 3. Free. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Molloy College Art Gallery, 1000 Hempstead Avenue. (516) 678-5000.</p>
        <p>Roslyn Harbor ''Picasso and the School of Paris,'' works by Picasso and others who lived in Paris from the 1920s to 1950s. Through Feb. 4. ''Chuck Close,'' photographic works. Through Feb. 4. Admission: $4 to $10; children under 5 and members, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 4:45 p.m. Nassau County Museum of Art, 1 Museum Drive. (516) 484-9337.</p>
        <p>Southampton ''2007 School Art Festival,'' works by students from pre-K through eighth grade. Through March 4. $7; seniors and students, $5; children under 18, free. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Parrish Art Museum, 25 Job's Lane. (631) 283-2118, Extension 32.</p>
        <p>Uniondale ''Woven, Knotted, Tied and Sewn,'' fiber crafts by Ellen Dickinson, Sally Shore and others. Through March 2. Reception: Thursday, 6:30 to 8:30 p.m. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 6:30 p.m. Omni Gallery, 333 Earle Ovington Boulevard. (631) 589-3093.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on in and around Nassau and Suffolk Counties this week. Items for the guide should be sent at least three weeks in advance to lical@nytimes.com, or by mail to Long Island Weekly, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036-3959.</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE</p>
        <p>Bay Shore Kevin Covais, vocalist. Friday at 8 p.m. $25. Boulton Center for the Performing Arts, 37 West Main Street. (631) 969-1101.</p>
        <p>Brookville ''An Evening of Jazz,'' presented by Nassau-Suffolk Performing Arts Jazz Band, Jazz Ensemble and Vocal Jazz Ensemble. Friday at 8 p.m. $37 to $65. Tony DeSare, vocalist. Feb. 3 at 8 and 10 p.m. $30 to $40. The Nassau Performing Arts Concert Band and Wind Symphony. Feb. 4 at 2 p.m. $10 to $20. Tilles Center for the Performing Arts, 720 Northern Boulevard, C.W. Post Campus, Long Island University. (516) 299-3100.</p>
        <p>Farmingdale Thursday, with Fear Before the March of Flames, Murder By Death, and Heavy Heavy Low Low, hard rock. Thursday at 6 p.m. $18 to $20. Crazy Donkey, 1058 Route 110. (631) 753-1975.</p>
        <p>Garden City Works by Mozart, Bloch and others presented by the Mineola Choral Society. Jan. 28 at 4 p.m. $15; seniors and students, $10. Cathedral of the Incarnation, 50 Cathedral Avenue. (631) 293-2222.</p>
        <p>Great River Daniel Lippel, classical guitar. Jan. 28 at 2 p.m. Soyeon Lee, piano. Feb. 4 at 2 p.m. Both free. Bayard Cutting Arboretum State Park, 440 Montauk Highway. (631) 224-5420.</p>
        <p>Holbrook The Devotions, pop. Jan. 28 at 2 p.m. Free. Sachem Public Library, 150 Holbrook Library. (631) 588-5024.</p>
        <p>Huntington Keb' Mo', blues. Feb. 2 at 7 and 9:30 p.m. $45; members, $34. Buckwheat Zydeco. Feb. 3 at 8 p.m. $37.50; members, $28.50. Inter-Media Art Center, 370 New York Avenue. (631) 549-2787.</p>
        <p>Long Beach ''An Afternoon of Classical Piano Music,'' performed by Matthew Weissman. Feb. 4 at 2 p.m. Both free. Long Beach Public Library, 111 West Park Avenue. (516) 432-7201.</p>
        <p>Patchogue Live in the Lobby: Millers Crossing, rock. Thursday at 7:30 p.m. $5. Quartet New Generation, recorder chamber ensemble. Feb. 4 at 3 p.m. $15; seniors and students, $12. Patchogue Theater for the Performing Arts, 71 East Main Street. (631) 207-1313.</p>
        <p>Port Washington Odetta with the Shepherd's Singers, gospel. Feb. 3 at 8 p.m. $17 to $23. Jeanne Rimsky Theater at the Landmark on Main Street, 232 Main Street. (516) 767-6444.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook The New Century Saxophone Quartet. Jan. 28 at 3 p.m. $32. Staller Center for the Arts, Stony Brook University. (631) 632-2787.</p>
        <p>Tony Brook Fred Eaglesmith, singer-songwriter. Feb. 4 at 2 p.m. $15 to $20. University Cafe, Stony Brook Union Building, Stony Brook University. (631) 632-6027.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook ''A Concert of Chamber Music,'' presented by the North Shore Pro Musica. Jan. 28 at 5 p.m. $15; students, $10. Ward Melville Heritage Educational and Cultural Center, Main Street. (631) 473-5220.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>Bohemia ''Godspell'' by Stephen Schwartz and John-Michael Tebelak. Through Jan. 28. $14 to $20. Airport Playhouse, 218 Knickerbocker Avenue. (631) 589-7588.</p>
        <p>Bridgehampton Eve Ensler's ''The Vagina Monologues,'' presented by the River Theater Company, directed by Toni Munna. Feb. 3 at 8 p.m. and Feb. 4 at 2 p.m. $25. Unitarian Universalist Congregation of the South Fork, 997 Bridgehampton-Sag Harbor Turnpike. (631) 259-3399.</p>
        <p>East Farmingdale ''Happy Birthday Bridgit,'' comedy by Marc Camoletti. Through Feb. 4. $18 to $22. Arena Players Second Stage Theater, 294 Route 109. (516) 293-0674.</p>
        <p>East Hampton Eve Ensler's ''The Vagina Monologues,'' presented by the Retreat, a domestic violence shelter. Friday and Feb. 3 at 8 p.m. $25. Ross School, 18 Goodfriend Drive. (631) 329-4398.</p>
        <p>East Hills ''Annie Get Your Gun'' by Irving Berlin, Herbert Fields, Dorothy Fields and Peter Stone, presented by the Sid Jacobson Adult Theater Company. Through Feb. 4. $18; members, seniors and students, $15. Sid Jacobson Jewish Community Center, 300 Forest Drive. (516) 484-1545.</p>
        <p>Hempstead ''Quartet'' by Ronald Harwood, directed by Bob Spiotto. Through Jan. 28. $18; seniors and students, $16. Emily and Jerry Spiegel Theater, Hofstra University, South Campus. (516) 463-6644.</p>
        <p>Lynbrook ''Gilbert and Sullivan From A to Z,'' presented by the Gilbert and Sullivan Light Opera Company. Feb. 4 at 3 p.m. $8; seniors, $6. Lynbrook Library, Eldert Street and Carpenter Avenue. (516) 599-8630.</p>
        <p>Quogue Edward Albee's ''Everything in the Garden,'' presented by the Hampton Theater Company, directed by Sarah Hunnewell. Through Jan. 28. $10 to $20. Quogue Community Hall, 126 Jessup Avenue. (631) 653-8955.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>Bay Shore ''Dead End,'' directed by William Wyler, followed by book signing with Leonard Getz, author of ''From Broadway to the Bowery.'' Jan. 28 at 2 p.m. $8. ''Some Like It Hot,'' directed by Billy Wilder. Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. $5. Boulton Center for the Performing Arts, 37 West Main Street. (631) 969-1101.</p>
        <p>East Hampton ''Day Break,'' directed by Hamid Rahmanian; in Persian with English subtitles. Jan. 28 at 7 p.m. Free. Guild Hall, 158 Main Street. (631) 324-4050.</p>
        <p>Great Neck Furman Film Series: ''Starter for Ten,'' directed by Tom Vaughan. Thursday at 7:30 p.m. $15; series subscription; $75. Clearview Squire Cinema, 115 Middle Neck Road. (516) 829-2570.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''Buffalo Bill and the Indians, or Sitting Bull's History Lesson,'' directed by Robert Altman. Jan. 28 at 11 a.m.; bagel breakfast at 10 a.m. $13; members, $10; reservations recommended. ''Absolute Wilson,'' documentary about Robert Wilson, directed by Katharina Otto. Tuesday at 7:30 p.m. $12; members, $8; reservations recommended; includes reception with guests from the film. Theater of the Wild: ''Tears of the Black Tiger,'' directed by Wisit Sasanatieng; with English subtitles. Wednesday at 7 and 9 p.m. $4.50 to $9. Cinema Arts Center, 423 Park Avenue. (631) 423-7611.</p>
        <p>Sag Harbor ''Sweet Liberty,'' directed by Alan Alda; post-screening discussion with Mr. Alda. Feb. 3 at 8 p.m. $50. Bay Street Theater, Main and Bay Streets. (631) 725-9500.</p>
        <p>Wading River Lunfest: Festival of nine films directed by women plus belly dance and self-defense workshops. Feb. 4 at 1 p.m. $35. Inn at East Wind, 5720 Route 25A. (631) 846-2313.</p>
        <p>Westhampton Beach Finest in World Cinema Series: ''The Painted Veil,'' directed by John Curran. Jan. 28 at 1 and 4 p.m. ''Sweet Land,'' directed by Ali Selim. Friday and Feb. 3 at 7:30 p.m.; Feb. 4 at 1 and 4 p.m. $3 to $10. Westhampton Beach Performing Arts Center, 76 Main Street. (631) 288-1500.</p>
        <p>Outdoors</p>
        <p>Captree Island ''Evening Lighthouse Tower Tour.'' Friday at 4:30 p.m. $10; reservations required. Fire Island Lighthouse Preservation Society, 4640 Captree Island. (631) 661-4876.</p>
        <p>Long Beach Nature Center Seal Walks, introductory program and walk to view wintering seals. Feb. 4 at 10:30 a.m. $3; children under 3, free. Theodore Roosevelt Nature Center, Ocean Parkway. (516) 679-7254.</p>
        <p>Smithtown ''Early Birds,'' adult nature program to observe birds; bring binoculars. Feb. 4 at 9 a.m. $3; reservations required. Caleb Smith State  Park Preserve, Jericho Turnpike. (631) 265-1054.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>Huntington Jay Jii, author of ''Solar Tapestry: A Collection of Poetry, Prose and Art.'' Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. Book Revue, 313 New York Avenue. (631) 271-1442.</p>
        <p>Montauk Clem Healy, author of ''North Fork Cemeteries'' and ''South Fork Cemeteries.'' Jan. 28 at 2:30 p.m. Free. Montauk Library, 871 Montauk Highway. (631) 668-3377.</p>
        <p>For Children</p>
        <p>Bay Shore The Russian American Kids Circus, presented by child performers trained by the Moscow Circus. Feb. 3 at 7 p.m. $12. Boulton Center for the Performing Arts, 37 West Main Street. (631) 969-1101.</p>
        <p>Brookville Fred Garbo Inflatable Theater Company. All ages. Feb. 3  at 2 p.m. $15 to $25. Tilles Center for the Performing Arts, 720 Northern Boulevard, C.W. Post Campus, Long Island University. (516) 299-3100.</p>
        <p>Dix Hills ''Peter Pan'' by James M. Barrie, Mark Charlap and Carolyn Leigh, directed by Tony Frangipane and performed by fifth-grade students. Jan. 28 at 1 p.m. $10; seniors and students, $5. Eugene Orloff Auditorium, East High School, 50 Vanderbilt Parkway. (631) 592-3185.</p>
        <p>Garden City Kids First! Film Club: ''The Journey of Henry (Box) Brown,'' selection of short animated films. Ages 3 and up. Friday at 4:30 p.m. ''Unlock My Heart.'' Learn about and decorate Welsh love spoons. Ages 3 and up. Feb. 3 at 12:30 and 2:30 p.m. Bari Koral Family Rock Band. Ages 3 and up. Feb. 3 at 1 and 3 p.m. ''Portuguese Traditional Dances,'' Juventude dance workshop. Ages 3 to 12. Feb. 4 at 11 a.m. $5; $3 with museum admission. Long Island Children's Museum, 11 Davis Avenue. (516) 224-5800.</p>
        <p>Islip ''Peter Pan and Wendy,'' presented by BroadHollow Theater; followed by a princess tea party. Through Feb. 3. $8; $20 for show and tea party. BayWay Arts Center, 265 East Main Street. (631) 581-2700.</p>
        <p>Lindenhurst ''Wizard of Oz,'' presented by BroadHollow Theater; followed by a princess tea party. Feb. 3 through 24. $8; $20 for show and tea party. Studio Theater, 141 South Wellwood Avenue. (631) 581-2700.</p>
        <p>Assapequa Special Youth Concert, presented by the Massapequa Philharmonic Orchestra, with Greta Hayes, cello. Jan. 28 at 2 p.m. Free. Berner Middle School, Carmans Mill Road. (516) 795-4071.</p>
        <p>Oakdale ''Animal Tracking,'' learn to track animals. Ages 5 and up. Feb. 3 at 9:30 a.m. $3; children, $2; reservations required. Connetquot River State Park, Sunrise Highway. (631) 581-1005.</p>
        <p>Oakdale ''High School Musical,'' children's musical adapted from the film by Kenny Ortega. Through Jan. 28. $12. CM Performing Arts Center, 931 Montauk Highway. (631) 218-2810.</p>
        <p>Riverhead ''Pinwheels and Parachutes,'' make parachutes by testing a variety of materials. Jan. 28, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m. ''Feed the Birds.'' Learn to identify birds and their nests and create a birdfeeder. Feb. 4, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m. $2; children, $5. Long Island Science Center, 11 West Main Street. (631) 208-8000.</p>
        <p>Smithtown ''Candle Making 101,'' family program to make drip candles; bring empty soup can. All ages. Jan. 28 at 1:30 p.m. $3; children, $2; reservations required. Caleb Smith State Park Preserve, Jericho Turnpike. (631) 265-1054.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook ''11th Annual Chinese New Year Celebration,'' crafts, dance performances and taiko drumming concert. Feb. 4 at 1:30 p.m. $10; seniors and children under 12, $8; advance tickets required. Ward Melville Heritage Educational and Cultural Center, Main Street. (631) 473-</p>
        <p>5220.</p>
        <p>Westbury ''Third Annual Winterfest,'' magic show, wild animal visits, food, gardening and craft activities. All ages. Jan. 28 from 9 a.m. to 4 p.m. Free. Hicks Nurseries, 100 Jericho Turnpike. (516) 334-0066.</p>
        <p>Museums and Galleries</p>
        <p>Cold Spring Harbor ''What If? Long Island That Might Have Been,'' exhibition featuring unrealized design plans for Long Island. Through Jan. 28. $1. Hours: Daily, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Society for the Preservation of Long Island Antiquities, 1 Shore Road. (631) 692-4664.</p>
        <p>Cold Spring Harbor ''Toys, Kids and Boats,'' exhibition of children's toys from the whaling era. Through August. $4; seniors and students, $3; children under 5, free. Whaling Museum, Route 25A. (631) 367-3418.</p>
        <p>East Islip ''Animal House,'' works by various artists who portray animals to comment on contemporary society. Through Jan. 28. Donation: $3. Hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Islip Art Museum, 50 Irish Lane. (631) 224-5402.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''East Coast/West Coast and Beyond: Colin Campbell Cooper, American Impressionist.'' Through Jan. 28. ''Picturing Long Island: Abstract, Figurative and Historical,'' works by various Long Island artists. Feb. 3 through March 25. $5; seniors, $3; children ages 5 to 12, $1; under 5, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Fridays, 10 a.m. to 8:30 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 8:30 p.m. The  Heckscher Museum of Art, 2 Prime Avenue. (631) 351-3250.</p>
        <p>Oakdale ''Inventory Control,'' multimedia works by Elise Engler, Chris Bors and others. Through Feb. 25. Hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Anthony Giordano Gallery, Dowling College, Idle Hour Boulevard. (631) 244-3016.</p>
        <p>Riverhead ''Between Mobility and Immobility,'' works by Hideaki Ariizumi, Christopher Chambers and Mark Hage. Feb. 3 through March 11. Hours: Thursdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Art Sites, 651 West Main Street. (631) 323-1426.</p>
        <p>Riverhead ''Ice Age: Revisited,'' exhibition featuring animals that lived during the ice age. Through March 18. $11; seniors and children 12 to 18, $9; children 3 to 11, $8; children 2 and under, free. Hours: Daily, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Dinosaur Walk Museum, 221 East Main Street. (631) 369-6556.</p>
        <p>Riverhead Caroline M. Bell and the Peconic Bay Impressionists. Through April 30. Suffolk County Historical Society, 300 West Main Street. (631) 727-2881.</p>
        <p>Rockville Centre Exhibition of work by the Long Island Black Artist Association. Through March 3. Free. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Molloy College Art Gallery, 1000 Hempstead Avenue. (516) 678-5000.</p>
        <p>Roslyn Harbor ''Picasso and the School of Paris,'' works by Picasso and others who lived in Paris from the 1920s to 1950s. Through Feb. 4. ''Chuck Close,'' photographic works. Through Feb. 4. Admission: $4 to $10; children under 5 and members, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 4:45 p.m. Nassau County Museum of Art, 1 Museum Drive. (516) 484-9337.</p>
        <p>Southampton ''2007 School Art Festival,'' works by students from pre-K through eighth grade. Through March 4. $7; seniors and students, $5; children under 18, free. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Parrish Art Museum, 25 Job's Lane. (631) 283-2118, Extension 32.</p>
        <p>Uniondale ''Woven, Knotted, Tied and Sewn,'' fiber crafts by Ellen Dickinson, Sally Shore and others. Through March 2. Reception: Thursday, 6:30 to 8:30 p.m. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 6:30 p.m. Omni Gallery, 333 Earle Ovington Boulevard. (631) 589-3093.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
