<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CALENDAR</title>
    <meta content="28ctlistingsCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1821960"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE3D8163FF93BA15752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2434" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CALENDAR</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on in and around Connecticut this week. Items for the guide should be sent at least three weeks in advance to ctcal@nytimes.com, or by mail to Connecticut Weekly, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036-3959.</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE</p>
        <p>Danbury Trombones de Costa Rica, trombone quartet. Feb. 3 at 8 p.m. $5 to $10. Ives Concert Hall in White Hall, 181 White Street, Western Connecticut University Midtown Campus. (203) 837-8350.</p>
        <p>East Hartford Dan Paisley and the Southern Grass, bluegrass. Feb. 3 at 7:30 p.m. $10 to $17. East Hartford Community Cultural Center, 50 Chapman Place. (860) 528-1458.</p>
        <p>Fairfield Beethoven's Symphony No. 6 and other works, presented by the American Chamber Orchestra, directed by Christopher Hisey, with Kangho Lee, cello. Friday at 8 p.m. $15; students, $10. First Presbyterian Church of Fairfield, 2475 Easton Turnpike. (203) 222-7190.</p>
        <p>Fairfield Puccini's ''Tosca,'' presented by the Bulgarian State Opera. Friday at 8 p.m. $40 to $50. Quick Center for the Arts, 1073 North Benson Road. (203) 254-4010.</p>
        <p>Greenwich ''The Spirit of Elegance,'' presented by the Greenwich Symphony Orchestra, directed by David Gilbert. Feb. 3 at 8 p.m. and Feb. 4 at 4 p.m. $25; students, $10. Greenwich High School, 10 Hillside Road. (203) 869-2664.</p>
        <p>Greenwich Inon Barnatan, piano. Jan. 28 at 4 p.m. Free. Greenwich Library, 101 West Putnam Avenue. (203) 622-7900.</p>
        <p>Middletown ''Deeply There (stories of a neighborhood)'' and ''Stay Together,'' presented by the Joe Goode Performance Group. Friday and Feb. 3 at 8 p.m. $8 to $20. Center for the Arts, Wesleyan University. (860) 685-3355.</p>
        <p>New Canaan Notes in Midwinter Concert Series: Moxie, swing ensemble. Jan. 28 at 2 p.m. Free. New Canaan Library, 151 Main Street. (203) 594-5000.</p>
        <p>New Haven Jazz on the Wharf: Steve Davis, slide trombone. Friday at 9 p.m. $15. Long Wharf Theater, 222 Sargent Drive. (203) 787-4282.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Isn't It Romantic?'' presented by the New Haven Symphony Orchestra, conducted by Gerald Steichen. Friday at 7:30 p.m. $15 to $48. Shubert Theater, 247 College Street. (203) 624-1825.</p>
        <p>New Haven Works by Ezra Laderman, Martin Bresnick and Aaron Jay Kernis, performed by the Alianza Quartet. Monday at 8 p.m. Free. Works by Beethoven, Dvorak and Martin Bresnick, performed by the Jupiter Trio. Tuesday at 8 p.m. $13 to $33. Sprague Hall, Yale University, College and Wall Streets. (203) 432-4158.</p>
        <p>Old Lyme Works by Mendelssohn, Haydn and Brahms, presented by Musical Masterworks. Feb. 3 at 5 p.m. and Feb. 4 at 3 p.m. $5 to $30. First Congregational Church of Old Lyme, 2 Ferry Road. (860) 434-2252.</p>
        <p>Ridgefield Tret Fure, folk. Jan. 28 at 7 p.m. $15 to $20. Temple Shearith Israel, 46 Peaceable Street. (201) 431-6501.</p>
        <p>Stamford DanceFest 2007: Complexions Contemporary Ballet. Thursday at 8 p.m. $37. ''Student Festival Performance.'' Feb. 4 at 5 p.m. $12 to $24. Rich Forum, Stamford Center for the Arts, 307 Atlantic Street. (203) 325-4466.</p>
        <p>Stamford ''Music for Harp,'' presented by the Treetops Chamber Music Society, with Lisa Tannenbaum, harp, the Shanghai Quartet and others. Feb. 3 and 4 at 4 p.m. $20 to $50. The Treetops Studio, 359 Merriebrook Lane. (203) 979-6051.</p>
        <p>Storrs Joshua Bell, violin. Tuesday at 8 p.m. $28 to $40. ''Gospel Festival 2007,'' with Vickie Winans and others. Feb. 3 at 5 p.m. $25. Jorgensen Center for the Performing Arts, 2132 Hillside Road, University of Connecticut. (860) 486-4226.</p>
        <p>Wallingford Sugarland, country. Thursday at 7:30 p.m. $38 to $48. Chevrolet Theater, 95 South Turnpike Road. (203) 265-1501.</p>
        <p>Wilton ''Prevailing Winds of Connecticut,'' presented by Ralph Kirmser, oboe, with a woodwind quintet. Jan. 28 at 4 p.m. Wilton Library, 137 Old Ridgefield Road. (203) 762-3950.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>Hartford ''Fences,'' by August Wilson, directed by Jonathan Wilson. Through Feb. 11. $25 to $45. Hartford Stage, 50 Church Street. (860) 527-5151.</p>
        <p>New Britain ''Bat Boy: The Musical'' by Keythe Farley, Brian Flemming and Laurence O'Keefe, directed by Philip D. Vetro. Through Feb. 10. $20. Hole in the Wall Theater, 116 Main Street. (860) 229-3049.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''The Cocktail Hour'' by A. R. Gurney, directed by Kim Rubinstein. Through Feb. 4. $30 to $60. Long Wharf Theater, 222 Sargent Drive. (203) 787-4282.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Live Radio/Vintage Suspense,'' adapted from works by Gunter Eich and Lucille Fletcher, directed by Naomi Okuyama. Thursday through Feb. 3. $10 to $15. Yale Cabaret, 217 Park Street. (203) 432-1566.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''In the Continuum,'' written and performed by Danai Gurira and Nikkole Salter, directed by Robert O'Hara. Through Feb. 10. $20 to $40. Yale Repertory Theater, 1120 Chapel Street. (203) 432-1234.</p>
        <p>Ridgefield ''Loss of Color'' by Timothy Ford, staged reading. Tuesday at 7:30 p.m. Free. Ridgefield Theater Barn, 37 Halpin Lane. (203) 431-9850.</p>
        <p>Stratford ''Rounding Third'' by Richard Dresser, presented by Square One Theater Company. Friday through Feb. 17. $16; seniors and students, $15. Stratford Theater, 2422 Main Street. (203) 375-8778.</p>
        <p>Torrington The Nancy Marine Studio Theater Season: ''The Odd Couple.'' Friday through Feb. 11. $10.50 to $15.50. Warner Theater, 68 Main Street. (860) 489-7180.</p>
        <p>Wallingford ''Winter Cabaret,'' student production. Jan. 28. $10; seniors, $9. Paul Mellon Arts Center, Christian Street. (203) 697-2261.</p>
        <p>West Hartford ''Lend Me a Tenor'' by Ken Ludwig, directed by Howard Hirsch. Through Feb. 4. $25; students, $10. Park Road Playhouse, 244 Park Road. (860) 586-8500.</p>
        <p>Westport ''Selected Shorts,'' readings by John Shea, Isaiah Sheffer and Tazewell Thompson. Tuesday at 7:30 p.m. $15 to $25. Westport Country Playhouse, 25 Powers Court. (203) 227-4177.</p>
        <p>Westport ''Spinning Into Butter'' by Rebecca Gilman. Friday through Feb. 18. $12 to $16. Westport Town Hall, 110 Myrtle Avenue. (203) 226-1983.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>Fairfield ''Borders of the Mind,'' psychic show presented by Joshua Kane. Feb. 3 at 3 and 8 p.m.; Feb. 4 at 3 p.m. $15; children, $12. Quick Center for the Arts, 1073 North Benson Road. (203) 254-4010.</p>
        <p>Old Greenwich Lawrence Malkin, author of ''Kruger's Men.'' Tuesday at 7:30 p.m. Julia Chiapetta, author of ''Breast Cancer: The Notebook.'' Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. Arcadia Coffee Company, 20 Arcadia Road. (203) 637-8766.</p>
        <p>COMEDY</p>
        <p>Wallingford Lewis Black. Feb. 3 at 8 p.m. $38. Chevrolet Theater, 95 South Turnpike Road. (203) 265-1501.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>Bridgeport ''Oliver Twist,'' a new version of Dickens's classic set to pop music, directed by Bert Bernardi. Through Feb. 18. $13.50. Downtown Cabaret Theater, 263 Golden Hill Street. (203) 576-1636.</p>
        <p>Cold Spring Harbor ''Scrimshaw,'' create a keepsake box. Ages 6 to 12. Jan. 28 at 1 p.m. $7; members, $2.50; reservations required. Whaling Museum, Route 25A. (631) 367-3418.</p>
        <p>Glastonbury ''Aquatic Mammals: Muskrats,'' learn about muskrats and hike to find them. Ages 5 to 10. Tuesday at 4 p.m. $13; members, $10. The Connecticut Audubon Society Center at Glastonbury, 1361 Main Street. (860) 633-8402.</p>
        <p>Stamford ''Pajama Storytime,'' stories and songs; wear pajamas. Ages 3 and up. Monday at 7 p.m. Free. Ferguson Library, 115 Vine Road. (203) 964-1000.</p>
        <p>Waterbury ''Cam Jansen,'' children's musical adapted from the books by David A. Adler, presented by the Young People's Theater. Feb. 3 at 3 p.m. $7. John F. Kennedy High School Auditorium, Highland Avenue. (203) 577-2377.</p>
        <p>Waterbury ''Alice'' by Whoopi Goldberg, adapted by Kim Hines. Ages 5 to 12. Wednesday at 10 a.m. and noon. $8. Palace Theater of Connecticut, 100 East Main Street. (203) 755-4700.</p>
        <p>West Hartford ''Color Play: The Art and Science of Color and Light,'' explore light and holographic refraction. Ages 12 and under. Through June 17. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. The Children's Museum, 950 Trout Brook Drive. (860) 231-</p>
        <p>2824.</p>
        <p>Woodbridge ''Super Bowl Sunday Magic Show,'' presented by Ed Popielarczyk. Feb. 4 at 2 p.m. Free. Woodbridge Library, 10 Newton Road. (203) 389-3439.</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>Brookfield ''The Sound of Earth: Ceramic Musical Instruments,'' works by Rod Kendall, Susan Rawcliffe and others. Friday through March 18. Reception: Feb. 4, 2 to 4 p.m. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Brookfield Craft Center, 286 Whisconier Road. (203) 775-4526.</p>
        <p>Fairfield ''Romare Bearden: Scenes From the Portfolios.'' Through Feb. 26. Hours: Mondays through Thursdays, noon to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. The Gallery of Contemporary Art, Sacred Heart University, 5151 Park Avenue. (203) 365-7650.</p>
        <p>Fairfield ''Multiple Visions: Traveling Art Boxes from Argentina, Mexico and Uruguay,'' works by more than 20 artists. Through March 11. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Thomas J. Walsh Art Galley, 1073 North Benson Road. (203) 254-4000.</p>
        <p>Greenwich ''Black and White Since 1960,'' 25 large-scale etchings and lithographs from the collection of Reba and Dave Williams, with works by Jasper Johns, Claes Oldenburg and others. Through Feb. 25. ''In Response to Place: Photographs From the Nature Conservancy's Last Great Places,'' photographs by William Wegman, Annie Liebovitz, Lee Friedlander and others. Through Jan. 28. $7; seniors and students, $6; children 5 and under, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Bruce Museum of Arts and Sciences, 1 Museum Drive. (203) 869-0376.</p>
        <p>Hartford ''Crewel World,'' exhibition of textiles embroidered using the crewel technique. Through Feb. 25. ''Soul Food: African-American Cooking and Creativity,'' art and artifacts exploring Southern cooking and culture; presented by the Amistad Center for Art and Culture. Through April 22. ''Picasso to Pop: Aspects of Modern Art,'' exhibition of the museum's holdings from many 20th-century genres. Through Nov. 18. $3 to $10; members and children 12 and under, free. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; first Thursdays of the month, 11 a.m. to 8 p.m. Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art, 600 Main Street. (860) 838-4058.</p>
        <p>Mashantucket ''Booming Out: Mohawk Ironworkers Build New York,'' photographs and sculpture documenting the Mohawk sky-walking construction tradition passed through six generations. Through May 27. $10 to $15; children under 6, free. Hours: Daily, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; last admission, 3 p.m. Mashantucket Pequot Museum and Research Center, 110 Pequot Trail. (800) 411-9671.</p>
        <p>Middletown ''Xanadu,'' video installation by Robert Boyd. Through March 4. Free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Ezra and Cecile Zilkha Gallery, Wesleyan University, 283 Washington Terrace. (860) 685-3355.</p>
        <p>Middletown ''Tibet's Living Art: Paintings by Jampa Tsondue.'' Through March 9. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Mansfield Freeman Center for East Asian Studies Gallery, Wesleyan University, 343 Washington Terrace. (860) 685-2330.</p>
        <p>New Canaan ''Four/Play,'' works by Susan Sharp. Through Feb. 4. Vassos Gallery, 1037 Silvermine Road. (203) 966-9700.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Loud,'' juried exhibition with works by artists who are visually or aurally loud. Through Feb. 4. Free. Hours: Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Arts + Literature Laboratory, 319 Peck Street. (203) 671-5175.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Howard Hodgkin: Paintings 1992-2007.'' Thursday through April 1. Free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Yale Center for British Art, 1080 Chapel Street. (203) 432-2800.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Jasper Johns: From Plate to Print.'' Through April 1. ''Making a Mark: Four Contemporary Artists in Print,'' prints by Enrique Chagoya, Carroll Dunham, Jane Hammond and Kiki Smith. Through April 1. Hours: Tuesdays, Wednesdays, Fridays and Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 6 p.m. Yale University Art Gallery. (203) 432-9525.</p>
        <p>New London ''femme brut(e),'' works by female artists including May Stevens, Nancy Spero, Barbara Kruger and others. Through Feb. 4. $3 and $4; children 6 and under, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Lyman Allyn Art Museum, 625 Williams Street. (860) 443-2545.</p>
        <p>New Milford Michael and Helen Cherney, acrylics, watercolors, oils and pastels. Through Feb. 10. Hours: Mondays, Thursdays and Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Tuesdays and Wednesdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 1 p.m. New Milford Public Library, 24 Main Street. (860) 355-1191.</p>
        <p>Old Lyme ''The Freedom Business: Connecticut Landscapes Through the Eyes of Venture Smith,'' poems by Marilyn Nelson paired with paintings from the museum's collection. Through June 24. ''A Collective Endeavor: Three Decades of Acquisitions.'' Through March 25. $4 to $8; under 6, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5p. Florence Griswold Museum, 96 Lyme Street. (860) 434-5542.</p>
        <p>Ridgefield ''Bitter Fruit,'' photographs by Paul Fusco. Through Feb. 25. ''No Reservations: Native American History and Culture in Contemporary Art.'' Through Feb. 25. $7; seniors and students, $4; members, K-12 teachers and children under 18, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Aldrich Contemporary Art Museum, 258 Main Street. (203) 438-4519.</p>
        <p>Ridgefield ''History of the Present: African-American Self-Taught Artists of the South,'' works by seven outsider artists, including Thornton Dial, Mary Proctor and others. Feb. 3 through March 3. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Ridgefield Guild of Artists Gallery, 34 Halpin Lane. (203) 438-8863.</p>
        <p>Storrs ''Printerly Prints,'' exhibition of printmakers including Brad Brown, Jane Hammond and others. Through Feb. 23. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. Contemporary Art Galleries, 830 Bolton Road, University of Connecticut, Storrs Campus. (860) 486-1511.</p>
        <p>Storrs ''Intemperate Times: Kathe Kollwitz, 1918-1934.'' Through May 6. ''Landscape: Fact and Fiction,'' landscape photography by John Pfahl, Deborah Bright and others. Through March 2. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 4:30 p.m. William Benton Museum of Art, 245 Glenbrook Road. (860) 486-4520.</p>
        <p>West Hartford ''From Theater and Teahouse: Actors and Courtesans in Japanese Woodblock Prints,'' historical works by various artists. Through Jan. 28. Hours: Tuesdays, Wednesdays, Fridays and Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Thursdays, 11 a.m. to 7 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. St. Joseph College Art Gallery, 1678 Asylum Avenue. (860) 231-5399.</p>
        <p>Westport ''Art and the Good Earth: As Seen Through the Painter's Eye,'' works by 14 artists. Through May 11. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Westport Historical Society, 25 Avery Place. (203) 224-1424.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on in and around Connecticut this week. Items for the guide should be sent at least three weeks in advance to ctcal@nytimes.com, or by mail to Connecticut Weekly, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036-3959.</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE</p>
        <p>Danbury Trombones de Costa Rica, trombone quartet. Feb. 3 at 8 p.m. $5 to $10. Ives Concert Hall in White Hall, 181 White Street, Western Connecticut University Midtown Campus. (203) 837-8350.</p>
        <p>East Hartford Dan Paisley and the Southern Grass, bluegrass. Feb. 3 at 7:30 p.m. $10 to $17. East Hartford Community Cultural Center, 50 Chapman Place. (860) 528-1458.</p>
        <p>Fairfield Beethoven's Symphony No. 6 and other works, presented by the American Chamber Orchestra, directed by Christopher Hisey, with Kangho Lee, cello. Friday at 8 p.m. $15; students, $10. First Presbyterian Church of Fairfield, 2475 Easton Turnpike. (203) 222-7190.</p>
        <p>Fairfield Puccini's ''Tosca,'' presented by the Bulgarian State Opera. Friday at 8 p.m. $40 to $50. Quick Center for the Arts, 1073 North Benson Road. (203) 254-4010.</p>
        <p>Greenwich ''The Spirit of Elegance,'' presented by the Greenwich Symphony Orchestra, directed by David Gilbert. Feb. 3 at 8 p.m. and Feb. 4 at 4 p.m. $25; students, $10. Greenwich High School, 10 Hillside Road. (203) 869-2664.</p>
        <p>Greenwich Inon Barnatan, piano. Jan. 28 at 4 p.m. Free. Greenwich Library, 101 West Putnam Avenue. (203) 622-7900.</p>
        <p>Middletown ''Deeply There (stories of a neighborhood)'' and ''Stay Together,'' presented by the Joe Goode Performance Group. Friday and Feb. 3 at 8 p.m. $8 to $20. Center for the Arts, Wesleyan University. (860) 685-3355.</p>
        <p>New Canaan Notes in Midwinter Concert Series: Moxie, swing ensemble. Jan. 28 at 2 p.m. Free. New Canaan Library, 151 Main Street. (203) 594-5000.</p>
        <p>New Haven Jazz on the Wharf: Steve Davis, slide trombone. Friday at 9 p.m. $15. Long Wharf Theater, 222 Sargent Drive. (203) 787-4282.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Isn't It Romantic?'' presented by the New Haven Symphony Orchestra, conducted by Gerald Steichen. Friday at 7:30 p.m. $15 to $48. Shubert Theater, 247 College Street. (203) 624-1825.</p>
        <p>New Haven Works by Ezra Laderman, Martin Bresnick and Aaron Jay Kernis, performed by the Alianza Quartet. Monday at 8 p.m. Free. Works by Beethoven, Dvorak and Martin Bresnick, performed by the Jupiter Trio. Tuesday at 8 p.m. $13 to $33. Sprague Hall, Yale University, College and Wall Streets. (203) 432-4158.</p>
        <p>Old Lyme Works by Mendelssohn, Haydn and Brahms, presented by Musical Masterworks. Feb. 3 at 5 p.m. and Feb. 4 at 3 p.m. $5 to $30. First Congregational Church of Old Lyme, 2 Ferry Road. (860) 434-2252.</p>
        <p>Ridgefield Tret Fure, folk. Jan. 28 at 7 p.m. $15 to $20. Temple Shearith Israel, 46 Peaceable Street. (201) 431-6501.</p>
        <p>Stamford DanceFest 2007: Complexions Contemporary Ballet. Thursday at 8 p.m. $37. ''Student Festival Performance.'' Feb. 4 at 5 p.m. $12 to $24. Rich Forum, Stamford Center for the Arts, 307 Atlantic Street. (203) 325-4466.</p>
        <p>Stamford ''Music for Harp,'' presented by the Treetops Chamber Music Society, with Lisa Tannenbaum, harp, the Shanghai Quartet and others. Feb. 3 and 4 at 4 p.m. $20 to $50. The Treetops Studio, 359 Merriebrook Lane. (203) 979-6051.</p>
        <p>Storrs Joshua Bell, violin. Tuesday at 8 p.m. $28 to $40. ''Gospel Festival 2007,'' with Vickie Winans and others. Feb. 3 at 5 p.m. $25. Jorgensen Center for the Performing Arts, 2132 Hillside Road, University of Connecticut. (860) 486-4226.</p>
        <p>Wallingford Sugarland, country. Thursday at 7:30 p.m. $38 to $48. Chevrolet Theater, 95 South Turnpike Road. (203) 265-1501.</p>
        <p>Wilton ''Prevailing Winds of Connecticut,'' presented by Ralph Kirmser, oboe, with a woodwind quintet. Jan. 28 at 4 p.m. Wilton Library, 137 Old Ridgefield Road. (203) 762-3950.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>Hartford ''Fences,'' by August Wilson, directed by Jonathan Wilson. Through Feb. 11. $25 to $45. Hartford Stage, 50 Church Street. (860) 527-5151.</p>
        <p>New Britain ''Bat Boy: The Musical'' by Keythe Farley, Brian Flemming and Laurence O'Keefe, directed by Philip D. Vetro. Through Feb. 10. $20. Hole in the Wall Theater, 116 Main Street. (860) 229-3049.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''The Cocktail Hour'' by A. R. Gurney, directed by Kim Rubinstein. Through Feb. 4. $30 to $60. Long Wharf Theater, 222 Sargent Drive. (203) 787-4282.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Live Radio/Vintage Suspense,'' adapted from works by Gunter Eich and Lucille Fletcher, directed by Naomi Okuyama. Thursday through Feb. 3. $10 to $15. Yale Cabaret, 217 Park Street. (203) 432-1566.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''In the Continuum,'' written and performed by Danai Gurira and Nikkole Salter, directed by Robert O'Hara. Through Feb. 10. $20 to $40. Yale Repertory Theater, 1120 Chapel Street. (203) 432-1234.</p>
        <p>Ridgefield ''Loss of Color'' by Timothy Ford, staged reading. Tuesday at 7:30 p.m. Free. Ridgefield Theater Barn, 37 Halpin Lane. (203) 431-9850.</p>
        <p>Stratford ''Rounding Third'' by Richard Dresser, presented by Square One Theater Company. Friday through Feb. 17. $16; seniors and students, $15. Stratford Theater, 2422 Main Street. (203) 375-8778.</p>
        <p>Torrington The Nancy Marine Studio Theater Season: ''The Odd Couple.'' Friday through Feb. 11. $10.50 to $15.50. Warner Theater, 68 Main Street. (860) 489-7180.</p>
        <p>Wallingford ''Winter Cabaret,'' student production. Jan. 28. $10; seniors, $9. Paul Mellon Arts Center, Christian Street. (203) 697-2261.</p>
        <p>West Hartford ''Lend Me a Tenor'' by Ken Ludwig, directed by Howard Hirsch. Through Feb. 4. $25; students, $10. Park Road Playhouse, 244 Park Road. (860) 586-8500.</p>
        <p>Westport ''Selected Shorts,'' readings by John Shea, Isaiah Sheffer and Tazewell Thompson. Tuesday at 7:30 p.m. $15 to $25. Westport Country Playhouse, 25 Powers Court. (203) 227-4177.</p>
        <p>Westport ''Spinning Into Butter'' by Rebecca Gilman. Friday through Feb. 18. $12 to $16. Westport Town Hall, 110 Myrtle Avenue. (203) 226-1983.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>Fairfield ''Borders of the Mind,'' psychic show presented by Joshua Kane. Feb. 3 at 3 and 8 p.m.; Feb. 4 at 3 p.m. $15; children, $12. Quick Center for the Arts, 1073 North Benson Road. (203) 254-4010.</p>
        <p>Old Greenwich Lawrence Malkin, author of ''Kruger's Men.'' Tuesday at 7:30 p.m. Julia Chiapetta, author of ''Breast Cancer: The Notebook.'' Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. Arcadia Coffee Company, 20 Arcadia Road. (203) 637-8766.</p>
        <p>COMEDY</p>
        <p>Wallingford Lewis Black. Feb. 3 at 8 p.m. $38. Chevrolet Theater, 95 South Turnpike Road. (203) 265-1501.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>Bridgeport ''Oliver Twist,'' a new version of Dickens's classic set to pop music, directed by Bert Bernardi. Through Feb. 18. $13.50. Downtown Cabaret Theater, 263 Golden Hill Street. (203) 576-1636.</p>
        <p>Cold Spring Harbor ''Scrimshaw,'' create a keepsake box. Ages 6 to 12. Jan. 28 at 1 p.m. $7; members, $2.50; reservations required. Whaling Museum, Route 25A. (631) 367-3418.</p>
        <p>Glastonbury ''Aquatic Mammals: Muskrats,'' learn about muskrats and hike to find them. Ages 5 to 10. Tuesday at 4 p.m. $13; members, $10. The Connecticut Audubon Society Center at Glastonbury, 1361 Main Street. (860) 633-8402.</p>
        <p>Stamford ''Pajama Storytime,'' stories and songs; wear pajamas. Ages 3 and up. Monday at 7 p.m. Free. Ferguson Library, 115 Vine Road. (203) 964-1000.</p>
        <p>Waterbury ''Cam Jansen,'' children's musical adapted from the books by David A. Adler, presented by the Young People's Theater. Feb. 3 at 3 p.m. $7. John F. Kennedy High School Auditorium, Highland Avenue. (203) 577-2377.</p>
        <p>Waterbury ''Alice'' by Whoopi Goldberg, adapted by Kim Hines. Ages 5 to 12. Wednesday at 10 a.m. and noon. $8. Palace Theater of Connecticut, 100 East Main Street. (203) 755-4700.</p>
        <p>West Hartford ''Color Play: The Art and Science of Color and Light,'' explore light and holographic refraction. Ages 12 and under. Through June 17. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. The Children's Museum, 950 Trout Brook Drive. (860) 231-</p>
        <p>2824.</p>
        <p>Woodbridge ''Super Bowl Sunday Magic Show,'' presented by Ed Popielarczyk. Feb. 4 at 2 p.m. Free. Woodbridge Library, 10 Newton Road. (203) 389-3439.</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>Brookfield ''The Sound of Earth: Ceramic Musical Instruments,'' works by Rod Kendall, Susan Rawcliffe and others. Friday through March 18. Reception: Feb. 4, 2 to 4 p.m. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Brookfield Craft Center, 286 Whisconier Road. (203) 775-4526.</p>
        <p>Fairfield ''Romare Bearden: Scenes From the Portfolios.'' Through Feb. 26. Hours: Mondays through Thursdays, noon to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. The Gallery of Contemporary Art, Sacred Heart University, 5151 Park Avenue. (203) 365-7650.</p>
        <p>Fairfield ''Multiple Visions: Traveling Art Boxes from Argentina, Mexico and Uruguay,'' works by more than 20 artists. Through March 11. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Thomas J. Walsh Art Galley, 1073 North Benson Road. (203) 254-4000.</p>
        <p>Greenwich ''Black and White Since 1960,'' 25 large-scale etchings and lithographs from the collection of Reba and Dave Williams, with works by Jasper Johns, Claes Oldenburg and others. Through Feb. 25. ''In Response to Place: Photographs From the Nature Conservancy's Last Great Places,'' photographs by William Wegman, Annie Liebovitz, Lee Friedlander and others. Through Jan. 28. $7; seniors and students, $6; children 5 and under, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Bruce Museum of Arts and Sciences, 1 Museum Drive. (203) 869-0376.</p>
        <p>Hartford ''Crewel World,'' exhibition of textiles embroidered using the crewel technique. Through Feb. 25. ''Soul Food: African-American Cooking and Creativity,'' art and artifacts exploring Southern cooking and culture; presented by the Amistad Center for Art and Culture. Through April 22. ''Picasso to Pop: Aspects of Modern Art,'' exhibition of the museum's holdings from many 20th-century genres. Through Nov. 18. $3 to $10; members and children 12 and under, free. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; first Thursdays of the month, 11 a.m. to 8 p.m. Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art, 600 Main Street. (860) 838-4058.</p>
        <p>Mashantucket ''Booming Out: Mohawk Ironworkers Build New York,'' photographs and sculpture documenting the Mohawk sky-walking construction tradition passed through six generations. Through May 27. $10 to $15; children under 6, free. Hours: Daily, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; last admission, 3 p.m. Mashantucket Pequot Museum and Research Center, 110 Pequot Trail. (800) 411-9671.</p>
        <p>Middletown ''Xanadu,'' video installation by Robert Boyd. Through March 4. Free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Ezra and Cecile Zilkha Gallery, Wesleyan University, 283 Washington Terrace. (860) 685-3355.</p>
        <p>Middletown ''Tibet's Living Art: Paintings by Jampa Tsondue.'' Through March 9. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Mansfield Freeman Center for East Asian Studies Gallery, Wesleyan University, 343 Washington Terrace. (860) 685-2330.</p>
        <p>New Canaan ''Four/Play,'' works by Susan Sharp. Through Feb. 4. Vassos Gallery, 1037 Silvermine Road. (203) 966-9700.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Loud,'' juried exhibition with works by artists who are visually or aurally loud. Through Feb. 4. Free. Hours: Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Arts + Literature Laboratory, 319 Peck Street. (203) 671-5175.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Howard Hodgkin: Paintings 1992-2007.'' Thursday through April 1. Free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Yale Center for British Art, 1080 Chapel Street. (203) 432-2800.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Jasper Johns: From Plate to Print.'' Through April 1. ''Making a Mark: Four Contemporary Artists in Print,'' prints by Enrique Chagoya, Carroll Dunham, Jane Hammond and Kiki Smith. Through April 1. Hours: Tuesdays, Wednesdays, Fridays and Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 6 p.m. Yale University Art Gallery. (203) 432-9525.</p>
        <p>New London ''femme brut(e),'' works by female artists including May Stevens, Nancy Spero, Barbara Kruger and others. Through Feb. 4. $3 and $4; children 6 and under, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Lyman Allyn Art Museum, 625 Williams Street. (860) 443-2545.</p>
        <p>New Milford Michael and Helen Cherney, acrylics, watercolors, oils and pastels. Through Feb. 10. Hours: Mondays, Thursdays and Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Tuesdays and Wednesdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 1 p.m. New Milford Public Library, 24 Main Street. (860) 355-1191.</p>
        <p>Old Lyme ''The Freedom Business: Connecticut Landscapes Through the Eyes of Venture Smith,'' poems by Marilyn Nelson paired with paintings from the museum's collection. Through June 24. ''A Collective Endeavor: Three Decades of Acquisitions.'' Through March 25. $4 to $8; under 6, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5p. Florence Griswold Museum, 96 Lyme Street. (860) 434-5542.</p>
        <p>Ridgefield ''Bitter Fruit,'' photographs by Paul Fusco. Through Feb. 25. ''No Reservations: Native American History and Culture in Contemporary Art.'' Through Feb. 25. $7; seniors and students, $4; members, K-12 teachers and children under 18, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Aldrich Contemporary Art Museum, 258 Main Street. (203) 438-4519.</p>
        <p>Ridgefield ''History of the Present: African-American Self-Taught Artists of the South,'' works by seven outsider artists, including Thornton Dial, Mary Proctor and others. Feb. 3 through March 3. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Ridgefield Guild of Artists Gallery, 34 Halpin Lane. (203) 438-8863.</p>
        <p>Storrs ''Printerly Prints,'' exhibition of printmakers including Brad Brown, Jane Hammond and others. Through Feb. 23. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. Contemporary Art Galleries, 830 Bolton Road, University of Connecticut, Storrs Campus. (860) 486-1511.</p>
        <p>Storrs ''Intemperate Times: Kathe Kollwitz, 1918-1934.'' Through May 6. ''Landscape: Fact and Fiction,'' landscape photography by John Pfahl, Deborah Bright and others. Through March 2. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 4:30 p.m. William Benton Museum of Art, 245 Glenbrook Road. (860) 486-4520.</p>
        <p>West Hartford ''From Theater and Teahouse: Actors and Courtesans in Japanese Woodblock Prints,'' historical works by various artists. Through Jan. 28. Hours: Tuesdays, Wednesdays, Fridays and Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Thursdays, 11 a.m. to 7 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. St. Joseph College Art Gallery, 1678 Asylum Avenue. (860) 231-5399.</p>
        <p>Westport ''Art and the Good Earth: As Seen Through the Painter's Eye,'' works by 14 artists. Through May 11. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Westport Historical Society, 25 Avery Place. (203) 224-1424.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
