<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Few Raindrops Fall on the Big-Money Parade in Arizona</title>
    <meta content="28AUCTION" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/28/automobiles/collectibles/28AUCTION.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070204T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1822031"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="COLLECTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Martin, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E0D6163FF93BA15752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="696" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Few Raindrops Fall on the Big-Money Parade in Arizona</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Few Raindrops Fall on the Big-Money Collector Car Auctions in Arizona</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH MARTIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Martin, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>SCOTTSDALE, Ariz.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Four collector-car auctions in Phoenix area end with sale of 3,923 cars for total of $164 million; figures indicate that red-hot collector-car market is cooling a bit; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN most circumstances, selling a single used car of nearly any type for $41,000 would be cause for celebration. Selling 3,923 at that average price over six days, for a total of more than $164 million, would be a reason to start popping Champagne corks.</p>
        <p>But under unusually rainy skies this month in Arizona, sales figures at four collector car auctions indicated that the red-hot market was cooling a bit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Under unusually rainy skies this month in Arizona, sales figures at four collector car auctions indicated that the red-hot market was cooling a bit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN most circumstances, selling a single used car of nearly any type for $41,000 would be cause for celebration. Selling 3,923 at that average price over six days, for a total of more than $164 million, would be a reason to start popping Champagne corks.</p>
        <p>But under unusually rainy skies this month in Arizona, sales figures at four collector car auctions indicated that the red-hot market was cooling a bit.</p>
        <p>In contrast to the transparency of the stock market, where billions of shares are openly traded every day and the results are published immediately, there is an opacity to the collector car market. Many cars, especially the most significant ones, trade privately for undisclosed prices.</p>
        <p>Only twice a year are large car auctions held at the same time in the same area. Each August, it happens on the Monterey Peninsula of California, where five auctions take place. The other market barometer comes in a single week of January in the Phoenix area. Four companies, each with a different focus, put their consignors' wares in front of thousands of bidders and, in some cases, millions of television viewers.</p>
        <p>After peaking in 1991 and then collapsing, the collector-car market had been slowly gathering strength for five years. Sales figures for the Barrett-Jackson auction here, the largest in the world in terms of dollars spent, tell the tale. Barrett-Jackson had sales of $34 million in 2004, $65 million in 2005 and $98 million in 2006.</p>
        <p>But just as with dot-com stocks or Miami condos, values cannot rise forever, and the sales results in Arizona indicated that the market's meteoric climb may be ending.</p>
        <p>While the prices of some types of cars remain strong, primarily low-production muscle cars with their original engines (''numbers matching'' is the trade term) or sports racing cars like Ferraris, other more common cars produced in larger numbers, or cars whose engines have been replaced, are holding their values, at best.</p>
        <p>In a response to questions sent by e-mail, Steve Davis, the president of Barrett-Jackson, said, ''The strongest overall segment of the market is the interest in certain muscle cars, such as Boss 429s and specific Shelby GT500/350 Mustangs.'' He added, ''Austin Healeys, Mercedes 300SL roadsters and Gullwings currently command top dollar, and there is also an increased interest in the classic segment of the market.''</p>
        <p>For two of the four auctions, sales were down slightly from a year earlier. While Barrett-Jackson showed an uptick to $109 million, that figure included an added sales day and 191 more cars. The average price per car at Barrett-Jackson was $92,301 in 2006; this year, it was $87,001. Barrett-Jackson also had by far the largest field, with 1,254 cars both offered and sold.</p>
        <p>While Barrett-Jackson specializes in American muscle cars from the '60s and '70s, RM Auctions of Blenheim, Ontario, features mainline collectibles like Duesenbergs and Ferraris. RM offers far fewer cars than Barrett-Jackson, but has a much higher average price per car. RM sold 106 out of 114 cars offered for a total of nearly $30 million. This was down $1.4 million from 2006, and the average price per car ($281,838) was down $13,382 from a year earlier.</p>
        <p>In an e-mail message, RM's president, Rob Myers, said, ''We see sports racing cars as the strongest growth segment of the market and also keep an eye on the great antiques and classics that will continue to be strong.''</p>
        <p>Another auction company, Russo &amp; Steele, is known for offering American muscle cars. Russo &amp; Steele raised its total slightly from 2006, selling 280 out of 431 cars for $20.2 million, up from $19.8 million. The company's owner, Drew Alcazar, said that while well-documented cars were still strong, customized cars and nonoriginal creations had started to show weakness.</p>
        <p>The average price per car sold at Russo &amp; Steele was up slightly, from $66,318 in 2006 to $68,000.</p>
        <p>The final event of the weekend, by Silver Auctions of Spokane, Wash., reported sales of 276 cars for about $5 million, down from $5.7 million and 233 cars in 2006. The average price per car sold this year was $18,116, indicative of the ''affordable classics'' market segment in which Silver specializes.</p>
        <p>COLLECTING</p>
        <p>Correction:  February 4, 2007, Sunday  An article last Sunday about four recent collector-car auctions in Arizona misstated some sales results for this year and previous years. A total of 1,916 cars were reported sold, not 3,923, at an average price of about $86,000, not $41,000. The average price at one auction company, Russo &amp; Steele, was $72,213, not $68,000. Another company, Barrett-Jackson, had sales of $37 million, not $34 million, at the 2004 auction, and $62 million, not $65 million, at the 2005 event.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: February 4, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about four recent collector-car auctions in Arizona misstated some sales results for this year and previous years. A total of 1,916 cars were reported sold, not 3,923, at an average price of about $86,000, not $41,000. The average price at one auction company, Russo &amp; Steele, was $72,213, not $68,000. Another company, Barrett-Jackson, had sales of $37 million, not $34 million, at the 2004 auction, and $62 million, not $65 million, at the 2005 event.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
