<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Night. Shall We Snorkel, Cycle or Hike?</title>
    <meta content="28journeys" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/28/travel/28journeys.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1822282"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="JOURNEYS: NOCTURNAL PURSUITS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glusac, Elaine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Snorkeling and Diving</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Biking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Snorkeling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snorkeling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E4DA1F30F93BA15752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1323" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Night. Shall We Snorkel, Cycle or Hike?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">It’s Night. Shall We Snorkel, Cycle or Hike?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELAINE GLUSAC</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glusac, Elaine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elaine Glusac travel article on latest nighttime pursuits being offered by tour groups, resorts, spas and tourist attractions in several cities; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN night falls in New York or Paris, one goes clubbing or bar hopping. In a Texas park, the choices include bat detecting; in the Channel Islands of Britain, full-moon tidal treks; and in St. Louis, candlelight museum prowls.</p>
        <p>More and more resorts, spas and tourist attractions are offering creative alternatives to dining and drinking the night away. Keyed to the science and mood of darkness, and inaugurated by activities like turtle-nesting watches in Costa Rica and guided stargazing in Hawaii, the new breed of night programs breaks from the mold of ghost-telling tours and pub crawls in nocturnal outings that range from novel to educational. Here are some of the latest offerings aimed at keeping you up at night.</p>
        <p>Night-Vision Assisted</p>
        <p>The popularity of night-vision technology has lit up the recreational world, allowing scope-toting hikers to see nocturnal creatures and more stars than the naked eye allows. For instance, Desert Storm Hummer Tours combines two military-turned-civilian inventions in its night-vision-assisted drive through the Sonoran Desert near Scottsdale, Ariz., after dark. After issuing riders night-vision monoculars, guides wearing three-pound night-vision headsets drive an eight-mile desert trail without headlights, looking for coyote, bobcats, rattlesnakes and other critters. Ultra-violet lights on the desert floor illuminate tarantulas and scorpions, and guests pass around a thermal-image scope, allowing the eye to capture all warm-blooded creatures within 500 feet. Offered nightly, tours cost $125 for adults, $100 for those 6 to 16; (866) 374-8637; www.dshummer.com.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>More and more resorts, spas and tourist attractions are offering creative alternatives to dining and drinking the night away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN night falls in New York or Paris, one goes clubbing or bar hopping. In a Texas park, the choices include bat detecting; in the Channel Islands of Britain, full-moon tidal treks; and in St. Louis, candlelight museum prowls.</p>
        <p>More and more resorts, spas and tourist attractions are offering creative alternatives to dining and drinking the night away. Keyed to the science and mood of darkness, and inaugurated by activities like turtle-nesting watches in Costa Rica and guided stargazing in Hawaii, the new breed of night programs breaks from the mold of ghost-telling tours and pub crawls in nocturnal outings that range from novel to educational. Here are some of the latest offerings aimed at keeping you up at night.</p>
        <p>Night-Vision Assisted</p>
        <p>The popularity of night-vision technology has lit up the recreational world, allowing scope-toting hikers to see nocturnal creatures and more stars than the naked eye allows. For instance, Desert Storm Hummer Tours combines two military-turned-civilian inventions in its night-vision-assisted drive through the Sonoran Desert near Scottsdale, Ariz., after dark. After issuing riders night-vision monoculars, guides wearing three-pound night-vision headsets drive an eight-mile desert trail without headlights, looking for coyote, bobcats, rattlesnakes and other critters. Ultra-violet lights on the desert floor illuminate tarantulas and scorpions, and guests pass around a thermal-image scope, allowing the eye to capture all warm-blooded creatures within 500 feet. Offered nightly, tours cost $125 for adults, $100 for those 6 to 16; (866) 374-8637; www.dshummer.com.</p>
        <p>At the new Hyatt Regency Lost Pines Resort and Spa near Austin, Tex., guests explore the neighboring McKinney Roughs Nature Park in interpretive night hikes led by a naturalist. Guests share night-vision equipment to spy possums, armadillos and deer while a ''bat detector'' picks up the echolocations of darting bats. Tours daily in summer, weekends the rest of the year; $12; (512) 308-1234; www.lostpines.hyatt.com.</p>
        <p>From 9 to 11 nightly, guests of Disney's Animal Kingdom Lodge in Orlando, Fla., can glimpse some of the resort savannah's 200 animals and birds. Guides lend night-vision glasses for looks at zebras, wildebeests and giraffes as close as 15 feet away; (407) 938-3000; www.disneyworld.disney.go.com.</p>
        <p>As night-vision scopes are to adult adventures, flashlights are to children's programs. Zoos and aquariums around the country including the Jacksonville Zoo and Gardens in Florida (Pack Prowls: $20; 904-757-4463; www.jaxzoo.org) and Waikiki Aquarium in Hawaii (Aquarium After Dark: $10; 808-923-9741; www.waquarium.org) offer special evening tours by flashlight. The Nashville Zoo lets adults in on the action in an after-hours peek at snakes and reptiles in its St. Patrick's Day-themed Adventure Social complete with beer March 15 ($40; 615-833-1534; www.nashvillezoo.org).</p>
        <p>Walking and Diving</p>
        <p>At Spring Creek Ranch in Jackson Hole, Wyo., a resident naturalist, Kurt Johnson, leads on-property hikes to call for owls, playing recorded owl cries and noting any responses. Owl Hoots are offered as part of a summer astronomy program, free to guests twice weekly; (307) 733-8833; www.springcreekranch.com.</p>
        <p>Nighttime walks in the Francis Beidler Forest, the world's largest virgin cypress-tupelo swamp forest, some 50 miles west of Charleston, S.C., venture into the eerie quiet of the 1,000-year-old woods. Trekkers follow a one-and-three-quarter-mile boardwalk over the swamp listening for owls and otters and, with flashlights, spot alligator eyes and spider nests. Night walks, $8, are held monthly; (843) 462-2150; www.beidlerforest.com.</p>
        <p>Taking a cue from night scuba dives, snorkelers too can witness the nocturnal action on the oceans' reefs. Squid, moray eels and Caribbean lobsters emerge after dark on the reefs around St. Thomas in the United States Virgin Islands where the guide, Homer Calloway of Homer's Scuba and Snorkel Tours, supplies mask, fins, wet suit and underwater flashlight. Tours Tuesday to Saturday, $38; (866) 719-1856; www.nightsnorkel.com. The Sheraton Keauhou on Hawaii's Big Island offers nighttime snorkeling and diving trips to the manta ray feeding grounds just offshore, setting up lights on the ocean floor. Tours Monday through Friday, $79 adults, $59 ages 4 to 12; (808) 930-4900; www.sheratonkeauhou.com.</p>
        <p>The Sporting Life</p>
        <p>Guests at the new Anantara Resort Maldives, opened in September on a five-acre island in the South Male Atoll, can shove off at sunset to fish from an indigenous dhoni sailboat, trailing local tackle -- that is, a baited hook on a fishing line. The catch is wok-fried by the chef back at the resort. Two-hour fishing outings take place three times a week for $49 a person; (66) 2877-5803; www.anantara.com.</p>
        <p>Cycling in the dark at the Boulders Resort in Carefree, Ariz., is far less suicidal than in urban traffic. Led by a guide and supplied with a 15-watt light, bike and helmet, riders follow the halogen-lighted paved golf-cart paths, looking for coyotes and hares and stopping for a bit of stargazing. The 90-minute tours cost $95; (866) 397-6520; www.theboulders.com.</p>
        <p>Moonlight Events</p>
        <p>Where downhill skiers have slopes illuminated by flood lamps to boost their vertical mileage, snowshoers and cross-country skiers rely on moonshine. The Mammoth Mountain ski resort in California organizes full-moon snowshoeing and cross-country skiing at its Tamarack Cross Country Ski Center in the company of a naturalist. The tours, which cost $35, conclude with dessert by the lodge's fireplace and are held on six dates January through March; (800) 626-6684; www.mammothmountain.com.</p>
        <p>Moonlight massages promise relaxation under the stars for couples in a candlelit poolside spot at Peninsula Spa in the Peninsula Beverly Hills. Cost is $350; 310-551-2888; www.beverlyhills.peninsula.com. During candlelight watsu at Sanctuary on Camelback Resort's Sanctuary Spa in Paradise Valley, Ariz., votives ring the heated, outdoor pool encircled by walls that frame the stars above. Winter only; from $135; (480) 948-2100; www.sanctuaryoncamelback.com.</p>
        <p>Come full moons, the tides on the British Channel Island of Jersey recede up to two miles. During these events, most dramatic at the spring and autumn equinox, Derek Hairon, a guide with Jersey Kayak Adventures, offers ''moonwalks,'' two-and-a-half-hour night hikes on the lunarlike, drained ocean bed. The cost is £12 ($24 at $2 to the pound); (44-1534) 853033; www.jerseykayakadventures.co.uk.</p>
        <p>Culture in the Dark</p>
        <p>While beating the summer desert heat, two-hour night tours of Taliesin West, the seasonal home and studio of Frank Lloyd Wright, offer the beauty of viewing Wright's organic buildings lighted from within like lanterns arrayed on the 600-acre campus. Last year the organization expanded from Fridays only to also include Thursdays from March through September. Tours cost $30; (480) 860-2700; www.franklloydwright.org.</p>
        <p>On Friday and Saturday nights, the innovative City Museum in St. Louis, an artist-designed children's museum that appeals to all ages, fills the subterranean and vertical climbing tunnels with candles placed strategically in the mouths of relief sculptures of gargoyles and dragons. Admission is $8 after 5 p.m. and the museum stays open until 1 a.m. for night prowls; (314) 231-2489; www.citymuseum.org.</p>
        <p>At Conner Prairie, a living history museum near Indianapolis, participants are offered the disturbing experience of acting as fugitive slaves following the Underground Railroad, encountering re-enacted slave sales and slave hunts in the dark of night. Offered weekends in April and November, the often-harrowing event is limited to participants over the age of 12. Cost is $16; (317) 776-6006; www.connerprairie.org.</p>
        <p>This winter the Museum of Neon Art in Los Angeles begins its Poet's Beat Neon Tour featuring the spoken-word performer Mike Sonksen on a drive through the neon corridor of illuminated bowling pins, a bakery and theater marquees from downtown to Hollywood. En route the bus stops at three bars with admirable neon outdoors and libations within. The monthly winter itinerary supplements the Saturday night Neon Cruises held by the museum weekly June through October in an open-air double-decker bus. Poet's cruise, $25; neon cruise, $45; (213) 489-9918, www.neonmona.org.</p>
        <p>Miniaturizing the drive-in to living-room level, Las Ventanas al Paraiso, a Rosewood Resort in Los Cabos, Mexico, newly offers guests private movie screenings on the beach at night. Guests get their own private serape-topped beach lounge chairs, 50-inch plasma TVs, a 219-title DVD selection and ''cinema butlers'' to fetch lime-chili-cilantro popcorn, guacamole and drinks. Thursday evening screenings are $250 a couple; (888) 767-3966; www.lasventanas.com.</p>
        <p>JOURNEYS: NOCTURNAL PURSUITS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
