<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Record Day for Women Highlights Reebok Games</title>
    <meta content="28track" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/28/sports/othersports/28track.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1822182"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TRACK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Litsky, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dibaba, Tirunesh</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Webb, Alan</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Flanagan, Shalane</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EFD6173FF93BA15752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="613" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Record Day for Women Highlights Reebok Games</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Women Set Record Pace at Reebok Games</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK LITSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Litsky, Frank</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, Jan. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tirunesh Dibaba wins 5,000-meter race at Reebok Boston Indoor Games (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tirunesh Dibaba, a 21-year-old Ethiopian, likes running in Boston, and who can blame her?</p>
        <p>Two years ago, in the Reebok Boston Indoor Games, she set a world record of 14 minutes 32.95 seconds for the 5,000 meters. Saturday night, in the same meet before a near-capacity crowd of 4,000 at the Reggie Lewis Center, she lowered the record to 14:27.42.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tirunesh Dibaba, a 21-year-old Ethiopian, lowered the indoor record for the 5,000 meters to 14:27.42 on Saturday in the Reebok Boston Indoor Games.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tirunesh Dibaba, a 21-year-old Ethiopian, likes running in Boston, and who can blame her?</p>
        <p>Two years ago, in the Reebok Boston Indoor Games, she set a world record of 14 minutes 32.95 seconds for the 5,000 meters. Saturday night, in the same meet before a near-capacity crowd of 4,000 at the Reggie Lewis Center, she lowered the record to 14:27.42.</p>
        <p>The world record outdoors is 14:24.53 by Meseret Defar, another Ethiopian, who ran here in the 3,000 meters and won in 8:30.31, the fifth-fastest time ever. Shalane Flanagan finished a strong second in 8:33.25, an American record.</p>
        <p>Had Defar raced against Dibaba, the excitement could have been overwhelming. But meet officials, aware of the popularity of distance racing here and the ticket-buying support of the city's large Ethiopian community, opted to have the women run in different distance races.</p>
        <p>The women's exploits overshadowed the men's mile, even though that event created an excitement of its own. Alan Webb, who ran his indoor best of 3:56.70 a week ago at the New Balance Track &amp; Field Center in Upper Manhattan, lowered that mark to 3:55.18. He led by as much as 30 meters and won by 18 meters over Kevin Sullivan of Canada (3:57.33). Next up for Webb is the Wanamaker Mile in the 100th annual Millrose Games on Friday night at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>This was the first major meet of the American indoor track season. Of the six runners in the women's 5,000, three were Ethiopians and two of the three others were rabbits.</p>
        <p>There was little doubt who would win. From the start, Dibaba and her 24-year-old sister, Ejegayehu, pressed the pace. By 2,600 meters, the rabbits were gone and Tirunesh started pulling away from her sister.</p>
        <p>On her last time around the fast 200-meter track, she lapped her sister, sprinted the final 200 meters in 29.72 seconds and won, looking as strong as when she had started. Then she collected her rewards: an Ethiopian flag, a bottle of water and a $25,000 check for breaking a world record.</p>
        <p>''I'm very happy about what I accomplished,'' she said through an interpreter. ''I was so prepared. I didn't do any cross-country because I was concentrating on this race, so I had the confidence to break the record. With two laps to go, I knew I would do it, but I didn't think I would do it by this much.''</p>
        <p>In the men's mile, Webb had high expectations and lived up to them. He burst out at the start behind Moise Joseph of Haiti, the rabbit, ran the first quarter-mile in 55.3 seconds and left the others 20 meters behind.</p>
        <p>''I don't know why anyone would be surprised,'' Webb said. ''At 250 meters, I was a loner. I think my strength is really good.</p>
        <p>''I think I'm just getting used to running this fast. I have the ability to run fast indoors because that strength is inside of me.''</p>
        <p>NOTES</p>
        <p>The men's winners included Shawn Crawford in the 60-meter dash (6.55 seconds), David Payne in the 60-meter hurdles (7.58 seconds), Nick Symmonds in the 800 meters (1:48.15), the 40-year-old Mark Coogan in the masters mile (4:24.71), Craig Mottram of Australia in the 3,000 (7:39.24), Steven Hooker of Australia in the pole vault (19 feet  3/4 inch) and Dan Taylor in the shot-put (70-9 1/4, his best ever indoors). Among the women's winners were Sarah Jamieson of Australia in the mile (4:28.03), Marshevet Hooker in the 60 (7.24 seconds), Perdita Felicien of Canada in the 60 hurdles (7.97 seconds), Monica Hargrove in the 400 (52.85) and Jenn Stuczynski in the pole vault (15-3 1/4). Mottram, Hooker and Jamieson set Australian indoor records.</p>
        <p>TRACK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
