<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Courageous Decision At Life's End</title>
    <meta content="l28island-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1822214"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kagan, Barbara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koff, Teri</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Span, Paula</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE4DF143FF93BA15752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="345" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Courageous Decision At Life's End</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Barbara Kagan and elder-care specialist Teri Koff letters on Paula Span's January 21 Generations essay on her elderly father</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I had to laugh when I read Paula Span's comments on her father's cheapness (''Care in Old Age: Confronting the Inevitable,'' Generations, Jan. 21).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I had to laugh when I read Paula Span's comments on her father's cheapness (''Care in Old Age: Confronting the Inevitable,'' Generations, Jan. 21).</p>
        <p>It wasn't the only similarity I saw in my own father, who once spent way too much time arguing with the post office because it refused to let him use Scotch tape on a stamp that had lost its stickiness. He just couldn't stand the idea that he had to throw the stamp away.</p>
        <p>My dad always kept us up to date on where all the important papers were. Before he died, he gave us all a great gift: He made his own decision to forgo a feeding tube. He stated simply that he had had a good long life, and that it was time to go.</p>
        <p>As Ms. Span so eloquently put it, it was a final act of parenthood. I admired him so much for having the strength and courage to make the decision. Because he spared us from having to make difficult, final choices, I was able to finally forgive him for so many other parental injustices.</p>
        <p>Barbara Kagan  Clinton, Conn.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''Care in Old Age: Confronting the Inevitable'' effectively highlighted the challenges individuals face when caring for the needs of our aging population. Most Americans do not abandon their frail, aging parents but are blindsided by the enormous costs and legal barriers that must be surmounted to provide adequate and safe care in this country.</p>
        <p>The Boy Scout motto, ''Be prepared,'' is the best defense baby boomers have to combat the complicated facets of elder care and to effectively facilitate change. Some individuals may find the discussion of sensitive issues facing older adults difficult and distasteful; therefore they delay and deny its importance. Planning ahead and seeking professional advice is empowering.</p>
        <p>The value of addressing these issues alleviates the frustration when a loved one's capacity is in question and there are no advance directives in place.</p>
        <p>Teri Koff  New York</p>
        <p>The writer is an elder-care specialist.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
