<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>5,000 More Parking Spaces For Metro-North Stations</title>
    <meta content="28ctweekCN-3" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1822219"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WEEK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E3DF143FF93BA15752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="312" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>5,000 More Parking Spaces For Metro-North Stations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF HOLTZ</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>About 5,000 parking spaces will be added at Metro-North train stations over the next few years, the State Department of Transportation said last week.</p>
        <p>The department said 3,000 spaces would be for two new stations, one planned for the border of Orange and West Haven, which would get 2,000 spaces, and the other, a second station in Fairfield, near the Bridgeport line, which would get 1,000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>About 5,000 parking spaces will be added at Metro-North train stations over the next few years, the State Department of Transportation said last week.</p>
        <p>The department said 3,000 spaces would be for two new stations, one planned for the border of Orange and West Haven, which would get 2,000 spaces, and the other, a second station in Fairfield, near the Bridgeport line, which would get 1,000.</p>
        <p>A new surface lot and two new decks to be built on the existing garage in Bridgeport would add 500 spaces; a planned multideck garage in Stratford would add 435; and another 100 would be on a deck to be built over the present lot in Wilton, the department said. As many as 1,000 spaces could also be added in New Haven.</p>
        <p>Eugene J. Colonese, the department's rail administrator, said that the earliest that work on the new garages could begin would be this year in Bridgeport.</p>
        <p>State Senator John McKinney, Republican of Fairfield, a member of the Legislature's transportation committee, said that 5,000 spaces would not be enough. He said other lots at stations between Stamford and Fairfield were also overcrowded.</p>
        <p>In Westport, for example, the police said 930 people were waiting for about 1,500 reserved spaces at its Saugatuck and Greens Farms stations. They said the wait was about four years for a town resident and about six years for nonresidents.</p>
        <p>Mr. McKinney said towns should develop plans for more parking and the state should make money available to help. ''We have $600 million committed to buying new rail cars to increase ridership on Metro-North, but we're not going to be able to do that if people can't park at the train station,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Colonese said the transportation department was always looking for ways to add parking. ''We realize it is a constraint on ridership,'' he said.</p>
        <p>JEFF HOLTZ</p>
        <p>THE WEEK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
