<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Jail Break, But Not to Fear</title>
    <meta content="28jail" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/28/nyregion/thecity/28jail.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070204T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1822071"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: SOUTH BRONX"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Construction and Maintenance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Bronx (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E1DC173FF93BA15752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="422" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Jail Break, But Not to Fear</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Jail Break, but Not to Fear</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER BLEYER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bronx House of Detention was reduced to little more than a mountain of rubble by last week. A high-reach excavator clawed ferociously at the last of its steel beams, adding them to a heap of brick and stone.</p>
        <p>But salvaged from the Art Deco-detailed jail were various architectural flourishes that are to find new life in a setting very different from the old one. The elements will be installed in a new shopping mall, the Gateway Center, which is being built on the site.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bronx House of Detention was reduced to little more than a mountain of rubble by last week. A high-reach excavator clawed ferociously at the last of its steel beams, adding them to a heap of brick and stone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Bronx House of Detention was reduced to little more than a mountain of rubble by last week. A high-reach excavator clawed ferociously at the last of its steel beams, adding them to a heap of brick and stone.</p>
        <p>But salvaged from the Art Deco-detailed jail were various architectural flourishes that are to find new life in a setting very different from the old one. The elements will be installed in a new shopping mall, the Gateway Center, which is being built on the site.</p>
        <p>The 350-cell jail, designed by Joseph Freedlander and located a few blocks south of Yankee Stadium, was built as a Works Progress Administration project and opened in 1937 as the Bronx County Jail. Although the inside view failed to gladden its tenants for the obvious reasons, its exterior was highly regarded for the noble heft and the stately ornamentation of granite and limestone, including a frieze of Corinthian columns and eagles in bas-relief near the top of its central pavilion, and two prominent eagle statues.</p>
        <p>The jail closed in 2000, and the city later struck a deal with the Related Companies, a major developer, to demolish it and build the $500 million Gateway Center, which will include 1 million square feet of retail space and a new park along the Harlem River. Ground was broken in August for the project, which will also encompass the site of the Bronx Terminal Market.</p>
        <p>As the approval process advanced, the New York State Office of Historic Preservation recommended saving some of the jail's distinctive ornaments. As a result, the eagles, parts of the frieze and the jail's gatehouse have been cleaned, crated and placed in a Bronx storage facility.</p>
        <p>Robert Ursini, the senior vice president for Related Retail Corporation, said the ornaments will be positioned in the Gateway Center's plaza along River Avenue, and the frieze bands will be installed directly in the new mall's exterior architecture.</p>
        <p>''It gives the project a unique flavor,'' Mr. Ursini said.</p>
        <p>Additionally, he said, a plaque will be installed in the plaza describing the significance of the Bronx House of Detention and of Mr. Freedlander, the architect, who also designed the nearby Bronx County Courthouse.</p>
        <p>Some of those interested in the city's corrections past were pleased that at least part of the Bronx jail's memory is being preserved.</p>
        <p>''It was part of people's lives,'' said Thomas McMurphy, a former corrections officer who runs the New York Correction History Society. ''My hat is off to the people who saved the day.''</p>
        <p>JENNIFER BLEYER</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: SOUTH BRONX</p>
        <p>Correction:  February 4, 2007, Sunday  An article last Sunday about architectural decorations salvaged during the demolition of the Bronx House of Detention misstated the surname of the New York Correction History Society's general secretary, who commented on the effort. He is Thomas McCarthy, not McMurphy. The article also misstated his former position. He was a civilian employee of the city's Department of Correction -- not a corrections officer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: February 4, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about architectural decorations salvaged during the demolition of the Bronx House of Detention misstated the surname of the New York Correction History Society's general secretary, who commented on the effort. He is Thomas McCarthy, not McMurphy. The article also misstated his former position. He was a civilian employee of the city's Department of Correction -- not a corrections officer.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
