<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cozy, Friendly, Full of Surprises</title>
    <meta content="07weekend" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/07/travel/07weekend.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1816884"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEEKEND IN NEW YORK | INDEPENDENT BOOKSTORES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kugel, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E0D61F31F934A35752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1104" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cozy, Friendly, Full of Surprises</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Independent Bookstores: Cozy, Friendly, Full of Surprises</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH KUGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kugel, Seth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Seth Kugel Weekend in New York column on some of city's independent bookstores; list; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK has always been known as a city capable of sating any desire: for money, for high fashion, for companionship. But if you're just a bespectacled out-of-towner who suffers from simple book lust, its eclectic collection of independent bookstores can scratch your itch, too.</p>
        <p>Even with the Jolly Green Corporate Bookstore Giant spreading its shelves throughout Manhattan faster than Meg Ryan's 1998 laptop can say ''You've got mail,'' the city still has many spots where specialized collections, cozy atmosphere and friendly and knowledgeable staff win out over huge selection, standardized décor and jam-packed cafes (serving coffee from that other Jolly Green Corporate Giant).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you’re a bespectacled out-of-towner who suffers from simple book lust, the city’s eclectic collection of independent bookstores can scratch your itch.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK has always been known as a city capable of sating any desire: for money, for high fashion, for companionship. But if you're just a bespectacled out-of-towner who suffers from simple book lust, its eclectic collection of independent bookstores can scratch your itch, too.</p>
        <p>Even with the Jolly Green Corporate Bookstore Giant spreading its shelves throughout Manhattan faster than Meg Ryan's 1998 laptop can say ''You've got mail,'' the city still has many spots where specialized collections, cozy atmosphere and friendly and knowledgeable staff win out over huge selection, standardized décor and jam-packed cafes (serving coffee from that other Jolly Green Corporate Giant).</p>
        <p>The Complete Traveller Bookstore is the perfect example of a tiny shop that can suck you in and not spit you out till hours later, lost in dreamy thoughts of other places and times. It is set up like the travel section of a regular bookstore -- that is, geographically -- except that all the books here are vintage, if not downright ancient.</p>
        <p>Harry A. Franck's ''Roaming Through the West Indies'' was undoubtedly a useful guidebook in the 1920s, long before Lonely Planet made traveling the planet much less lonely. And you don't see too many book titles like ''A Yankee in Pygmy Land'' these days.</p>
        <p>The back room also has a beguiling batch of W.P.A. American Guides from the 1930s and early 1940s, when out-of-work writers were paid by the government to write guidebooks to the 48 states. For the cartographically inclined, there is an absorbing collection of historical United States and international maps for sale, many of them hand-colored.</p>
        <p>For those traveling with children (who, for some reason, tend to get bored with guidebooks by federally employed writers from the 1930s), there is Books of Wonder, a children's bookshop with a conscience: books adapted from movies, television and video games are not sold. The store holds story time every Sunday at noon, there is a rare books section (full of Frank Baum's Oz series) and, best of all, a staff so friendly and knowledgeable that they would probably be fired from average retail jobs for spending too much time with customers. Sharing the space is an outpost of the Cupcake Cafe, which makes this one-stop shopping for kids' two most urgent needs: fine literature and sugar.</p>
        <p>Forbidden Planet, which shares its name with the 1956 science fiction movie that introduced Robby the Robot, spans the exotic worlds of science fiction and fantasy, comic books and comic strips and Japanese anime and manga. And this funky store, which turned 25 last year, also has many action figures for all budgets. Seeking that lifesize Bride of Chucky doll or a die-cast version of Speed Racer's Mach 5? Then this is the place.</p>
        <p>If reading in languages other than English is your thing, there are many bookstores for you. One, Librairie de France, is right at Rockefeller Center, where thousands of tourists pass by every day without noticing it. Surprisingly, the store also has a good selection of Spanish literature, but French rules, with everything from the complete works of Anatole France to more about the Petit Prince than could fit onto Asteroid B612. And there are signs that would boost the ego of any Francophile feline: ''Attention -- Chat Féroce.''</p>
        <p>There are plenty of other specialty spots, from the astrological, metaphysical and spiritual collection at Quest Bookshop on the East Side, to the Drama Bookshop for theater lovers in Midtown, to the gay and lesbian Oscar Wilde Bookshop in Greenwich Village, to the Mysterious Bookshop in TriBeCa, whose crime novels figuratively drip with blood and which is the perfect place to find a hot thriller to keep you warm on a cold winter's night.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, though, you just want a regular bookstore. At McNally Robinson in NoLIta, the selection is broad but not overwhelming, the cafe serves tea with a board-game-size hourglass so it does not steep for too long, and the bathroom wall carries short quotes from the likes of Henry Miller, Ralph Ellison and Anne Tyler -- and a longer one from Annie Dillard. On Saturdays at noon, a Spanish discussion group meets, led by Javier Molea (who owned a bookstore in Uruguay).</p>
        <p>St. Mark's Bookshop is a good last stop since it's open till midnight on Fridays and Saturdays. It's a general bookstore that leans toward the literary (and the left). The black shelves are placed at odd angles, as if they were the stacks in a college library after a minor earthquake.</p>
        <p>And, of course, there's the Strand, which says it offers 18 miles of new and used books -- that's roughly from Midtown to Paterson, N.J. It's not for those looking for a peaceful, comfy corner to settle down in, but the used books and discounted new ones are impossible to match. Anyone can build an instant (though quirky) library from the dollar shelves on the sidewalk outside, and search inside for everything from ''The Field Guide to Warblers of North America'' to Anne Lamott's ''Bird by Bird'' to William Wharton's ''Birdy.''</p>
        <p>NEED A COPY OF ANATOLE FRANCE?</p>
        <p>A sampling of independent bookshops in Manhattan; only weekend hours are shown.</p>
        <p>Books of Wonder, 18 West 18th Street between Fifth and Sixth Avenues, (212) 989-3270; Saturday, 10 a.m. to 7 p.m.; Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>Complete Traveller Bookstore, 199 Madison Avenue at 35th Street, (212) 685-9007; Saturday, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Sunday, noon to 5 p.m.</p>
        <p>Drama Book Shop, 250 West 40th Street, between Seventh and Eighth Avenues, (212) 944-0595; Saturday, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Sunday, noon to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>Forbidden Planet, 840 Broadway at 13th Street, (212) 473-1576; Saturday, 10 a.m. to midnight; Sunday, 10 a.m. to 10 p.m.</p>
        <p>Librairie de France, 610 Fifth Avenue on the Rockefeller Center Promenade, (212) 581-8810; Saturday, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; closed Sunday.</p>
        <p>McNally Robinson, 52 Prince Street between Lafayette and Mulberry Streets, (212) 274-1160; Saturday, 10 a.m. to 10 p.m.; Sunday, 10 a.m. to 9 p.m.</p>
        <p>Mysterious Bookshop, 58 Warren Street between West Broadway and Church Street, (212) 587-1011; Saturday and Sunday, 11 a.m. to 7 p.m.</p>
        <p>Oscar Wilde Bookshop, 15 Christopher Street between Sixth and Seventh Avenues, (212) 255-8097; Saturday and Sunday, 11 a.m. to 7 p.m.</p>
        <p>Quest Bookshop, 240 East 53rd Street between Second and Third Avenues, (212) 758-5521; Saturday, noon to 8 p.m.; Sunday, 1 to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>St. Mark's Bookshop, 31 Third Avenue at Ninth Street, (212) 260-7853; Saturday, 10 a.m. to midnight; Sunday, 11 a.m. to midnight.</p>
        <p>Strand Bookstore, 828 Broadway at 12th Street, (212) 473-1452; Saturday, 9:30 a.m. to 10:30 p.m.; Sunday, 11 a.m. to 10:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>WEEKEND IN NEW YORK | INDEPENDENT BOOKSTORES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
