<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Special Election, Another Hurdle for G.O.P.</title>
    <meta content="07lipolLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/07/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/07lipol.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1816976"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON POLITICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislature</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nassau County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rather, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mondello, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Balboni, Michael A L (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spitzer, Eliot (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E4D91730F934A35752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="672" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Special Election, Another Hurdle for G.O.P.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Special Election, Another Hurdle for G.O.P.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RATHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rather, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Rather On Politics column on possible political challenges that New York State Republican chairman Joseph Mondello faces in special election to fill seat of Sen Michael Balboni; Balboni has been named by Gov Eliot Spitzer to head up homeland security; Democrats hold slight registration edge in Nassau County but Mondello would benefit if Republican won seat; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Republican leaders meeting in Albany on Nov. 30 named Joseph N. Mondello their state chairman on the heels of an election in which Republicans took a historic drubbing, Mr. Mondello, in a flash of candor, said he was taking over a party that had hit rock bottom.</p>
        <p>''We've got almost no place further down that we can go,'' Mr. Mondello, the longtime Nassau Republican chairman, said in an interview that day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Republican leaders meeting in Albany on Nov. 30 named Joseph N. Mondello their state chairman on the heels of an election in which Republicans took a historic drubbing, Mr. Mondello, in a flash of candor, said he was taking over a party that had hit rock bottom.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Republican leaders meeting in Albany on Nov. 30 named Joseph N. Mondello their state chairman on the heels of an election in which Republicans took a historic drubbing, Mr. Mondello, in a flash of candor, said he was taking over a party that had hit rock bottom.</p>
        <p>''We've got almost no place further down that we can go,'' Mr. Mondello, the longtime Nassau Republican chairman, said in an interview that day.</p>
        <p>Now, a little more than a month but a political eternity later, it appears Mr. Mondello may have spoken too soon.</p>
        <p>Never mind that Joseph L. Bruno, the State Senate leader and, with the end of the Pataki era, the most powerful Republican in the state, has since disclosed that he is under federal investigation for his outside consulting work.</p>
        <p>With a new Democratic governor, Eliot Spitzer, reaching across party lines in late December to name a Republican, State Senator Michael A. L. Balboni of East Williston, to head up homeland security, Mr. Mondello is abruptly facing a bruising special election in his home base to fill Mr. Balboni's seat. Mr. Spitzer will set the date for the election, probably for early to mid-February.</p>
        <p>If a Democrat wins the northwestern Nassau district, where Democrats hold a slight registration edge, it would be a major embarrassment for Mr. Mondello, the first chipping away of the Republican grip on all nine State Senate seats for Long Island. It would also further narrow the slender majority Republicans hold in the Senate.</p>
        <p>But if a Republican wins, Mr. Mondello would gain luster. And if Mr. Bruno, who chose Mr. Mondello for state chairman, were forced out, Mr. Mondello has close ties to the heir apparent, State Senator Dean G. Skelos, of Rockville Centre.</p>
        <p>Anthony Santino, a spokesman for Mr. Mondello, said last week that no decision had been made on a candidate. But Mr. Mondello's widely expected choice is Maureen O'Connell, 56, of East Williston, a former registered nurse and lawyer who served in the State Assembly from 1999 to last January, when she took over as Nassau County clerk.</p>
        <p>Ms. O'Connell did not answer calls to her office. Mr. Santino said Mr. Mondello was unavailable. ''We're certainly going to wage a very aggressive campaign to keep the seat Republican,'' Mr. Santino said.</p>
        <p>Jay S. Jacobs, the Nassau Democratic chairman, said Mr. Spitzer's landslide election on a reform platform gave local Democrats momentum. He said federal scrutiny of Mr. Bruno would be an issue. ''Joe Mondello was handpicked by Joseph Bruno, so you do the math,'' Mr. Jacobs said. ''Their candidate would be critical of Bruno at his or her peril.''</p>
        <p>Craig M. Johnson, 33, of Port Washington, who is a third-term Nassau County legislator and whose district is within the senatorial district, was seen as a front-runner for the Democratic nomination.</p>
        <p>Mr. Johnson, a lawyer with a practice in bankruptcy and commercial law, earned notice in March when he endorsed Mr. Spitzer for governor at a time when Nassau's top Democratic official, County Executive Thomas R. Suozzi, was seeking the office. Mr. Johnson declined to comment last week on his candidacy.</p>
        <p>Other leading candidates are Michelle Schimel, the North Hempstead town clerk, and Matthew Cuomo, a cousin of State Attorney General Andrew M. Cuomo and nephew of former Gov. Mario M. Cuomo. Nassau County Legislator Roger H. Corbin and Rocco Iannarelli, the North Hempstead tax receiver, were also on the list. State Assemblyman Thomas P. DiNapoli of Great Neck could also emerge as a candidate unless Mr. Spitzer names him to succeed State Comptroller Alan G. Hevesi, who resigned last month in an ethics scandal involving misuse of state money to chauffeur his wife.</p>
        <p>Desmond Ryan, a veteran political lobbyist, said Mr. Spitzer's reform initiatives and Mr. Bruno's legal situation played strongly to the advantage of the Democrats. ''Their candidate will be able to say, 'Elect me and I will help you reform state government,' '' he said. He added that Long Island Republicans ''never do well in special elections.''</p>
        <p>ON POLITICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
