<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>36 Hours; Atlanta</title>
    <meta content="07hours" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/07/travel/07hours.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1816883"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Atlanta (Ga)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Georgia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dewan, Shaila</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/36 Hours</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia/Atlanta</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Atlanta (Ga)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E1D61F31F934A35752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1606" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>36 Hours; Atlanta</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">36 Hours in Atlanta</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHAILA DEWAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dewan, Shaila</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Shaila Dewan travel article on 36-hour visit to Atlanta, Ga; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FIRST, don't call it Hotlanta anymore. It's the ATL, the code for the teeming airport that is a fitting emblem for a city so transient it barely recognizes itself, where more than half the adult population is from somewhere else, and where every urban fad, from underground parking to savory ice cream, is embraced. A corporate stronghold, a Southern belle and a hip-hop capital, Atlanta wrestled with identity dysphoria as it searched for a new slogan (''Every day is an opening day,'' accompanied by a new theme song by the hip-hop impresario Dallas Austin) and tried to name its newborn giant panda (Bling Bling was rejected). Major civic investments like the new, grandiose $220 million aquarium, a significant expansion of the High Museum of Art by the architect Renzo Piano, and the purchase of the papers of the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. add up to a high tide of enthusiasm, even in a city where optimism is liberally indulged.</p>
        <p>Friday</p>
        <p>5:30 p.m.  1. Tastes of the Town</p>
        <p>Few places can be said to be definitively Atlantan, but the Colonnade (1879 Cheshire Bridge Road NE, 404-874-5642) is one: a meat-and-three restaurant with a full bar (rare) and a sizable gay clientele (more rare). The resulting mix is spectacular: black fingernails, Sansabelt trousers, birthday tiaras, Hawaiian shirts, all in a buzzing carpeted dining room with efficiently friendly waiters. When it comes to ordering, stick to the classics: a Bloody Mary to start ($5.50), fried chicken with yeasty dinner rolls straight from the school cafeteria ($10.95) and the day's pie ($3.50).</p>
        <p>7:30 p.m.  2. Men in Skirts</p>
        <p>Though it sounds vaguely revolutionary, contredansing is a folk tradition that involves following instructions from a caller, like square-dancing. If the notion of trying this in public gives you qualms, remember that 1) the likelihood of being seen by someone you know is low and 2) the tolerance quotient, at a weekly event where some men wear skirts to keep cool, is high. Show up at the gymnasium of the Morningside Baptist Church (1700 Piedmont Avenue) at 7:30 for basic lessons by the Chattahoochee County Dancers (770-939-8646; www.contradance.org), then swing your partner (you can easily find one there) to live old-time bands with names like Jump in the Skillet and Cattywampus (admission $7). Wear soft-soled shoes, or boogie in your socks.</p>
        <p>10:30 p.m.  3. Where Heads Spin</p>
        <p>Since you're already dizzy, visit the Sun Dial, the revolving bar atop the Westin (210 Peachtree Street; 404-589-7506; www.sundialrestaurant.com), where young Atlantans come for the throwback cool and occasional exhibitions of local art. Sip an Atlanta Hurricane (it's in the colada-daiquiri family and arrives in a souvenir glass, $14.95) or a chocolate martini as you orient yourself with a glittery panoramic view of downtown, the Georgia Dome, CNN's headquarters and the new aquarium.</p>
        <p>11:30 p.m.  4. On a Roll</p>
        <p>Roller-skating is an integral part of hip-hop culture in Atlanta, which is home to OutKast, Usher and Young Jeezy among other stars. Beyoncé had her 21st birthday party at the Cascade roller rink here, and Dallas Austin paid homage to the flawless moves of skate dancers in his recent movie ''The ATL.'' On Friday nights, the virtuosos descend on Golden Glide (2750 Wesley Chapel Road in Decatur, but it's tucked behind a shopping strip, 404-288-7773; www.atlantarollerskating.com) for adult skate, where posses practice their smooth moves (11:30 p.m. to 2:30 a.m., $7 including skate rental). If you haven't been practicing, skate inside the green line for your own safety. Or just stay on the sideline and gawk.</p>
        <p>Saturday</p>
        <p>Noon  5. Refueling</p>
        <p>You had a late night, so take your time getting to Watershed (406 West Ponce de Leon Avenue, Decatur; 404-378-4900), the gas station converted into an airy Southern restaurant where one of the Indigo Girls, Emily Saliers, is an owner, and Scott Peacock, an authority on Southern cooking, is the executive chef. Reservations are recommended, and child-tolerance is required, but the chicken hash with griddle cakes and poached eggs ($9) is worth the bother.</p>
        <p>1:30 p.m.  6. Posters and Aprons</p>
        <p>After brunch, browse the chic specialty shops near the main square of Decatur, the city-suburb that has won praise for its sensitive take on urban revitalization. One favorite is Mingei World Arts (427 Church Street; 404-371-0101; www.mingeiworldarts.com), an import store with a sense of humor, which offers vintage Bollywood posters ($25) and baskets woven from telephone wire ($24 to $45). For the designer chef there's Taste (416 Church Street; 404-370-1863), with two-handed Dumbo cups ($14.95) and vintage-print aprons ($34).</p>
        <p>3:30 p.m.  7. War on Canvas</p>
        <p>When Gen. John A. Logan was considering a run for vice president in the 1880s, he commissioned a political ad in the form of a giant painting of the Battle of Atlanta, in which he for a time commanded the Army of the Tennessee for the Union. The work, billed as the world's largest oil painting, is now housed in Grant Park, in a circular room not unlike a planetarium, and viewed from a rotating bank of seats (Atlanta Cyclorama and Civil War Museum, 800 Cherokee Avenue, 404-624-1071; www.bcaatlanta.com; adult admission $7). It is accompanied by a taped narration, a good way to get your requisite dose of Civil War history. A diorama was added in the 1930s, which sounds like a terrible idea until you see how seamlessly it blends into the painting, or notice a replica of Clark Gable as a dead Yankee. Tours begin every hour and half-hour; leave some time to see the exhibit on the Great Locomotive Chase, a slapstick adventure involving hand cars, cut wires and engines traveling in reverse.</p>
        <p>6 p.m.  8. Spreading the Sopchoppy</p>
        <p>A city where a treasured chef's departure can be front-page news, Atlanta has more than its share of fine restaurants, many of them cavernous, overdesigned colonizations of old industrial buildings. Smaller and friendlier is Restaurant Eugene (2277 Peachtree Road, 404-355-0321; www.restauranteugene.com), where the staff shares its passions readily and the menu can read like a Southern safari by Linton Hopkins, the chef: foie gras on French toast with Sopchoppy brand molasses from Florida ($21); A &amp; J Farms squash blossoms with Anson Mills's grits and Sweetgrass Dairy goat cheese ($12). The house mixologist, Greg Best, will prattle on about such matters as James Bond's favorite cocktail as he concocts something special from his homemade bitters and tinctures.</p>
        <p>8:30 p.m.  9. Where the Money Was</p>
        <p>Restored bank buildings are nothing new, but the owners of Pie Bar (2160 Monroe Drive; 404-815-1605; www.piebar.com) refurbished a 1962 branch -- yes, one of ''The Jetsons,'' flying-saucer kind, visible from the freeway like a ''Blade Runner'' mirage. The result is a sophisticated sports bar for a slick young crowd. Every wine is the same price (red $7, white $5). Pick a glass, then sample some lime-rosemary sorbet ($4).</p>
        <p>10 p.m.  10. Car-Driven Culture</p>
        <p>The Starlight Six Drive-In (2000 Moreland Avenue SE; 404-627-5786; $6 per person, cash only) -- ''movies and fun since 1949'' -- has that Southern-culture-on-the-skids charm, retro with a hint of rockabilly. Sometimes used for campy evenings of B-movies and bands (check www.starlightdrivein.com for the schedule), the rest of the time this is just a straight-up, steamy-windowed cinematic experience in a hummocky parking lot. It's not hard to find a decent movie on the schedule, but bring your own refreshments as the snack bar is paltry.</p>
        <p>Sunday</p>
        <p>10 a.m.  11. Quiet Neighbors</p>
        <p>The gruff proprietor of Ria's Bluebird (421 Memorial Drive SE, 404-521-3737; www.riasbluebird.com) has the word ''hate'' tattooed on the nape of her neck. But local residents give her nothing but love, lining up, pleasantly sleep-tousled, on weekend mornings for what some customers say are the world's best pancakes ($5.25 for a short stack with toasted pecans). The light-filled storefront is just right if you feel the need to keep your sunglasses on in the morning; the floor is made from wooden wall paneling, creating the illusion of an old barroom. If pancakes are a bit too sinful, try one of the inventive daily eggs Benedict specials, a mean chicken salad on a warm croissant ($8.50), and the house-made jam. The restaurant is across the street from Atlanta's oldest and loveliest cemetery, Oakland Cemetery (404-688-2107; www.oaklandcemetery.com), where Margaret Mitchell, 25 mayors and thousands of unidentified Confederate soldiers are buried. In warm weather, guided tours are available Sunday afternoons at 2. Save time for a stroll before you leave town.</p>
        <p>THE BASICS</p>
        <p>It is easy to fly nonstop into Hartsfield-Jackson International Airport, which is a major travel hub. But if you fly in, you'll do well to rent a car. Public transportation is limited and taxis are not easily hailed.</p>
        <p>A hot new hotel, with full amenities including a check-in kiosk (you don't have to talk to a person!) is Twelve Atlantic Station, in a bustling new development in Midtown. The rooms, which are all suites, begin at $195 (361 17th Street NW; 404-961-1212; www.twelvehotels.com).</p>
        <p>The Glenn Hotel is in a renovated 1920s building downtown that has gossamer curtains (110 Marietta Street NW; 866-404-5366; www.glennhotel.com). Rooms begin at about $250, but check for specials. The rooftop bar and restaurant have a gimmick, apparently attractive to the rich and famous, where you can eat on a bed, but beware the snobby doormen and minimum spending requirements.</p>
        <p>Travelers looking to spend less can try the Hotel Indigo, a ''budget boutique'' hotel across from the ornate Fox Theater (683 Peachtree Street NE; 800-972-2404; www.hotelindigo.com). Rooms are small (it was once a Days Inn), but nicely furnished and start at under $200.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A weekend itinerary in a city where optimism is liberally indulged and whose slogan is: “Every day is an opening day.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FIRST, don't call it Hotlanta anymore. It's the ATL, the code for the teeming airport that is a fitting emblem for a city so transient it barely recognizes itself, where more than half the adult population is from somewhere else, and where every urban fad, from underground parking to savory ice cream, is embraced. A corporate stronghold, a Southern belle and a hip-hop capital, Atlanta wrestled with identity dysphoria as it searched for a new slogan (''Every day is an opening day,'' accompanied by a new theme song by the hip-hop impresario Dallas Austin) and tried to name its newborn giant panda (Bling Bling was rejected). Major civic investments like the new, grandiose $220 million aquarium, a significant expansion of the High Museum of Art by the architect Renzo Piano, and the purchase of the papers of the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. add up to a high tide of enthusiasm, even in a city where optimism is liberally indulged.</p>
        <p>Friday</p>
        <p>5:30 p.m.  1. Tastes of the Town</p>
        <p>Few places can be said to be definitively Atlantan, but the Colonnade (1879 Cheshire Bridge Road NE, 404-874-5642) is one: a meat-and-three restaurant with a full bar (rare) and a sizable gay clientele (more rare). The resulting mix is spectacular: black fingernails, Sansabelt trousers, birthday tiaras, Hawaiian shirts, all in a buzzing carpeted dining room with efficiently friendly waiters. When it comes to ordering, stick to the classics: a Bloody Mary to start ($5.50), fried chicken with yeasty dinner rolls straight from the school cafeteria ($10.95) and the day's pie ($3.50).</p>
        <p>7:30 p.m.  2. Men in Skirts</p>
        <p>Though it sounds vaguely revolutionary, contredansing is a folk tradition that involves following instructions from a caller, like square-dancing. If the notion of trying this in public gives you qualms, remember that 1) the likelihood of being seen by someone you know is low and 2) the tolerance quotient, at a weekly event where some men wear skirts to keep cool, is high. Show up at the gymnasium of the Morningside Baptist Church (1700 Piedmont Avenue) at 7:30 for basic lessons by the Chattahoochee County Dancers (770-939-8646; www.contradance.org), then swing your partner (you can easily find one there) to live old-time bands with names like Jump in the Skillet and Cattywampus (admission $7). Wear soft-soled shoes, or boogie in your socks.</p>
        <p>10:30 p.m.  3. Where Heads Spin</p>
        <p>Since you're already dizzy, visit the Sun Dial, the revolving bar atop the Westin (210 Peachtree Street; 404-589-7506; www.sundialrestaurant.com), where young Atlantans come for the throwback cool and occasional exhibitions of local art. Sip an Atlanta Hurricane (it's in the colada-daiquiri family and arrives in a souvenir glass, $14.95) or a chocolate martini as you orient yourself with a glittery panoramic view of downtown, the Georgia Dome, CNN's headquarters and the new aquarium.</p>
        <p>11:30 p.m.  4. On a Roll</p>
        <p>Roller-skating is an integral part of hip-hop culture in Atlanta, which is home to OutKast, Usher and Young Jeezy among other stars. Beyoncé had her 21st birthday party at the Cascade roller rink here, and Dallas Austin paid homage to the flawless moves of skate dancers in his recent movie ''The ATL.'' On Friday nights, the virtuosos descend on Golden Glide (2750 Wesley Chapel Road in Decatur, but it's tucked behind a shopping strip, 404-288-7773; www.atlantarollerskating.com) for adult skate, where posses practice their smooth moves (11:30 p.m. to 2:30 a.m., $7 including skate rental). If you haven't been practicing, skate inside the green line for your own safety. Or just stay on the sideline and gawk.</p>
        <p>Saturday</p>
        <p>Noon  5. Refueling</p>
        <p>You had a late night, so take your time getting to Watershed (406 West Ponce de Leon Avenue, Decatur; 404-378-4900), the gas station converted into an airy Southern restaurant where one of the Indigo Girls, Emily Saliers, is an owner, and Scott Peacock, an authority on Southern cooking, is the executive chef. Reservations are recommended, and child-tolerance is required, but the chicken hash with griddle cakes and poached eggs ($9) is worth the bother.</p>
        <p>1:30 p.m.  6. Posters and Aprons</p>
        <p>After brunch, browse the chic specialty shops near the main square of Decatur, the city-suburb that has won praise for its sensitive take on urban revitalization. One favorite is Mingei World Arts (427 Church Street; 404-371-0101; www.mingeiworldarts.com), an import store with a sense of humor, which offers vintage Bollywood posters ($25) and baskets woven from telephone wire ($24 to $45). For the designer chef there's Taste (416 Church Street; 404-370-1863), with two-handed Dumbo cups ($14.95) and vintage-print aprons ($34).</p>
        <p>3:30 p.m.  7. War on Canvas</p>
        <p>When Gen. John A. Logan was considering a run for vice president in the 1880s, he commissioned a political ad in the form of a giant painting of the Battle of Atlanta, in which he for a time commanded the Army of the Tennessee for the Union. The work, billed as the world's largest oil painting, is now housed in Grant Park, in a circular room not unlike a planetarium, and viewed from a rotating bank of seats (Atlanta Cyclorama and Civil War Museum, 800 Cherokee Avenue, 404-624-1071; www.bcaatlanta.com; adult admission $7). It is accompanied by a taped narration, a good way to get your requisite dose of Civil War history. A diorama was added in the 1930s, which sounds like a terrible idea until you see how seamlessly it blends into the painting, or notice a replica of Clark Gable as a dead Yankee. Tours begin every hour and half-hour; leave some time to see the exhibit on the Great Locomotive Chase, a slapstick adventure involving hand cars, cut wires and engines traveling in reverse.</p>
        <p>6 p.m.  8. Spreading the Sopchoppy</p>
        <p>A city where a treasured chef's departure can be front-page news, Atlanta has more than its share of fine restaurants, many of them cavernous, overdesigned colonizations of old industrial buildings. Smaller and friendlier is Restaurant Eugene (2277 Peachtree Road, 404-355-0321; www.restauranteugene.com), where the staff shares its passions readily and the menu can read like a Southern safari by Linton Hopkins, the chef: foie gras on French toast with Sopchoppy brand molasses from Florida ($21); A &amp; J Farms squash blossoms with Anson Mills's grits and Sweetgrass Dairy goat cheese ($12). The house mixologist, Greg Best, will prattle on about such matters as James Bond's favorite cocktail as he concocts something special from his homemade bitters and tinctures.</p>
        <p>8:30 p.m.  9. Where the Money Was</p>
        <p>Restored bank buildings are nothing new, but the owners of Pie Bar (2160 Monroe Drive; 404-815-1605; www.piebar.com) refurbished a 1962 branch -- yes, one of ''The Jetsons,'' flying-saucer kind, visible from the freeway like a ''Blade Runner'' mirage. The result is a sophisticated sports bar for a slick young crowd. Every wine is the same price (red $7, white $5). Pick a glass, then sample some lime-rosemary sorbet ($4).</p>
        <p>10 p.m.  10. Car-Driven Culture</p>
        <p>The Starlight Six Drive-In (2000 Moreland Avenue SE; 404-627-5786; $6 per person, cash only) -- ''movies and fun since 1949'' -- has that Southern-culture-on-the-skids charm, retro with a hint of rockabilly. Sometimes used for campy evenings of B-movies and bands (check www.starlightdrivein.com for the schedule), the rest of the time this is just a straight-up, steamy-windowed cinematic experience in a hummocky parking lot. It's not hard to find a decent movie on the schedule, but bring your own refreshments as the snack bar is paltry.</p>
        <p>Sunday</p>
        <p>10 a.m.  11. Quiet Neighbors</p>
        <p>The gruff proprietor of Ria's Bluebird (421 Memorial Drive SE, 404-521-3737; www.riasbluebird.com) has the word ''hate'' tattooed on the nape of her neck. But local residents give her nothing but love, lining up, pleasantly sleep-tousled, on weekend mornings for what some customers say are the world's best pancakes ($5.25 for a short stack with toasted pecans). The light-filled storefront is just right if you feel the need to keep your sunglasses on in the morning; the floor is made from wooden wall paneling, creating the illusion of an old barroom. If pancakes are a bit too sinful, try one of the inventive daily eggs Benedict specials, a mean chicken salad on a warm croissant ($8.50), and the house-made jam. The restaurant is across the street from Atlanta's oldest and loveliest cemetery, Oakland Cemetery (404-688-2107; www.oaklandcemetery.com), where Margaret Mitchell, 25 mayors and thousands of unidentified Confederate soldiers are buried. In warm weather, guided tours are available Sunday afternoons at 2. Save time for a stroll before you leave town.</p>
        <p>THE BASICS</p>
        <p>It is easy to fly nonstop into Hartsfield-Jackson International Airport, which is a major travel hub. But if you fly in, you'll do well to rent a car. Public transportation is limited and taxis are not easily hailed.</p>
        <p>A hot new hotel, with full amenities including a check-in kiosk (you don't have to talk to a person!) is Twelve Atlantic Station, in a bustling new development in Midtown. The rooms, which are all suites, begin at $195 (361 17th Street NW; 404-961-1212; www.twelvehotels.com).</p>
        <p>The Glenn Hotel is in a renovated 1920s building downtown that has gossamer curtains (110 Marietta Street NW; 866-404-5366; www.glennhotel.com). Rooms begin at about $250, but check for specials. The rooftop bar and restaurant have a gimmick, apparently attractive to the rich and famous, where you can eat on a bed, but beware the snobby doormen and minimum spending requirements.</p>
        <p>Travelers looking to spend less can try the Hotel Indigo, a ''budget boutique'' hotel across from the ornate Fox Theater (683 Peachtree Street NE; 800-972-2404; www.hotelindigo.com). Rooms are small (it was once a Days Inn), but nicely furnished and start at under $200.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
