<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Doctor Killed by Ex-Owner Of Yonkers Home, Police Say</title>
    <meta content="07yonkers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/07/nyregion/07yonkers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1817258"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yonkers (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saunders, Samuel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lozada, Leandro (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ramirez, Anthony</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Foreclosures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreclosures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Yonkers (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE2DD1530F934A35752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="523" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Doctor Killed by Ex-Owner Of Yonkers Home, Police Say</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Doctor Killed by Ex-Owner of Yonkers Home, Police Say</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY RAMIREZ; Erin Duggan and Stephen Heyman contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ramirez, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Samuel Saunders, former owner of Yonkers home where Dr Leandro Lozada was found shot to death on Jan 3, is arrested for his murder; Lozada bought house after it went into some state of foreclosure; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The former owner of a Yonkers house where a doctor was found shot to death last week has been charged in the murder, the Yonkers police said yesterday. They also suggested that he may have had an accomplice.</p>
        <p>The former owner, Samuel Saunders, 60, of the Bronx, was arrested yesterday and arraigned in Yonkers Criminal Court on a charge of murder in the second degree. If convicted, he faces a maximum sentence of life imprisonment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The former owner of a Yonkers house where a doctor was found shot to death last week has been charged in the murder, the Yonkers police said yesterday. They also suggested that he may have had an accomplice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The former owner of a Yonkers house where a doctor was found shot to death last week has been charged in the murder, the Yonkers police said yesterday. They also suggested that he may have had an accomplice.</p>
        <p>The former owner, Samuel Saunders, 60, of the Bronx, was arrested yesterday and arraigned in Yonkers Criminal Court on a charge of murder in the second degree. If convicted, he faces a maximum sentence of life imprisonment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Saunders bought the home, a three-bedroom, ranch-style house on Brendon Hill Road near the Scarsdale border, in June 2005 for $825,000, with a $650,000 mortgage. But the house was in some stage of foreclosure when the victim, Dr. Leandro Lozada, bought it eight months ago, the police said. Specifics of the sale were not available.</p>
        <p>Because of the continuing investigation and the possibility of suspects still at large, the police provided few details of Mr. Saunders's arrest or the case. They would not discuss any possible motive for the crime.</p>
        <p>But the arrest ended at least one chapter in one of the city's more baffling homicides. On Wednesday, Dr. Lozada, 46, who operated a medical clinic for the poor in the Bronx, was found by his female companion dead on the floor of his bedroom. He had been shot at point-blank range several times, including at least once in the face and once in the back of the head, the police said. No weapon was found at the scene.</p>
        <p>The doctor lived alone and there were no signs of a struggle, prompting the police to speculate that he knew his attacker.</p>
        <p>When Dr. Lozada completed the purchase of the house, he changed the locks, the police said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Edmund Hartnett, the Yonkers police commissioner, said yesterday at police headquarters, ''This act would be very difficult for one person to commit.'' He did not elaborate.</p>
        <p>The commissioner said investigators had recovered items of interest from Mr. Saunders's apartment, including clothing that was possibly stained with human blood.</p>
        <p>It was not immediately clear whether Mr. Saunders had hired a lawyer. He has a criminal record, including grand larceny in 1996, the police said.</p>
        <p>Kim VanZandt, who lives next to the house, said Mr. Saunders had put it back on the market after living there just one month. She said he believed when he bought the house that it had a larger backyard, and was angry when the owners of a house abutting his property erected a stone wall in what he considered his yard.</p>
        <p>At Mr. Saunders's apartment building in the Bronx, on Pennyfield Avenue near the Throgs Neck Bridge, a woman answering the buzzer for his apartment declined to be interviewed. ''It's private,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lozada was a native of the Dominican Republic who earned his medical degree at the University of Santo Domingo. He spent much of his time at his practice, Hispanic Pediatrics, at 229 East Kingsbridge Road in the Bronx, where he treated mainly immigrant patients.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, dozens of patients stopped by Dr. Lozada's office to set up a shrine in his memory.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
