<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Waiting, and Waiting, for NSX 2.0</title>
    <meta content="07NUGGETacura" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="0" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1817301"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E3DD1130F934A35752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="264" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Waiting, and Waiting, for NSX 2.0</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICK KURCZEWSKI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Introduced on Sunday: Acura Advanced Sports Car design study</p>
        <p>Is it real? The mechanical bits are all present, and the body is metal, not Styrofoam. But Acura's Advanced Sports Car Concept is strictly a nonrunning prototype, with its doors and hood sealed for the run of the auto show.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Introduced on Sunday: Acura Advanced Sports Car design study</p>
        <p>Is it real? The mechanical bits are all present, and the body is metal, not Styrofoam. But Acura's Advanced Sports Car Concept is strictly a nonrunning prototype, with its doors and hood sealed for the run of the auto show.</p>
        <p>What's the point? The NSX was Acura's two-seat halo car, an Asian Ferrari that served as a showcase of technology and innovation. Since its demise, Acura's parent, Honda, has been hard at work on a replacement to keep the performance fires burning.</p>
        <p>What they said: ''I must tell you that my own passion is performance,'' Takeo Fukui, president and chief executive of Honda Motor Company, said.</p>
        <p>What they didn't say: That this is the next NSX, or that Acura is overdue for something more potent than the brand's current crop of V-6 engines. The next episode in the hunt for NSX V2.0 occurs at the Tokyo auto show, in October 2007.</p>
        <p>What makes it tick? The A.S.C.C. has a front-mounted V-10 coupled to sport-tuned version of Acura's all-wheel drive hardware.</p>
        <p>How much, how soon? No one would let us peek under the hood, much less mention anything as vulgar as a price or when to expect this car to be production ready.</p>
        <p>How's it look? The Advanced Sports Car Concept looks familiar -- we see a lot of Audi R8, minus the gaping grill, and the Lexus LF-A concept of 2005, in this Acura's front end. It could probably do with an extra dose of edginess when the second iteration appears in Tokyo.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
