<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CALENDAR</title>
    <meta content="07welistingsWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1817024"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E2DF1430F934A35752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2213" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CALENDAR</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on in and around Westchester and Putnam Counties this week. Items for the guide should be sent at least three weeks in advance to westweek@nytimes.com, or by mail to Westchester Cultural Calendar, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036-3959.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>Mamaroneck ''A Guide to Recognizing Your Saints,'' drama directed by Dito Montiel. Through Jan. 7. $8; subscribers and members, $5; matinees, $6. Emelin Theater, 153 Library Lane. (914) 698-0098.  Peekskill ''A Guide to Recognizing Your Saints.'' Through Jan. 7. ''Backstage,'' directed by Emmanuelle Bercot. Thursday through Jan. 14. $7 and $9. Paramount Center for the Arts, 1008 Brown Street. (914) 930-7588.  Pleasantville Rarely Seen Cinema: ''Dragon Squad,'' Hong Kong action thriller, directed by Daniel Lee; with question and answer session with Jonathan Demme. Jan. 7 at 6 p.m. $6.50 to $13. Jacob Burns Film Center, 364 Manville Road. (914) 773-7663.  White Plains ''Criss Cross,'' starring Burt Lancaster and Yvonne DeCarlo. Tuesday at 2 p.m. ''In Remembrance of Martin,'' documentary honoring the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. Jan. 14 at 2:30 p.m. White Plains Public Library, 100 Martine Avenue. (914) 422-1480.  Yonkers ''Men at Work,'' directed by Mani Haghighi; in Persian with subtitles. Wednesday at 2 p.m. Yonkers Public Library, Grinton I. Will branch, 1500 Central Park Avenue. (914) 337-1500.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>Montrose Parent/child crochet workshop. For ages 8 and up. Mondays through Feb. 26 at 6:45 p.m. $10; includes yarn, hook and instructional booklet. Hendrick Hudson Free Library, 185 Kings Ferry Road. (914) 739-5654.  Purchase ''Swimmy,'' ''Frederick'' and ''Inch by Inch,'' children's works by Leo Lionni, presented by the Mermaid Theater of Nova Scotia. Jan. 14 at 3 p.m. $14 and $20. Dance Lab Theater, 735 Anderson Hill Road. (914) 251-6830.  Scarsdale ''Meet the Animals,'' Travis Brady, museum manager, will introduce patrons to animal museum favorites. Jan. 14 at 2 p.m. Free and $5. Greenburgh Nature Center, 99 Dromore Road. (914) 723-3470.  White Plains ''Curious George and Monkey Friends Pajamarama,'' story time with songs, activities and a bedtime snack. For ages 2 and up. Wednesday at 7 p.m. White Plains Public Library, 100 Martine Avenue. (914) 422-1480.  Yonkers ''Surviving the Winter,'' children's program detailing different methods that birds and animals use to get through the winter. For ages 7 to 10. Jan. 13, 10 to 11 a.m. Free; pre-registration required. Lenoir Preserve, Dudley Street.  Yonkers ''Music and Merriment,'' children's program. For ages 11/2 to 5. Wednesday through June 20. Yonkers Crestwood Library, 16 Thompson Street. (914) 337-1500 x360.</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE</p>
        <p>Beacon Anthony da Costa, folk. Friday, 8 to 10 p.m. $5. Chthonic Clash Coffeehouse, 453 Main Street. (845) 831-0359.  Beacon Howland Chamber Music Circle, works by Bach, Beethoven, Bartok and Schumann. Jan. 14 at 4 p.m. $12 and $25. Howland Cultural Center, 477 Main Street. (845) 297-9243.  Bronx Grupo Niche, salsa; with Jimmy Bosch, trombone, and his orchestra. Jan. 13 at 8 p.m. $30 to $45. Lehman Center for the Performing Arts, 250 Bedford Park Boulevard West. (718) 960-8833.  Katonah ''Giovani Stelle,'' benefit for Caramoor. Thursday. Caramoor Center for Music and the Arts, 149 Girdle Ridge Road. (914) 232-1252.  Mahopac Gilbert and Sullivan's ''Mikado,'' musical comedy, proceeds of which will sponsor the TBS Children's Choir. Jan. 13 and 14. $10. Temple Beth Shalom, 760 Route 6. (845) 628-6133.  Mamaroneck Miller's Crossing with Mike Burns and North Country, bluegrass. Fridayat 8 p.m. $28. Emelin Theater, 153 Library Lane. (914) 698-0098.  Rhinebeck Strata, piano trio, presented by the Rhinebeck Chamber Music Society. Jan. 13 at 8 p.m. $5 and $25. Church of the Messiah, 6436 Montgomery Street. (845) 876-2870.  Scarsdale ''The Great Puccini,'' Victoria Atwater and Bruce Reed, vocalists, perform arias from Puccini operas. Wednesday at 1 p.m. $21 to $23. J. C. C. of Mid-Westchester, 999 Wilmot Road. (914) 472-3300.  Scarsdale HB Artist Series: Lani King Chang, violinist, with Jenny Hayden, soprano; Michael Finckel, cello; and Edmund Niemann, piano. Jan. 14 at 4 p.m. $11 to $13. Scarsdale Community Baptist Church, Popham and Autenrieth Roads. (914) 723-1169.  Tarrytown ''Reels 'n Fugues,'' Irish music. Jan. 13 at 2:30 p.m. Warner Public Library, 121 North Broadway. (914) 631-7734.  White Plains Westchester's Interfaith Music Services: an interfaith group of Muslims, Jews and Christians celebrate the music of gospel pioneer Charles Albert Tindley. Jan. 14 at 4 p.m. Congregation Kol Ami, 252 Soundview Avenue. (914) 949-4717 ext. 103.  White Plains ''American Song Sampler,'' Rob Weintraub, baritone, and Lin Li, pianist. Wednesday at 12:10 p.m. Free. Grace Church, 33 Church Street. (914) 949-2478. ''An American Songbook,'' Rob Weintraub, baritone, and Lin Li, piano, perform songs by Gene Scheer, Walter Damrosch and others. Wednesday at 12:10 p.m. Grace Church, Mamaroneck Avenue. (914) 949-0384.  Yonkers ''Music and Words and Music,'' with Miriam Brickman, pianist. Jan. 7 at 2 p.m. Free. Yonkers Public Library, Grinton I. Will branch, 1500 Central Park Avenue. (914) 337-1500.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>Pawling ''The Heidi Chronicles,'' drama by Wendy Wasserstein, presented by the Pawling Theater Company. Friday through Jan. 27. $11 to $15. Pawling High School, Reservoir Road. (845) 855-1965.  Pleasantville ''Salome,'' staged reading and discussion. Jan. 14 at 2 p.m. Mondays, Tuesdays and Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Wednesdays, to 6 p.m.; Fridays through Sundays, to 5 p.m. Mount Pleasant Public Library, 350 Bedford Road. (914) 769-0548.  White Plains ''Guys and Dolls,'' musical by Abe Burrows and Jo Swerling; presented by the Play Group Theater. Through Jan. 14. $15; $20, groups of 20 or more. White Plains Performing Arts Center, 11 City Place. (914) 328-1600.</p>
        <p>SEASONAL</p>
        <p>Larchmont ''Celebration of French Galette des Rois,'' traditional French Twelfth Night gathering sponsored by Westchester Accueil. Thursdayat 9:30 a.m. Larchmont Public Library, 121 Larchmont Avenue. (914) 834-2281.  Somers ''Winter Fun for Families,'' adults and children make crafts and baked goods. Jan. 14, 1 to 3 p.m. Muscoot Farm, Route 100. (914) 864-7282.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>Mount Vernon ''The Lenape: Native Peoples of the Hudson Valley,'' a discussion of the history of the original Native American settlers of the area. Jan. 13 at 1 p.m. St. Paul's Church National Historic Site, 897 South Columbus Avenue. (914) 667-4116.  Rye Brook ''Identity Theft and Investment Scams,'' with Supervisory Agent Steven Garfinkel of the F.B.I. Thursday, 3 to 5 p.m. ''Collecting Books and Collecting Kipling,'' with David Richards, Rudyard Kipling expert. Jan. 14 at 2 p.m. Sterling Glen, 1200 King Street. (914) 939-2900.  Yonkers ''Crime and Punishment,'' a mini-course analyzing Dostoevsky's novel, taught by Melissa Frazier. Wednesday through Friday. ''Beethoven's Ninth Symphony,'' a mini-course conducted by Martin Goldray. Wednesday through Friday. $45. Reisinger Concert Hall, Sarah Lawrence College. (914) 395-2412.</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>Armonk ''Winter Solstice V: Expressions of Our Time and Place,'' group show. Through Jan. 28. Gallery talk by Marcy B. Freedman, Jan. 13 at 2 p.m.; $5; reservations required. Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. The Studio: An Alternative Space for Contemporary Art, 2 Maryland Avenue. (914) 273-1452.  Beacon ''bau 25: bau NOW,'' group exhibition featuring sculpture, painting and mixed media. Saturdays and Sundays, noon through 6 p.m., and by appointment. Beacon Artists Union (bau), 161 Main Street. (845) 440-7584.  Briarcliff Manor Watercolor and oil paintings by Julie Anello. Through Jan. 27. Wednesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Images Art Gallery, 1157 Pleasantville Road. (914) 762-3000.  Bronx ''South Bronx Contemporary,'' group show. Through March 10. Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. Longwood Art Gallery at Hostos, 450 Grand Concourse, C-190. (718) 518-6728.  Bronx ''Celebrating Winter Through Nature,'' contemporary artworks. Through Jan. 14. $2 to $4; members and under 6, free; free for everyone on Tuesdays; free for everyone Saturdays, 9 a.m. to noon. Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Wave Hill, 675 West 252nd Street. (718) 549-3200.  Greenburgh ''Captured Energy,'' student paintings and batik prints inspired by energy conservation. Through June 2007. Free. Greenburgh Town Hall, 177 Hillside Avenue. (914) 993-1649.  Greenburgh Watercolors by students of Brigitte Loritz. Through Jan. 31. Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. Madeleine Gutman Gallery, 177 Hillside Avenue. (914) 682-1574.  Greenburgh Contemporary landscapes by Leigh Trifari. Through Wednesday. Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. Town Court Gallery, Greenburgh Town Court, 188 Tarrytown Road. (914) 682-1574.  Harrison ''a few of my favorite things,'' watercolors by Caty Kendall. Through Jan. 26. Mondays and Wednesdays, 9:30 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Tuesdays, Thursdays and Fridays, to 5:30 p.m.; Saturdays, to 12:30 p.m. Harrison Public Library, Bruce Avenue. (914) 835-0324.  Hartsdale DeSanti Plaza Sculpture Project: ''Tinted Reflections II,'' sculpture by Anthony Krauss. Through March 1. DeSanti Plaza, across from Metro-North. (914) 478-4630.  Katonah ''Wild Edges,'' photographs by Gregory Conniff. Through Wednesday. ''Paterson II,'' A new series of photographs by George Tice. Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Sundays, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m. Candace Dwan Gallery, 27 Katonah Avenue. (914) 232-3966.  Katonah Sculpture by Michael Steiner. Through April 22. ''Michael Krondl: Rising Water, Falling Water,'' photographic mural. Through March 8. Admission: $5, $3 for seniors and students. ''The Way Things Go,'' video documenting a mad science experiment. Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Katonah Museum of Art, Route 22 at Jay Street. (914) 232-9555.  Larchmont ''Just a Moment,'' photography by Sid Hecker. Reception: Jan. 13, 3 to 4:30 p.m. Larchmont Public Library, 121 Larchmont Avenue. (914) 834-2281.  Larchmont ''Young Artists on the Rise,'' student group show featuring work from Mamaroneck and New Rochelle high school students. Reception: Jan. 18, 5 to 7 p.m. Tuesdays through Saturdays, noon to 5 p.m. Mamaroneck Artists Guild, 2120 Boston Post Road. (914) 834-1117.  New Rochelle ''Racing on a Broken Road,'' exhibit on the Underground Railroad. Through March 4. Tuesdays and Wednesdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Thursdays and Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Castle Gallery, 29 Castle Place. (914) 654-5423.  Newburgh ''Small Works in Time for Giving,'' painting, sculpture, paper works and photography, and found-object pieces by Charles Davidson. Both through Jan. 7. Decorative works curated by Elizabeth Oliver. Jan. 13 through Feb. 25. Yellow Bird Gallery, 19 Front Street. (845) 561-7204.  Peekskill ''Only the Paranoid Survive,'' works focusing on the ''culture of fear,'' curated by Daniel Fuller. Through Jan. 21. $5, adults; $1, children; members, free. Saturdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; group tours available by appointment. Hudson Valley Center for Contemporary Art, 1701 Main Street. (914) 788-7166.  Port Chester ''Pollinia,'' ceramic sculpture by Leigh Taylor Mickelson. Through Jan. 27. Mondays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Clay Art Center, 40 Beech Street. (914) 937-2047.  Purchase ''Crossing the Boulevard: Strangers, Neighbors, Aliens in a New America.'' Through Jan. 27. $3 to $5; members and children 12 and under, free. Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Neuberger Museum of Art, 735 Anderson Hill Road. (914) 251-6100.  Rockville Centre ''Poor Art Student ... Strike 3!'' mixed-media group show of student artwork, curated by Cristina Pugliese. Through Jan. 24. Free. Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Molloy College Art Gallery, 1000 Hempstead Avenue. (516) 678-5000.  Rye ''Cutting Across Cultures: The Art of Papercutting, Then and Now,'' works by traditional and contemporary paper-cutting artists. Through Feb. 17. Rye Arts Center, 51 Milton Road. (914) 967-0700.  Rye ''The Image Makers,'' works by members of the Westchester Photographic Society. Through Feb. 16. Rye Free Reading Room, 1061 Boston Post Road. (914) 967-0480.  Rye ''Shells and Trees,'' works by Elasah Schaff. Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Rye Nature Center, 873 Boston Post Road. (914) 967-5150.  Scarsdale ''Turning Points: Documents That Shaped America,'' historical documents. Through Jan. 20. $1.50 to $2; members, free. Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Scarsdale Historical Society Museum, 937 White Plains Post Road. (914) 723-1744.  West Point ''The Color of Loyalty: A Tribute to Dr. J. Robert Oppenheimer,'' works of Linda Jean Fisher. Through Feb. 11. Daily, 9 a.m. to 4 p.m. 1929 Gallery, Eisenhower Hall, United States Military Academy. (845) 938-2782.  White Plains ''Expressions of the Spirit,'' folk arts showcase. Through Jan. 13. Arts of Japan Workshop: Calligraphy with Yoshiko Katsumi. Jan. 13 at 2:30 p.m. $15. Arts Exchange, 31 Mamaroneck Avenue. (914) 428-4220, extension 273.  White Plains ''Once Upon a Time ... The Art of Children's Book Illustration,'' work of Howard Fine, Yumi Heo and Mary O'Keefe Young, with family story times and demonstrations by the artists on Jan. 14 at 2 p.m. Through Feb. 28. White Plains Public Library, 100 Martine Avenue. (914) 422-1480.  Woodstock ''Nature Without Glass,'' pinhole photographs by Mark Stetler. Jan. 5 through Feb. 12. Thursdays through Mondays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Gallery B. M. G., 12 Tannery Brook Road. (845) 679-0027.  Yonkers ''Quilt Stories,'' textile works by Sara Fasy. Through Friday. Esther Raushenbush Library, Sarah Lawrence College. (914) 395-2470.  Yonkers ''The Cubist Works of Pablo Picasso,'' sculpture by students at Yonkers Riverfront International Baccalaureate High School. Through Jan. 12. Free. Yonkers Public Library, One Larkin Center. (914) 337-1500, Extension 461.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on in and around Westchester and Putnam Counties this week. Items for the guide should be sent at least three weeks in advance to westweek@nytimes.com, or by mail to Westchester Cultural Calendar, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036-3959.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>Mamaroneck ''A Guide to Recognizing Your Saints,'' drama directed by Dito Montiel. Through Jan. 7. $8; subscribers and members, $5; matinees, $6. Emelin Theater, 153 Library Lane. (914) 698-0098.  Peekskill ''A Guide to Recognizing Your Saints.'' Through Jan. 7. ''Backstage,'' directed by Emmanuelle Bercot. Thursday through Jan. 14. $7 and $9. Paramount Center for the Arts, 1008 Brown Street. (914) 930-7588.  Pleasantville Rarely Seen Cinema: ''Dragon Squad,'' Hong Kong action thriller, directed by Daniel Lee; with question and answer session with Jonathan Demme. Jan. 7 at 6 p.m. $6.50 to $13. Jacob Burns Film Center, 364 Manville Road. (914) 773-7663.  White Plains ''Criss Cross,'' starring Burt Lancaster and Yvonne DeCarlo. Tuesday at 2 p.m. ''In Remembrance of Martin,'' documentary honoring the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. Jan. 14 at 2:30 p.m. White Plains Public Library, 100 Martine Avenue. (914) 422-1480.  Yonkers ''Men at Work,'' directed by Mani Haghighi; in Persian with subtitles. Wednesday at 2 p.m. Yonkers Public Library, Grinton I. Will branch, 1500 Central Park Avenue. (914) 337-1500.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>Montrose Parent/child crochet workshop. For ages 8 and up. Mondays through Feb. 26 at 6:45 p.m. $10; includes yarn, hook and instructional booklet. Hendrick Hudson Free Library, 185 Kings Ferry Road. (914) 739-5654.  Purchase ''Swimmy,'' ''Frederick'' and ''Inch by Inch,'' children's works by Leo Lionni, presented by the Mermaid Theater of Nova Scotia. Jan. 14 at 3 p.m. $14 and $20. Dance Lab Theater, 735 Anderson Hill Road. (914) 251-6830.  Scarsdale ''Meet the Animals,'' Travis Brady, museum manager, will introduce patrons to animal museum favorites. Jan. 14 at 2 p.m. Free and $5. Greenburgh Nature Center, 99 Dromore Road. (914) 723-3470.  White Plains ''Curious George and Monkey Friends Pajamarama,'' story time with songs, activities and a bedtime snack. For ages 2 and up. Wednesday at 7 p.m. White Plains Public Library, 100 Martine Avenue. (914) 422-1480.  Yonkers ''Surviving the Winter,'' children's program detailing different methods that birds and animals use to get through the winter. For ages 7 to 10. Jan. 13, 10 to 11 a.m. Free; pre-registration required. Lenoir Preserve, Dudley Street.  Yonkers ''Music and Merriment,'' children's program. For ages 11/2 to 5. Wednesday through June 20. Yonkers Crestwood Library, 16 Thompson Street. (914) 337-1500 x360.</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE</p>
        <p>Beacon Anthony da Costa, folk. Friday, 8 to 10 p.m. $5. Chthonic Clash Coffeehouse, 453 Main Street. (845) 831-0359.  Beacon Howland Chamber Music Circle, works by Bach, Beethoven, Bartok and Schumann. Jan. 14 at 4 p.m. $12 and $25. Howland Cultural Center, 477 Main Street. (845) 297-9243.  Bronx Grupo Niche, salsa; with Jimmy Bosch, trombone, and his orchestra. Jan. 13 at 8 p.m. $30 to $45. Lehman Center for the Performing Arts, 250 Bedford Park Boulevard West. (718) 960-8833.  Katonah ''Giovani Stelle,'' benefit for Caramoor. Thursday. Caramoor Center for Music and the Arts, 149 Girdle Ridge Road. (914) 232-1252.  Mahopac Gilbert and Sullivan's ''Mikado,'' musical comedy, proceeds of which will sponsor the TBS Children's Choir. Jan. 13 and 14. $10. Temple Beth Shalom, 760 Route 6. (845) 628-6133.  Mamaroneck Miller's Crossing with Mike Burns and North Country, bluegrass. Fridayat 8 p.m. $28. Emelin Theater, 153 Library Lane. (914) 698-0098.  Rhinebeck Strata, piano trio, presented by the Rhinebeck Chamber Music Society. Jan. 13 at 8 p.m. $5 and $25. Church of the Messiah, 6436 Montgomery Street. (845) 876-2870.  Scarsdale ''The Great Puccini,'' Victoria Atwater and Bruce Reed, vocalists, perform arias from Puccini operas. Wednesday at 1 p.m. $21 to $23. J. C. C. of Mid-Westchester, 999 Wilmot Road. (914) 472-3300.  Scarsdale HB Artist Series: Lani King Chang, violinist, with Jenny Hayden, soprano; Michael Finckel, cello; and Edmund Niemann, piano. Jan. 14 at 4 p.m. $11 to $13. Scarsdale Community Baptist Church, Popham and Autenrieth Roads. (914) 723-1169.  Tarrytown ''Reels 'n Fugues,'' Irish music. Jan. 13 at 2:30 p.m. Warner Public Library, 121 North Broadway. (914) 631-7734.  White Plains Westchester's Interfaith Music Services: an interfaith group of Muslims, Jews and Christians celebrate the music of gospel pioneer Charles Albert Tindley. Jan. 14 at 4 p.m. Congregation Kol Ami, 252 Soundview Avenue. (914) 949-4717 ext. 103.  White Plains ''American Song Sampler,'' Rob Weintraub, baritone, and Lin Li, pianist. Wednesday at 12:10 p.m. Free. Grace Church, 33 Church Street. (914) 949-2478. ''An American Songbook,'' Rob Weintraub, baritone, and Lin Li, piano, perform songs by Gene Scheer, Walter Damrosch and others. Wednesday at 12:10 p.m. Grace Church, Mamaroneck Avenue. (914) 949-0384.  Yonkers ''Music and Words and Music,'' with Miriam Brickman, pianist. Jan. 7 at 2 p.m. Free. Yonkers Public Library, Grinton I. Will branch, 1500 Central Park Avenue. (914) 337-1500.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>Pawling ''The Heidi Chronicles,'' drama by Wendy Wasserstein, presented by the Pawling Theater Company. Friday through Jan. 27. $11 to $15. Pawling High School, Reservoir Road. (845) 855-1965.  Pleasantville ''Salome,'' staged reading and discussion. Jan. 14 at 2 p.m. Mondays, Tuesdays and Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Wednesdays, to 6 p.m.; Fridays through Sundays, to 5 p.m. Mount Pleasant Public Library, 350 Bedford Road. (914) 769-0548.  White Plains ''Guys and Dolls,'' musical by Abe Burrows and Jo Swerling; presented by the Play Group Theater. Through Jan. 14. $15; $20, groups of 20 or more. White Plains Performing Arts Center, 11 City Place. (914) 328-1600.</p>
        <p>SEASONAL</p>
        <p>Larchmont ''Celebration of French Galette des Rois,'' traditional French Twelfth Night gathering sponsored by Westchester Accueil. Thursdayat 9:30 a.m. Larchmont Public Library, 121 Larchmont Avenue. (914) 834-2281.  Somers ''Winter Fun for Families,'' adults and children make crafts and baked goods. Jan. 14, 1 to 3 p.m. Muscoot Farm, Route 100. (914) 864-7282.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>Mount Vernon ''The Lenape: Native Peoples of the Hudson Valley,'' a discussion of the history of the original Native American settlers of the area. Jan. 13 at 1 p.m. St. Paul's Church National Historic Site, 897 South Columbus Avenue. (914) 667-4116.  Rye Brook ''Identity Theft and Investment Scams,'' with Supervisory Agent Steven Garfinkel of the F.B.I. Thursday, 3 to 5 p.m. ''Collecting Books and Collecting Kipling,'' with David Richards, Rudyard Kipling expert. Jan. 14 at 2 p.m. Sterling Glen, 1200 King Street. (914) 939-2900.  Yonkers ''Crime and Punishment,'' a mini-course analyzing Dostoevsky's novel, taught by Melissa Frazier. Wednesday through Friday. ''Beethoven's Ninth Symphony,'' a mini-course conducted by Martin Goldray. Wednesday through Friday. $45. Reisinger Concert Hall, Sarah Lawrence College. (914) 395-2412.</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>Armonk ''Winter Solstice V: Expressions of Our Time and Place,'' group show. Through Jan. 28. Gallery talk by Marcy B. Freedman, Jan. 13 at 2 p.m.; $5; reservations required. Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. The Studio: An Alternative Space for Contemporary Art, 2 Maryland Avenue. (914) 273-1452.  Beacon ''bau 25: bau NOW,'' group exhibition featuring sculpture, painting and mixed media. Saturdays and Sundays, noon through 6 p.m., and by appointment. Beacon Artists Union (bau), 161 Main Street. (845) 440-7584.  Briarcliff Manor Watercolor and oil paintings by Julie Anello. Through Jan. 27. Wednesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Images Art Gallery, 1157 Pleasantville Road. (914) 762-3000.  Bronx ''South Bronx Contemporary,'' group show. Through March 10. Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. Longwood Art Gallery at Hostos, 450 Grand Concourse, C-190. (718) 518-6728.  Bronx ''Celebrating Winter Through Nature,'' contemporary artworks. Through Jan. 14. $2 to $4; members and under 6, free; free for everyone on Tuesdays; free for everyone Saturdays, 9 a.m. to noon. Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Wave Hill, 675 West 252nd Street. (718) 549-3200.  Greenburgh ''Captured Energy,'' student paintings and batik prints inspired by energy conservation. Through June 2007. Free. Greenburgh Town Hall, 177 Hillside Avenue. (914) 993-1649.  Greenburgh Watercolors by students of Brigitte Loritz. Through Jan. 31. Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. Madeleine Gutman Gallery, 177 Hillside Avenue. (914) 682-1574.  Greenburgh Contemporary landscapes by Leigh Trifari. Through Wednesday. Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. Town Court Gallery, Greenburgh Town Court, 188 Tarrytown Road. (914) 682-1574.  Harrison ''a few of my favorite things,'' watercolors by Caty Kendall. Through Jan. 26. Mondays and Wednesdays, 9:30 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Tuesdays, Thursdays and Fridays, to 5:30 p.m.; Saturdays, to 12:30 p.m. Harrison Public Library, Bruce Avenue. (914) 835-0324.  Hartsdale DeSanti Plaza Sculpture Project: ''Tinted Reflections II,'' sculpture by Anthony Krauss. Through March 1. DeSanti Plaza, across from Metro-North. (914) 478-4630.  Katonah ''Wild Edges,'' photographs by Gregory Conniff. Through Wednesday. ''Paterson II,'' A new series of photographs by George Tice. Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Sundays, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m. Candace Dwan Gallery, 27 Katonah Avenue. (914) 232-3966.  Katonah Sculpture by Michael Steiner. Through April 22. ''Michael Krondl: Rising Water, Falling Water,'' photographic mural. Through March 8. Admission: $5, $3 for seniors and students. ''The Way Things Go,'' video documenting a mad science experiment. Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Katonah Museum of Art, Route 22 at Jay Street. (914) 232-9555.  Larchmont ''Just a Moment,'' photography by Sid Hecker. Reception: Jan. 13, 3 to 4:30 p.m. Larchmont Public Library, 121 Larchmont Avenue. (914) 834-2281.  Larchmont ''Young Artists on the Rise,'' student group show featuring work from Mamaroneck and New Rochelle high school students. Reception: Jan. 18, 5 to 7 p.m. Tuesdays through Saturdays, noon to 5 p.m. Mamaroneck Artists Guild, 2120 Boston Post Road. (914) 834-1117.  New Rochelle ''Racing on a Broken Road,'' exhibit on the Underground Railroad. Through March 4. Tuesdays and Wednesdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Thursdays and Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Castle Gallery, 29 Castle Place. (914) 654-5423.  Newburgh ''Small Works in Time for Giving,'' painting, sculpture, paper works and photography, and found-object pieces by Charles Davidson. Both through Jan. 7. Decorative works curated by Elizabeth Oliver. Jan. 13 through Feb. 25. Yellow Bird Gallery, 19 Front Street. (845) 561-7204.  Peekskill ''Only the Paranoid Survive,'' works focusing on the ''culture of fear,'' curated by Daniel Fuller. Through Jan. 21. $5, adults; $1, children; members, free. Saturdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; group tours available by appointment. Hudson Valley Center for Contemporary Art, 1701 Main Street. (914) 788-7166.  Port Chester ''Pollinia,'' ceramic sculpture by Leigh Taylor Mickelson. Through Jan. 27. Mondays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Clay Art Center, 40 Beech Street. (914) 937-2047.  Purchase ''Crossing the Boulevard: Strangers, Neighbors, Aliens in a New America.'' Through Jan. 27. $3 to $5; members and children 12 and under, free. Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Neuberger Museum of Art, 735 Anderson Hill Road. (914) 251-6100.  Rockville Centre ''Poor Art Student ... Strike 3!'' mixed-media group show of student artwork, curated by Cristina Pugliese. Through Jan. 24. Free. Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Molloy College Art Gallery, 1000 Hempstead Avenue. (516) 678-5000.  Rye ''Cutting Across Cultures: The Art of Papercutting, Then and Now,'' works by traditional and contemporary paper-cutting artists. Through Feb. 17. Rye Arts Center, 51 Milton Road. (914) 967-0700.  Rye ''The Image Makers,'' works by members of the Westchester Photographic Society. Through Feb. 16. Rye Free Reading Room, 1061 Boston Post Road. (914) 967-0480.  Rye ''Shells and Trees,'' works by Elasah Schaff. Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Rye Nature Center, 873 Boston Post Road. (914) 967-5150.  Scarsdale ''Turning Points: Documents That Shaped America,'' historical documents. Through Jan. 20. $1.50 to $2; members, free. Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Scarsdale Historical Society Museum, 937 White Plains Post Road. (914) 723-1744.  West Point ''The Color of Loyalty: A Tribute to Dr. J. Robert Oppenheimer,'' works of Linda Jean Fisher. Through Feb. 11. Daily, 9 a.m. to 4 p.m. 1929 Gallery, Eisenhower Hall, United States Military Academy. (845) 938-2782.  White Plains ''Expressions of the Spirit,'' folk arts showcase. Through Jan. 13. Arts of Japan Workshop: Calligraphy with Yoshiko Katsumi. Jan. 13 at 2:30 p.m. $15. Arts Exchange, 31 Mamaroneck Avenue. (914) 428-4220, extension 273.  White Plains ''Once Upon a Time ... The Art of Children's Book Illustration,'' work of Howard Fine, Yumi Heo and Mary O'Keefe Young, with family story times and demonstrations by the artists on Jan. 14 at 2 p.m. Through Feb. 28. White Plains Public Library, 100 Martine Avenue. (914) 422-1480.  Woodstock ''Nature Without Glass,'' pinhole photographs by Mark Stetler. Jan. 5 through Feb. 12. Thursdays through Mondays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Gallery B. M. G., 12 Tannery Brook Road. (845) 679-0027.  Yonkers ''Quilt Stories,'' textile works by Sara Fasy. Through Friday. Esther Raushenbush Library, Sarah Lawrence College. (914) 395-2470.  Yonkers ''The Cubist Works of Pablo Picasso,'' sculpture by students at Yonkers Riverfront International Baccalaureate High School. Through Jan. 12. Free. Yonkers Public Library, One Larkin Center. (914) 337-1500, Extension 461.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
