<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Volvo XC60: No More Swedish Meatballs</title>
    <meta content="07NUGGETvolvo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="0" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1817460"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E2DD1130F93BA35752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="246" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Volvo XC60: No More Swedish Meatballs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERRY GARRETT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Introduced on Sunday: Volvo XC60 Concept</p>
        <p>Is it real? This concept will bear a stronger resemblance to the production model than Bruce Wayne does to Batman, minus the cape and funny hat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Introduced on Sunday: Volvo XC60 Concept</p>
        <p>Is it real? This concept will bear a stronger resemblance to the production model than Bruce Wayne does to Batman, minus the cape and funny hat.</p>
        <p>What's the point? Ford has this new Land Rover LR2 platform sitting around, all lonely and otherwise unused, so why not stick a Volvo crossover body on top of it?</p>
        <p>What they said: ''It is time to once and for all to forget about boxy Volvos,'' said Steve Mattin, the chief designer. ''Instead we will make our Swedish design heritage more emotional and radiant by adding sculptured, exciting shapes and new innovative features.''</p>
        <p>What they didn't say: This platform may make for a wimpy Land Rover, if you expect your Land Rovers to run with the gazelles and swim with the crocodiles. Chances are, the architecture will be happier as a Volvo cross-dresser. Fancy design tricks like see-through seats, a glass roof and a split tailgate are destined for the cutting room floor.</p>
        <p>What makes it tick? The concept uses the 3.2-liter in-line 6 from the S80 and base XC90 that is optimized to run on E85 ethanol. In this configuration it makes 30 more horsepower (265 total) than the gasoline version. Faux greenery alert: the ethanol model gets 20 percent worse fuel mileage.</p>
        <p>How much, how soon? On sale early in 2009. Expect it to be priced like most new Volvo models: high.</p>
        <p>How's it look? Ikea meets Herman Miller.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
