<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FIRST GLANCE: Toyota's Texas-Size CrewMax: A Heavy-Duty That Really Is</title>
    <meta content="07NUGGETtoyota" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1817458"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3DD1130F93BA35752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="299" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FIRST GLANCE: Toyota's Texas-Size CrewMax: A Heavy-Duty That Really Is</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM McCRAW</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Introduced on Sunday:Toyota Tundra CrewMax 4-door pickup</p>
        <p>Is it real? It's real. So real that a legion of executives from Ford, General Motors and Dodge, were seen to swoon. Or maybe it was just the hot, dark, crowded ballroom that made them swoon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Introduced on Sunday:Toyota Tundra CrewMax 4-door pickup</p>
        <p>Is it real? It's real. So real that a legion of executives from Ford, General Motors and Dodge, were seen to swoon. Or maybe it was just the hot, dark, crowded ballroom that made them swoon.</p>
        <p>What's the point? Hot on the heels of the redesigned regular-cab Tundra and the double-cab version comes the CrewMax, a Texas-built truck that's just short of having enough rear-seat room for Yao Ming and the rest of the Houston Rockets.</p>
        <p>What they said: Jim Lentz, executive vice president of Toyota Motor Sales USA, said: ''We are fully aware of how many chips are on the table. Competition will be fierce.'' He also said it's the most American product ever launched, with contributions from California, Michigan, Indiana, Alabama, North Carolina and Texas.</p>
        <p>What they didn't say: The 800-pound gorilla has now spoken on the subject of heavy-duty pickup trucks, with an initial sales target of 200,000 trucks a year, and they are serious about making this line of trucks into a huge market success -- whatever it takes.</p>
        <p>What makes it tick? Either a 271-horsepower 4.7-liter V-8 or a 381-horsepower 5.7-liter V-8 engine, with 6-speed automatic transmission only. It also comes with a heavy-duty frame and very heavy duty rear axle, and can tow up to 10,800 pounds. Later in the year, a flexible-fuel Tundra capable of burning E85 will be offered as a 2009 model.</p>
        <p>How much, how soon? Prices for any of the new Tundra trucks won't be announced for several weeks, but look for very competitive pricing.</p>
        <p>How's it look? We don't think any of the three Tundra models is particularly attractive on the outside -- their chrome grilles are Dodge Ram wannabes -- but the rest of the package looks like a winner.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
