<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>50 Years Too Late, but Right on Time</title>
    <meta content="08NUGGETefijy" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="0" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1817461"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E2DD1130F93BA35752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="265" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>50 Years Too Late, but Right on Time</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERRY GARRETT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On display at the G.M. exhibit: Holden Efijy design study</p>
        <p>Is it real? Why is it that the coolest concept car is the one that never makes it to production?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On display at the G.M. exhibit: Holden Efijy design study</p>
        <p>Is it real? Why is it that the coolest concept car is the one that never makes it to production?</p>
        <p>What's the point? The 1953 Holden FJ was the original lead sled for Australian hot-rodders. This is an homage to that timeless design. The Efijy was just a show-stopper from the 2005 Sydney Motor Show until someone at General Motors decided it deserved to be seen by a worldwide audience.</p>
        <p>What they said: ''I don't see why you couldn't build it for production,'' said its designer, Richard Ferlazzo, head of G.M.'s Holden design studio in Melbourne, Australia. ''It's doable. But that's like, who would have thought that about the Prowler, way back then? By the way, do you know (Prowler designer) Chip Foose? A lot of people here said I should meet him.''</p>
        <p>What they didn't say: Though it steered a lot of floor traffic toward the G.M. display, the gorgeous Efijy nevertheless became something of a distraction. During press days, the Holden seemed to always be surrounded by gawkers while mainstream G.M. cars nearby sat like wallflowers at the high school dance.</p>
        <p>What makes it tick? Built on a Corvette C5 chassis, it has a 600-horsepower Corvette LS2 V-8 under that grand piano hood.</p>
        <p>How much, how soon? If it were priced less than a 'Vette, would you buy one? Find 20,000 others who think so and contact Ed Welburn, the head of G.M. design, ASAP.</p>
        <p>How's it look? As if it just jumped off the screen from the movie ''Cars.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
