<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cadillac's Plan: Less Edge for the Next CTS</title>
    <meta content="08NUGGETcadillac" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="0" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1817464"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E1DD1130F93BA35752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="255" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cadillac's Plan: Less Edge for the Next CTS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM McCRAW</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Introduced on Monday: 2008 Cadillac CTS</p>
        <p>Is it real? Real as an Oscar de la Hoya body blow, completely redesigned inside and out, introduced not to the strains of Led Zeppelin but rather to the chamber music of the Panache String Quartet and the Nuthin' But Strings rap violin duo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Introduced on Monday: 2008 Cadillac CTS</p>
        <p>Is it real? Real as an Oscar de la Hoya body blow, completely redesigned inside and out, introduced not to the strains of Led Zeppelin but rather to the chamber music of the Panache String Quartet and the Nuthin' But Strings rap violin duo.</p>
        <p>What's the point? There was some resistance to the knife-edge design of the original CTS and the exuberant patchwork of interior textures, so they softened the outside and straightened out the inside.</p>
        <p>What they said: ''It's my job to make sure the customers get more than they expect,'' Jim Taylor, general marketing manager of Cadillac, said. ''In the luxury car business, the tiniest detail can make the greatest difference.''</p>
        <p>What they didn't say: The CTS has found a nice niche among the sports sedans with American buyers, and now they want to turn the niche into a much bigger market slice.</p>
        <p>What makes it tick? CTS will have a new 3.6-liter gasoline direct-injection V-6 producing 300 horsepower, coupled to a 6-speed automatic transmission. About a year after introduction, the high-performance CTS-V will come along, packing a 400-horsepower V-8 and 6-speed manual transmission.</p>
        <p>How much, how soon? The 2008 CTS goes on sale in August; prices will range from $30,000 to a bit above $40,000 for a loaded version</p>
        <p>How's it look? Our hat is off to John Manoogian and his staff of designers for making this second, softened CTS about twice as appealing as the original -- big grille, cool headlights and all.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
