<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LIVING HERE | Houses Near Ice Boating; Fun When It Freezes</title>
    <meta content="26live" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1821465"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Iceboating</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Monona (Wis)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kolner, Doug</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyttle, Bethany</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Havens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Living Here</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Wisconsin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01EED7163FF935A15752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="882" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LIVING HERE | Houses Near Ice Boating; Fun When It Freezes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">As told to Bethany Lyttle</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyttle, Bethany</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Doug Kolner about his vacation cabin on lake in Monona, Wis, where he enjoys building ice boats and going ice sailing; photos and brief descriptions of similar properties for sale around country (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This cabin is less than 10 minutes from our house in Madison and it's only about 700 square feet. But it's right on the lake, and it has a detached garage. That was the real attraction for me, because up until then, I'd been trying to build a Renegade ice yacht in my basement. This required punching a hole in the wall, something that wasn't very pleasing to my wife. This garage, on the other had, is already in borderline tear-down condition, so, you know, knocking out holes isn't that big a deal.</p>
        <p>I must have been 11 or 12 years old the first time I saw an ice boat. It was one of those years with beautiful black ice on the lake. I was skating with a group of friends, and this guy sailed by and offered to tow us across the lake. I knew I had to have one.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This cabin is less than 10 minutes from our house in Madison and it's only about 700 square feet. But it's right on the lake, and it has a detached garage. That was the real attraction for me, because up until then, I'd been trying to build a Renegade ice yacht in my basement. This required punching a hole in the wall, something that wasn't very pleasing to my wife. This garage, on the other had, is already in borderline tear-down condition, so, you know, knocking out holes isn't that big a deal.</p>
        <p>I must have been 11 or 12 years old the first time I saw an ice boat. It was one of those years with beautiful black ice on the lake. I was skating with a group of friends, and this guy sailed by and offered to tow us across the lake. I knew I had to have one.</p>
        <p>So, right after college, I started building and sailing. From the beginning, I had great help from the guys at the Four Lakes Ice Yacht Club. It's been around for about 80 years, and the older guys have been real mentors to me. Nothing gets me out of bed like checking on the work I did on a boat the day before. I just grab a cup of coffee and go straight to the garage to take a look.</p>
        <p>Ice boating is similar to sailing, but unlike regular sailing, the friction is minimal, you can sail upward of five times the speed of wind. Therein lies the thrill. Sitting low, so close to the ice, it feels like you're going 100 miles an hour. For years, I was able to lie about things like that, but now with global positioning systems, I know it's more like 60.</p>
        <p>As told to Bethany Lyttle</p>
        <p>Information on properties was supplied by the owners or the listing companies.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Houghton Lake, Mich.  WHAT -- 3-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $369,000</p>
        <p>This 1,652-square-foot ranch-style house is on Houghton Lake, a popular destination for ice sailing and other winter sports. The house has large windows with full lake views. The property has 50 feet of lakefront, a seawall and a sandy bottom beach. There are two bathrooms, a large family room with lake views, a sun room, a remodeled kitchen, a stone fireplace and a one-car garage. Lake Houghton is 120 miles north of Lansing. Broker: Sheila Sensor, Century 21 Professional Realty, 800-536-1103. www.century21-professionalrealty.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Tonka Bay, Minn.  WHAT -- 3-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $1.25 million</p>
        <p>On Lafayette Bay on Lake Minnetonka, this 1,800-square-foot house overlooks a protected harbor with a dock large enough for a 35-foot boat. It has 68 feet of water frontage and a lakefront terrace. Built in 1958, the house has two bathrooms, beamed ceilings and a stone corner fireplace flanked by large windows with lake views. Agent: Mark Grieger, Edina Realty, (952) 476-5360; www.markgproperties.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Alton, N.H.  WHAT -- 3-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $795,000</p>
        <p>Built in 2003, this 1,952-square-foot house is located on Rattlesnake Island, the largest island in Lake Winnipesaukee, home to the Winnipesaukee Frolic and other ice boating events. The property has 100 feet of lake frontage, a dock and a boat house. The house has two bathrooms, granite countertops, vaulted ceilings and a wooden spiral staircase to a loft. Alton is about 25 miles northeast of Concord. The property can be reached only by boat. Agent: Jason Starr, Prudential Spencer-Hughes Real Estate, (603) 875-2020; www.spencerhughes.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Red Bank, N.J.  WHAT -- 5-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $1,975,000</p>
        <p>This 1920s Dutch Colonial-style house overlooks the Navesink River, which is popular with ice boaters. The property has a dock and more than 100 feet of waterfront. The house, which is about 3,500 square feet, was completely renovated about 12 years ago and has three bathrooms. The master bedroom has a wall of windows overlooking the river, as does the master bath. The house is minutes from train, bus and ferry transportation to New York City. Agent: Christine Doran, Gloria Nilson GMAC Real Estate, (732) 842-6009; www.glorianilson.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Germantown, N.Y.  WHAT -- 4-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $575,000</p>
        <p>This approximately 2,000-square-foot Victorian house is situated on 1.5 acres on a hill with views of the Hudson River and the Catskill Mountains. Germantown is home to The Hudson River Ice Yacht Club. The house, which was built in 1900, has original woodwork, hardwood floors, stained-glass windows and a wraparound porch. There are two bathrooms and a one-car garage. Germantown is about 100 miles north of New York City. Broker: Patricia Hinkein, Patricia Hinkein Realty, (518) 537-4888; www.hinkeinrealty.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Malone, Wis.  WHAT -- 3-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $354,900</p>
        <p>This waterfront house looks over 215-square-mile Lake Winnebago, the largest lake in Wisconsin. The lake is home to both national and international ice boating regattas. The house is 1,800 square feet and was built in the 1950s and remodeled in 1996, when an 800-square-foot addition and a basement were added. There are two bathrooms, a detached two-car garage and a boat house. Malone is about 65 miles northwest of Milwaukee. Agent: Bob Brendemuehl, Brendy Realty, (888) 743-1601; www.brendyrealty.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
