<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gains in Wireless Customers Help Lift AT&amp;T's Earnings 17%</title>
    <meta content="26phone" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/26/technology/26phone.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1821515"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">At&amp;t Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Flynn, Laurie J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">AT&amp;T Corp</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E5DE173FF935A15752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="701" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gains in Wireless Customers Help Lift AT&amp;T's Earnings 17%</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Gains in Wireless Customers Help Lift AT&amp;T’s Earnings 17%</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURIE J. FLYNN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Flynn, Laurie J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>AT&amp;T reports 17 percent increase in 2006 quarterly profits on strength of sizable increase in wireless subscribers; posts net income of $1.94 billion, compared with $1.66 billion in fourth quarter of 2005; quarterly revenue increased 23.1 percent, to $15.9 billion, from $12.9 billion (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Capping a whirlwind year of merging and rebranding that has come to characterize the telecommunications business, AT&amp;T reported a 17 percent increase in quarterly profits yesterday driven by a sizable increase in wireless subscribers.</p>
        <p>''We closed the year strong,'' Edward E. Whitacre Jr., chairman and chief executive of AT&amp;T, said in a conference call with analysts. ''We are headed into 2007 with excellent momentum.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT&amp;T reported a 17 percent increase in quarterly profits driven by a sizable increase in wireless subscribers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Capping a whirlwind year of merging and rebranding that has come to characterize the telecommunications business, AT&amp;T reported a 17 percent increase in quarterly profits yesterday driven by a sizable increase in wireless subscribers.</p>
        <p>''We closed the year strong,'' Edward E. Whitacre Jr., chairman and chief executive of AT&amp;T, said in a conference call with analysts. ''We are headed into 2007 with excellent momentum.''</p>
        <p>Net income at AT&amp;T for the fourth quarter was $1.94 billion, or 50 cents a share, compared with $1.66 billion, or 46 cents a share, in the fourth quarter last year.</p>
        <p>Quarterly revenue at the company, based in San Antonio, increased 23.1 percent, to $15.9 billion, from $12.9 billion in the previous year, mostly because of the company's acquisition of the old AT&amp;T in November 2005. The company, formerly called SBC Communications, bought AT&amp;T and adopted the well-known AT&amp;T name as its own.</p>
        <p>Results for AT&amp;T yesterday largely excluded BellSouth, which the company bought for $86 billion in a deal completed in the last few days of December 2006. With the BellSouth merger, AT&amp;T became the sole owner of Cingular Wireless, and two weeks ago the company said it was dropping the Cingular brand in favor of the AT&amp;T name. AT&amp;T previously owned 60 percent of Cingular, and BellSouth owned 40 percent. The combined company now offers wireless and landline service in 22 states.</p>
        <p>''It was a great quarter by all the parts; SBC, AT&amp;T, Cingular and BellSouth,'' said Christopher Larsen, an analyst at Credit Suisse.</p>
        <p>In a bit of encouraging news for investors, Mr. Whitacre said he expected even greater savings from AT&amp;T's merger with BellSouth than previously projected. The company raised the forecast for total cost savings to about $22 billion, up from the original figure of $18 billion, although the company did not specify a time frame for those savings. AT&amp;T now anticipates savings of $800 million to $1.2 billion for the current year, compared with a previous estimate of $500 million to $800 million.</p>
        <p>''It was a decent quarter, without a whole lot of surprises,'' said Christopher C. King, an analyst at Stifel Nicolaus. ''The company continues to do an excellent job of delivering what they say they will.''</p>
        <p>Excluding costs related to the merger and other items, quarterly earnings rose to 61 cents a share from 48 cents a share a year earlier. Wall Street analysts had forecast earnings of 59 cents a share, according to a survey by Thomson Financial.</p>
        <p>Shares of AT&amp;T rose 16 cents, to close at $36.79 after the release of the results, which were announced before the start of trading.</p>
        <p>Bright spots in AT&amp;T's report were its wireless and high-speed Internet businesses. The wireless business is seen as the main driver of growth, with that operation adding a net 2.4 million customers for a total of nearly 61 million. Wireless service revenue was up 13.1 percent, while wireless data revenue grew 68.6 percent. The company's high-speed Internet business grew 23 percent.</p>
        <p>Mr. King said the wireless business was feeling intense competitive pressure from Verizon, which appeared to have gained in market share during the quarter.</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T's traditional consumer phone lines totaled 25.3 million at the end of December, down 5 percent from 26.7 million a year ago, illustrating the challenge the company faces as it adapts to the decreasing demand for wire-line phone service.</p>
        <p>In its final quarter as an independent company, BellSouth had profit of $1.2 billion, 29 percent higher than a year earlier. Revenue increased 4.6 percent, to $9.1 billion. During the quarter, BellSouth added 183,000 new high-speed Internet connections, but access lines were down 6.4 percent compared with last year.</p>
        <p>The report from AT&amp;T came a day after Cingular issued a quarterly earnings report for the last time. On Wednesday, Cingular reported its quarterly profits more than tripled to $782 million as it added 2.4 million new subscribers. That report led AT&amp;T shares to gain almost 4 percent.</p>
        <p>For the full year, AT&amp;T reported $7.36 billion in net income, or $1.89 a share, a 54 percent increase over the $4.79 billion, or $1.42 a share, last year. Revenue was $63.1 billion, a 44 percent increase from $43.8 billion in 2005.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
