<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TONIGHT'S TV LISTINGS: What's on Friday Night</title>
    <meta content="0126tvcol" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/26/arts/television/0126tvcol.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1821610"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Tonight's TV Listings"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EEDD173FF935A15752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="455" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TONIGHT'S TV LISTINGS: What's on Friday Night</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">What’s on Friday Night</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHRYN SHATTUCK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>8 P.M.(Turner Classic Movies) PARIS WHEN IT SIZZLES (1964). Paris isn't just for springtime. Tonight, TCM takes a winter break in the City of Light, starting with this William Holden and Audrey Hepburn vehicle about a boozy writer who has two days to deliver a script to a Hollywood producer and hires a temporary secretary to help him get the job done. They fall in love, but of course. At 10, Gene Kelly and Leslie Caron trip the light fantastic to a luscious Gershwin score in the grand musical ''An American in Paris'' (1951). And at midnight, Alec Guinness and Vernon Gray play a Scottish father and son who visit the city and tumble into mild infatuations -- the son with an older woman, the father with a girl -- in ''To Paris, With Love'' (1955).</p>
        <p>8 P.M. (Fox) NANNY 911 Nanny Deb helps the McDowell family, whose three rambunctious boys think they're in charge.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>8 P.M.(Turner Classic Movies) PARIS WHEN IT SIZZLES (1964). Paris isn’t just for springtime. Tonight, TCM takes a winter break in the City of Light, starting with this William Holden and Audrey Hepburn vehicle about a boozy writer who has two days to deliver a script to a Hollywood producer and hires a temporary secretary to help him get the job done. They fall in love, but of course. At 10, Gene Kelly and Leslie Caron trip the light fantastic to a luscious Gershwin score in the grand musical “An American in Paris” (1951). And at midnight, Alec Guinness and Vernon Gray play a Scottish father and son who visit the city and tumble into mild infatuations  the son with an older woman, the father with a girl  in “To Paris, With Love” (1955).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>8 P.M.(Turner Classic Movies) PARIS WHEN IT SIZZLES (1964). Paris isn't just for springtime. Tonight, TCM takes a winter break in the City of Light, starting with this William Holden and Audrey Hepburn vehicle about a boozy writer who has two days to deliver a script to a Hollywood producer and hires a temporary secretary to help him get the job done. They fall in love, but of course. At 10, Gene Kelly and Leslie Caron trip the light fantastic to a luscious Gershwin score in the grand musical ''An American in Paris'' (1951). And at midnight, Alec Guinness and Vernon Gray play a Scottish father and son who visit the city and tumble into mild infatuations -- the son with an older woman, the father with a girl -- in ''To Paris, With Love'' (1955).</p>
        <p>8 P.M. (Fox) NANNY 911 Nanny Deb helps the McDowell family, whose three rambunctious boys think they're in charge.</p>
        <p>8 P.M. (CMT) COWBOY U The greenhorns toughen up in this episode, in which the challenges include driving a horse and wagon and, after a lesson from a professional bullfighter, getting into the ring with a 1,500-pound bull in Seven Rings of Fire, a competition the show is calling a ''terrifying test of courage.'' But maybe it's just in preparation for the campfire elimination.</p>
        <p>9 P.M. (Fox) TRADING SPOUSES: MEET YOUR NEW MOMMY Marguerite Perrin, a k a the God Warrior, concludes her second trade. Last time, Ms. Perrin initially refused the $50,000 traditionally given at the end of the show, declaring it tainted -- and then decided to use it for gastric-bypass surgery. No word yet on what she'll do with this stint's prize.</p>
        <p>9 P.M. (USA) MONK Natalie suspects foul play in the deaths of her parents' neighbors. Good thing she has Mr. Monk as an employer.</p>
        <p>9:30 P.M. (Sundance) THE MOTEL (2005). A 13-year-old Chinese-American boy (Jeffrey Chyau) who lives and works in a sleazy motel run by his mother finds a father figure in a ne'er-do-well tenant (Sung Kang), who takes a room at the inn for an hour with a prostitute -- and then decides to stay. He likes to give advice, including how to seduce women.</p>
        <p>10 P.M. (USA) PSYCH Vulnerability is such an attractive trait, isn't it? When Lassiter starts having doubts about his own crime-solving ability, Shawn tries to give him a confidence boost by helping him solve an astronomer's mysterious death.</p>
        <p>10 P.M. (Showtime) WASHINGTONIANS Revisionist history: after his grandmother's funeral, a man (Jonathan Schaech) finds an artifact in her basement that suggests that George Washington was a cannibal in this ''Masters of Horror'' episode. Turns out Washington's followers didn't mind treating themselves to a nibble now and then either.</p>
        <p>KATHRYN SHATUCK</p>
        <p>Tonight's TV Listings</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
