<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Old San Juan, for the Young</title>
    <meta content="26kids" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/26/travel/escapes/26kids.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1821434"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEEKEND WITH THE KIDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">San Juan (Puerto Rico)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Puerto Rico</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gerszberg, Caren Osten</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Puerto Rico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Puerto Rico/San Juan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">San Juan (Puerto Rico)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E7D7163FF935A15752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1564" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Old San Juan, for the Young</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Old San Juan, for the Young</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAREN OSTEN GERSZBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gerszberg, Caren Osten</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Weekend With the Kids column on visit to Old San Juan, Puerto Rico; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PUERTO RICO is a lush island, 100 by 35 miles, outlined by long stretches of white beach, which, for most tourists, are reason enough to visit. But on a recent trip with my husband and three children, I was struck by how much the island offers in addition to its coastline. As we discovered an array of historical sights and opportunities for natural adventures, I quickly concluded that giving up my beach chaise -- at least part of the time -- was a smart move.</p>
        <p>Driving around the island gives visitors a taste of Puerto Rico's exotic beauty, while a visit to Old San Juan reveals how thoroughly the island is steeped in history. Now a cross of Hispanic and Anglo cultures, Puerto Rico was visited in 1493 by Christopher Columbus. Under the leadership of Juan Ponce de León, the island became a strategic military outpost for Spain, and with its massive forts built in the early 1500s -- and still standing (and a favorite tourist stop) -- the island protected its port of San Juan from attacks by the English and Dutch.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The island offers more than just a pretty coastline for families. An array of historical sights and natural adventures await.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PUERTO RICO is a lush island, 100 by 35 miles, outlined by long stretches of white beach, which, for most tourists, are reason enough to visit. But on a recent trip with my husband and three children, I was struck by how much the island offers in addition to its coastline. As we discovered an array of historical sights and opportunities for natural adventures, I quickly concluded that giving up my beach chaise -- at least part of the time -- was a smart move.</p>
        <p>Driving around the island gives visitors a taste of Puerto Rico's exotic beauty, while a visit to Old San Juan reveals how thoroughly the island is steeped in history. Now a cross of Hispanic and Anglo cultures, Puerto Rico was visited in 1493 by Christopher Columbus. Under the leadership of Juan Ponce de León, the island became a strategic military outpost for Spain, and with its massive forts built in the early 1500s -- and still standing (and a favorite tourist stop) -- the island protected its port of San Juan from attacks by the English and Dutch.</p>
        <p>As part of the Spanish empire, Puerto Rico thrived during the 1800s. After the Spanish-American War in 1898, Puerto Rico became a part of the United States (which also makes it one of the few Caribbean destinations that Americans can still visit without a passport).</p>
        <p>A walk through Old San Juan should include a visit to El Morro (Calle Norzagaray, 787-729-6777), a fortress built by Spanish colonists on a promontory 140 feet above the sea. Kids love to touch the fort's cannons and explore the maze of dungeons, towers and tunnels. A green esplanade just outside the fort -- perfect for kite flying -- separates it from the historic town it was built to safeguard.</p>
        <p>Where El Morro guarded against attacks from the sea, San Cristóbal (Calle Norzagaray, 787-729-6960), a fort one mile to the east, was built to stave off land attacks. Finished in 1790 and covering 27 acres, the fort offers spectacular views and a chance to walk on the ramparts. Both forts are managed by the National Park Service (www.nps.gov/saju) and are Unesco world heritage sites. Admission is $3 to visit one fort; $5 for both. Children 15 and younger are free.</p>
        <p>The children's museum, Museo del Niño (150 Calle Cristo, 787-722-3791; www.museodelninopr.org), into which I dragged my reluctant 13-year-old, turned out to be an entertaining stop for both of us. Its three floors are filled with interactive learning activities, art projects, a mock plaza with a food market, puppet shows and special events -- while there, we made juggling balls out of balloons and rice. The museum, which also has a rooftop garden, is closed on Monday; admission is $5; $4 for children under 12.</p>
        <p>NATURE'S DIVERSIONS</p>
        <p>A 40-minute drive from San Juan puts you in the Caribbean National Forest, known locally as El Yunque (Route 191, 787-888-1880; www.fs.fed.us/r8/caribbean), the only tropical rain forest in the United States National Forest Service system and where more than 250 inches of rain falls each year. On 28,000 lush acres, you can view birds, like the endangered Puerto Rican parrot, and hundreds of species of trees and plants. Be sure to listen for the song of the coquí, a tiny tree frog native to the island, which you won't see but will most likely hear. The Big Tree Trail, 1.4 miles round trip, takes you to La Mina waterfall where -- if you don't get wet from a rainfall -- you can cool off. Before you start exploring, make a stop at the El Portal visitors center (open daily 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.), where there are multimedia displays and several hands-on activities for youngsters.</p>
        <p>The Rio Camuy Cave Park (Route 129, kilometer 18.9, 787-898-3100), a 90-minute drive west of San Juan, is a big cave system, formed by the Camuy River, one of the world's longest underground rivers. From the visitors center (admission is $12; $7 ages 4 to 12), you can take an open-air trolley down to the caves through a 200-foot deep sinkhole, a chasm where sunlight reaches down to thriving tropical trees and flowers. There are many caves in this 268-acre ecosystem, with winding footpaths and ''rooms'' with stalactites, stalagmites and huge limestone formations. Keep an eye out for the bats.</p>
        <p>For a different type of eco-adventure, try a nighttime boat or kayak ride on a ''bio bay.'' About an hour and a half drive from San Juan, the bioluminescent lagoon at Las Cabezas Nature Reserve in Fajardo (Route 987 near Las Croabas; 787-722-5882)is lighted by millions of microscopic organisms called dinoflagellates. Adults ($7) and older kids ($4 ages 5 to 11) may like getting close to the water in a kayak, and there are boats for those with younger children. Admission is by reservation only; guided tours are recommended.</p>
        <p>You can reach all of the above destinations by renting a car, and most hotels offer group tours. Or, you can hire a private guide, which is more costly but allows for greater flexibility. The guide we used, Tony Sanchez, used to work for the Fish and Wildlife Service, and was very knowledgeable about the island's flora and fauna (Island Tours, 787-240-6818 ).</p>
        <p>DOWN TIME</p>
        <p>On a hot day, there's nothing like a Phish Food ice cream cone from Ben &amp; Jerry's (61 Calle Cristo, Old San Juan; 787-977-6882). On Saturdays from 3 to 5 p.m., children are invited for a story ''hour'' (with music) -- part in English and part in Spanish. While the kids are entranced and licking their cones, parents can check e-mail on one of the parlor's two computers ($3 for 15 minutes; $5 for 30 minutes).</p>
        <p>Skip the outlets (yes, Ralph Lauren, Coach and the like are here) and stop in to see the colorful crafts at the family-owned Mi Pequeño San Juan (107 Calle Cristo, 787-977-1636; www.ducart.net). Peruse the variety of handmade miniature reproductions -- all one-of-a-kind replicas of doors, houses and buildings in Old San Juan.</p>
        <p>At the end of Calle Cristo, make a stop to feed the pigeons at the Parque de las Palomas. Constructed during the 18th century and originally a rampart for cannon emplacement, the park got its name from the hundreds of pigeons that lived here, and still do. There is a kiosk there where one dollar buys a bag of seed. You can watch the pigeons, and kids, run wild.</p>
        <p>WHERE TO EAT</p>
        <p>For a casual, family-run place in Old San Juan with good local food --mofongo, or mashed plantain, is a Puerto Rican specialty but children will probably prefer the sugary plantain version -- try El Jibarito (280 Calle Sol, Old San Juan, 787-725-8375; www.eljibaritopr.com), where you can expect to pay about $30 for two for dinner.</p>
        <p>At Pamela's (1 Santa Ana Street, Ocean Park, 787-726-5010; www.numero1guesthouse.com), diners sit indoors or at tables on the beach, steps from the ocean. The chef, a graduate of the Culinary Institute of America, grills traditional dishes from Puerto Rico and other Caribbean islands. The menu might include jalapeño- and ginger-sautéed shrimp for $26, and guajillo-pepper-rubbed roasted chicken for $22. Restaurant Barrachina (104 Fortaleza Street, Old San Juan, 787-721-5852; www.barrachina.com) claims to be the birthplace of the piña colada, and the bartender is happy to make them without alcohol ($4.85 virgin; $6.39 with rum). The food isn't much to rave about, but there is a children's menu with standard fare (miniburgers and chicken fingers cost $5.95 each, with fries and a soda). You can sit in the interior courtyard where there are two large talking parrots in a cage nearby, or inside where there is a flamenco show on Friday and Saturday nights from 8 to 9 p.m.</p>
        <p>WHERE TO STAY</p>
        <p>A few minutes from the international airport, the Ritz-Carlton San Juan (6961 Avenue of the Governors, 787-253-1700; www.ritzcarlton.com) is on eight oceanfront acres in the Isla Verde neighborhood. Children are happy in the Ritz Kids program, and adults might be happy with two outposts of New York restaurants: Laurent Tourandel has opened a BLT Steak, and the hotel also has a branch of Il Mulino Italian restaurant. Rates for a double room start at $489.</p>
        <p>For those who want to stay in the old city, Hotel El Convento (100 Calle Cristo; 800-468-2779; www.elconvento.com) is a good choice. Once a Carmelite convent, the 350-year-old building, in the middle of Old San Juan, has been transformed into a luxurious boutique hotel with 70 rooms and a small plunge pool. Double rooms start at $365 a night.</p>
        <p>On the northeastern tip of the island, perched on a cliff overlooking the Atlantic, the El Conquistador Resort (1000 El Conquistador Avenue; 800-468-5228; www.elconresort.com) has over 900 rooms and looks like a small city with fountain-filled plazas and cobblestone streets connecting its villas. The hotel has a Golden Door Spa and an Arthur Hills golf course, and its beach is on a private island just off shore, reached by a shuttle boat. Rates start at $239 for a double.</p>
        <p>For a charming -- and affordable -- place to stay, try the Numero Uno Guest House (1 Santa Ana Street; 866-726-5010; www.numero1guesthouse.com), site of the child-friendly Pamela's restaurant. Situated on the beach in the Ocean Park neighborhood, just a 15-minute drive from Old San Juan, the hotel was built as a private home in the late 1940s and now how has 14 guest rooms, starting at $115.</p>
        <p>WEEKEND WITH THE KIDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
