<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Listings: Jan. 26-Feb. 1</title>
    <meta content="26theater" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070127T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1821423"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E0D8163FF935A15752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="14864" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Listings: Jan. 26-Feb. 1</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'ADRIFT IN MACAO' In previews; opens on Feb 13. Primary Stages presents Christopher Durang and Peter Melnick's new musical send-up of the sexy, shadowy world of film noir (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'THE COAST OF UTOPIA: SALVAGE' Previews start on Tuesday. Opens on Feb. 15. Tom Stoppard's epic trilogy about 19th-century Russian intelligentsia comes to an end with this final installment, which once again stars a vigorous and immense cast, including Brian F. O'Byrne, Jennifer Ehle, Billy Crudup and Ethan Hawke. Jack O'Brien directs (2:30). Vivian Beaumont Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'THE FEVER' In previews; opens on Monday. Wallace Shawn stars in his own play about a man who wakes up in a war-torn country feeling under the weather (1:30). Acorn Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'FRANK'S HOME' In previews; opens on Tuesday. Richard Nelson's new bio-play about the life and work of Frank Lloyd Wright stars Peter Weller (as Wright) and Harris Yulin (who plays Louis Sullivan) (1:45). Playwrights Horizons Mainstage, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 719-4200.</p>
        <p>'IN THE HEIGHTS' In previews; opens on Feb. 8. A new Off Broadway musical about two days in the life of Washington Heights, presented from the vantage point of a corner bodega (2:10). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'THE LAST WORD ' Previews start on Tuesday. Opens on Feb. 8. This new play by Oren Safdie (''Private Jokes, Public Places'') is about a retired ad executive who wants to be a playwright. Daniel J. Travanti (''Hill Street Blues'') stars (1:30). Theater at St. Clement's, 423 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'THE MADRAS HOUSE' Previews start on Wednesday. Opens on Feb. 15. Yet another modern-sounding play by Harley Granville Barker (''Waste'') comes out of the woodwork: a 1909 drama about business battles, family values and sex (2:30). Mint Theater, 311 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 315-0231.</p>
        <p>'MARY ROSE' Previews start on Thursday. Opens on Feb. 20. Although it can sometimes seem otherwise, J. M. Barrie wrote stories besides ''Peter Pan,'' including this one about a girl who might be a ghost. Tina Landau directs (1:45). Vineyard Theater, 108 East 15th Street, (212) 353-0303.</p>
        <p>'THE MERCHANT OF VENICE' In previews; opens on Feb. 4. F. Murray Abraham plays Shylock in this Theater for a New Audience production. Darko Tresnjak directs (2:20). The Duke on 42nd Street, 229 West 42nd Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'A SPANISH PLAY' In previews; opens on Thursday. Zoe Caldwell leads an extraordinary cast (Linda Emond, Denis O'Hare, Larry Pine, Katherine Borowitz) in Yasmina Reza's new backstage play, in which real life and fiction blur (1:30). Classic Stage Company, 136 East 13th Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101.</p>
        <p>'A VERY COMMON PROCEDURE' Previews start on Wednesday. Opens on Feb. 14. Michael Greif (''Rent'') directs MCC Theater's new play about a married woman who has an affair with a doctor (1:20). Lucille Lortel Theater, 121 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE APPLE TREE' The amazing Kristin Chenoweth gives Imax-screen-size life to three curvaceous doodles who by rights shouldn't be any larger than figures in the Sunday funnies. Jerry Bock and Sheldon Harnick's 1966 musical, directed by Gary Griffin, shows its age but is given theatrical verve by Ms. Chenoweth, Brian d'Arcy James and Marc Kudisch (2:30). Studio 54, 254 West 54th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>'A CHORUS LINE' If you want to know why this show was such a big deal when it opened 31 years ago, you need only experience the thrilling first five minutes of this revival. Otherwise, this archivally exact production, directed by Bob Avian, feels like a vintage car that has been taken out of the garage, polished up and sent on the road once again (2:00). Schoenfeld Theater, 236 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE COAST OF UTOPIA' The exhilarating first two installments of Tom Stoppard's trilogy about 19th-century Russian intellectuals dreaming of revolution, these productions pulse with the dizzy, spring-green arrogance and anxiety of a new generation moving as fast as it can toward the future. Jack O'Brien directs a fresh, vigorous and immense cast that includes Brian F. O'Byrne, Jennifer Ehle, Billy Crudup and Ethan Hawke (2:45). Vivian Beaumont Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'COMPANY' Fire, beckoning and dangerous, flickers beneath the frost of John Doyle's elegant, unexpectedly stirring revival of Stephen Sondheim and George Furth's era-defining musical from 1970, starring a compellingly understated Raul Esparza. Like Mr. Doyle's ''Sweeney Todd,'' this production finds new clarity of feeling in Sondheim by melding the roles of performers and musicians (2:20). Barrymore Theater, 243 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE'  (Tony Awards, best book of a musical and best original score, 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920s stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, it has theatergoers responding as if they were withering houseplants finally being watered after long neglect. Bob Martin and Sutton Foster are the standouts in the avid, energetic cast (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'GREY GARDENS' Christine Ebersole is absolutely glorious as the middle-aged, time-warped debutante called Little Edie Beale in this uneven musical adaptation of the notorious 1975 documentary of the same title. She and the wonderful Mary Louise Wilson (as her bedridden mother), in the performances of their careers, make ''Grey Gardens'' an experience no passionate theatergoer should miss (2:40). Walter Kerr Theater, 219 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE LITTLE DOG LAUGHED' The comedy of manners, a form widely believed to be extinct in the American theater, has actually resurfaced on Broadway with all its vital signs intact in Douglas Carter Beane's breezy but trenchant satire about truth and illusion, Hollywood style. With the wonderful Julie White as the movie agent you hate to love (but just can't help it) (2:00). Cort Theater, 138 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MARY POPPINS' This handsome, homily-packed, mechanically ingenious and rather tedious musical, adapted from the P. L. Travers stories and the 1964 Disney film, is ultimately less concerned with inexplicable magic than with practical psychology. Ashley Brown, who sings prettily as the family-mending nanny, looks like Joan Crawford trying to be nice and sounds like Dr. Phil. Directed by Richard Eyre and Matthew Bourne (2:30). New Amsterdam Theater, 214 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LES MISÉRABLES' This premature revival, a slightly scaled-down version of the well-groomed behemoth that closed only three years ago, appears to be functioning in a state of mild sedation. Appealingly sung and freshly orchestrated, this fast-moving adaptation of Victor Hugo's novel isn't sloppy or blurry. But its pulse rate stays well below normal (2:55). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' Duncan Sheik and Steven Sater's bold adaptation of the Frank Wedekind play is the freshest and most exciting new musical Broadway has seen in some time. Set in 19th-century Germany but with a ravishing rock score, it exposes the splintered emotional lives of adolescents just discovering the joys and sorrows of sex. Performed with brio by a great cast, with supple direction by Michael Mayer and inventive choreography by Bill T. Jones (2:00). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN'  This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a superdeluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE VERTICAL HOUR' David Hare's soggy consideration of the Anglo-American cultural divide stars Julianne Moore (representing the Americans) and Bill Nighy (leading the British), directed by Sam Mendes. The Yanks don't stand a chance. With his irresistibly mannered performance as a laconic doctor, Mr. Nighy mops the floor with Ms. Moore. Actually, he mops the floor with Mr. Hare's play (2:20). Music Box Theater, 239 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'AS YET THOU ART YOUNG AND RASH' An abstract collage of shards of feeling built out of Euripides' ''Suppliant Women,'' this meditation on grief and the death of children in senseless war offers plenty of parallels to current society without doing anything so obvious as explicitly referring to them. The five-member cast, led by three beautiful middle-aged women, is strong; the director, David Herskovits, has helped them shape an evocative piece that might be too nonliteral for some tastes, but is both moving and distinctive (1:10). The Ohio Theater, 66 Wooster Street, SoHo, (212) 352-3101. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>'DUTCHMAN' A revival of the poet Amiri Baraka's screed on race and American values, 43 years after its Greenwich Village debut, aims for all the fire and might of a Malcolm X speech but none of the rhetorical elegance. It shouts so loudly that you can't hear a thing (1:00). Cherry Lane Theater, 38 Commerce Street, between Barrow and Bedford Streets, West Village (212) 239-6200. (Ginia Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'GUTENBERG! THE MUSICAL' A very funny if not terribly original satire of musical theater features what must be the worst backers' audition of all time. The excellent duo Jeremy Shamos and Christopher Fitzgerald make the pitch (2:05). The Actors' Playhouse, 100 Seventh Avenue South, at Fourth Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 239-6200. (Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'JACQUES BREL IS ALIVE AND WELL AND LIVING IN PARIS' A powerfully sung revival of the 1968 revue, presented with affectionate nostalgia by the director Gordon Greenberg. As in the original, two men and two women perform a wide selection of Brel's plaintive ballads and stirring anthems (2:00). Zipper Theater, 336 West 37th Street, (212) 239-6200.(Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'MEET ME IN ST. LOUIS' This musical is too big for its stage, but the young turn-of-the-last-century sweethearts have great chemistry, and there are four terrific songs (2:00). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>'NO GREAT SOCIETY' The brainy experimentalists of Elevator Repair Service provide a madcap and almost dreamlike re-enactment of a 1968 episode of William F. Buckley's ''Firing Line,'' which features Mr. Buckley squaring off with Jack Kerouac (1:30). New York Theater Workshop, 79 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 239-6200. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'THE SCENE' Theresa Rebeck's latest is a sharp-witted, sharp-elbowed comedy about the savage economies of sex and show business in Manhattan. Tony Shalhoub plays an out-of-work actor, Charlie, happily married -- but not really -- to Patricia Heaton's frazzled chat show booker. Enter the femme fatale Clea, played by the gifted Anna Camp, and goodbye, Charlie (2:00). Second Stage Theater, 307 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 246-4422. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'TOYS IN THE ATTIC' Austin Pendleton's fine revival of Lillian Hellman's last play faithfully attacks the corrosive attachments of family. What good is a family, and thus a society, the play implicitly asks, that can only look in the mirror? (2:30) Pearl Theater, 80 St. Marks Place, East Village, (212) 598-9802. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'VICTORIA MARTIN: MATH TEAM QUEEN' Must all stage teenagers speak in that exaggerated surfer-dude style in which ''awesome'' and ''totally'' make up about 50 percent of any conversation? Yes, apparently they must, from the evidence presented in this thin comedy, which is about a high school girl who finds herself on the all-male math team. The playwright, Kathryn Walat, seems to have been trying to grab the coattails of a certain spelling-bee-related show. She missed (2:00). The Julia Miles Theater, 424 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>* 'THE VOYSEY INHERITANCE' David Mamet has cleanly and cannily adapted Harley Granville Barker's 1905 play about corruption in the genteel world of Victorian finance. An excellent cast and a sumptuous production bring extra immediacy to a tale of embezzlement and entitlement that feels as fresh as tomorrow's stock options (1:50). Atlantic Theater, 336 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE WOMEN OF TRACHIS' In Kate Ryan's wonderfully perceptive adaptation, Sophocles' rarely produced tragedy about the death of the hero Heracles and his wife, Deianira, has terrific contemporary traction. Alice Reagan's superbly cast and infectiously energetic production is fun, intelligent and eminently worth seeing. (1:00). The Ohio Theater, 66 Wooster Street, SoHo, (212) 352-3101. (Jonathan Kalb)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>* 'THE DIRTY TALK' Kevin Cristaldi and Sidney Williams are just great in this two-hander by Michael Puzzo about strangers stranded in a hunting cabin. How they came to be there is hilariously doled out by Mr. Puzzo, along with some thoughts about identity, the Internet and the liar in all of us. Padraic Lillis, the director, has the two actors in perfect sync (1:20). Center Stage, 41 West 21st Street, Chelsea, (212) 352-3101. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'T J AND DAVE' The comics T. J. Jagodowski and Dave Pasquesi miraculously improvise a one-hour play at every performance (1:00). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden Theater, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' Singing CliffsNotes for Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' Often more entertaining than the real thing (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS'  The biomusical that walks like a man (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT'  A singing scrapbook for Monty Python fans (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' ''A Chorus Line'' with pimples (1:45). Circle in the Square, 254 West 50th Street, Manhattan, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* 'A BEAUTIFUL VIEW' The Canadian playwright and director Daniel MacIvor mines two funny, subdued and entirely affecting performances from Caroline Gillis and Tracy Wright as women whose enduring friendship may be more (1:20). The Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200; closes on Sunday. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'THE BROTHERS SIZE' Loosely based on West African myths, this impressive and emotionally absorbing debut by Tarrell Alvin McCraney portrays two battling brothers in Louisiana (1:30). The Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200; closes on Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>* 'THE CLEAN HOUSE' Sarah Ruhl's comedy about the painful but beautiful disorder of life has arrived in New York at last in a gorgeous production directed by Bill Rauch. Blair Brown and Jill Clayburgh delight as sisters with different views on the meaning of cleaning, and Vanessa Aspillaga is equally good as the depressed maid with little affection for her work but a deep conviction that a good joke can be a matter of life and death (2:15). Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200; closes on Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'DEAD SET #3' Themes of apocalypse and trauma echo throughout the Big Art Group's flashy and shallow new entry in the ever-expanding genre of high-tech theater (1:15). The Kitchen, 512 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 255-5793, Ext. 11; closes tomorrow. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'FLUKE' A meditative collage of enigmatic riffs on ''Moby-Dick'' presented by the rambunctious experimental company Radiohole (1:30). Collapsable Hole, 146 Metropolitan Avenue, at Berry Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 388-2251; closes on Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'GET YOUR WAR ON' Based on the absurdist comic strip of David Rees, this sardonic history lesson of the past six years will delight Bush-haters (1:10). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200; closes on Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'INVINCIBLE SUMMER' The performance artist Mike Daisey's monologue is a showcase of facile observation. During his first summer in New York six years ago, he discovers that it's hot and that people are generally much nicer than their comportment on subways would lead you to believe (1:30). The Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200; closes on Sunday. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'REGRETS ONLY' Old acquaintance comes under siege in Paul Rudnick's chiffon-thin comedy about the varieties of love and marriage. But no one who sees this latest offering from one of the funniest quipmeisters alive is going to doubt that Christine Baranski is a one-liner's best friend (2:00). City Center Stage I, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212; closes on Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TWO TRAINS RUNNING'  Directed by Lou Bellamy, a rough-edged revival of August Wilson's 1992 play about the stark economics of life and death for African-Americans, set in a dying diner in Pittsburgh in the late 1960s. The pace drags in this production, but it remains a bracing reminder of Mr. Wilson's singular talent for making cold, hard numbers sing hot, molten blues (3:40). Signature Theater at Peter Norton Space, 555 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 352-3101; closes on Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE VIETNAMIZATION OF NEW JERSEY (AN AMERICAN TRAGEDY)' A revival of Christopher Durang's satire of war, family life and Bicentennial fever, on the 30th anniversary of its debut at the Yale Repertory Theater, swishes along at the speed of a Nascar race. Blanche Baker is a gem as an out-of-it 1970s matron who just can't dust off the Eisenhower era. The Beckett Theater, on Theater Row, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200; closes on Sunday. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>'ALPHA DOG' (R, 117 minutes) Based on a true Southern California crime, Nick Cassavetes's entertaining exploitation flick features a lot of attractive, talented young actors shimmying across the screen while embodying the collective parental nightmare. Do you know where your children are? Well, in this film they're getting busy, chilling out, smoking blunts and chugging coolers faster than a toothless wino. Oh, and committing murder. (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>'ALONE WITH HER' (No rating, 79 minutes) In this voyeuristic thriller, a young man named Doug (Colin Hanks) becomes smitten with a coffee shop waitress named Amy (Ana Claudia Talancón) and tries to insinuate himself into her life through high-tech means, videotaping her routines from afar, then bugging her apartment. In the end, though, the characters seem less archetypal than vague, and aside from its sophisticated presentation, the film doesn't differ all that much from its template -- the late 1980s/early '90s Fill-in-the-Blanks-From-Hell movies that followed ''Fatal Attraction,'' many of whose elements are revived almost verbatim. (Matt Zoller Seitz)</p>
        <p>'ARTHUR AND THE INVISIBLES' (PG, 94 minutes) Luc Besson serves up a hybrid of live actors and computer-generated figures to tell a not-endearing-enough story about a boy (Freddie Highmore) who shrinks to microscopic size to find some gems and his missing grandfather. Lots of famous names (Madonna, Robert De Niro, David Bowie, Snoop Dogg) lend their voices to the computerized part of the movie, but only briefly near the end does everything click. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'BABEL' (R, 143 minutes, in English, Spanish, Japanese, Berber, Arabic and sign language) This hugely ambitious movie tells four loosely linked, not quite simultaneous stories set on three different continents, with dialogue in several languages. The themes, to the extent they are decipherable, include loss, fate and the terrible consequences of miscommunication. Written by Guillermo Arriaga and directed by Alejandro Gonzalez Iñárritu, the movie is an intellectual muddle but a visceral tour de force, and the power of the filmmaking almost overcomes the fuzziness of the ideas. Almost. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>'BLOOD DIAMOND' (R, 138 minutes) The makers of this foolish thriller about illegal diamond trafficking in Africa, starring an excellent Leonardo DiCaprio, want you to know there may be blood on your hands, specifically your wedding finger. Too bad they haven't thought through what it means to turn human misery into entertainment. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'CHILDREN OF MEN' (R, 100 minutes) The end is nigh in this superbly directed political thriller by Alfonso Cuarón about a nervously plausible future. Based on the P. D. James book, the film stars an excellent Clive Owen and features equally sterling support from the actors Michael Caine, Danny Huston and Chiwetel Ejiofior, among others, as well as the great cinematographer Emmanuel Lubezki. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'THE DEPARTED' (R, 150 minutes) Martin Scorsese's cubistic entertainment about men divided by power, loyalty and their own selves is at once a success and a relief. Based on the crackling Hong Kong thriller ''Infernal Affairs,'' it features fine twinned performances from Matt Damon and Leonardo DiCaprio, and a showboating Jack Nicholson. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'DREAMGIRLS' (PG-13, 131 minutes) The Broadway musical arrives on the screen, capably directed by Bill Condon, ardently acted and sung by Jamie Foxx, Eddie Murphy, Beyoncé Knowles and (especially) Jennifer Hudson, but undone by mediocre and anachronistic songs. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'GOD GREW TIRED OF US' (PG, 90 minutes) This sober, uplifting documentary, which won two major awards at last year's Sundance Film Festival, follows the resettlement in the United States of three Sudanese young men uprooted as children by the civil war. Handsomely photographed, and inspirational but not cloyingly so, it is the rare contemporary documentary that doesn't leave a residue of cynicism and outrage. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE HITCHER' (R, 90 minutes) Like the 1986 cult favorite of the same title, this remake is a crash-and-burn action horror film with intellectual pretensions. The overachieving Irish character actor Sean Bean plays the Hitcher as a philosophical sadist, toying with people who didn't get the memo saying that God is dead, but the movie is too shallow to embellish that vision. The merger of mystical solemnity and chain-reaction slapstick suggests a Road Runner cartoon directed by John Woo. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>'THE ITALIAN' (PG-13, 99 minutes, in Russian) This dark fairy tale from Russia pulls you into a richly atmospheric, persuasively inhabited world teeming with young foundlings and pathos, and upended by one remarkable little boy. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE LAST KING OF SCOTLAND' (R, 121 minutes) Kevin Macdonald paints a queasily enjoyable portrait of the Ugandan dictator Idi Amin from inside the palace walls. Forest Whitaker plays the mad king, while James McAvoy plays the fool. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'LETTERS FROM IWO JIMA' (R, 141 minutes, in Japanese) Another masterwork from Clint Eastwood's astonishing late period, and one of the best war movies ever. Ken Watanabe is especially fine as the general commanding Japanese troops in the doomed defense of the island of Iwo Jima. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'LITTLE CHILDREN' (R, 130 minutes) Todd Field's adaptation of Tom Perrotta's novel of suburban adultery is unfailingly intelligent and faultlessly acted. Kate Winslet and Patrick Wilson are superb as the parents of young children who meet at the playground and enact a two-handed variation on ''Madame Bovary'' against a backdrop of social paranoia and middle-class malaise. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'Little Miss Sunshine' (R, 101 minutes) A bittersweet comedy of dysfunction that takes place at the terminus of the American dream. The excellent cast includes Greg Kinnear, Steve Carell, Toni Collette, Paul Dano and that national treasure, Alan Arkin. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'MAFIOSO' (No rating, 99 minutes, in Italian) This 1962 film, revived by Rialto Pictures, is a rambunctious, astonishing blend of farce, thriller and social satire. The director, Alberto Lattuada, follows an up-and-coming Fiat manager (Alberto Sordi) on a visit from Milan to his native village in Sicily. His homecoming is full of surprises -- painful for him, altogether delightful for the audience. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'NOTES ON A SCANDAL' (R, 92 minutes) Judi Dench and Cate Blanchett play a misogynistic game of cat and mouse from which no one emerges unscathed, including the audience. Adapted by Patrick Marber from a novel by Zoë Heller and directed by Richard Eyre. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'PAN'S LABYRINTH' (R, 119 minutes, in Spanish) Guillermo del Toro's tale of a young girl's ordeal in post-Civil-War fascist Spain is either a fairy tale in the guise of a political allegory or vice versa. In either case it is a moving, enchanting, strange and humane example of popular art at its very best. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE PAINTED VEIL' (PG-13, 125 minutes) Nicely directed by John Curran, this version of the W. Somerset Maugham novel draws you in by turning a distaff bildungsroman into a fine romance with Naomi Watts and Edward Norton. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'PRIMEVAL' (R, 94 minutes) A giant crocodile named Gustave terrorizes Western journalists in war-torn Burundi. Not as much fun as it might have been, but not as terrible either. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE PURSUIT OF HAPPYNESS' (PG-13, 117 minutes) How you respond to this fairy tale in realist drag may depend on whether you find Will Smith's performances so overwhelmingly winning that you buy the idea that poverty is a function of bad luck and bad choices, and success the result of heroic toil and dreams. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'THE QUEEN' (PG-13, 103 minutes) Directed by Stephen Frears from a very smart script by Peter Morgan, and starring a magnificent Helen Mirren in the title role, ''The Queen'' pries open a window in the House of Windsor around the time of the death of Diana, Princess of Wales, blending fact with fiction. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'REGULAR LOVERS' (No rating, 175 minutes, in French) Philippe Garrel's tender portrait of late-1960s French youth stars the filmmaker's son, Louis Garrel, as a 20-year-old Parisian struggling through the fires of revolutionary promise and its smoldering remains. Magnificent. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'STOMP THE YARD' (PG-13, 109 minutes) Brotherhood is powerful in this sometimes compelling, sometimes complacent movie about stepping and African-American fraternity life at an Atlanta institution called Truth University. D J (Columbus Short), a street-style dancer, needs to find his place in a university ruled by Gammas and Thetas and stepping. (Rachel Saltz)</p>
        <p>'TEARS OF THE BLACK TIGER' (No rating, 113 minutes, in Thai) A western weepie from Thailand, filmed in garish color. In spite of the relentless genre pastiche, it has a charming sincerity. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'VENUS' (R, 91 minutes) A modest, diverting, touching tale of a young woman who attracts the interest -- avuncular and also erotic -- of an aging actor, played with effortless aplomb by the great Peter O'Toole. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'VOLVER' (R, 121 minutes, in Spanish) Another keeper from Pedro Almodóvar, with Penélope Cruz -- as a resilient widow -- in her best role to date. (Scott)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>CRITICS CHOICE: GREAT DOCUMENTARIES (Sunday) A series of significant documentaries introduced by members of the New York Film Critics Circle continues with Ross McElwee's family history ''Bright Leaves'' (2003), presented by Lisa Schwarzbaum of Entertainment Weekly, and Werner Herzog's ''Grizzly Man,'' a 2005 study of a man who mistakenly (and tragically) believed that he understood bears, presented by Kyle Smith of The New York Post. (Through Feb. 25.) Museum of the Moving Image, 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718) 784-0077, movingimage.us; $10. (Dave Kehr)</p>
        <p>I AM NOT A WAR PHOTOGRAPHER: FILMS OF LYNNE SACHS (Tonight through Sunday) Three programs of nontraditional documentaries by a filmmaker who employs subjective perspectives and abstract visual effects to examine contemporary conflicts. Tonight ''Which Way Is East: Notebooks from Vietnam'' (1994) is doubled with ''Investigation of a Flame: The Catonsville Nine'' (2001). Tomorrow brings a program of four short films and ''Invisible,'' a 30-minute work-in-progress. Sunday's screening is ''States of Unbelonging,'' a new video feature about Revital Ohayon, an Israeli filmmaker killed in 2002 in a terrorist attack near the West Bank. Anthology Film Archives, 32 Second Avenue, at Second Street, East Village, (212) 505-5181, anthologyfilmarchives.org; $8. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>STORM WARNINGS: THE FILMS OF BAHMAN FARMANARA (Tonight through Thursday) This retrospective focuses on the work of one of the few Iranian directors to work before and after the revolution. His ''Prince Ehtejab'' (1974), screening tonight, tomorrow and Monday, is a Visconti-like historical epic about the end of the Qajar Dynasty, centered on the last prince of the line, who withdraws from political conflict into the private reality of his palace. An international success, it led to Mr. Farmanara's appointment as the head of the Iranian Film Development Company, but his 1979 work ''Tall Shadows in the Wind'' (tonight, Sunday and Wednesday) was banned by the shah's shaky government, and Mr. Farmanara spent the next several years in Canada, eventually returning to the new Iran, where he encountered a different form of censorship. After having 10 scripts rejected by the government censors, he was able to film in 2000 the gently satiric, self-reflective ''Smell of Camphor, Fragrance of Jasmine'' (tomorrow, Tuesday and Wednesday), a hit at the New York Film Festival that marked Mr. Farmanara's comeback. The series also includes two recent films, ''A Little Kiss'' from 2005 (tonight through Wednesday) and ''A House Built on Water'' from 2002 (Sunday, Monday and Wednesday). Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 975-5600, filmlinc.org; $10. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>THE BOOKS (Tomorrow) Nick Zammuto and Paul de Jong of the Books make beguiling electronic collages out of disembodied vocal samples, a few plucks from a banjo or another string instrument, and unclassifiable noises that fade in and out like traffic. Part of the pleasure of listening is trying to figure out just why all this chaos works so wonderfully and wittily. With Jack Rose and Essie Jain. At 6:30 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; $20. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>* DAVID BYRNE (Thursday) He may have set a still unsurpassed standard with Talking Heads for art-pop that is as arty as it is truly poppy, but Mr. Byrne's influence reaches much wider than the rock world, into theater, film and, especially, world music. (He also has the best blog of any rock star, at davidbyrne.com.) He begins his four-day Perspectives series at Carnegie Hall with music from ''The Knee Plays,'' a 1985 collaboration with the theater director Robert Wilson, which features Mr. Byrne's work as well as arrangements of gospel and Bulgarian folk songs. At 9 p.m., Zankel Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $35 to $45. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>RHYS CHATHAM (Tomorrow) A force in the fruitful meeting of drone minimalism with loud guitar-rock in the 1970s, Mr. Chatham remains a lover of big, electrified din. For his current tour he revisits a 1970s piece, ''Guitar Trio,'' with members of his band augmented by a phalanx of guitarists, including Thurston Moore, Lee Ranaldo and Kim Gordon of Sonic Youth, an important inheritor of Mr. Chatham's style. At 8 p.m., Issue Project Room, 400 Carroll Street, between Bond and Nevins Streets, Carroll Gardens, Brooklyn, (718) 330-0313, issueprojectroom.org; $25. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DEERHOOF (Tonight) More than a decade into its career, this avant-garde rock band from San Francisco still has plenty of surprises. Deerhoof's stop-start songs, with jagged guitars, a drum style somewhere between jazz and metal, and Satomi Matsuzaki's nursery rhyme vocals, sound intriguingly extraterrestrial. With Busdriver and Proton Proton. At 9, Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800, irvingplaza.com; $16. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>EARLY YEARS (Tonight and tomorrow night) Destination: trippy outer space. Vehicle: buoyant, puslating guitars of this young British band, which borrows from 1980s and '90s neo-psych visionaries like My Bloody Valentine and Spacemen 3. Tonight at 8, with Daylight's for the Birds, a New York band equally devoted to '80s British ''dream pop''; at Union Hall, 702 Union Street, at Fifth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 638-4400, unionhallny.com; $8. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Union Pool, 484 Union Avenue, at Meeker Avenue, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 609-0484; $8. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ISAAC HAYES (Tomorrow) From his days as a songwriter and producer at Stax/Volt to the orchestrated funk of his album ''Hot Buttered Soul'' to his former cartoon role (as Chef) in ''South Park,'' Isaac Hayes has adapted his deep voice and down-home charm to every era. At 7:30 and 10:30 p.m., B. B. King Blues Club &amp; Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $40 in advance, $45 at the door. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>JOHNNY SOCIETY (Tonight) Johnny Society is led by Kenny Siegal, a songwriter who scuffs up the melodicism of the Beatles and Brian Wilson in songs that know all too well about how relationships can crumble. With the London Souls, Le Firm, the Luxury Flats and the Shills. At 8, Sin-é, 150 Attorney Street, at Stanton Street, Lower East Side, (212) 388-0077, sin-e.com; $10. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>SLEEPY LABEEF(Sunday) An unregenerate rockabilly singer and guitarist from Arkansas, Sleepy LaBeef reels off one twangy tune after another, known and obscure, like a jukebox come to life. At 10 p.m., Rodeo Bar, 375 Third Avenue, at 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 683-6500, rodeobar.com; no cover. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>* LINCOLN CENTER'S AMERICAN SONGBOOK (Wednesday and Thursday) Now in its ninth season, this series has greatly expanded from its origins as a home for the midcentury pantheon of Harold Arlen, Richard Rodgers and the like. Wednesday features an acoustic show by Josh Ritter, a 30-year-old songwriter whose guileless, boy-next-door voice belies the depth and ambition of his songs, whether he is confessing a simple crush or following his thoughts on a long, Whitmanesque incantation. On Thursday Howard Fishman, who has long been rummaging through the attic of American song, pays tribute to Bob Dylan and the Band's monumental ''Basement Tapes.'' At 8:30 p.m., Allen Room, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Broadway at 60th Street, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; sold out on Wednesday, $35 to $70 on Thursday. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* MAUDE MAGGART (Tonight and tomorrow night, and Tuesday through Thursday) In her must-see cabaret show, ''Good Girl/Bad Girl,'' this 31-year-old singer, a knockout in a red dress, uses an astutely chosen selection of songs to explore conflicting female sexual stereotypes from the perspective of a young woman who understands but rejects abject surrender to a man. High point: Joan Baez's ''Love Song to a Stranger.'' At 9, with additional shows tonight and tomorrow night at 11:30, Oak Room at the Algonquin Hotel, 59 West 44th Street, Manhattan, (212) 419-9331, algonquinhotel.com; $60 cover; $25 minimum, with $65 dinner required for the early shows tonight and tomorrow. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>RITA MORENO (Tonight and tomorrow night, and Tuesday through Thursday) If you look as fresh and unbowed as Rita Moreno at 75, you may as well flaunt your age, which is what Ms. Moreno does with zest and humor in ''Little Tributes,'' her breezy new cabaret act. The show is a smooth, comfortable ride with a performer who knows who she is. At 8:45, with additional shows tonight and tomorrow at 10:45, Café Carlyle, Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212) 744-1600, thecarlyle.com; tonight and tomorrow, $70 cover at tables, $50 at the bar; Tuesday through Thursday, $65 at tables, $40 at the bar. (Holden)</p>
        <p>NORTHSIX (Tonight and Wednesday night) Another rock club bites the dust, but this time there's a twist: the gentrification is happening in Brooklyn, not Manhattan, and the gentrifier is another rock club. Northsix was a pioneer when it opened in Williamsburg six years ago, and has been an important incubator for the Brooklyn scene; it will close after this week's shows for renovations by its new owners, the proprietors of the Bowery Ballroom and the Mercury Lounge, and reopen later this year as the Music Hall of Williamsburg. Tonight features a solo set by Ted Leo, a veteran pop-punk bandleader who is one of the best songwriters in the game, and on Wednesday is Radio 4, which emulates the frantic punk-funk of early-'80s British bands like Gang of Four and Public Image Limited. At 9, 66 North Sixth Street, (718) 599-5103, northsix.com; $15; $13 in advance for Wednesday's show. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PAOLO NUTINI (Wednesday) A Scottish heartthrob who just turned 20, Mr. Nutini has already conquered the British charts with snappy, vaguely racy tunes like ''Jenny Don't Be Hasty,'' about an affair with an, ahem, older woman. (She's 23, he's 18.) He begins a coordinated American invasion next week, with the release of his debut album, ''These Streets'' (Atlantic), and appearances on ''Late Night With Conan O'Brien'' and the ''Today'' show. With Musiq Soulchild. At 7 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>O'DEATH, T K WEBB (Wednesday and Thursday) O'Death draws from the starkness and spiritual purity of Appalachian folk, the menace of punk and the rowdy theatricality of Tom Waits, jumbling sacred and profane. A Brooklynite by way of rural Missouri, the singer and guitarist T K Webb plays ragged, stark Delta blues about desolation and dying young, surrounding his creaky tenor with a halo of eerie reverb. Wednesday At 7 p.m., Europa, 98 Meserole Avenue, at Manhattan Avenue, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 383-5723, europaclub.com; $8. Mr. Webb also plays on Thursday at 8 p.m., with Shortstack and These United States, at Cake Shop, 152 Ludlow Street, between Stanton and Rivington Streets, Lower East Side, (212) 253-0036, cake-shop.com; $6. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ANDERS PARKER (Wednesday) Mr. Parker, who led the band Varnaline, immerses his songs in the stoic drama of country and folk music, resulting in a melancholy that is sometimes indistinguishable from cynicism. (''The hours I've wasted here I could have wasted anywhere.'') At 9 p.m., Living Room, 154 Ludlow Street, near Stanton Street, Lower East Side, (212) 533-7235, livingroomny.com; $8. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PETER, BJORN AND JOHN (Monday and Tuesday) The latest sharp and impeccably stylish import from Sweden, this trio sets breathy, heavy-hearted vocals over spare but peppery band arrangements that recall 1960s folk-pop. Best of all: lots of great whistling. With Born Ruffians and the White Rabbits. Monday at 8 p.m., Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700, mercuryloungenyc.com; Tuesday at 7:30 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; both shows sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>TOSHI REAGON (Tonight through Sunday) Singing about both love and politics with the same sense of independence, Ms. Reagon applies her gutsy voice and syncopated guitar playing to songs steeped in blues and funk. Tonight and tomorrow she celebrates the 10th anniversary of her band, Big Lovely. Sunday's show is devoted to sacred music, which Ms. Reagon will sing with her mother, Bernice Johnson Reagon, the scholar and founder of the long-running a cappella group Sweet Honey in the Rock. Tonight and tomorrow night at 9, Sunday at night at 7, Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* JONATHAN RICHMAN (Thursday) No rock star delivers intimacy like Mr. Richman, the eternally youthful and eternally nebbishy granddaddy of New Wave and indie rock. He fell in love with the acoustic guitar decades ago, and backed up by the tiniest of bands -- a drummer playing a snare and little more -- sings of simple pleasures lost and found with tiptoe dynamics. He begins a four-night stand, kicking off the Knitting Factory's 20th-anniversary celebration. At 8 p.m., 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3006, knittingfactory.com; $20 in advance, $23 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>SUNBURNED HAND OF THE MAN (Sunday and Monday) Improvisation means lots of things in rock, but to this Massachusetts collective, which has been churning out dozens of albums and homemade recordings since the mid-'90s, it means spacey, meandering drones that seem like endless psychedelic trips. On Sunday the band accompanies films by Ira Cohen, including the 1968 avant-garde classic ''The Invasion of Thunderbolt Pagoda,'' and on Monday it plays a club date with the bands Bunnybrains and Heavy Hands. Sunday at 3 p.m., Issue Project Room, 400 Carroll Street, between Bond and Nevins Streets, Carroll Gardens, Brooklyn, (718) 330-0313, issueprojectroom.org; $15. Monday at 9 p.m., Club Midway, 25 Avenue B, at Second Street, East Village, (212) 253-2595, clubmidway.com; $8 in advance, $10 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* M. WARD (Tonight) Ubiquitous as a sideman for indie-rock royalty -- Cat Power, Bright Eyes, Beth Orton, Jenny Lewis -- M. Ward stepped into the fore last year with an extraordinary solo album, ''Post-War'' (Merge). Over scratchy, portentous acoustic blues, he sings of malaise and loss in a dry, spectral voice: ''He was a good man but now he's gone,'' goes a deadpan requiem for a soldier. With Portastatic. At 8, Town Hall, 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 840-2824, the-townhall-nyc.org; $25. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* PAUL WELLER (Monday through Wednesday) In a three-part musical autobiography, Mr. Weller, a hallowed rock star in his native Britain who has remained a cult figure in America for 30 years, reviews the neatly defined phases of his career. On Monday he revisits his early years with the Jam, whose version of punk was shaded with soul music and the mod style of the early Who; next is the Style Council, Mr. Weller's R&amp;B-and-synthesizers 1980s band; and on Wednesday he looks over his whole output, including the comfy, sometimes indulgent soul-rock of his recent solo albums. At 8 p.m., Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800, irvingplaza.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ZEMOG EL GALLO BUENO (Tomorrow) Fierce salsa grooves lead into daring free-jazz improvisations in Zemog el Gallo Bueno, a Boston band that's equally fond of Tito Puente and Sun Ra. With Mofongo and DJ Philharmonic. At 8 p.m., Makor, 35 West 67th Street, Manhattan, (212) 601-1000, makor.org; $12. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>RALPH ALESSI QUINTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) As a trumpeter, Ralph Alessi combines pristine technique with an exploratory yen. His quintet includes resourceful collaborators like the tenor saxophonist Tony Malaby, the pianist Andy Milne, the bassist Drew Gress and the drummer Mark Ferber. At 9 and 10:30, Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $15. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>ROY AYERS (Tonight through Sunday night) Mr. Ayers, a vibraphonist associated with the heyday of jazz-funk, pays tribute to the exuberant forefather of his instrument, Lionel Hampton, with a band that includes two singers, John Pressley and Richard Shade. At 7:30 and 9:30, with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow night, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BALLIN' THE JACK (Thursday) This ensemble, led by the clarinetist and saxophonist Matt Darriau, customarily spikes a swing-era repertory with madcap irreverence. That's especially true of this engagement, featuring music from Marx Brothers film soundtracks, complete with Grouchoesque vocals from the alto saxophonist Roy Nathanson. At 8 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* BEBOP LIVES! (Tonight and tomorrow night) The spirit of Charlie Parker animates a concert by two esteemed saxophonists who have fully absorbed his language -- James Moody and Charles McPherson -- along with a trumpeter, Roy Hargrove, and a singer, Roberta Gambarini. At 8, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 721-6500, jalc.org; $37.50 to $127.50. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LOU DONALDSON QUARTET (Wednesday and Thursday) Bebop, blues and boogaloo are all fair game for the veteran alto saxophonist Lou Donaldson, whose rock-solid rhythm section comprises Dr. Lonnie Smith on organ, Randy Johnston on guitar and Fukushi Tainaka on drums. (Through Feb. 3.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Manhattan, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BILL EVANS'S SOULGRASS (Tonight through Sunday night) Virtuosity, the chief ingredient shared by bluegrass and fusion, will be in copious supply during this summit organized by the saxophonist Bill Evans, with Tony Trischka on banjo, Sam Bush on mandolin, Christian Howes on violin, Richard Bona on bass and Dave Weckl on drums. At 8 and 10:30, Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $35 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ANAT FORT (Tomorrow and Sunday) The prepossessing pianist Anat Fort previews music from an album on the ECM label, with her regular rhythm team of the bassist Gary Wang and the drummer Roland Schneider, plus Perry Robinson on clarinet and saxophone. Tomorrow at 9 and 10:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. Sunday at 7 p.m., St. Peter's Church, 619 Lexington Avenue, at 54th Street, (212) 935-2200, saintpeters.org; $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JIMMY GREENE QUINTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) Jimmy Greene brings an athletic endurance to his saxophone style and leads a top-shelf band with Xavier Davis on piano, Reuben Rogers on bass and Eric Harland on drums. At 8, 10 and 11:30, Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, (212) 864-6662, smokejazz.com; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DONALD HARRISON QUARTET/MULGREW MILLER TRIO (Tuesday through Thursday) Two satisfying bands, each with an assertive and soulful guide: Donald Harrison, an alto saxophonist equally steeped in bebop and New Orleans groove, and Mulgrew Miller, a modern pianist with roots in Mississippi blues. (Through Feb. 4.) At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $25 at tables, $15 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* JOHN HOLLENBECK (Thursday) Mr. Hollenbeck, a percussionist and composer, wrote ''The Drum Major'' years ago as a corollary to a sermon by the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. It's a moving tone poem for drums and three trombones -- in this iteration, Curtis Hasselbring, Jacob Garchik and Brian Drye -- designed to accompany a recording of the sermon in total darkness. For this performance Mr. Hollenbeck will also unveil what he calls a companion piece for piano, accordion and guitar. At 7:30 p.m., Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, symphonyspace.org; $21 in advance; $25 on Thursday; $17 for members; $10 rush tickets. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>FRANK KIMBROUGH TRIO (Tonight and tomorrow night) Drawing from a fine recent album, ''Play'' (Palmetto), the pianist Frank Kimbrough leads an appealingly elastic trio with the bassist Jay Anderson and the drummer Matt Wilson. At 8 and 9:45, Kitano Hotel, 66 Park Avenue, at 38th Street, (212) 885-7119, kitano.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE LEHMAN QUINTET/TYSHAWN SOREY'S OBLIQUE (Wednesday) Steve Lehman, an intense saxophonist, features his own sharp-cornered compositions in a group with Jonathan Finlayson on trumpet, Bryan Carrott on vibraphone, Drew Gress on bass and Tyshawn Sorey on drums. In an earlier set Mr. Sorey leads his own group, which features Loren Stillman on saxophones and Ben Gerstein on trombone. At 8 and 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* PAUL MOTIAN TRIO 2000 +1 (Tuesday through Thursday) Show tunes and standards receive loving interpretations on ''Paul Motian on Broadway Vol. 4'' (Winter &amp; Winter), one of last year's standout jazz releases. Mr. Motian's teasingly suggestive drumming is well matched with the abstruse pianism of Masabumi Kikuchi; Rebecca Martin handles vocals with a casual purity; and the bassist Larry Grenadier adds some welcome heft. (Through Feb. 4.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GREG OSBY AND THE ORGANIZATION (Tonight through Sunday night) The alto saxophonist Greg Osby has a brittle and dartlike style, well suited to exploratory post-bop or slippery free-funk. His constituents here are Trudy Pitts on organ and keyboards, Paul Bollenback on guitar and Gene Jackson on drums. At 7:30 and 9:30, with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow night, Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $25; $20 on Sunday. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BEN RILEY'S MONK LEGACY SEPTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ben Riley, one of the most buoyant drummers ever to serve in Thelonious Monk's employ, honors that pianist and composer's memory with this rock-solid septet, stocked with players like the trumpeter Don Sickler and the saxophonists Wayne Escoffery and Bruce Williams. At 9 and 11, Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JENNY SCHEINMAN (Tuesday) Ms. Scheinman is that rare jazz violinist who embraces her instrument's folksier side without making concessions to genre. Her Tuesday night engagement features different players each week; this time around, the cast includes the guitarist Steve Cardenas and the drummer Scott Amendola. At 7 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ELLIOTT SHARP PLAYS MONK (Thursday) On his most recent album -- ''Sharp? Monk? Sharp! Monk!'' (Clean Feed) -- Mr. Sharp transports Thelonious Monk's pianistic topography to the strings and fretboard of his acoustic guitar. At 8:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* SONGS MADE TO BE PLAYED: PIANISTS AND THEIR PIECES (Tomorrow) Dick Hyman presents a handsome tribute to an honor roll of pianist-composers, including Erroll Garner, Eddie Heywood, Fats Waller and Bill Evans. The evening's pianistic interpreters, in addition to Mr. Hyman, are Barry Harris, Ted Rosenthal, Judy Carmichael, Derek Smith and Jon Weber; its bassist is Nicki Parrott, and its drummer is Willie Jones III. At 8 p.m., 92nd Street Y, 1395 Lexington Avenue, (212) 415-5500, 92y.org; $45. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TIN HAT (Tonight) Celebrating the recent release of an album called ''The Sad Machinery of Spring'' (Hannibal/Rykodisc), this professionally eclectic improvising chamber group explores its broad tonal palette onstage; in addition to Carla Kihlstedt, a violinist and founding member, the group will include Ben Goldberg on clarinets and Zeena Parkins on harp. At 7:30 and 9:30, Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, symphonyspace.org; $25; $17 for members; $10 rush tickets. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* CHARLES TOLLIVER BIG BAND (Tuesday through Thursday) The trumpeter Charles Tolliver recently ended a long, dry spell of public appearances with this band, an upgraded edition of his hard-driving orchestra of the '70s. This engagement celebrates the release of a strong album, ''With Love'' (Blue Note), that seals Mr. Tolliver's comeback with a kiss. (Through Feb. 3.) At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JAMES (BLOOD) ULMER (Tonight through Sunday night) Mr. Ulmer's singing and guitar playing describe an oddly hypnotic combination of influences: Ornette Coleman's polytonality crossed with the psychedelic swagger of Jimi Hendrix. He performs here with a group that includes the keyboardist Amina Claudine Myers and the drummer Aubrey Dale. At 8:30 and 10:30, with a midnight set tonight and tomorrow night, Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>WARREN VACHÉ (Tonight) Mr. Vaché is a trumpeter and cornetist well versed in the deep traditions of his instrument; he's at his best in sparse settings like this one, with Nicki Parrott on bass and Vincent Corrao on guitar. At 7, Rubin Museum of Art, 150 West 17th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 620-5000, Ext. 344, www.rmanyc.org; $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* RANDY WESTON (Tonight) Now in his 80s, Mr. Weston has a warm and rippling touch at the piano, and a style that reflects a grasp of pan-African folk traditions, including the blues. He performs a solo recital at Fazioli Salon, a series at the Klavierhaus piano workshop. At 8 p.m., Klavierhaus, 211 West 58th Street, Manhattan, (212) 245-4535, pianoculture.com; $30. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* CASSANDRA WILSON (Tomorrow) Before she was a honey-toned earth mother, Ms. Wilson jostled around the funkier regions of the contemporary jazz avant-garde. She allows an echo of that experience here, with cohorts including the alto saxophonist Steve Coleman, the drummer Dafnis Prieto and the pianist Jason Moran. At 8 and 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>'CAVALLERIA RUSTICANA' AND 'PAGLIACCI' (Tonight and Tuesday) Those deathless twin barnburners return to the Metropolitan Opera tonight. In ''Cavalleria,'' Dolora Zajick will strike the match. Look for Salvatore Licitra's Canio in ''Pagliacci.'' Tonight at 8, Tuesday night at 7:30, Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $110 to $205 tickets remaining tonight, $15 to $175 on Tuesday. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>'JENUFA' (Monday) Grand operas make their living off unhappy love, but few are as sincerely heart-wrenching as this Janacek masterpiece. Karita Mattila returns in the title role. At 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $15 to $175. (Holland)</p>
        <p>* 'IL SIGNOR BRUSCHINO' (Sunday, Tuesday and Thursday) Mention Rossini, and most people come up with ''The Barber of Seville,'' but this work -- in which the composer honed the comic gift that came to the fore in ''Barber'' and other opera buffe -- hasn't been staged in New York since 1933. The Gotham Chamber Opera has set itself apart among the city's small opera companies with quality performances of lesser-known operas (with good singers), conducted by the company's founder, Neal Goren. Robin Guarino directs the company's performance of this frothy piece of fun. Sunday at 2 p.m., Tuesday and Thursday at 8 p.m., Abrons Arts Center, 466 Grand Street, at Pitt Street, Lower East Side, (212) 279-4200, gothamchamberopera.org; $30 to $65. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>* 'LA TRAVIATA' (Tomorrow and Thursday) The soprano Hei-Kyung Hong gives a beautifully sung and deeply felt portrayal of Violetta in the Met revival of Verdi's ''Traviata,'' in Franco Zeffirelli's extravagant 1998 production. The other news is the promising performance of an artist who, like Ms. Hong, is from South Korea: the tenor Wookyung Kim, singing Alfredo in his Met debut season. As a Verdi tenor, Mr. Kim is a little green, but he has an appealing and robust voice, and at his best, sings with ardor and flair. The baritone Charles Taylor, who was ill on opening night, sings Germont. Carlo Rizzi conducts. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; sold out tomorrow, $15 to $175 on Thursday. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>BARGEMUSIC (Tonight through Sunday) Tonight the likable critic and musicologist Maya Pritsker is host of a piano recital by Alexander Korsantia, who will play Haydn, Stravinsky and Mussorgsky at Bargemusic, Brooklyn's floating concert hall. Tomorrow and Sunday the Amernet Quartet offers Mozart, Grieg and the first New York performances of a Quintet for Bassoon and String Quartet by another critic, Russell Platt, whose day job is at The New Yorker. Tonight and tomorrow night at 7:30, Sunday at 4 p.m., Fulton Ferry Landing, Brooklyn, (718) 624-4061, bargemusic.org. Tonight and tomorrow, $35; $30 for 65+; $20 for students. Sunday, $40; $25 for students. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>DA CAPO CHAMBER PLAYERS (Sunday) This superb new-music ensemble looks at the Second Viennese School and its more modern adherents in a program that includes Schoenberg's Chamber Symphony, Eisler's Duo for Violin and Cello, Berg's Four Pieces, George Perle's ''Night Song,'' Milton Babbitt's ''None but the Lonely Flute'' and a new work by Kati Agocs. At 8 p.m., Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, Manhattan, (212) 501-3330, dacapochamberplayers.org; $20; $10 for students and 65+. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* 'DECASIA' (Tonight and tomorrow night) The composer Michael Gordon and the filmmaker Bill Morrison have collaborated on this enveloping multimedia work. Mr. Morrison's contribution is a fast-cut montage of antique films, in which bubbles and other signs of decay create patterns as crucial to the work as the images of cowboys, flappers, factory workers, dancers, parachutists and the exotic Middle East and North Africa. Mr. Gordon's powerful 65-minute score -- played by an orchestra deployed in the balconies -- evolves from a faint, metallic rattle to a barrage of percussion, electric guitars, brass choirs, woodwinds and strings. At 7 and 9:30, Orensanz Center for the Arts, 172 Norfolk Street, Lower East Side, (212) 352-3101; $25. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>DAVID FINCKEL AND WU HAN (Tuesday) This cello-piano, husband-wife duo are customarily to be found on the Upper West Side running the Chamber Music Society of Lincoln Center, but on Tuesday they cross town for a recital at the Morgan Library &amp; Museum's spiffy new recital hall. The program includes Schubert's heavenly ''Arpeggione'' Sonata. At 7:30 p.m., 225 Madison Avenue, at 36th Street, (212) 685-0008, themorgan.org; $45. (Holland)</p>
        <p>* FOCUS FESTIVAL (Tonight, and Monday through Thursday) The Juilliard School's annual new-music festival turns its sights this year on Hungarian music since Bartok. A few of the composers -- Gyorgy Kurtag, Gyorgy Ligeti, Peter Eotvos and Istvan Marta, for example -- are already forceful presences in the world of chamber music. But the festival's longtime director, Joel Cohen, invariably turns up a number of worthy newcomers. At 8, Peter Jay Sharp Theater, 155 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 769-7406, juilliard.edu; free, but tickets are required for tonight's concert. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>SUSAN GRAHAM (Monday) An eloquent interpreter of a large repertory, from German Classicism to contemporary American music, this American mezzo-soprano is devoting her recital at Carnegie Hall to French art song, with works by Bizet, Franck, Fauré, Lalo, Gounod, Debussy, Chausson, Duparc, Ravel, Messiaen, Honegger, Poulenc and others. At 8 p.m., (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $25 to $80. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>HAMBURG SYMPHONY ORCHESTRA (Tonight and tomorrow night) The Hamburg Symphony, founded in 1957, is not to be confused with the Hamburg Philharmonic or the Norddeutscher Rundfunk Symphony Orchestra, based in the same city, which will come to Carnegie Hall in March. This one, led by Andrey Boreyko, is embarking on its first United States tour and will make its New York debut tonight in a program of Mendelssohn's ''Hebrides'' Overture, Brahms's Second Symphony and Tchaikovsky's Violin Concerto, with the soloist Robert McDuffie. Tomorrow the Brahms and Tchaikovsky are on the program at the Tilles Center. Tonight at 8, Metropolitan Museum of Art, (212) 570-3949, metmuseum.org; $40. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Tilles Center for the Performing Arts, at the C. W. Post campus of Long Island University, Brookville, N.Y., (516) 299-3100, tillescenter.org; $48 to $90. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>ISRAEL PHILHARMONIC (Tuesday and Thursday) This orchestra, founded in 1936 and originally named the Palestine Orchestra, begins its 70th-anniversary celebrations with a United States tour. On Tuesday Lorin Maazel, who was named an honorary life member of the orchestra in 1985, will conduct the program, which features Beethoven's Violin Concerto with the stellar violinist Maxim Vengerov as soloist, Beethoven's ''Leonore'' Overture No. 3 and Mussorgsky's ''Pictures at an Exhibition.'' On Thursday Zubin Mehta, the Philharmonic's music director, leads a program including Berlioz's ''Symphonie Fantastique'' and Mahler's Rückert Lieder with Thomas Hampson, a baritone. Tuesday at 8 p.m., Thursday at 7 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $45 to $125. (Vivien Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* MOSCOW SOLOISTS (Sunday) The violist and conductor Yuri Bashmet will lead his Moscow Soloists in orchestral arrangements of chamber works. Mahler arranged Schubert's ''Death and the Maiden'' Quartet and Beethoven's String Quartet in F minor (Op. 95), the so-called ''Quartetto Serioso,'' to attract a larger audience for these pieces, then considered esoteric. The program also includes Britten's ''Lachrymae,'' based on a song by John Dowland (which Britten initially wrote for piano and viola and later arranged for orchestra), and Schnittke's ''Monologue.'' At 2 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $23 to $75. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* 'MOZART AT 251' (Tomorrow) For years, Uri Caine, a jazz player and musical polyglot, has intelligently deconstructed music by classical composers with a blend that might include jazz, bossa nova, klezmer and tango. Having already reimagined Bach's ''Goldberg'' Variations and Beethoven's ''Diabelli'' Variations, he now turns to Mozart. The program opens with a ''pure'' reading of Mozart's Divertimento in E flat (K. 563), by the cellist Matt Haimovitz, the violinist Jonathan Crow and the violist Douglas McNabney. Then Mr. Haimovitz will join Mr. Caine, the clarinetist Chris Speed, the bassist Drew Gress and others for a renegade Mozartian jam session. At 8 p.m., Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, Manhattan, (212) 501-3330, ekcc.org; $30 in advance, $35 at the door. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC (Tonight and tomorrow night) The Italian maestro Riccardo Muti has also fared well with the New York Philharmonic. His first of two programs last week was predictably distinguished. This weekend he conducts an unusual all-Italian program, beginning with the Piano Concerto No. 2 by Giuseppe Martucci (1856-1909), a conductor, pianist and composer much admired in his day. This 1886 concerto was taken up by noted conductors, including Mahler and Toscanini. Gerhard Oppitz will be the soloist. Mr. Muti will also conduct ''Feste Romane'' by Ottorino Respighi, who was a composition student of Martucci's, and the ballet music from Verdi's ''Macbeth.'' On Thursday Esa-Pekka Salonen arrives in his dual roles as conductor and composer. His program includes the premiere of his Piano Concerto, a Philharmonic commission, with Yefim Bronfman as soloist. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Thursday at 7:30 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nyphil.org; $28 to $96. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>OBERLIN CONSERVATORY SYMPHONY ORCHESTRA (Tonight) Robert Spano, the energetic music director of the Atlanta Symphony Orchestra, leads the Oberlin Conservatory Symphony Orchestra in a concert that includes Jennifer Higdon's ''Blue Cathedral.'' Mr. Spano has championed this appealing work, which is performed more regularly than most new pieces, and recorded it in 2004 with the Atlanta Symphony. The program also includes Bartok's Concerto for Orchestra and Mozart's Piano Concerto No. 25 in C (K. 503), with the pianist Pedja Muzijevic. At 8, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $20; $5 for students. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>GARRICK OHLSSON (Sunday) This past summer the American pianist Garrick Ohlsson, an exciting virtuoso as well as an artist of integrity, presented acclaimed cycles of the complete 32 Beethoven piano sonatas at the Ravinia and Tanglewood festivals. Beginning Sunday, he performs the first of three Beethoven sonata programs at Lincoln Center. The opener offers two well-known sonatas, the ''Pathétique'' and the ''Appassionata,'' along with two inventive, bracing early sonatas, No. 6 in F and No. 11 in B flat. The latter is a score the composer was especially pleased with. At 2 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $50. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>ST. LAWRENCE STRING QUARTET (Monday) This energetic Canadian quartet helped open the Baryshnikov Arts Center last season and returns to that loftlike space to play works including Schumann's Quartet Op. 41, No. 2, and Shostakovich's searing Quartet No. 8. At 7 p.m., 450 West 37th Street, Manhattan, (212) 218-7540, baryshnikovdancefoundation.org; free, but reservations are required. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* JOHN SCOTT (Sunday) Having just started a cycle of the complete organ works of Buxtehude, Mr. Scott, the organist and director of music at St. Thomas Church, focuses on Ligeti for a day. He opens the Miller Theater's two-part ''Remembering Ligeti'' mini-festival with a concert offering the rare and exciting chance to hear his complete organ works. Alongside Ligeti's ''Ricercare: Omaggio a Frescobaldi'' (1953), Two Études (1967-69) and ''Volumina'' (1962-66), Mr. Scott will perform Jonathan Harvey's ''Fantasia'' (1991), Toccata for organ and tape (1980) and ''Laus Deo'' (1969). At 5:15 p.m., Fifth Avenue at 53rd Street, (212) 854-7799, millertheater.com; free. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* 'THE SONG CONTINUES' (Tonight) The Marilyn Horne Foundation winds up its annual mini-festival dedicated to the art of song with a gala concert called ''Gypsy in My Soul,'' featuring Ms. Horne as its host and a quartet of singers and a guest artist who's more Sicilian than Gypsy, the tenor Marcello Giordani, as performers. The wide-ranging program includes the world premieres of two pieces the foundation commissioned from Gabriela Lena Frank, as well as songs by Brahms, Vaughn Williams, Dvorak and Turina. At 7:30, Zankel Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $37 and $45. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>VOX VOCAL ENSEMBLE (Tomorrow) George Steel has been exploring Tudor church music for the last several years, both in his programming for the Miller Theater and on the podium of the Vox Vocal Ensemble, his virtuoso choir. In the latest installment of that exploration, sponsored by Miller but performed in the acoustically more amenable Church of St. Mary the Virgin, Mr. Steel leads his Vox group in settings of parts of the Lamentations of Jeremiah by Byrd, Tallis, White, Mundy and Parsley. At 8 p.m., 145 West 46th Street, Manhattan, (212) 854-7799, millertheater.com; $35; $21 for students. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>AFRO-BRAZILIAN MUSIC &amp; DANCE (Tonight) The New York-based Ologunde company celebrates the Afro-Brazilian culture of Salvador, Bahia, in a program that includes the candomble, capoeira, maculele and samba da roda. At 8, Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 545-7536 or 212 864-5400, worldmusicinstitute.org; $27; $15 for students. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>* ASPEN SANTA FE BALLET (Tonight through Sunday) The troupe will perform Twyla Tharp's rarely seen ''Sweet Fields'' and new works by Jorma Elo and Nicolo Fonte. Tonight at 8; tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m.; Sunday at 2 p.m. Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800 or Joyce.org; $42. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* JANIS BRENNER &amp; GUESTS (Thursday) Janis Brenner will celebrate a quarter-century in dance with her own choreography and an excerpt from ''Porcelain Dialogues'' by Murray Louis, which will be performed by Nikolais-Louis company alumni, including Ms. Brenner, Robert Small and Sara Pearson. (Through Feb. 4.) At 8:30 p.m., Danspace Project at St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194 or danspaceproject.org; $20 or T.D.F. vouchers (Dunning)</p>
        <p>ANDREA DEL CONTE DANZA ESPANA (Tonight through Sunday night) This program of flamenco dance will feature the dancer Marco De Ana and the fusion band Gazpacho Andalú. At 8, Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, between Houston and Prince Streets, (212) 334-7479, joyce.org; $28; $25 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* EVIDENCE: A DANCE COMPANY (Tuesday through Thursday) Ronald K. Brown and his Evidence troupe will present two programs. The first includes his new ''Truth Don Die,'' which tells the story of a Nigerian preacher whose holy words do not die with him and is set to music by Omotayo Wunmi Olaiya, Me Shell Ndegeocello and Femi Kuti. It also includes ''Order My Steps'' and Mr. Brown's signature ''Grace.'' The second program includes ''Ebony Magazine,'' ''Better Days'' and ''Upside Down.'' (Through Feb. 4.) Tuesday and Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. (first program), Thursday at 8 p.m. (second program), Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800, joyce.org; $38. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* MARTHA GRAHAM DANCE COMPANY (Tomorrow) A new generation of dancers, but what they perform is the mother-lode of American modern dance, still cutting through to the human heart with remarkable immediacy. At 8 p.m., Performing Arts Center, Purchase College, 735 Anderson Hill Road, Purchase, N.Y., (914) 251-6200; $45 to $65. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* TRAJAL HARRELL (Tonight through Sunday) Mr. Harrell has become known for authoritatively oddball choreography and visual design. His latest work is ''Showpony,'' in which he examines vogueing, postmodernism and the fashion spectacle and muses on his own choice to be part of a performing culture. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8:30, Sunday at 7:30 p.m. (followed by a discussion with the artists). Danspace Project at St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194, danspaceproject.org; $15 or T.D.F. voucher. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>'MODERN MOVEMENT: A WINTER DANCE SAMPLER' (Tomorrow) The participants in this nicely varied program include the Rebecca Stenn/Perks Dance Theater, Carolyn Dorfman Dance Company, Nicolas Andre Dance Theater and Julian Barrett. At 8 p.m., JCC in Manhattan, 334 Amsterdam Avenue, at 76th Street, (646) 505-5708; $20. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* MARK MORRIS DANCE GROUP (Tonight and tomorrow night) Welcome 2007 a little late with a celebratory program of dances by Mark Morris that includes ''Italian Concerto,'' set to Bach, and ''The Argument,'' ''Sang-Froid'' and ''Love Song Waltzes.'' At 7:30, Mark Morris Dance Center, 3 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place (across the street from the Brooklyn Academy of Music), Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (212) 352-3101, mmdg.org; sold out. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE OF WEST AFRICA (Tomorrow) The program features the polyphonic drumming and dancing of the Wolof people of Senegal, performed by the Sing Sing Rhythms and the Fula Flute Ensemble. At 8 p.m., Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, worldmusicinstitute.org; $27; $15 for students. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* NEW YORK CITY BALLET (Tonight through Sunday, and Tuesday through Thursday) The company is getting the jump on a spring-season celebration of Lincoln Kirstein with ''Tribute to Kirstein'' tomorrow and Wednesday nights. It was Kirstein who made City Ballet happen by coaxing George Balanchine to the United States. The program includes ''Episodes,'' ''Vienna Waltzes'' and a piece by Christopher d'Amboise. Other programs for the week include ''Tradition and Innovation'' (''Mozartiana,'' ''In Vento'' and Tchaikovsky's Piano Concerto No. 2) tonight; ''Stravinsky and Balanchine: an Eternal Partnership'' (''Agon,'' ''Monumentum pro Gesualdo,'' ''Movements for Piano and Orchestra,'' ''Duo Concertant'' and ''Symphony in Three Movements'') on Sunday; and ''Essential Balanchine'' (''Square Dance,'' ''Liebeslieder Walzer'' and ''Stars and Stripes'') on Tuesday and Thursday. Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 3 p.m., Tuesday and Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m. New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 870-5570, nycballet.com; $30 to $82. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>LAURA PETERSON CHOREOGRAPHY (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ms. Peterson, who has danced with everyone from Risa Jaroslow to Poppo and the GoGo Boys, describes her new ''I Love Dan Flavin'' as a tongue-in-cheek futuristic dance with fluorescent light and pioneering techno music. At 8, Dixon Place, 258 Bowery, between Houston and Prince Streets, Lower East Side, (212) 219-0736, Ext. 11, dixonplace.org; $15 or T.D.F. vouchers; $12 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>PHILADANCO (Sunday) This veteran modern-dance company is known for its high-powered performing and choice repertory of work by black choreographers. At 3 p.m., Lehman Center for the Performing Arts, Lehman College, 250 Bedford Park Boulevard West, at Goulden Avenue, Bedford Park, the Bronx, (718) 960-8833, lehmancenter.org; $20 to $35. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>RAGAMALA MUSIC AND DANCE THEATER (Tomorrow) The company will perform ''From Temple to Theater,'' which includes both traditional Bharata Natyam dances and contemporary choreography. At 7:30 p.m., Colden Auditorium, Kupferberg Center for the Arts, Queens College, Kissena Boulevard and the Long Island Expressway, Flushing, (718) 793-8080, kuperferbergcenter.org; $12. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* TAMAR ROGOFF'S 'EDITH &amp; JENNY' (Tonight through Sunday) Ms. Rogoff's piece alludes to the childhood friendship of her daughter, Ariel Rogoff Flavin, and Claire Danes, who trained in dance before becoming a film actress, as well as roles each played as 11-year-olds in films by Jeff Mueller. (Through Feb. 4.) Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 5 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 5 p.m., Performance Space 122, 150 First Avenue, at Ninth Street, East Village, (212) 477-5288, ps122.org; $20; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* STATE BALLET THEATER OF RUSSIA (Tonight) The great Russian ballet dancer Vladimir Vasiliev has choreographed a new production of ''Cinderella,'' set to the familiar Prokofiev score. At 7:30, New Jersey Performing Arts Center, 1 Center Street, Newark, N.J., (888) 466-5722, njpac.org; $20 to $58. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>TAKE DANCE COMPANY (Thursday) Takehiro Ueyama, a former Paul Taylor dancer, is becoming known for gutsy, well-plotted dances, here set to music by composers and groups that include Bach, Arvo Pärt and the Southern All Stars. (Through Feb. 4.) At 8 p.m., Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, between Houston and Prince Streets, (212) 334-7479, joyce.org; $20; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>'TWO: DUETS' (Tonight and tomorrow night) Chosen by Nicki Marshall and Helen Styring Tocci, five pairs of dance artists explore the intimacy and colliding energies of the duet form. At 8, WOW Cafe Theater, 59 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 777-4280; $15; $12 for students and artists. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>ANTONIETTA VICARIO MAKES DANCES (Tonight through Sunday) Ms. Vicario, who has worked with choreographers including John Jasperse and Yvonne Meier, will present a new full-evening piece called ''I cannot escape being me so that is what I will show you,'' which explores conventional notions of sexuality. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 3 p.m., Dance New Amsterdam, 280 Broadway, at Chambers Street, TriBeCa, (212) 279-4200, ticketcentral.com; $17. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Art Fairs</p>
        <p>53RD ANNUAL WINTER ANTIQUES SHOW, through Sunday. Mature is the word in the trade for fairs like the Winter Antiques Show, though time-honored, even venerable, would be closer to the mark. The show has been around forever (well, since 1955). It delivers substantial, sometimes spectacular, retail. Dealers and clients alike return, like swallows to Capistrano, year after year. So if solid tradition, rather than Basel-Miami-style blowouts, is what you want in a fair, this one's for you. Seventh Regiment Armory, 643 Park Avenue, at 67th Street, (718) 292-7392. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* American Museum of Natural History: 'GOLD,' through Aug. 19. This astounding array of art, artifacts and natural samples -- larded with fascinating facts and tales -- ranges from prehistoric times to the present. Stops along the way include pre-Columbian empires, sunken treasure and the moon landing. It turns out that gold comes from the earth in forms as beautiful as anything man has thought to do with it. Central Park West and 79th Street, (212) 769-5100, amnh.org. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>* GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'Spanish Painting from El Greco to Picasso, TIME, TRUTH, AND HISTORY' through March 28. This show is carried along on its sheer star power and optical finesse. There are dozens of Goyas and Velázquezes and Zurbaráns and El Grecos and Riberas and Dalís and Picassos, many famous, many not. I can't tell you how often I was stopped by a picture so good or unexpected that it made me do a double take. Velázquez's painting of a dwarf is alone worth crossing a continent to see. 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3500, guggenheim.org. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL CENTER OF PHOTOGRAPHY: 'HENRI CARTIER-BRESSON'S SCRAPBOOK: PHOTOGRAPHS, 1932-46,' through April 29. This show has more than 300 of the prints Henri Cartier-Bresson glued into an album and toted to New York for curators at the Museum of Modern Art to cull. Captured by the Nazis, he had been presumed dead when the Modern planned his retrospective. Then he turned up alive -- the ''posthumous'' exhibition opened, with him in attendance, in 1947. The current exhibition reconstructs as best as possible the original layout of the scrapbook. It's an eye-straining affair, but it surveys the revolutionary work he shot in Spain, Italy, Mexico, Britain and France. Here are the familiar, and, more interestingly, some less familiar, shots of crowds in Hyde Park in London at George VI's coronation, of picnickers on the banks of the Marne in France and whores in Valencia, Spain. His taste for uncanny detail linked him to Surrealism and Surrealist wit, but unlike many Surrealists, he remained committed to human values. Boys mug at his camera. Prostitutes swan. Their gazes equalize them with us. 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000, icp.org. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL CENTER OF PHOTOGRAPHY: 'MARTIN MUNKACSI: THINK WHILE YOU SHOOT!' through April 29. Munkacsi, who inspired Cartier-Bresson, was, by contrast, self-taught, a creature of his own devising. This is the most complete retrospective, with a thick catalog (not too well researched) and dozens of vintage prints from the 1920s through the early '60s. He favored scenes of daily life, absorbing avant-garde ideas about odd angles and abstract compositions. Munkacsi was a stylist, and he made catchy images the only way he knew how, in a modernist mode, which, being an opportunistic form, could serve any master. (See above.) (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* THE METROPOLITAN MUSEUM OF ART: 'GLITTER AND DOOM: GERMAN PORTRAITS FROM THE 1920S,' through Feb. 19. The 100 paintings and drawings on display here are by 10 artists, including George Grosz, Christian Schad, and Karl Hubbuch, and most conspicuously the unrelentingly savage Otto Dix and his magnificent other, Max Beckmann. In their works the Weimar Republic's porous worlds reassemble; we look into the faces of museum directors and cabaret performers, society matrons and scarred war veterans, prostitutes and jaded aristocrats who were watching their world slide from one cataclysm to the next. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* THE MET: 'ONE OF A KIND: THE STUDIO CRAFT MOVEMENT,' through Sept. 3. Focusing on the postwar development of artist-craftsmen, this display of furniture, glass, ceramics, metalwork, jewelry and fiber includes funny, quirky, provocative and sometimes gorgeous things. Among its stars are a witty bust by the California funk ceramicist Robert Arneson (1920-92) portraying the mother of the 16th-century painter and printmaker Albrecht Durer; and Bonnie Seeman's fetching ceramic coffeepot and tray, whose mock cabbage leaves and rhubarb stalks evoke the genteel tradition of 18th-century British and Continental china, but can also be read as human rather than vegetative tissue. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>* MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'DOUG AITKEN: SLEEPWALKERS,' through Feb. 12. Produced in concert with Creative Time Inc., this monumental video projection, screened nightly (from 5 to 10) on three sides of the sleek exterior of the newly expanded Museum of Modern Art, consists of short, silent and rather too glamorous meditations on the working nights of five emblematic New Yorkers played somnolently by musicians and actors who include Donald Sutherland and Tilda Swinton. But Mr. Aitken's astute and restless cinematic ambition and commanding sense of scale are in full force, especially in the more abstract portions of the piece, resulting in a fitting ode to the city that never sleeps and that the camera has always loved. (212) 708-9400, daily. (Smith)</p>
        <p>WHITNEY MUSEUM OF AMERICAN ART: 'KIKI SMITH: A GATHERING, 1980-2005,' through Feb. 11. Many things fly and float here: men and women, harpies and angels, birds and beasts, toadstools and stars. And some things fall to earth, or rather to the museum's black stone floors, maybe to rise again, maybe not. The whole show, a midcareer retrospective, suggests a Victorian fairy tale, its tone at once light, grievous and dreamlike. But fanciful as it is, Ms. Smith's art is also deeply, corporeally realistic. It wears moral and mortal seriousness on its sleeve, if not tattooed on its wrist. It is about life and death, the essential things. 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676, whitney.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>* ROBERT IRWIN: 'WHO'S AFRAID OF RED, YELLOW AND BLUE 3' In the past, Robert Irwin has paid homage to Joseph Albers. Now he makes a bow to a different kind of perceptual magician, Barnett Newman, turning Newman's 1966-70 paintings titled ''Who's Afraid of Red, Yellow and Blue'' into a kind of self-reflective architecture. Optical illusionism has long been Mr. Irwin's calling card, but here he has achieved it by bare-bones means, offering quieting visual fare for an overstimulated world. PaceWildenstein, 545 West 22nd Street, (212) 989-4258, pacewildenstein.com, through Feb. 3 . (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* PORTIA MUNSON: GREEN On the floor, all manner of discarded plastic objects and cheap toys coalesce into a dense scatter piece that commemorates the fall of nature, the rise of suburbia and the varied tonalities of indigenous if artificial green. On the walls, exquisite mille-fleur-like color photographs made on a scanner redirect set-up photography back toward the experimental nature prints and photogenic drawings of the 19th century. P.P.O.W., 555 West 25th Street, (212) 647-1043, through Feb. 3. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* BRONX MUSEUM OF THE ARTS: 'TROPICALIA: A REVOLUTION IN BRAZILIAN CULTURE,' Tropicalia, or Tropicalism, wasn't a style or a movement as much as an atmosphere, a rush of youthful, cosmopolitan, liberating optimism that broke over Brazil in the late 1960s like a sun shower, and soaked into everything -- art, music, film, theater and architecture -- until a military government clamped down. This show is an attempt to recapture the moment's fugitive spirit, and with the presence of artists like Helio Oiticica and Lygia Clark, the architect Lina Bo Bardi, and musicians like Gilberto Gil and Caetano Veloso, it comes close. 1040 Grand Concourse, at 165th Street, Morrisania, (718) 681-6000, bronxmuseum.org; closes on Sunday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'TIGERS OF WRATH: WATERCOLORS BY WALTON FORD,' This show assembles more than 50 of Mr. Ford's large-scale watercolors of birds, animals, snakes and lushly exotic flora, produced since the early '90s. They frequently depict moments in which a wild animal encounters human culture, often to its detriment. Sometimes the threat is overt, as in pictures of animals and birds roped or wounded; in other images the sense is that some horrible violence has occurred or is about to. Though they're wonderfully lucid and dramatic, the moralizing of these images can become a little tedious. But this popular artist imparts an environmental message, couched in a lament for the irreversible loss that occurs when a sense of ethics does not govern the treatment of animals. 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, Brooklyn (718) 638-5000, brooklynmuseum.org; closes on Sunday. (Benjamin Genocchio)</p>
        <p>* 'THE CONSTANT POSSIBILITY OF ERASURE' Organized by Donna Harkavy and Gracie Mansion, this excellent group show is at once witty and elegaic, exploring transience as an existential reality and as a conceptual ploy in late-20th-century art. Robert Rauschenberg's 1953 ''Erased de Kooning'' is an important reference point, present through Mike Bidlo's painstaking recreation. Joseph Beuys, Gary Simmons and Christian Xarec all have chalk pieces on blackboards, while Allan Kaprow preferred drawing, and simultaneously erasing, chalk pictures on the sidewalks or streets. Joanne Stamerra Hendricks uses erasers as a medium, and Jim Dingilian uses smoke. Dorsky Gallery Curatorial Projects, 11-03 45th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 937-6317; closes on Monday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* 'THE EARLY WORK OF WILLIAM KING' The spindly figure sculptures by William King that we know best have arms like I-beams, legs like stilts, and heads that are barely there. But his early work looks quite different, and that's the revelation of this absorbing show, assembled by the art critic Sanford Schwartz at Alexandre Gallery. Much of the material is hand-size or toy-size and comes in a variety of forms and media, and most of it is being exhibited for the first time. Alexandre Gallery, 41 East 57th Street, (212) 755-2828; closes tomorrow. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* FRICK COLLECTION: 'MASTERPIECES OF EUROPEAN PAINTING FROM THE CLEVELAND MUSEUM OF ART,' This exhibition transcends the usual traveling masterpieces-from genre, with room to spare. The 14 paintings include almost always outstanding works by household names like Velázquez, Caravaggio, El Greco, Turner and Poussin, as well as Annibale Carracci, Francisco de Zurbarán and Andrea del Sarto. But the astute installation makes the most of all this star power, letting the works talk among themselves to a remarkable degree, illuminating their likenesses, differences and collective progress. Extending John Berger's famous title, the show might be called ''Ways of Seeing Paintings.'' 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700; closes on Sunday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>THE MET: 'AMERICANS IN PARIS: 1860-1900,' The Americanization of the world may be a done deal now, but not so long ago the United States was a buyer rather than a seller of cultural information, and France was a major source between the Civil War and World War I. That's the story told in this exhibition that goes a little way toward reversing the fall season's trend of big, surveyish shows made up of splashy objects and bland ideas. In this case, the basic ideas, though undeveloped, are inherently interesting, and the art, with some notable exceptions, is conservative and staid. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org; closes on Sunday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'MANET AND THE EXECUTION OF MAXIMILIAN,' This gripping show reminds us of Modernism's mutinous, myth-scouring origins. And it does so by bringing one of art's great path-cutters, Edouard Manet, onto the scene, wry, politically infuriated and painting like Lucifer. There's not a lot of him here -- eight paintings, three on a single theme: the death by firing squad of the Austrian archduke Ferdinand Maximilian in Mexico in 1867. But it's enough. Manet's images, surrounded by a riveting selection of prints and photographs, are electrifying. (212) 708-9400, www.moma.org; closes on Monday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>NEWARK MUSEUM, THE JEWISH MUSEUM: 'MASTERS OF AMERICAN COMICS'  Organized by the Hammer Museum and the Museum of Contemporary Art in Los Angeles, where it made a splash, this show has come east, cut in size and split between the far-flung Newark and Jewish museums, in which it looks cramped. Art Spiegelman, one of the masters who helped instigate the exhibition, felt so aggrieved by the circumstances that at nearly the 11th hour he pulled his work. This was a pity, for the obvious reasons, and also because the Jewish Museum scrambled to fill the gap he left by appending a half-baked display of superhero comic artists. Still, the show shouldn't be missed. It spotlights artists like Chris Ware and Gary Panter, amazing talents and endearing in the tradition of those shy, gifted kids who drew endlessly in their roomswhen other kids wouldn't play with them, dreaming about someday telling the world, ''I told you so.'' Newark Museum, 49 Washington Street, (973) 596-6550, newarkmuseum.org; and the Jewish Museum, 1109 Fifth Avenue, at 92nd Street, (212) 423-3200, thejewishmuseum.org; closes on Sunday. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>P.S. 1 CONTEMPORARY ART CENTER: 'MUSIC IS A BETTER NOISE' An involvement of some sort with music is the main criterion for this disparate but engaging show. The artist-musicians on hand include Jutta Koether, the rapper Rammellzee, Don Van Vliet (a k a Captain Beefheart) and Devendra Banhart. Chuck Naney contributes a beautiful sound-light installation in the stairwell, and Rodney Graham tries his hand at music video. 22-25 Jackson Avenue, at 46th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 784-2084, ps1.org; closes on Monday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>RUBIN MUSEUM OF ART: 'I SEE NO STRANGER: EARLY SIKH ART AND DEVOTION,' Sikhism is the world's fifth-largest organized religion, but how many Westerners know that it was conceived as universalist in scope and radically egalitarian socially? Or that its holy book, far from being a catalog of sectarian dos and don'ts, is a bouquet of poetic songs blending the fragrances of Hindu ragas, Muslim hymns, and Punjabi folk tunes? This is precisely the information delivered by this small and beautiful show. Vivid and concentrated, it presents, mostly through miniature paintings, a kind of Sikh self-portrait, the image of a history shaped by hard work, pluralism and mystical transport, as well as by militancy. 150 West 17th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 620-5000, rmanyc.org; closes on Monday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>THE WHITNEY MUSEUM OF AMERICAN ART: 'PICASSO AND AMERICAN ART,' Despite the glamorous pictures in it, this is one of those dull affairs incubated in the world of academe: a walk-through slide show that states the obvious. Picasso's ''Woman in White,'' a picture of heavenly arrogance, hangs between Arshile Gorky's ''Artist and His Mother'' and de Kooning's ''Standing Man,'' terrific paintings too. We are meant to register the plain insinuation of Picasso's neo-Classicism, then move on. The show ends not with the lively question of Picasso's impact on young artists today but with a virtual retrospective of the later, Picasso-inspired works by Jasper Johns. In picture after picture, Johns buries allusions to the great Spaniard, aspiring presumably to Picasso's own late meditations on Velázquez. Except that even when he was old and running out of steam, Picasso still had joie de vivre. Johns doesn't so much enthrone Picasso as repeatedly entomb him; closes on Sunday. (See above.) (Kimmelman)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'ADRIFT IN MACAO' In previews; opens on Feb 13. Primary Stages presents Christopher Durang and Peter Melnick's new musical send-up of the sexy, shadowy world of film noir (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'THE COAST OF UTOPIA: SALVAGE' Previews start on Tuesday. Opens on Feb. 15. Tom Stoppard's epic trilogy about 19th-century Russian intelligentsia comes to an end with this final installment, which once again stars a vigorous and immense cast, including Brian F. O'Byrne, Jennifer Ehle, Billy Crudup and Ethan Hawke. Jack O'Brien directs (2:30). Vivian Beaumont Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'THE FEVER' In previews; opens on Monday. Wallace Shawn stars in his own play about a man who wakes up in a war-torn country feeling under the weather (1:30). Acorn Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'FRANK'S HOME' In previews; opens on Tuesday. Richard Nelson's new bio-play about the life and work of Frank Lloyd Wright stars Peter Weller (as Wright) and Harris Yulin (who plays Louis Sullivan) (1:45). Playwrights Horizons Mainstage, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 719-4200.</p>
        <p>'IN THE HEIGHTS' In previews; opens on Feb. 8. A new Off Broadway musical about two days in the life of Washington Heights, presented from the vantage point of a corner bodega (2:10). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'THE LAST WORD ' Previews start on Tuesday. Opens on Feb. 8. This new play by Oren Safdie (''Private Jokes, Public Places'') is about a retired ad executive who wants to be a playwright. Daniel J. Travanti (''Hill Street Blues'') stars (1:30). Theater at St. Clement's, 423 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'THE MADRAS HOUSE' Previews start on Wednesday. Opens on Feb. 15. Yet another modern-sounding play by Harley Granville Barker (''Waste'') comes out of the woodwork: a 1909 drama about business battles, family values and sex (2:30). Mint Theater, 311 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 315-0231.</p>
        <p>'MARY ROSE' Previews start on Thursday. Opens on Feb. 20. Although it can sometimes seem otherwise, J. M. Barrie wrote stories besides ''Peter Pan,'' including this one about a girl who might be a ghost. Tina Landau directs (1:45). Vineyard Theater, 108 East 15th Street, (212) 353-0303.</p>
        <p>'THE MERCHANT OF VENICE' In previews; opens on Feb. 4. F. Murray Abraham plays Shylock in this Theater for a New Audience production. Darko Tresnjak directs (2:20). The Duke on 42nd Street, 229 West 42nd Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'A SPANISH PLAY' In previews; opens on Thursday. Zoe Caldwell leads an extraordinary cast (Linda Emond, Denis O'Hare, Larry Pine, Katherine Borowitz) in Yasmina Reza's new backstage play, in which real life and fiction blur (1:30). Classic Stage Company, 136 East 13th Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101.</p>
        <p>'A VERY COMMON PROCEDURE' Previews start on Wednesday. Opens on Feb. 14. Michael Greif (''Rent'') directs MCC Theater's new play about a married woman who has an affair with a doctor (1:20). Lucille Lortel Theater, 121 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE APPLE TREE' The amazing Kristin Chenoweth gives Imax-screen-size life to three curvaceous doodles who by rights shouldn't be any larger than figures in the Sunday funnies. Jerry Bock and Sheldon Harnick's 1966 musical, directed by Gary Griffin, shows its age but is given theatrical verve by Ms. Chenoweth, Brian d'Arcy James and Marc Kudisch (2:30). Studio 54, 254 West 54th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>'A CHORUS LINE' If you want to know why this show was such a big deal when it opened 31 years ago, you need only experience the thrilling first five minutes of this revival. Otherwise, this archivally exact production, directed by Bob Avian, feels like a vintage car that has been taken out of the garage, polished up and sent on the road once again (2:00). Schoenfeld Theater, 236 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE COAST OF UTOPIA' The exhilarating first two installments of Tom Stoppard's trilogy about 19th-century Russian intellectuals dreaming of revolution, these productions pulse with the dizzy, spring-green arrogance and anxiety of a new generation moving as fast as it can toward the future. Jack O'Brien directs a fresh, vigorous and immense cast that includes Brian F. O'Byrne, Jennifer Ehle, Billy Crudup and Ethan Hawke (2:45). Vivian Beaumont Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'COMPANY' Fire, beckoning and dangerous, flickers beneath the frost of John Doyle's elegant, unexpectedly stirring revival of Stephen Sondheim and George Furth's era-defining musical from 1970, starring a compellingly understated Raul Esparza. Like Mr. Doyle's ''Sweeney Todd,'' this production finds new clarity of feeling in Sondheim by melding the roles of performers and musicians (2:20). Barrymore Theater, 243 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE'  (Tony Awards, best book of a musical and best original score, 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920s stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, it has theatergoers responding as if they were withering houseplants finally being watered after long neglect. Bob Martin and Sutton Foster are the standouts in the avid, energetic cast (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'GREY GARDENS' Christine Ebersole is absolutely glorious as the middle-aged, time-warped debutante called Little Edie Beale in this uneven musical adaptation of the notorious 1975 documentary of the same title. She and the wonderful Mary Louise Wilson (as her bedridden mother), in the performances of their careers, make ''Grey Gardens'' an experience no passionate theatergoer should miss (2:40). Walter Kerr Theater, 219 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE LITTLE DOG LAUGHED' The comedy of manners, a form widely believed to be extinct in the American theater, has actually resurfaced on Broadway with all its vital signs intact in Douglas Carter Beane's breezy but trenchant satire about truth and illusion, Hollywood style. With the wonderful Julie White as the movie agent you hate to love (but just can't help it) (2:00). Cort Theater, 138 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MARY POPPINS' This handsome, homily-packed, mechanically ingenious and rather tedious musical, adapted from the P. L. Travers stories and the 1964 Disney film, is ultimately less concerned with inexplicable magic than with practical psychology. Ashley Brown, who sings prettily as the family-mending nanny, looks like Joan Crawford trying to be nice and sounds like Dr. Phil. Directed by Richard Eyre and Matthew Bourne (2:30). New Amsterdam Theater, 214 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LES MISÉRABLES' This premature revival, a slightly scaled-down version of the well-groomed behemoth that closed only three years ago, appears to be functioning in a state of mild sedation. Appealingly sung and freshly orchestrated, this fast-moving adaptation of Victor Hugo's novel isn't sloppy or blurry. But its pulse rate stays well below normal (2:55). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' Duncan Sheik and Steven Sater's bold adaptation of the Frank Wedekind play is the freshest and most exciting new musical Broadway has seen in some time. Set in 19th-century Germany but with a ravishing rock score, it exposes the splintered emotional lives of adolescents just discovering the joys and sorrows of sex. Performed with brio by a great cast, with supple direction by Michael Mayer and inventive choreography by Bill T. Jones (2:00). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN'  This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a superdeluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE VERTICAL HOUR' David Hare's soggy consideration of the Anglo-American cultural divide stars Julianne Moore (representing the Americans) and Bill Nighy (leading the British), directed by Sam Mendes. The Yanks don't stand a chance. With his irresistibly mannered performance as a laconic doctor, Mr. Nighy mops the floor with Ms. Moore. Actually, he mops the floor with Mr. Hare's play (2:20). Music Box Theater, 239 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'AS YET THOU ART YOUNG AND RASH' An abstract collage of shards of feeling built out of Euripides' ''Suppliant Women,'' this meditation on grief and the death of children in senseless war offers plenty of parallels to current society without doing anything so obvious as explicitly referring to them. The five-member cast, led by three beautiful middle-aged women, is strong; the director, David Herskovits, has helped them shape an evocative piece that might be too nonliteral for some tastes, but is both moving and distinctive (1:10). The Ohio Theater, 66 Wooster Street, SoHo, (212) 352-3101. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>'DUTCHMAN' A revival of the poet Amiri Baraka's screed on race and American values, 43 years after its Greenwich Village debut, aims for all the fire and might of a Malcolm X speech but none of the rhetorical elegance. It shouts so loudly that you can't hear a thing (1:00). Cherry Lane Theater, 38 Commerce Street, between Barrow and Bedford Streets, West Village (212) 239-6200. (Ginia Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'GUTENBERG! THE MUSICAL' A very funny if not terribly original satire of musical theater features what must be the worst backers' audition of all time. The excellent duo Jeremy Shamos and Christopher Fitzgerald make the pitch (2:05). The Actors' Playhouse, 100 Seventh Avenue South, at Fourth Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 239-6200. (Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'JACQUES BREL IS ALIVE AND WELL AND LIVING IN PARIS' A powerfully sung revival of the 1968 revue, presented with affectionate nostalgia by the director Gordon Greenberg. As in the original, two men and two women perform a wide selection of Brel's plaintive ballads and stirring anthems (2:00). Zipper Theater, 336 West 37th Street, (212) 239-6200.(Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'MEET ME IN ST. LOUIS' This musical is too big for its stage, but the young turn-of-the-last-century sweethearts have great chemistry, and there are four terrific songs (2:00). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>'NO GREAT SOCIETY' The brainy experimentalists of Elevator Repair Service provide a madcap and almost dreamlike re-enactment of a 1968 episode of William F. Buckley's ''Firing Line,'' which features Mr. Buckley squaring off with Jack Kerouac (1:30). New York Theater Workshop, 79 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 239-6200. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'THE SCENE' Theresa Rebeck's latest is a sharp-witted, sharp-elbowed comedy about the savage economies of sex and show business in Manhattan. Tony Shalhoub plays an out-of-work actor, Charlie, happily married -- but not really -- to Patricia Heaton's frazzled chat show booker. Enter the femme fatale Clea, played by the gifted Anna Camp, and goodbye, Charlie (2:00). Second Stage Theater, 307 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 246-4422. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'TOYS IN THE ATTIC' Austin Pendleton's fine revival of Lillian Hellman's last play faithfully attacks the corrosive attachments of family. What good is a family, and thus a society, the play implicitly asks, that can only look in the mirror? (2:30) Pearl Theater, 80 St. Marks Place, East Village, (212) 598-9802. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'VICTORIA MARTIN: MATH TEAM QUEEN' Must all stage teenagers speak in that exaggerated surfer-dude style in which ''awesome'' and ''totally'' make up about 50 percent of any conversation? Yes, apparently they must, from the evidence presented in this thin comedy, which is about a high school girl who finds herself on the all-male math team. The playwright, Kathryn Walat, seems to have been trying to grab the coattails of a certain spelling-bee-related show. She missed (2:00). The Julia Miles Theater, 424 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>* 'THE VOYSEY INHERITANCE' David Mamet has cleanly and cannily adapted Harley Granville Barker's 1905 play about corruption in the genteel world of Victorian finance. An excellent cast and a sumptuous production bring extra immediacy to a tale of embezzlement and entitlement that feels as fresh as tomorrow's stock options (1:50). Atlantic Theater, 336 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE WOMEN OF TRACHIS' In Kate Ryan's wonderfully perceptive adaptation, Sophocles' rarely produced tragedy about the death of the hero Heracles and his wife, Deianira, has terrific contemporary traction. Alice Reagan's superbly cast and infectiously energetic production is fun, intelligent and eminently worth seeing. (1:00). The Ohio Theater, 66 Wooster Street, SoHo, (212) 352-3101. (Jonathan Kalb)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>* 'THE DIRTY TALK' Kevin Cristaldi and Sidney Williams are just great in this two-hander by Michael Puzzo about strangers stranded in a hunting cabin. How they came to be there is hilariously doled out by Mr. Puzzo, along with some thoughts about identity, the Internet and the liar in all of us. Padraic Lillis, the director, has the two actors in perfect sync (1:20). Center Stage, 41 West 21st Street, Chelsea, (212) 352-3101. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'T J AND DAVE' The comics T. J. Jagodowski and Dave Pasquesi miraculously improvise a one-hour play at every performance (1:00). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden Theater, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' Singing CliffsNotes for Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' Often more entertaining than the real thing (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS'  The biomusical that walks like a man (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT'  A singing scrapbook for Monty Python fans (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' ''A Chorus Line'' with pimples (1:45). Circle in the Square, 254 West 50th Street, Manhattan, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* 'A BEAUTIFUL VIEW' The Canadian playwright and director Daniel MacIvor mines two funny, subdued and entirely affecting performances from Caroline Gillis and Tracy Wright as women whose enduring friendship may be more (1:20). The Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200; closes on Sunday. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'THE BROTHERS SIZE' Loosely based on West African myths, this impressive and emotionally absorbing debut by Tarrell Alvin McCraney portrays two battling brothers in Louisiana (1:30). The Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200; closes on Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>* 'THE CLEAN HOUSE' Sarah Ruhl's comedy about the painful but beautiful disorder of life has arrived in New York at last in a gorgeous production directed by Bill Rauch. Blair Brown and Jill Clayburgh delight as sisters with different views on the meaning of cleaning, and Vanessa Aspillaga is equally good as the depressed maid with little affection for her work but a deep conviction that a good joke can be a matter of life and death (2:15). Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200; closes on Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'DEAD SET #3' Themes of apocalypse and trauma echo throughout the Big Art Group's flashy and shallow new entry in the ever-expanding genre of high-tech theater (1:15). The Kitchen, 512 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 255-5793, Ext. 11; closes tomorrow. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'FLUKE' A meditative collage of enigmatic riffs on ''Moby-Dick'' presented by the rambunctious experimental company Radiohole (1:30). Collapsable Hole, 146 Metropolitan Avenue, at Berry Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 388-2251; closes on Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'GET YOUR WAR ON' Based on the absurdist comic strip of David Rees, this sardonic history lesson of the past six years will delight Bush-haters (1:10). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200; closes on Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'INVINCIBLE SUMMER' The performance artist Mike Daisey's monologue is a showcase of facile observation. During his first summer in New York six years ago, he discovers that it's hot and that people are generally much nicer than their comportment on subways would lead you to believe (1:30). The Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200; closes on Sunday. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'REGRETS ONLY' Old acquaintance comes under siege in Paul Rudnick's chiffon-thin comedy about the varieties of love and marriage. But no one who sees this latest offering from one of the funniest quipmeisters alive is going to doubt that Christine Baranski is a one-liner's best friend (2:00). City Center Stage I, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212; closes on Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TWO TRAINS RUNNING'  Directed by Lou Bellamy, a rough-edged revival of August Wilson's 1992 play about the stark economics of life and death for African-Americans, set in a dying diner in Pittsburgh in the late 1960s. The pace drags in this production, but it remains a bracing reminder of Mr. Wilson's singular talent for making cold, hard numbers sing hot, molten blues (3:40). Signature Theater at Peter Norton Space, 555 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 352-3101; closes on Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE VIETNAMIZATION OF NEW JERSEY (AN AMERICAN TRAGEDY)' A revival of Christopher Durang's satire of war, family life and Bicentennial fever, on the 30th anniversary of its debut at the Yale Repertory Theater, swishes along at the speed of a Nascar race. Blanche Baker is a gem as an out-of-it 1970s matron who just can't dust off the Eisenhower era. The Beckett Theater, on Theater Row, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200; closes on Sunday. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>'ALPHA DOG' (R, 117 minutes) Based on a true Southern California crime, Nick Cassavetes's entertaining exploitation flick features a lot of attractive, talented young actors shimmying across the screen while embodying the collective parental nightmare. Do you know where your children are? Well, in this film they're getting busy, chilling out, smoking blunts and chugging coolers faster than a toothless wino. Oh, and committing murder. (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>'ALONE WITH HER' (No rating, 79 minutes) In this voyeuristic thriller, a young man named Doug (Colin Hanks) becomes smitten with a coffee shop waitress named Amy (Ana Claudia Talancón) and tries to insinuate himself into her life through high-tech means, videotaping her routines from afar, then bugging her apartment. In the end, though, the characters seem less archetypal than vague, and aside from its sophisticated presentation, the film doesn't differ all that much from its template -- the late 1980s/early '90s Fill-in-the-Blanks-From-Hell movies that followed ''Fatal Attraction,'' many of whose elements are revived almost verbatim. (Matt Zoller Seitz)</p>
        <p>'ARTHUR AND THE INVISIBLES' (PG, 94 minutes) Luc Besson serves up a hybrid of live actors and computer-generated figures to tell a not-endearing-enough story about a boy (Freddie Highmore) who shrinks to microscopic size to find some gems and his missing grandfather. Lots of famous names (Madonna, Robert De Niro, David Bowie, Snoop Dogg) lend their voices to the computerized part of the movie, but only briefly near the end does everything click. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'BABEL' (R, 143 minutes, in English, Spanish, Japanese, Berber, Arabic and sign language) This hugely ambitious movie tells four loosely linked, not quite simultaneous stories set on three different continents, with dialogue in several languages. The themes, to the extent they are decipherable, include loss, fate and the terrible consequences of miscommunication. Written by Guillermo Arriaga and directed by Alejandro Gonzalez Iñárritu, the movie is an intellectual muddle but a visceral tour de force, and the power of the filmmaking almost overcomes the fuzziness of the ideas. Almost. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>'BLOOD DIAMOND' (R, 138 minutes) The makers of this foolish thriller about illegal diamond trafficking in Africa, starring an excellent Leonardo DiCaprio, want you to know there may be blood on your hands, specifically your wedding finger. Too bad they haven't thought through what it means to turn human misery into entertainment. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'CHILDREN OF MEN' (R, 100 minutes) The end is nigh in this superbly directed political thriller by Alfonso Cuarón about a nervously plausible future. Based on the P. D. James book, the film stars an excellent Clive Owen and features equally sterling support from the actors Michael Caine, Danny Huston and Chiwetel Ejiofior, among others, as well as the great cinematographer Emmanuel Lubezki. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'THE DEPARTED' (R, 150 minutes) Martin Scorsese's cubistic entertainment about men divided by power, loyalty and their own selves is at once a success and a relief. Based on the crackling Hong Kong thriller ''Infernal Affairs,'' it features fine twinned performances from Matt Damon and Leonardo DiCaprio, and a showboating Jack Nicholson. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'DREAMGIRLS' (PG-13, 131 minutes) The Broadway musical arrives on the screen, capably directed by Bill Condon, ardently acted and sung by Jamie Foxx, Eddie Murphy, Beyoncé Knowles and (especially) Jennifer Hudson, but undone by mediocre and anachronistic songs. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'GOD GREW TIRED OF US' (PG, 90 minutes) This sober, uplifting documentary, which won two major awards at last year's Sundance Film Festival, follows the resettlement in the United States of three Sudanese young men uprooted as children by the civil war. Handsomely photographed, and inspirational but not cloyingly so, it is the rare contemporary documentary that doesn't leave a residue of cynicism and outrage. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE HITCHER' (R, 90 minutes) Like the 1986 cult favorite of the same title, this remake is a crash-and-burn action horror film with intellectual pretensions. The overachieving Irish character actor Sean Bean plays the Hitcher as a philosophical sadist, toying with people who didn't get the memo saying that God is dead, but the movie is too shallow to embellish that vision. The merger of mystical solemnity and chain-reaction slapstick suggests a Road Runner cartoon directed by John Woo. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>'THE ITALIAN' (PG-13, 99 minutes, in Russian) This dark fairy tale from Russia pulls you into a richly atmospheric, persuasively inhabited world teeming with young foundlings and pathos, and upended by one remarkable little boy. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE LAST KING OF SCOTLAND' (R, 121 minutes) Kevin Macdonald paints a queasily enjoyable portrait of the Ugandan dictator Idi Amin from inside the palace walls. Forest Whitaker plays the mad king, while James McAvoy plays the fool. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'LETTERS FROM IWO JIMA' (R, 141 minutes, in Japanese) Another masterwork from Clint Eastwood's astonishing late period, and one of the best war movies ever. Ken Watanabe is especially fine as the general commanding Japanese troops in the doomed defense of the island of Iwo Jima. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'LITTLE CHILDREN' (R, 130 minutes) Todd Field's adaptation of Tom Perrotta's novel of suburban adultery is unfailingly intelligent and faultlessly acted. Kate Winslet and Patrick Wilson are superb as the parents of young children who meet at the playground and enact a two-handed variation on ''Madame Bovary'' against a backdrop of social paranoia and middle-class malaise. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'Little Miss Sunshine' (R, 101 minutes) A bittersweet comedy of dysfunction that takes place at the terminus of the American dream. The excellent cast includes Greg Kinnear, Steve Carell, Toni Collette, Paul Dano and that national treasure, Alan Arkin. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'MAFIOSO' (No rating, 99 minutes, in Italian) This 1962 film, revived by Rialto Pictures, is a rambunctious, astonishing blend of farce, thriller and social satire. The director, Alberto Lattuada, follows an up-and-coming Fiat manager (Alberto Sordi) on a visit from Milan to his native village in Sicily. His homecoming is full of surprises -- painful for him, altogether delightful for the audience. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'NOTES ON A SCANDAL' (R, 92 minutes) Judi Dench and Cate Blanchett play a misogynistic game of cat and mouse from which no one emerges unscathed, including the audience. Adapted by Patrick Marber from a novel by Zoë Heller and directed by Richard Eyre. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'PAN'S LABYRINTH' (R, 119 minutes, in Spanish) Guillermo del Toro's tale of a young girl's ordeal in post-Civil-War fascist Spain is either a fairy tale in the guise of a political allegory or vice versa. In either case it is a moving, enchanting, strange and humane example of popular art at its very best. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE PAINTED VEIL' (PG-13, 125 minutes) Nicely directed by John Curran, this version of the W. Somerset Maugham novel draws you in by turning a distaff bildungsroman into a fine romance with Naomi Watts and Edward Norton. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'PRIMEVAL' (R, 94 minutes) A giant crocodile named Gustave terrorizes Western journalists in war-torn Burundi. Not as much fun as it might have been, but not as terrible either. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE PURSUIT OF HAPPYNESS' (PG-13, 117 minutes) How you respond to this fairy tale in realist drag may depend on whether you find Will Smith's performances so overwhelmingly winning that you buy the idea that poverty is a function of bad luck and bad choices, and success the result of heroic toil and dreams. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'THE QUEEN' (PG-13, 103 minutes) Directed by Stephen Frears from a very smart script by Peter Morgan, and starring a magnificent Helen Mirren in the title role, ''The Queen'' pries open a window in the House of Windsor around the time of the death of Diana, Princess of Wales, blending fact with fiction. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'REGULAR LOVERS' (No rating, 175 minutes, in French) Philippe Garrel's tender portrait of late-1960s French youth stars the filmmaker's son, Louis Garrel, as a 20-year-old Parisian struggling through the fires of revolutionary promise and its smoldering remains. Magnificent. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'STOMP THE YARD' (PG-13, 109 minutes) Brotherhood is powerful in this sometimes compelling, sometimes complacent movie about stepping and African-American fraternity life at an Atlanta institution called Truth University. D J (Columbus Short), a street-style dancer, needs to find his place in a university ruled by Gammas and Thetas and stepping. (Rachel Saltz)</p>
        <p>'TEARS OF THE BLACK TIGER' (No rating, 113 minutes, in Thai) A western weepie from Thailand, filmed in garish color. In spite of the relentless genre pastiche, it has a charming sincerity. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'VENUS' (R, 91 minutes) A modest, diverting, touching tale of a young woman who attracts the interest -- avuncular and also erotic -- of an aging actor, played with effortless aplomb by the great Peter O'Toole. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'VOLVER' (R, 121 minutes, in Spanish) Another keeper from Pedro Almodóvar, with Penélope Cruz -- as a resilient widow -- in her best role to date. (Scott)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>CRITICS CHOICE: GREAT DOCUMENTARIES (Sunday) A series of significant documentaries introduced by members of the New York Film Critics Circle continues with Ross McElwee's family history ''Bright Leaves'' (2003), presented by Lisa Schwarzbaum of Entertainment Weekly, and Werner Herzog's ''Grizzly Man,'' a 2005 study of a man who mistakenly (and tragically) believed that he understood bears, presented by Kyle Smith of The New York Post. (Through Feb. 25.) Museum of the Moving Image, 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718) 784-0077, movingimage.us; $10. (Dave Kehr)</p>
        <p>I AM NOT A WAR PHOTOGRAPHER: FILMS OF LYNNE SACHS (Tonight through Sunday) Three programs of nontraditional documentaries by a filmmaker who employs subjective perspectives and abstract visual effects to examine contemporary conflicts. Tonight ''Which Way Is East: Notebooks from Vietnam'' (1994) is doubled with ''Investigation of a Flame: The Catonsville Nine'' (2001). Tomorrow brings a program of four short films and ''Invisible,'' a 30-minute work-in-progress. Sunday's screening is ''States of Unbelonging,'' a new video feature about Revital Ohayon, an Israeli filmmaker killed in 2002 in a terrorist attack near the West Bank. Anthology Film Archives, 32 Second Avenue, at Second Street, East Village, (212) 505-5181, anthologyfilmarchives.org; $8. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>STORM WARNINGS: THE FILMS OF BAHMAN FARMANARA (Tonight through Thursday) This retrospective focuses on the work of one of the few Iranian directors to work before and after the revolution. His ''Prince Ehtejab'' (1974), screening tonight, tomorrow and Monday, is a Visconti-like historical epic about the end of the Qajar Dynasty, centered on the last prince of the line, who withdraws from political conflict into the private reality of his palace. An international success, it led to Mr. Farmanara's appointment as the head of the Iranian Film Development Company, but his 1979 work ''Tall Shadows in the Wind'' (tonight, Sunday and Wednesday) was banned by the shah's shaky government, and Mr. Farmanara spent the next several years in Canada, eventually returning to the new Iran, where he encountered a different form of censorship. After having 10 scripts rejected by the government censors, he was able to film in 2000 the gently satiric, self-reflective ''Smell of Camphor, Fragrance of Jasmine'' (tomorrow, Tuesday and Wednesday), a hit at the New York Film Festival that marked Mr. Farmanara's comeback. The series also includes two recent films, ''A Little Kiss'' from 2005 (tonight through Wednesday) and ''A House Built on Water'' from 2002 (Sunday, Monday and Wednesday). Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 975-5600, filmlinc.org; $10. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>THE BOOKS (Tomorrow) Nick Zammuto and Paul de Jong of the Books make beguiling electronic collages out of disembodied vocal samples, a few plucks from a banjo or another string instrument, and unclassifiable noises that fade in and out like traffic. Part of the pleasure of listening is trying to figure out just why all this chaos works so wonderfully and wittily. With Jack Rose and Essie Jain. At 6:30 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; $20. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>* DAVID BYRNE (Thursday) He may have set a still unsurpassed standard with Talking Heads for art-pop that is as arty as it is truly poppy, but Mr. Byrne's influence reaches much wider than the rock world, into theater, film and, especially, world music. (He also has the best blog of any rock star, at davidbyrne.com.) He begins his four-day Perspectives series at Carnegie Hall with music from ''The Knee Plays,'' a 1985 collaboration with the theater director Robert Wilson, which features Mr. Byrne's work as well as arrangements of gospel and Bulgarian folk songs. At 9 p.m., Zankel Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $35 to $45. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>RHYS CHATHAM (Tomorrow) A force in the fruitful meeting of drone minimalism with loud guitar-rock in the 1970s, Mr. Chatham remains a lover of big, electrified din. For his current tour he revisits a 1970s piece, ''Guitar Trio,'' with members of his band augmented by a phalanx of guitarists, including Thurston Moore, Lee Ranaldo and Kim Gordon of Sonic Youth, an important inheritor of Mr. Chatham's style. At 8 p.m., Issue Project Room, 400 Carroll Street, between Bond and Nevins Streets, Carroll Gardens, Brooklyn, (718) 330-0313, issueprojectroom.org; $25. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DEERHOOF (Tonight) More than a decade into its career, this avant-garde rock band from San Francisco still has plenty of surprises. Deerhoof's stop-start songs, with jagged guitars, a drum style somewhere between jazz and metal, and Satomi Matsuzaki's nursery rhyme vocals, sound intriguingly extraterrestrial. With Busdriver and Proton Proton. At 9, Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800, irvingplaza.com; $16. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>EARLY YEARS (Tonight and tomorrow night) Destination: trippy outer space. Vehicle: buoyant, puslating guitars of this young British band, which borrows from 1980s and '90s neo-psych visionaries like My Bloody Valentine and Spacemen 3. Tonight at 8, with Daylight's for the Birds, a New York band equally devoted to '80s British ''dream pop''; at Union Hall, 702 Union Street, at Fifth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 638-4400, unionhallny.com; $8. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Union Pool, 484 Union Avenue, at Meeker Avenue, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 609-0484; $8. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ISAAC HAYES (Tomorrow) From his days as a songwriter and producer at Stax/Volt to the orchestrated funk of his album ''Hot Buttered Soul'' to his former cartoon role (as Chef) in ''South Park,'' Isaac Hayes has adapted his deep voice and down-home charm to every era. At 7:30 and 10:30 p.m., B. B. King Blues Club &amp; Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $40 in advance, $45 at the door. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>JOHNNY SOCIETY (Tonight) Johnny Society is led by Kenny Siegal, a songwriter who scuffs up the melodicism of the Beatles and Brian Wilson in songs that know all too well about how relationships can crumble. With the London Souls, Le Firm, the Luxury Flats and the Shills. At 8, Sin-é, 150 Attorney Street, at Stanton Street, Lower East Side, (212) 388-0077, sin-e.com; $10. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>SLEEPY LABEEF(Sunday) An unregenerate rockabilly singer and guitarist from Arkansas, Sleepy LaBeef reels off one twangy tune after another, known and obscure, like a jukebox come to life. At 10 p.m., Rodeo Bar, 375 Third Avenue, at 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 683-6500, rodeobar.com; no cover. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>* LINCOLN CENTER'S AMERICAN SONGBOOK (Wednesday and Thursday) Now in its ninth season, this series has greatly expanded from its origins as a home for the midcentury pantheon of Harold Arlen, Richard Rodgers and the like. Wednesday features an acoustic show by Josh Ritter, a 30-year-old songwriter whose guileless, boy-next-door voice belies the depth and ambition of his songs, whether he is confessing a simple crush or following his thoughts on a long, Whitmanesque incantation. On Thursday Howard Fishman, who has long been rummaging through the attic of American song, pays tribute to Bob Dylan and the Band's monumental ''Basement Tapes.'' At 8:30 p.m., Allen Room, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Broadway at 60th Street, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; sold out on Wednesday, $35 to $70 on Thursday. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* MAUDE MAGGART (Tonight and tomorrow night, and Tuesday through Thursday) In her must-see cabaret show, ''Good Girl/Bad Girl,'' this 31-year-old singer, a knockout in a red dress, uses an astutely chosen selection of songs to explore conflicting female sexual stereotypes from the perspective of a young woman who understands but rejects abject surrender to a man. High point: Joan Baez's ''Love Song to a Stranger.'' At 9, with additional shows tonight and tomorrow night at 11:30, Oak Room at the Algonquin Hotel, 59 West 44th Street, Manhattan, (212) 419-9331, algonquinhotel.com; $60 cover; $25 minimum, with $65 dinner required for the early shows tonight and tomorrow. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>RITA MORENO (Tonight and tomorrow night, and Tuesday through Thursday) If you look as fresh and unbowed as Rita Moreno at 75, you may as well flaunt your age, which is what Ms. Moreno does with zest and humor in ''Little Tributes,'' her breezy new cabaret act. The show is a smooth, comfortable ride with a performer who knows who she is. At 8:45, with additional shows tonight and tomorrow at 10:45, Café Carlyle, Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212) 744-1600, thecarlyle.com; tonight and tomorrow, $70 cover at tables, $50 at the bar; Tuesday through Thursday, $65 at tables, $40 at the bar. (Holden)</p>
        <p>NORTHSIX (Tonight and Wednesday night) Another rock club bites the dust, but this time there's a twist: the gentrification is happening in Brooklyn, not Manhattan, and the gentrifier is another rock club. Northsix was a pioneer when it opened in Williamsburg six years ago, and has been an important incubator for the Brooklyn scene; it will close after this week's shows for renovations by its new owners, the proprietors of the Bowery Ballroom and the Mercury Lounge, and reopen later this year as the Music Hall of Williamsburg. Tonight features a solo set by Ted Leo, a veteran pop-punk bandleader who is one of the best songwriters in the game, and on Wednesday is Radio 4, which emulates the frantic punk-funk of early-'80s British bands like Gang of Four and Public Image Limited. At 9, 66 North Sixth Street, (718) 599-5103, northsix.com; $15; $13 in advance for Wednesday's show. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PAOLO NUTINI (Wednesday) A Scottish heartthrob who just turned 20, Mr. Nutini has already conquered the British charts with snappy, vaguely racy tunes like ''Jenny Don't Be Hasty,'' about an affair with an, ahem, older woman. (She's 23, he's 18.) He begins a coordinated American invasion next week, with the release of his debut album, ''These Streets'' (Atlantic), and appearances on ''Late Night With Conan O'Brien'' and the ''Today'' show. With Musiq Soulchild. At 7 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>O'DEATH, T K WEBB (Wednesday and Thursday) O'Death draws from the starkness and spiritual purity of Appalachian folk, the menace of punk and the rowdy theatricality of Tom Waits, jumbling sacred and profane. A Brooklynite by way of rural Missouri, the singer and guitarist T K Webb plays ragged, stark Delta blues about desolation and dying young, surrounding his creaky tenor with a halo of eerie reverb. Wednesday At 7 p.m., Europa, 98 Meserole Avenue, at Manhattan Avenue, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 383-5723, europaclub.com; $8. Mr. Webb also plays on Thursday at 8 p.m., with Shortstack and These United States, at Cake Shop, 152 Ludlow Street, between Stanton and Rivington Streets, Lower East Side, (212) 253-0036, cake-shop.com; $6. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ANDERS PARKER (Wednesday) Mr. Parker, who led the band Varnaline, immerses his songs in the stoic drama of country and folk music, resulting in a melancholy that is sometimes indistinguishable from cynicism. (''The hours I've wasted here I could have wasted anywhere.'') At 9 p.m., Living Room, 154 Ludlow Street, near Stanton Street, Lower East Side, (212) 533-7235, livingroomny.com; $8. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PETER, BJORN AND JOHN (Monday and Tuesday) The latest sharp and impeccably stylish import from Sweden, this trio sets breathy, heavy-hearted vocals over spare but peppery band arrangements that recall 1960s folk-pop. Best of all: lots of great whistling. With Born Ruffians and the White Rabbits. Monday at 8 p.m., Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700, mercuryloungenyc.com; Tuesday at 7:30 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; both shows sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>TOSHI REAGON (Tonight through Sunday) Singing about both love and politics with the same sense of independence, Ms. Reagon applies her gutsy voice and syncopated guitar playing to songs steeped in blues and funk. Tonight and tomorrow she celebrates the 10th anniversary of her band, Big Lovely. Sunday's show is devoted to sacred music, which Ms. Reagon will sing with her mother, Bernice Johnson Reagon, the scholar and founder of the long-running a cappella group Sweet Honey in the Rock. Tonight and tomorrow night at 9, Sunday at night at 7, Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* JONATHAN RICHMAN (Thursday) No rock star delivers intimacy like Mr. Richman, the eternally youthful and eternally nebbishy granddaddy of New Wave and indie rock. He fell in love with the acoustic guitar decades ago, and backed up by the tiniest of bands -- a drummer playing a snare and little more -- sings of simple pleasures lost and found with tiptoe dynamics. He begins a four-night stand, kicking off the Knitting Factory's 20th-anniversary celebration. At 8 p.m., 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3006, knittingfactory.com; $20 in advance, $23 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>SUNBURNED HAND OF THE MAN (Sunday and Monday) Improvisation means lots of things in rock, but to this Massachusetts collective, which has been churning out dozens of albums and homemade recordings since the mid-'90s, it means spacey, meandering drones that seem like endless psychedelic trips. On Sunday the band accompanies films by Ira Cohen, including the 1968 avant-garde classic ''The Invasion of Thunderbolt Pagoda,'' and on Monday it plays a club date with the bands Bunnybrains and Heavy Hands. Sunday at 3 p.m., Issue Project Room, 400 Carroll Street, between Bond and Nevins Streets, Carroll Gardens, Brooklyn, (718) 330-0313, issueprojectroom.org; $15. Monday at 9 p.m., Club Midway, 25 Avenue B, at Second Street, East Village, (212) 253-2595, clubmidway.com; $8 in advance, $10 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* M. WARD (Tonight) Ubiquitous as a sideman for indie-rock royalty -- Cat Power, Bright Eyes, Beth Orton, Jenny Lewis -- M. Ward stepped into the fore last year with an extraordinary solo album, ''Post-War'' (Merge). Over scratchy, portentous acoustic blues, he sings of malaise and loss in a dry, spectral voice: ''He was a good man but now he's gone,'' goes a deadpan requiem for a soldier. With Portastatic. At 8, Town Hall, 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 840-2824, the-townhall-nyc.org; $25. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* PAUL WELLER (Monday through Wednesday) In a three-part musical autobiography, Mr. Weller, a hallowed rock star in his native Britain who has remained a cult figure in America for 30 years, reviews the neatly defined phases of his career. On Monday he revisits his early years with the Jam, whose version of punk was shaded with soul music and the mod style of the early Who; next is the Style Council, Mr. Weller's R&amp;B-and-synthesizers 1980s band; and on Wednesday he looks over his whole output, including the comfy, sometimes indulgent soul-rock of his recent solo albums. At 8 p.m., Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800, irvingplaza.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ZEMOG EL GALLO BUENO (Tomorrow) Fierce salsa grooves lead into daring free-jazz improvisations in Zemog el Gallo Bueno, a Boston band that's equally fond of Tito Puente and Sun Ra. With Mofongo and DJ Philharmonic. At 8 p.m., Makor, 35 West 67th Street, Manhattan, (212) 601-1000, makor.org; $12. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>RALPH ALESSI QUINTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) As a trumpeter, Ralph Alessi combines pristine technique with an exploratory yen. His quintet includes resourceful collaborators like the tenor saxophonist Tony Malaby, the pianist Andy Milne, the bassist Drew Gress and the drummer Mark Ferber. At 9 and 10:30, Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $15. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>ROY AYERS (Tonight through Sunday night) Mr. Ayers, a vibraphonist associated with the heyday of jazz-funk, pays tribute to the exuberant forefather of his instrument, Lionel Hampton, with a band that includes two singers, John Pressley and Richard Shade. At 7:30 and 9:30, with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow night, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BALLIN' THE JACK (Thursday) This ensemble, led by the clarinetist and saxophonist Matt Darriau, customarily spikes a swing-era repertory with madcap irreverence. That's especially true of this engagement, featuring music from Marx Brothers film soundtracks, complete with Grouchoesque vocals from the alto saxophonist Roy Nathanson. At 8 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* BEBOP LIVES! (Tonight and tomorrow night) The spirit of Charlie Parker animates a concert by two esteemed saxophonists who have fully absorbed his language -- James Moody and Charles McPherson -- along with a trumpeter, Roy Hargrove, and a singer, Roberta Gambarini. At 8, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 721-6500, jalc.org; $37.50 to $127.50. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LOU DONALDSON QUARTET (Wednesday and Thursday) Bebop, blues and boogaloo are all fair game for the veteran alto saxophonist Lou Donaldson, whose rock-solid rhythm section comprises Dr. Lonnie Smith on organ, Randy Johnston on guitar and Fukushi Tainaka on drums. (Through Feb. 3.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Manhattan, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BILL EVANS'S SOULGRASS (Tonight through Sunday night) Virtuosity, the chief ingredient shared by bluegrass and fusion, will be in copious supply during this summit organized by the saxophonist Bill Evans, with Tony Trischka on banjo, Sam Bush on mandolin, Christian Howes on violin, Richard Bona on bass and Dave Weckl on drums. At 8 and 10:30, Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $35 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ANAT FORT (Tomorrow and Sunday) The prepossessing pianist Anat Fort previews music from an album on the ECM label, with her regular rhythm team of the bassist Gary Wang and the drummer Roland Schneider, plus Perry Robinson on clarinet and saxophone. Tomorrow at 9 and 10:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. Sunday at 7 p.m., St. Peter's Church, 619 Lexington Avenue, at 54th Street, (212) 935-2200, saintpeters.org; $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JIMMY GREENE QUINTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) Jimmy Greene brings an athletic endurance to his saxophone style and leads a top-shelf band with Xavier Davis on piano, Reuben Rogers on bass and Eric Harland on drums. At 8, 10 and 11:30, Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, (212) 864-6662, smokejazz.com; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DONALD HARRISON QUARTET/MULGREW MILLER TRIO (Tuesday through Thursday) Two satisfying bands, each with an assertive and soulful guide: Donald Harrison, an alto saxophonist equally steeped in bebop and New Orleans groove, and Mulgrew Miller, a modern pianist with roots in Mississippi blues. (Through Feb. 4.) At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $25 at tables, $15 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* JOHN HOLLENBECK (Thursday) Mr. Hollenbeck, a percussionist and composer, wrote ''The Drum Major'' years ago as a corollary to a sermon by the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. It's a moving tone poem for drums and three trombones -- in this iteration, Curtis Hasselbring, Jacob Garchik and Brian Drye -- designed to accompany a recording of the sermon in total darkness. For this performance Mr. Hollenbeck will also unveil what he calls a companion piece for piano, accordion and guitar. At 7:30 p.m., Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, symphonyspace.org; $21 in advance; $25 on Thursday; $17 for members; $10 rush tickets. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>FRANK KIMBROUGH TRIO (Tonight and tomorrow night) Drawing from a fine recent album, ''Play'' (Palmetto), the pianist Frank Kimbrough leads an appealingly elastic trio with the bassist Jay Anderson and the drummer Matt Wilson. At 8 and 9:45, Kitano Hotel, 66 Park Avenue, at 38th Street, (212) 885-7119, kitano.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE LEHMAN QUINTET/TYSHAWN SOREY'S OBLIQUE (Wednesday) Steve Lehman, an intense saxophonist, features his own sharp-cornered compositions in a group with Jonathan Finlayson on trumpet, Bryan Carrott on vibraphone, Drew Gress on bass and Tyshawn Sorey on drums. In an earlier set Mr. Sorey leads his own group, which features Loren Stillman on saxophones and Ben Gerstein on trombone. At 8 and 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* PAUL MOTIAN TRIO 2000 +1 (Tuesday through Thursday) Show tunes and standards receive loving interpretations on ''Paul Motian on Broadway Vol. 4'' (Winter &amp; Winter), one of last year's standout jazz releases. Mr. Motian's teasingly suggestive drumming is well matched with the abstruse pianism of Masabumi Kikuchi; Rebecca Martin handles vocals with a casual purity; and the bassist Larry Grenadier adds some welcome heft. (Through Feb. 4.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GREG OSBY AND THE ORGANIZATION (Tonight through Sunday night) The alto saxophonist Greg Osby has a brittle and dartlike style, well suited to exploratory post-bop or slippery free-funk. His constituents here are Trudy Pitts on organ and keyboards, Paul Bollenback on guitar and Gene Jackson on drums. At 7:30 and 9:30, with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow night, Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $25; $20 on Sunday. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BEN RILEY'S MONK LEGACY SEPTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ben Riley, one of the most buoyant drummers ever to serve in Thelonious Monk's employ, honors that pianist and composer's memory with this rock-solid septet, stocked with players like the trumpeter Don Sickler and the saxophonists Wayne Escoffery and Bruce Williams. At 9 and 11, Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JENNY SCHEINMAN (Tuesday) Ms. Scheinman is that rare jazz violinist who embraces her instrument's folksier side without making concessions to genre. Her Tuesday night engagement features different players each week; this time around, the cast includes the guitarist Steve Cardenas and the drummer Scott Amendola. At 7 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ELLIOTT SHARP PLAYS MONK (Thursday) On his most recent album -- ''Sharp? Monk? Sharp! Monk!'' (Clean Feed) -- Mr. Sharp transports Thelonious Monk's pianistic topography to the strings and fretboard of his acoustic guitar. At 8:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* SONGS MADE TO BE PLAYED: PIANISTS AND THEIR PIECES (Tomorrow) Dick Hyman presents a handsome tribute to an honor roll of pianist-composers, including Erroll Garner, Eddie Heywood, Fats Waller and Bill Evans. The evening's pianistic interpreters, in addition to Mr. Hyman, are Barry Harris, Ted Rosenthal, Judy Carmichael, Derek Smith and Jon Weber; its bassist is Nicki Parrott, and its drummer is Willie Jones III. At 8 p.m., 92nd Street Y, 1395 Lexington Avenue, (212) 415-5500, 92y.org; $45. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TIN HAT (Tonight) Celebrating the recent release of an album called ''The Sad Machinery of Spring'' (Hannibal/Rykodisc), this professionally eclectic improvising chamber group explores its broad tonal palette onstage; in addition to Carla Kihlstedt, a violinist and founding member, the group will include Ben Goldberg on clarinets and Zeena Parkins on harp. At 7:30 and 9:30, Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, symphonyspace.org; $25; $17 for members; $10 rush tickets. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* CHARLES TOLLIVER BIG BAND (Tuesday through Thursday) The trumpeter Charles Tolliver recently ended a long, dry spell of public appearances with this band, an upgraded edition of his hard-driving orchestra of the '70s. This engagement celebrates the release of a strong album, ''With Love'' (Blue Note), that seals Mr. Tolliver's comeback with a kiss. (Through Feb. 3.) At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JAMES (BLOOD) ULMER (Tonight through Sunday night) Mr. Ulmer's singing and guitar playing describe an oddly hypnotic combination of influences: Ornette Coleman's polytonality crossed with the psychedelic swagger of Jimi Hendrix. He performs here with a group that includes the keyboardist Amina Claudine Myers and the drummer Aubrey Dale. At 8:30 and 10:30, with a midnight set tonight and tomorrow night, Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>WARREN VACHÉ (Tonight) Mr. Vaché is a trumpeter and cornetist well versed in the deep traditions of his instrument; he's at his best in sparse settings like this one, with Nicki Parrott on bass and Vincent Corrao on guitar. At 7, Rubin Museum of Art, 150 West 17th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 620-5000, Ext. 344, www.rmanyc.org; $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* RANDY WESTON (Tonight) Now in his 80s, Mr. Weston has a warm and rippling touch at the piano, and a style that reflects a grasp of pan-African folk traditions, including the blues. He performs a solo recital at Fazioli Salon, a series at the Klavierhaus piano workshop. At 8 p.m., Klavierhaus, 211 West 58th Street, Manhattan, (212) 245-4535, pianoculture.com; $30. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* CASSANDRA WILSON (Tomorrow) Before she was a honey-toned earth mother, Ms. Wilson jostled around the funkier regions of the contemporary jazz avant-garde. She allows an echo of that experience here, with cohorts including the alto saxophonist Steve Coleman, the drummer Dafnis Prieto and the pianist Jason Moran. At 8 and 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>'CAVALLERIA RUSTICANA' AND 'PAGLIACCI' (Tonight and Tuesday) Those deathless twin barnburners return to the Metropolitan Opera tonight. In ''Cavalleria,'' Dolora Zajick will strike the match. Look for Salvatore Licitra's Canio in ''Pagliacci.'' Tonight at 8, Tuesday night at 7:30, Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $110 to $205 tickets remaining tonight, $15 to $175 on Tuesday. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>'JENUFA' (Monday) Grand operas make their living off unhappy love, but few are as sincerely heart-wrenching as this Janacek masterpiece. Karita Mattila returns in the title role. At 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $15 to $175. (Holland)</p>
        <p>* 'IL SIGNOR BRUSCHINO' (Sunday, Tuesday and Thursday) Mention Rossini, and most people come up with ''The Barber of Seville,'' but this work -- in which the composer honed the comic gift that came to the fore in ''Barber'' and other opera buffe -- hasn't been staged in New York since 1933. The Gotham Chamber Opera has set itself apart among the city's small opera companies with quality performances of lesser-known operas (with good singers), conducted by the company's founder, Neal Goren. Robin Guarino directs the company's performance of this frothy piece of fun. Sunday at 2 p.m., Tuesday and Thursday at 8 p.m., Abrons Arts Center, 466 Grand Street, at Pitt Street, Lower East Side, (212) 279-4200, gothamchamberopera.org; $30 to $65. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>* 'LA TRAVIATA' (Tomorrow and Thursday) The soprano Hei-Kyung Hong gives a beautifully sung and deeply felt portrayal of Violetta in the Met revival of Verdi's ''Traviata,'' in Franco Zeffirelli's extravagant 1998 production. The other news is the promising performance of an artist who, like Ms. Hong, is from South Korea: the tenor Wookyung Kim, singing Alfredo in his Met debut season. As a Verdi tenor, Mr. Kim is a little green, but he has an appealing and robust voice, and at his best, sings with ardor and flair. The baritone Charles Taylor, who was ill on opening night, sings Germont. Carlo Rizzi conducts. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; sold out tomorrow, $15 to $175 on Thursday. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>BARGEMUSIC (Tonight through Sunday) Tonight the likable critic and musicologist Maya Pritsker is host of a piano recital by Alexander Korsantia, who will play Haydn, Stravinsky and Mussorgsky at Bargemusic, Brooklyn's floating concert hall. Tomorrow and Sunday the Amernet Quartet offers Mozart, Grieg and the first New York performances of a Quintet for Bassoon and String Quartet by another critic, Russell Platt, whose day job is at The New Yorker. Tonight and tomorrow night at 7:30, Sunday at 4 p.m., Fulton Ferry Landing, Brooklyn, (718) 624-4061, bargemusic.org. Tonight and tomorrow, $35; $30 for 65+; $20 for students. Sunday, $40; $25 for students. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>DA CAPO CHAMBER PLAYERS (Sunday) This superb new-music ensemble looks at the Second Viennese School and its more modern adherents in a program that includes Schoenberg's Chamber Symphony, Eisler's Duo for Violin and Cello, Berg's Four Pieces, George Perle's ''Night Song,'' Milton Babbitt's ''None but the Lonely Flute'' and a new work by Kati Agocs. At 8 p.m., Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, Manhattan, (212) 501-3330, dacapochamberplayers.org; $20; $10 for students and 65+. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* 'DECASIA' (Tonight and tomorrow night) The composer Michael Gordon and the filmmaker Bill Morrison have collaborated on this enveloping multimedia work. Mr. Morrison's contribution is a fast-cut montage of antique films, in which bubbles and other signs of decay create patterns as crucial to the work as the images of cowboys, flappers, factory workers, dancers, parachutists and the exotic Middle East and North Africa. Mr. Gordon's powerful 65-minute score -- played by an orchestra deployed in the balconies -- evolves from a faint, metallic rattle to a barrage of percussion, electric guitars, brass choirs, woodwinds and strings. At 7 and 9:30, Orensanz Center for the Arts, 172 Norfolk Street, Lower East Side, (212) 352-3101; $25. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>DAVID FINCKEL AND WU HAN (Tuesday) This cello-piano, husband-wife duo are customarily to be found on the Upper West Side running the Chamber Music Society of Lincoln Center, but on Tuesday they cross town for a recital at the Morgan Library &amp; Museum's spiffy new recital hall. The program includes Schubert's heavenly ''Arpeggione'' Sonata. At 7:30 p.m., 225 Madison Avenue, at 36th Street, (212) 685-0008, themorgan.org; $45. (Holland)</p>
        <p>* FOCUS FESTIVAL (Tonight, and Monday through Thursday) The Juilliard School's annual new-music festival turns its sights this year on Hungarian music since Bartok. A few of the composers -- Gyorgy Kurtag, Gyorgy Ligeti, Peter Eotvos and Istvan Marta, for example -- are already forceful presences in the world of chamber music. But the festival's longtime director, Joel Cohen, invariably turns up a number of worthy newcomers. At 8, Peter Jay Sharp Theater, 155 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 769-7406, juilliard.edu; free, but tickets are required for tonight's concert. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>SUSAN GRAHAM (Monday) An eloquent interpreter of a large repertory, from German Classicism to contemporary American music, this American mezzo-soprano is devoting her recital at Carnegie Hall to French art song, with works by Bizet, Franck, Fauré, Lalo, Gounod, Debussy, Chausson, Duparc, Ravel, Messiaen, Honegger, Poulenc and others. At 8 p.m., (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $25 to $80. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>HAMBURG SYMPHONY ORCHESTRA (Tonight and tomorrow night) The Hamburg Symphony, founded in 1957, is not to be confused with the Hamburg Philharmonic or the Norddeutscher Rundfunk Symphony Orchestra, based in the same city, which will come to Carnegie Hall in March. This one, led by Andrey Boreyko, is embarking on its first United States tour and will make its New York debut tonight in a program of Mendelssohn's ''Hebrides'' Overture, Brahms's Second Symphony and Tchaikovsky's Violin Concerto, with the soloist Robert McDuffie. Tomorrow the Brahms and Tchaikovsky are on the program at the Tilles Center. Tonight at 8, Metropolitan Museum of Art, (212) 570-3949, metmuseum.org; $40. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Tilles Center for the Performing Arts, at the C. W. Post campus of Long Island University, Brookville, N.Y., (516) 299-3100, tillescenter.org; $48 to $90. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>ISRAEL PHILHARMONIC (Tuesday and Thursday) This orchestra, founded in 1936 and originally named the Palestine Orchestra, begins its 70th-anniversary celebrations with a United States tour. On Tuesday Lorin Maazel, who was named an honorary life member of the orchestra in 1985, will conduct the program, which features Beethoven's Violin Concerto with the stellar violinist Maxim Vengerov as soloist, Beethoven's ''Leonore'' Overture No. 3 and Mussorgsky's ''Pictures at an Exhibition.'' On Thursday Zubin Mehta, the Philharmonic's music director, leads a program including Berlioz's ''Symphonie Fantastique'' and Mahler's Rückert Lieder with Thomas Hampson, a baritone. Tuesday at 8 p.m., Thursday at 7 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $45 to $125. (Vivien Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* MOSCOW SOLOISTS (Sunday) The violist and conductor Yuri Bashmet will lead his Moscow Soloists in orchestral arrangements of chamber works. Mahler arranged Schubert's ''Death and the Maiden'' Quartet and Beethoven's String Quartet in F minor (Op. 95), the so-called ''Quartetto Serioso,'' to attract a larger audience for these pieces, then considered esoteric. The program also includes Britten's ''Lachrymae,'' based on a song by John Dowland (which Britten initially wrote for piano and viola and later arranged for orchestra), and Schnittke's ''Monologue.'' At 2 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $23 to $75. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* 'MOZART AT 251' (Tomorrow) For years, Uri Caine, a jazz player and musical polyglot, has intelligently deconstructed music by classical composers with a blend that might include jazz, bossa nova, klezmer and tango. Having already reimagined Bach's ''Goldberg'' Variations and Beethoven's ''Diabelli'' Variations, he now turns to Mozart. The program opens with a ''pure'' reading of Mozart's Divertimento in E flat (K. 563), by the cellist Matt Haimovitz, the violinist Jonathan Crow and the violist Douglas McNabney. Then Mr. Haimovitz will join Mr. Caine, the clarinetist Chris Speed, the bassist Drew Gress and others for a renegade Mozartian jam session. At 8 p.m., Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, Manhattan, (212) 501-3330, ekcc.org; $30 in advance, $35 at the door. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC (Tonight and tomorrow night) The Italian maestro Riccardo Muti has also fared well with the New York Philharmonic. His first of two programs last week was predictably distinguished. This weekend he conducts an unusual all-Italian program, beginning with the Piano Concerto No. 2 by Giuseppe Martucci (1856-1909), a conductor, pianist and composer much admired in his day. This 1886 concerto was taken up by noted conductors, including Mahler and Toscanini. Gerhard Oppitz will be the soloist. Mr. Muti will also conduct ''Feste Romane'' by Ottorino Respighi, who was a composition student of Martucci's, and the ballet music from Verdi's ''Macbeth.'' On Thursday Esa-Pekka Salonen arrives in his dual roles as conductor and composer. His program includes the premiere of his Piano Concerto, a Philharmonic commission, with Yefim Bronfman as soloist. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Thursday at 7:30 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nyphil.org; $28 to $96. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>OBERLIN CONSERVATORY SYMPHONY ORCHESTRA (Tonight) Robert Spano, the energetic music director of the Atlanta Symphony Orchestra, leads the Oberlin Conservatory Symphony Orchestra in a concert that includes Jennifer Higdon's ''Blue Cathedral.'' Mr. Spano has championed this appealing work, which is performed more regularly than most new pieces, and recorded it in 2004 with the Atlanta Symphony. The program also includes Bartok's Concerto for Orchestra and Mozart's Piano Concerto No. 25 in C (K. 503), with the pianist Pedja Muzijevic. At 8, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $20; $5 for students. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>GARRICK OHLSSON (Sunday) This past summer the American pianist Garrick Ohlsson, an exciting virtuoso as well as an artist of integrity, presented acclaimed cycles of the complete 32 Beethoven piano sonatas at the Ravinia and Tanglewood festivals. Beginning Sunday, he performs the first of three Beethoven sonata programs at Lincoln Center. The opener offers two well-known sonatas, the ''Pathétique'' and the ''Appassionata,'' along with two inventive, bracing early sonatas, No. 6 in F and No. 11 in B flat. The latter is a score the composer was especially pleased with. At 2 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $50. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>ST. LAWRENCE STRING QUARTET (Monday) This energetic Canadian quartet helped open the Baryshnikov Arts Center last season and returns to that loftlike space to play works including Schumann's Quartet Op. 41, No. 2, and Shostakovich's searing Quartet No. 8. At 7 p.m., 450 West 37th Street, Manhattan, (212) 218-7540, baryshnikovdancefoundation.org; free, but reservations are required. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* JOHN SCOTT (Sunday) Having just started a cycle of the complete organ works of Buxtehude, Mr. Scott, the organist and director of music at St. Thomas Church, focuses on Ligeti for a day. He opens the Miller Theater's two-part ''Remembering Ligeti'' mini-festival with a concert offering the rare and exciting chance to hear his complete organ works. Alongside Ligeti's ''Ricercare: Omaggio a Frescobaldi'' (1953), Two Études (1967-69) and ''Volumina'' (1962-66), Mr. Scott will perform Jonathan Harvey's ''Fantasia'' (1991), Toccata for organ and tape (1980) and ''Laus Deo'' (1969). At 5:15 p.m., Fifth Avenue at 53rd Street, (212) 854-7799, millertheater.com; free. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* 'THE SONG CONTINUES' (Tonight) The Marilyn Horne Foundation winds up its annual mini-festival dedicated to the art of song with a gala concert called ''Gypsy in My Soul,'' featuring Ms. Horne as its host and a quartet of singers and a guest artist who's more Sicilian than Gypsy, the tenor Marcello Giordani, as performers. The wide-ranging program includes the world premieres of two pieces the foundation commissioned from Gabriela Lena Frank, as well as songs by Brahms, Vaughn Williams, Dvorak and Turina. At 7:30, Zankel Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $37 and $45. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>VOX VOCAL ENSEMBLE (Tomorrow) George Steel has been exploring Tudor church music for the last several years, both in his programming for the Miller Theater and on the podium of the Vox Vocal Ensemble, his virtuoso choir. In the latest installment of that exploration, sponsored by Miller but performed in the acoustically more amenable Church of St. Mary the Virgin, Mr. Steel leads his Vox group in settings of parts of the Lamentations of Jeremiah by Byrd, Tallis, White, Mundy and Parsley. At 8 p.m., 145 West 46th Street, Manhattan, (212) 854-7799, millertheater.com; $35; $21 for students. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>AFRO-BRAZILIAN MUSIC &amp; DANCE (Tonight) The New York-based Ologunde company celebrates the Afro-Brazilian culture of Salvador, Bahia, in a program that includes the candomble, capoeira, maculele and samba da roda. At 8, Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 545-7536 or 212 864-5400, worldmusicinstitute.org; $27; $15 for students. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>* ASPEN SANTA FE BALLET (Tonight through Sunday) The troupe will perform Twyla Tharp's rarely seen ''Sweet Fields'' and new works by Jorma Elo and Nicolo Fonte. Tonight at 8; tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m.; Sunday at 2 p.m. Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800 or Joyce.org; $42. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* JANIS BRENNER &amp; GUESTS (Thursday) Janis Brenner will celebrate a quarter-century in dance with her own choreography and an excerpt from ''Porcelain Dialogues'' by Murray Louis, which will be performed by Nikolais-Louis company alumni, including Ms. Brenner, Robert Small and Sara Pearson. (Through Feb. 4.) At 8:30 p.m., Danspace Project at St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194 or danspaceproject.org; $20 or T.D.F. vouchers (Dunning)</p>
        <p>ANDREA DEL CONTE DANZA ESPANA (Tonight through Sunday night) This program of flamenco dance will feature the dancer Marco De Ana and the fusion band Gazpacho Andalú. At 8, Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, between Houston and Prince Streets, (212) 334-7479, joyce.org; $28; $25 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* EVIDENCE: A DANCE COMPANY (Tuesday through Thursday) Ronald K. Brown and his Evidence troupe will present two programs. The first includes his new ''Truth Don Die,'' which tells the story of a Nigerian preacher whose holy words do not die with him and is set to music by Omotayo Wunmi Olaiya, Me Shell Ndegeocello and Femi Kuti. It also includes ''Order My Steps'' and Mr. Brown's signature ''Grace.'' The second program includes ''Ebony Magazine,'' ''Better Days'' and ''Upside Down.'' (Through Feb. 4.) Tuesday and Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. (first program), Thursday at 8 p.m. (second program), Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800, joyce.org; $38. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* MARTHA GRAHAM DANCE COMPANY (Tomorrow) A new generation of dancers, but what they perform is the mother-lode of American modern dance, still cutting through to the human heart with remarkable immediacy. At 8 p.m., Performing Arts Center, Purchase College, 735 Anderson Hill Road, Purchase, N.Y., (914) 251-6200; $45 to $65. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* TRAJAL HARRELL (Tonight through Sunday) Mr. Harrell has become known for authoritatively oddball choreography and visual design. His latest work is ''Showpony,'' in which he examines vogueing, postmodernism and the fashion spectacle and muses on his own choice to be part of a performing culture. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8:30, Sunday at 7:30 p.m. (followed by a discussion with the artists). Danspace Project at St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194, danspaceproject.org; $15 or T.D.F. voucher. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>'MODERN MOVEMENT: A WINTER DANCE SAMPLER' (Tomorrow) The participants in this nicely varied program include the Rebecca Stenn/Perks Dance Theater, Carolyn Dorfman Dance Company, Nicolas Andre Dance Theater and Julian Barrett. At 8 p.m., JCC in Manhattan, 334 Amsterdam Avenue, at 76th Street, (646) 505-5708; $20. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* MARK MORRIS DANCE GROUP (Tonight and tomorrow night) Welcome 2007 a little late with a celebratory program of dances by Mark Morris that includes ''Italian Concerto,'' set to Bach, and ''The Argument,'' ''Sang-Froid'' and ''Love Song Waltzes.'' At 7:30, Mark Morris Dance Center, 3 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place (across the street from the Brooklyn Academy of Music), Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (212) 352-3101, mmdg.org; sold out. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE OF WEST AFRICA (Tomorrow) The program features the polyphonic drumming and dancing of the Wolof people of Senegal, performed by the Sing Sing Rhythms and the Fula Flute Ensemble. At 8 p.m., Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, worldmusicinstitute.org; $27; $15 for students. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* NEW YORK CITY BALLET (Tonight through Sunday, and Tuesday through Thursday) The company is getting the jump on a spring-season celebration of Lincoln Kirstein with ''Tribute to Kirstein'' tomorrow and Wednesday nights. It was Kirstein who made City Ballet happen by coaxing George Balanchine to the United States. The program includes ''Episodes,'' ''Vienna Waltzes'' and a piece by Christopher d'Amboise. Other programs for the week include ''Tradition and Innovation'' (''Mozartiana,'' ''In Vento'' and Tchaikovsky's Piano Concerto No. 2) tonight; ''Stravinsky and Balanchine: an Eternal Partnership'' (''Agon,'' ''Monumentum pro Gesualdo,'' ''Movements for Piano and Orchestra,'' ''Duo Concertant'' and ''Symphony in Three Movements'') on Sunday; and ''Essential Balanchine'' (''Square Dance,'' ''Liebeslieder Walzer'' and ''Stars and Stripes'') on Tuesday and Thursday. Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 3 p.m., Tuesday and Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m. New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 870-5570, nycballet.com; $30 to $82. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>LAURA PETERSON CHOREOGRAPHY (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ms. Peterson, who has danced with everyone from Risa Jaroslow to Poppo and the GoGo Boys, describes her new ''I Love Dan Flavin'' as a tongue-in-cheek futuristic dance with fluorescent light and pioneering techno music. At 8, Dixon Place, 258 Bowery, between Houston and Prince Streets, Lower East Side, (212) 219-0736, Ext. 11, dixonplace.org; $15 or T.D.F. vouchers; $12 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>PHILADANCO (Sunday) This veteran modern-dance company is known for its high-powered performing and choice repertory of work by black choreographers. At 3 p.m., Lehman Center for the Performing Arts, Lehman College, 250 Bedford Park Boulevard West, at Goulden Avenue, Bedford Park, the Bronx, (718) 960-8833, lehmancenter.org; $20 to $35. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>RAGAMALA MUSIC AND DANCE THEATER (Tomorrow) The company will perform ''From Temple to Theater,'' which includes both traditional Bharata Natyam dances and contemporary choreography. At 7:30 p.m., Colden Auditorium, Kupferberg Center for the Arts, Queens College, Kissena Boulevard and the Long Island Expressway, Flushing, (718) 793-8080, kuperferbergcenter.org; $12. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* TAMAR ROGOFF'S 'EDITH &amp; JENNY' (Tonight through Sunday) Ms. Rogoff's piece alludes to the childhood friendship of her daughter, Ariel Rogoff Flavin, and Claire Danes, who trained in dance before becoming a film actress, as well as roles each played as 11-year-olds in films by Jeff Mueller. (Through Feb. 4.) Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 5 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 5 p.m., Performance Space 122, 150 First Avenue, at Ninth Street, East Village, (212) 477-5288, ps122.org; $20; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* STATE BALLET THEATER OF RUSSIA (Tonight) The great Russian ballet dancer Vladimir Vasiliev has choreographed a new production of ''Cinderella,'' set to the familiar Prokofiev score. At 7:30, New Jersey Performing Arts Center, 1 Center Street, Newark, N.J., (888) 466-5722, njpac.org; $20 to $58. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>TAKE DANCE COMPANY (Thursday) Takehiro Ueyama, a former Paul Taylor dancer, is becoming known for gutsy, well-plotted dances, here set to music by composers and groups that include Bach, Arvo Pärt and the Southern All Stars. (Through Feb. 4.) At 8 p.m., Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, between Houston and Prince Streets, (212) 334-7479, joyce.org; $20; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>'TWO: DUETS' (Tonight and tomorrow night) Chosen by Nicki Marshall and Helen Styring Tocci, five pairs of dance artists explore the intimacy and colliding energies of the duet form. At 8, WOW Cafe Theater, 59 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 777-4280; $15; $12 for students and artists. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>ANTONIETTA VICARIO MAKES DANCES (Tonight through Sunday) Ms. Vicario, who has worked with choreographers including John Jasperse and Yvonne Meier, will present a new full-evening piece called ''I cannot escape being me so that is what I will show you,'' which explores conventional notions of sexuality. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 3 p.m., Dance New Amsterdam, 280 Broadway, at Chambers Street, TriBeCa, (212) 279-4200, ticketcentral.com; $17. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Art Fairs</p>
        <p>53RD ANNUAL WINTER ANTIQUES SHOW, through Sunday. Mature is the word in the trade for fairs like the Winter Antiques Show, though time-honored, even venerable, would be closer to the mark. The show has been around forever (well, since 1955). It delivers substantial, sometimes spectacular, retail. Dealers and clients alike return, like swallows to Capistrano, year after year. So if solid tradition, rather than Basel-Miami-style blowouts, is what you want in a fair, this one's for you. Seventh Regiment Armory, 643 Park Avenue, at 67th Street, (718) 292-7392. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* American Museum of Natural History: 'GOLD,' through Aug. 19. This astounding array of art, artifacts and natural samples -- larded with fascinating facts and tales -- ranges from prehistoric times to the present. Stops along the way include pre-Columbian empires, sunken treasure and the moon landing. It turns out that gold comes from the earth in forms as beautiful as anything man has thought to do with it. Central Park West and 79th Street, (212) 769-5100, amnh.org. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>* GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'Spanish Painting from El Greco to Picasso, TIME, TRUTH, AND HISTORY' through March 28. This show is carried along on its sheer star power and optical finesse. There are dozens of Goyas and Velázquezes and Zurbaráns and El Grecos and Riberas and Dalís and Picassos, many famous, many not. I can't tell you how often I was stopped by a picture so good or unexpected that it made me do a double take. Velázquez's painting of a dwarf is alone worth crossing a continent to see. 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3500, guggenheim.org. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL CENTER OF PHOTOGRAPHY: 'HENRI CARTIER-BRESSON'S SCRAPBOOK: PHOTOGRAPHS, 1932-46,' through April 29. This show has more than 300 of the prints Henri Cartier-Bresson glued into an album and toted to New York for curators at the Museum of Modern Art to cull. Captured by the Nazis, he had been presumed dead when the Modern planned his retrospective. Then he turned up alive -- the ''posthumous'' exhibition opened, with him in attendance, in 1947. The current exhibition reconstructs as best as possible the original layout of the scrapbook. It's an eye-straining affair, but it surveys the revolutionary work he shot in Spain, Italy, Mexico, Britain and France. Here are the familiar, and, more interestingly, some less familiar, shots of crowds in Hyde Park in London at George VI's coronation, of picnickers on the banks of the Marne in France and whores in Valencia, Spain. His taste for uncanny detail linked him to Surrealism and Surrealist wit, but unlike many Surrealists, he remained committed to human values. Boys mug at his camera. Prostitutes swan. Their gazes equalize them with us. 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000, icp.org. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL CENTER OF PHOTOGRAPHY: 'MARTIN MUNKACSI: THINK WHILE YOU SHOOT!' through April 29. Munkacsi, who inspired Cartier-Bresson, was, by contrast, self-taught, a creature of his own devising. This is the most complete retrospective, with a thick catalog (not too well researched) and dozens of vintage prints from the 1920s through the early '60s. He favored scenes of daily life, absorbing avant-garde ideas about odd angles and abstract compositions. Munkacsi was a stylist, and he made catchy images the only way he knew how, in a modernist mode, which, being an opportunistic form, could serve any master. (See above.) (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* THE METROPOLITAN MUSEUM OF ART: 'GLITTER AND DOOM: GERMAN PORTRAITS FROM THE 1920S,' through Feb. 19. The 100 paintings and drawings on display here are by 10 artists, including George Grosz, Christian Schad, and Karl Hubbuch, and most conspicuously the unrelentingly savage Otto Dix and his magnificent other, Max Beckmann. In their works the Weimar Republic's porous worlds reassemble; we look into the faces of museum directors and cabaret performers, society matrons and scarred war veterans, prostitutes and jaded aristocrats who were watching their world slide from one cataclysm to the next. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* THE MET: 'ONE OF A KIND: THE STUDIO CRAFT MOVEMENT,' through Sept. 3. Focusing on the postwar development of artist-craftsmen, this display of furniture, glass, ceramics, metalwork, jewelry and fiber includes funny, quirky, provocative and sometimes gorgeous things. Among its stars are a witty bust by the California funk ceramicist Robert Arneson (1920-92) portraying the mother of the 16th-century painter and printmaker Albrecht Durer; and Bonnie Seeman's fetching ceramic coffeepot and tray, whose mock cabbage leaves and rhubarb stalks evoke the genteel tradition of 18th-century British and Continental china, but can also be read as human rather than vegetative tissue. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>* MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'DOUG AITKEN: SLEEPWALKERS,' through Feb. 12. Produced in concert with Creative Time Inc., this monumental video projection, screened nightly (from 5 to 10) on three sides of the sleek exterior of the newly expanded Museum of Modern Art, consists of short, silent and rather too glamorous meditations on the working nights of five emblematic New Yorkers played somnolently by musicians and actors who include Donald Sutherland and Tilda Swinton. But Mr. Aitken's astute and restless cinematic ambition and commanding sense of scale are in full force, especially in the more abstract portions of the piece, resulting in a fitting ode to the city that never sleeps and that the camera has always loved. (212) 708-9400, daily. (Smith)</p>
        <p>WHITNEY MUSEUM OF AMERICAN ART: 'KIKI SMITH: A GATHERING, 1980-2005,' through Feb. 11. Many things fly and float here: men and women, harpies and angels, birds and beasts, toadstools and stars. And some things fall to earth, or rather to the museum's black stone floors, maybe to rise again, maybe not. The whole show, a midcareer retrospective, suggests a Victorian fairy tale, its tone at once light, grievous and dreamlike. But fanciful as it is, Ms. Smith's art is also deeply, corporeally realistic. It wears moral and mortal seriousness on its sleeve, if not tattooed on its wrist. It is about life and death, the essential things. 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676, whitney.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>* ROBERT IRWIN: 'WHO'S AFRAID OF RED, YELLOW AND BLUE 3' In the past, Robert Irwin has paid homage to Joseph Albers. Now he makes a bow to a different kind of perceptual magician, Barnett Newman, turning Newman's 1966-70 paintings titled ''Who's Afraid of Red, Yellow and Blue'' into a kind of self-reflective architecture. Optical illusionism has long been Mr. Irwin's calling card, but here he has achieved it by bare-bones means, offering quieting visual fare for an overstimulated world. PaceWildenstein, 545 West 22nd Street, (212) 989-4258, pacewildenstein.com, through Feb. 3 . (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* PORTIA MUNSON: GREEN On the floor, all manner of discarded plastic objects and cheap toys coalesce into a dense scatter piece that commemorates the fall of nature, the rise of suburbia and the varied tonalities of indigenous if artificial green. On the walls, exquisite mille-fleur-like color photographs made on a scanner redirect set-up photography back toward the experimental nature prints and photogenic drawings of the 19th century. P.P.O.W., 555 West 25th Street, (212) 647-1043, through Feb. 3. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* BRONX MUSEUM OF THE ARTS: 'TROPICALIA: A REVOLUTION IN BRAZILIAN CULTURE,' Tropicalia, or Tropicalism, wasn't a style or a movement as much as an atmosphere, a rush of youthful, cosmopolitan, liberating optimism that broke over Brazil in the late 1960s like a sun shower, and soaked into everything -- art, music, film, theater and architecture -- until a military government clamped down. This show is an attempt to recapture the moment's fugitive spirit, and with the presence of artists like Helio Oiticica and Lygia Clark, the architect Lina Bo Bardi, and musicians like Gilberto Gil and Caetano Veloso, it comes close. 1040 Grand Concourse, at 165th Street, Morrisania, (718) 681-6000, bronxmuseum.org; closes on Sunday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'TIGERS OF WRATH: WATERCOLORS BY WALTON FORD,' This show assembles more than 50 of Mr. Ford's large-scale watercolors of birds, animals, snakes and lushly exotic flora, produced since the early '90s. They frequently depict moments in which a wild animal encounters human culture, often to its detriment. Sometimes the threat is overt, as in pictures of animals and birds roped or wounded; in other images the sense is that some horrible violence has occurred or is about to. Though they're wonderfully lucid and dramatic, the moralizing of these images can become a little tedious. But this popular artist imparts an environmental message, couched in a lament for the irreversible loss that occurs when a sense of ethics does not govern the treatment of animals. 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, Brooklyn (718) 638-5000, brooklynmuseum.org; closes on Sunday. (Benjamin Genocchio)</p>
        <p>* 'THE CONSTANT POSSIBILITY OF ERASURE' Organized by Donna Harkavy and Gracie Mansion, this excellent group show is at once witty and elegaic, exploring transience as an existential reality and as a conceptual ploy in late-20th-century art. Robert Rauschenberg's 1953 ''Erased de Kooning'' is an important reference point, present through Mike Bidlo's painstaking recreation. Joseph Beuys, Gary Simmons and Christian Xarec all have chalk pieces on blackboards, while Allan Kaprow preferred drawing, and simultaneously erasing, chalk pictures on the sidewalks or streets. Joanne Stamerra Hendricks uses erasers as a medium, and Jim Dingilian uses smoke. Dorsky Gallery Curatorial Projects, 11-03 45th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 937-6317; closes on Monday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* 'THE EARLY WORK OF WILLIAM KING' The spindly figure sculptures by William King that we know best have arms like I-beams, legs like stilts, and heads that are barely there. But his early work looks quite different, and that's the revelation of this absorbing show, assembled by the art critic Sanford Schwartz at Alexandre Gallery. Much of the material is hand-size or toy-size and comes in a variety of forms and media, and most of it is being exhibited for the first time. Alexandre Gallery, 41 East 57th Street, (212) 755-2828; closes tomorrow. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* FRICK COLLECTION: 'MASTERPIECES OF EUROPEAN PAINTING FROM THE CLEVELAND MUSEUM OF ART,' This exhibition transcends the usual traveling masterpieces-from genre, with room to spare. The 14 paintings include almost always outstanding works by household names like Velázquez, Caravaggio, El Greco, Turner and Poussin, as well as Annibale Carracci, Francisco de Zurbarán and Andrea del Sarto. But the astute installation makes the most of all this star power, letting the works talk among themselves to a remarkable degree, illuminating their likenesses, differences and collective progress. Extending John Berger's famous title, the show might be called ''Ways of Seeing Paintings.'' 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700; closes on Sunday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>THE MET: 'AMERICANS IN PARIS: 1860-1900,' The Americanization of the world may be a done deal now, but not so long ago the United States was a buyer rather than a seller of cultural information, and France was a major source between the Civil War and World War I. That's the story told in this exhibition that goes a little way toward reversing the fall season's trend of big, surveyish shows made up of splashy objects and bland ideas. In this case, the basic ideas, though undeveloped, are inherently interesting, and the art, with some notable exceptions, is conservative and staid. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org; closes on Sunday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'MANET AND THE EXECUTION OF MAXIMILIAN,' This gripping show reminds us of Modernism's mutinous, myth-scouring origins. And it does so by bringing one of art's great path-cutters, Edouard Manet, onto the scene, wry, politically infuriated and painting like Lucifer. There's not a lot of him here -- eight paintings, three on a single theme: the death by firing squad of the Austrian archduke Ferdinand Maximilian in Mexico in 1867. But it's enough. Manet's images, surrounded by a riveting selection of prints and photographs, are electrifying. (212) 708-9400, www.moma.org; closes on Monday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>NEWARK MUSEUM, THE JEWISH MUSEUM: 'MASTERS OF AMERICAN COMICS'  Organized by the Hammer Museum and the Museum of Contemporary Art in Los Angeles, where it made a splash, this show has come east, cut in size and split between the far-flung Newark and Jewish museums, in which it looks cramped. Art Spiegelman, one of the masters who helped instigate the exhibition, felt so aggrieved by the circumstances that at nearly the 11th hour he pulled his work. This was a pity, for the obvious reasons, and also because the Jewish Museum scrambled to fill the gap he left by appending a half-baked display of superhero comic artists. Still, the show shouldn't be missed. It spotlights artists like Chris Ware and Gary Panter, amazing talents and endearing in the tradition of those shy, gifted kids who drew endlessly in their roomswhen other kids wouldn't play with them, dreaming about someday telling the world, ''I told you so.'' Newark Museum, 49 Washington Street, (973) 596-6550, newarkmuseum.org; and the Jewish Museum, 1109 Fifth Avenue, at 92nd Street, (212) 423-3200, thejewishmuseum.org; closes on Sunday. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>P.S. 1 CONTEMPORARY ART CENTER: 'MUSIC IS A BETTER NOISE' An involvement of some sort with music is the main criterion for this disparate but engaging show. The artist-musicians on hand include Jutta Koether, the rapper Rammellzee, Don Van Vliet (a k a Captain Beefheart) and Devendra Banhart. Chuck Naney contributes a beautiful sound-light installation in the stairwell, and Rodney Graham tries his hand at music video. 22-25 Jackson Avenue, at 46th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 784-2084, ps1.org; closes on Monday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>RUBIN MUSEUM OF ART: 'I SEE NO STRANGER: EARLY SIKH ART AND DEVOTION,' Sikhism is the world's fifth-largest organized religion, but how many Westerners know that it was conceived as universalist in scope and radically egalitarian socially? Or that its holy book, far from being a catalog of sectarian dos and don'ts, is a bouquet of poetic songs blending the fragrances of Hindu ragas, Muslim hymns, and Punjabi folk tunes? This is precisely the information delivered by this small and beautiful show. Vivid and concentrated, it presents, mostly through miniature paintings, a kind of Sikh self-portrait, the image of a history shaped by hard work, pluralism and mystical transport, as well as by militancy. 150 West 17th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 620-5000, rmanyc.org; closes on Monday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>THE WHITNEY MUSEUM OF AMERICAN ART: 'PICASSO AND AMERICAN ART,' Despite the glamorous pictures in it, this is one of those dull affairs incubated in the world of academe: a walk-through slide show that states the obvious. Picasso's ''Woman in White,'' a picture of heavenly arrogance, hangs between Arshile Gorky's ''Artist and His Mother'' and de Kooning's ''Standing Man,'' terrific paintings too. We are meant to register the plain insinuation of Picasso's neo-Classicism, then move on. The show ends not with the lively question of Picasso's impact on young artists today but with a virtual retrospective of the later, Picasso-inspired works by Jasper Johns. In picture after picture, Johns buries allusions to the great Spaniard, aspiring presumably to Picasso's own late meditations on Velázquez. Except that even when he was old and running out of steam, Picasso still had joie de vivre. Johns doesn't so much enthrone Picasso as repeatedly entomb him; closes on Sunday. (See above.) (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>Correction:  January 27, 2007, Saturday  A classical music entry in the Listings pages of Weekend yesterday about the Juilliard School's Focus Festival misstated the surname of the festival's longtime director. He is Joel Sachs, not Cohen.</p>
        <p>Correction:  January 30, 2007, Tuesday  A classical music entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on Jan. 19 misstated the history of the performance in New York of ''Il Signor Bruschino,'' by Rossini, which the Gotham Chamber Orchestra is performing through Saturday. The Gotham Chamber Orchestra's production is the first professional staging of the work in New York since 1933, not the first staging since then. (The error was repeated in a Week Ahead entry in Arts &amp; Leisure on Jan. 21, in the Listings pages of Weekend on Friday and in a review of a performance on Saturday.)</p>
        <p>Correction:  February 1, 2007, Thursday  A classical music entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on Jan. 19 misstated the history of the performance in New York of ''Il Signor Bruschino,'' by Rossini, which is being performed in New York through Saturday. The current production is the first professional staging of the work in New York since 1933, not the first staging since then. (The error was repeated in a Week Ahead entry in Arts &amp; Leisure on Jan. 21, in the Listings pages of Weekend on Friday and in a review of a performance on Saturday.) A correction in this space on Tuesday misstated the name of the group that is currently presenting the work, at the Abrons Arts Center on the Lower East Side. It is the Gotham Chamber Opera, not Orchestra.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: January 27, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>A classical music entry in the Listings pages of Weekend yesterday about the Juilliard School's Focus Festival misstated the surname of the festival's longtime director. He is Joel Sachs, not Cohen.</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>Correction: January 30, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A classical music entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on Jan. 19 misstated the history of the performance in New York of ''Il Signor Bruschino,'' by Rossini, which the Gotham Chamber Orchestra is performing through Saturday. The Gotham Chamber Orchestra's production is the first professional staging of the work in New York since 1933, not the first staging since then. (The error was repeated in a Week Ahead entry in Arts &amp; Leisure on Jan. 21, in the Listings pages of Weekend on Friday and in a review of a performance on Saturday.)</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>Correction: February 1, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>A classical music entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on Jan. 19 misstated the history of the performance in New York of ''Il Signor Bruschino,'' by Rossini, which is being performed in New York through Saturday. The current production is the first professional staging of the work in New York since 1933, not the first staging since then. (The error was repeated in a Week Ahead entry in Arts &amp; Leisure on Jan. 21, in the Listings pages of Weekend on Friday and in a review of a performance on Saturday.) A correction in this space on Tuesday misstated the name of the group that is currently presenting the work, at the Abrons Arts Center on the Lower East Side. It is the Gotham Chamber Opera, not Orchestra.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
