<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spare Times: Jan. 26-Feb. 1</title>
    <meta content="26spar" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1821430"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EFD8163FF935A15752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1924" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spare Times: Jan. 26-Feb. 1</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Around Town</p>
        <p>Museums and Sites</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY, Central Park West and 79th Street. Sunday, ''Living in America: Streets of Gold,'' the last of three events in conjunction with the ''Gold'' exhibition, featuring a panel discussion on hardships endured by a group of Chinese immigrants (2 p.m.); and a performance of South African music and dance (4 p.m.) Through May 28, ''The Butterfly Conservatory: Tropical Butterflies Alive in Winter,'' a display with hundreds of butterflies in a re-creation of their natural habitat. In the Imax theater, ''Roving Mars,'' a film about NASA's Mars Rover. Timed tickets to ''Gold'' and ''The Butterfly Conservatory,'' which include museum admission, are $21; $16 for students and 60+; $12 for 12 and younger. Imax tickets, which include museum admission, are $21; $16 for students and 60+; $12 for children under 12. Suggested museum admission: $14; $10.50 for students and 60+; children, $8. Combination tickets, including museum and Rose Center admission and the Hayden Planetarium space show (''Cosmic Collisions''): $22; $16.50 for students and 60+; $13 for 12 and younger; under 2, free. Admission that includes all activities: $30; $23 for students and 60+; $19 for 12 and younger. Museum hours: daily, 10 a.m. to 5:45 p.m. (to 8:45 p.m. on Fridays). (212) 769-5100 or (212) 769-5200; amnh.org.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF THE CITY OF NEW YORK, Fifth Avenue at 103rd Street. Through Sunday, ''It's in the Bag,'' more than 100 purses from the museum's costume collection, some dating to the 18th century. Sunday at 2 p.m., ''The Future of Black Fashion,'' a discussion with fashion designers and writers, co-sponsored by Essence Magazine, in conjunction with the exhibition ''Black Style Now,'' on view through Feb. 19. Opening Thursday, ''Robert Moses and the Modern City: Remaking the Metropolis,'' one of three exhibitions dedicated to Moses at cultural institutions in the city; the others are at the Queens Museum of Art and the Wallach Art Gallery at Columbia University. In conjunction with the exhibition, on Thursday at 5:30 p.m., ''Robert Moses and the Modern City,'' a symposium with city officials, writers and others, at the New York Academy of Medicine, 1216 Fifth Avenue, near 102nd Street; $20 ($10 for members); reservations requested, (212) 534-1672, Ext. 3395. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Suggested admission: $9; $5 for students and 62+; free for children under 12; $20 for families; free on Sundays, 10 a.m. to noon. (212) 534-1672, mcny.org.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF THE MOVING IMAGE, 36-01 35th Avenue, Astoria, Queens. Tonight at 7:30, ''Your Career in Animation,'' a seminar with producers, designers and animators, featuring a panel discussion, screenings and a book signing; $10; $7.50 for college students; $5 for those 5 to 18; and free for members. Hours: Wednesdays and Thursdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Fridays, noon to 8 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6:30 p.m.; and by appointment. Films and videos, unless noted, are free with admission: $10; 65+ and students, $7.50; 5 to 18, $5; free for members and children 4 and younger; free for everyone on Fridays from 4 to 8 p.m. Friday night screenings require admission. (718) 784-0077, movingimage.us.</p>
        <p>NEW-YORK HISTORICAL SOCIETY, 2 West 77th Street, Manhattan. Through May 20, ''Carry Me Home: Dispatches From the Civil War,'' an exhibition of letters, photographs and other documents that illustrate first-hand accounts of the war from the front lines. Tuesday at 5:30 p.m., a lecture by Robert E. Bonner, an author and Civil War historian. Monday at 6:30 p.m., the basketball great Kareem Abdul-Jabbar will discuss his book ''On the Shoulders of Giants.'' Fee for each lecture, $15; $10 for students, educators and 65+; $8 for members. Through Sept. 3, ''New York Divided: Slavery and the Civil War,'' a display of historical documents, photographs, political cartoons and other items. Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; to 8 p.m. on Fridays. $10; $7 for educators and 65+; $6 for students; free for those under 12. (212) 873-3400; nyhistory.org.</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>BENEFIT ART AUCTION AND PARTY, Cue Art Foundation, 511 West 25th Street, Chelsea. Tuesday, 6:30 to 9:30 p.m., silent and live auctions, with much of the proceeds, along with ticket sales, to benefit the 2007-8 exhibition season. $75. (212) 206-3583; cueartfoundation.org.</p>
        <p>'INSIDE THE GRAND LODGE OF NEW YORK,' 71 West 23rd Street, Chelsea. Tomorrow at 11 a.m., a tour of the Masonic lodge designed by Percy Knowles, meeting at the lodge. Sponsored by the Municipal Art Society. $15; $12 for members. (212) 935-3960.</p>
        <p>92ND STREET Y, 1395 Lexington Avenue. Tomorrow night at 8:45, an Israeli folk dance marathon; $15. Tuesday at 1 p.m., a tour of Gracie Mansion, followed by a tea in the grand ballroom, meeting at the mansion, East End Avenue at 88th Street; $35; photo ID and advance registration required: (212) 415-5500.</p>
        <p>NATIONAL BLACK FINE ART SHOW, Puck Building, 295 Lafayette Street, SoHo. Thursday through Feb. 4. Featuring more than 35 international exhibitors. Thursday, noon to 8 p.m. $15 admission includes show catalog; $10 for students; $35 for three-day pass. (212) 925-5275; blackfineartshow.com.</p>
        <p>UNITED STATES CUSTOM HOUSE TOUR Sunday at 2 p.m., a tour of this historic Lower Manhattan building, meeting on the northwest corner of Broadway and Battery Place. Sponsored by Bernie's New York. $10. (718) 655-1883.</p>
        <p>WATSON ADVENTURES Tomorrow at 5:30 p.m., ''The Murder at the Met Hunt,'' a search for a curator's murderer at the Metropolitan Museum of Art. Fee: $39, including museum admission. Meeting place and reservations: (877) 946-4868.</p>
        <p>THIRD ANNUAL BROOKLYN ISRAEL FILM FESTIVAL, Kane Street Synagogue, 236 Kane Street, Cobble Hill, Brooklyn. Tomorrow night at 8, a screening of the documentary ''39 Pounds of Love,'' directed by Dani Menkin, followed by a discussion with Mr. Menkin. Sunday at 7 p.m., the feature film ''Out of Sight, directed by Daniel Syrkin''; a discussion follows with its screenwriter, Noa Greenberg. $10 per screening at the door. (718) 875-1550.</p>
        <p>ELEVENTH NEW YORK SEPHARDIC JEWISH FILM FESTIVAL, Center for Jewish History, 15 West 16th Street, Flatiron district, and the JCC in Manhattan, 334 Amsterdam Avenue, at 76th Street. Opens Thursday night at 7 at the Center for Jewish History with a screening of ''Three Mothers'' by Dina Zvi-Riklis, introduced by the filmmaker. $10; $8 for members and students; $40 for a festival pass. Through Feb. 8. (212) 294-8350; americansephardifederation.org.</p>
        <p>HOME ENERGY SMART FAIR, Gateway National Recreation Area, Fort Wadsworth Visitor Center, Bay Street and School Road, Staten Island. Tomorrow at 10 a.m., programs and exhibitions demonstrating energy-efficient systems for home owners. Free. Sponsored by the Friends of Gateway, the National Park Service and the New York State Energy Research and Development Authority. (212) 228-3126.</p>
        <p>Spoken Word</p>
        <p>CARRERE &amp; HASTINGS LECTURE, Woodlawn Cemetery, Woolworth Chapel, Bainbridge and Jerome Avenues, Norwood, the Bronx. Sunday at 2 p.m., a lecture on this architectural firm, whose works include designs in the cemetery, by Charles D. Warren, one of the authors of a new two-volume set about the architects. Free. Sponsored by Friends of Woodlawn Cemetery. (718) 920-1469.</p>
        <p>'WHAT IS THE FUTURE OF THEATERS ON BROADWAY?,' Municipal Art Society of New York, Urban Center, 457 Madison Avenue, at 51st Street. Monday at 6:30 p.m., a panel discussion with representatives from major Broadway production companies. Free, but reservations requested: (212) 935-2075.</p>
        <p>TRIBUTE TO PRIMO LEVI, Istituto Italiano di Cultura, 686 Park Avenue, at 68th Street. Monday at 6 p.m., a panel discussion about Levi in commemoration of the 62nd anniversary of the liberation of Auschwitz (actual date, Jan. 27, 1945), where he was imprisoned in 1944; participants include Roald Hoffmann, the 1981 Nobel Prize winner in chemistry, and Oliver Sacks, the scientist and writer. Free, but reservations requested: (212) 879-4242, Ext. 371.</p>
        <p>GALWAY KINNELL 80TH-BIRTHDAY GALA, Cooper Union, 7 East Seventh Street, East Village. Thursday night at 7, a free reading in celebration of this Pulitzer Prize-winning poet, with E. L. Doctorow, Mark Doty, Edward Hirsch, Cornelius Eady, Grace Paley, Gerald Stern, and Mr. Kinnell. (212) 353-4195.</p>
        <p>ARTISTS, PRINTERS AND PUBLISHERS FORUM, Grolier Club of New York, 47 East 60th Street, Manhattan. Wednesday night at 6, a forum in conjunction with ''Hot Off the Press: Prints of 2006 from New York Printshops,'' which illustrates the collaboration of 50 artists with master printers in the area; on view through Feb. 3. Free, but limited seating. (212) 838-6690.</p>
        <p>INSTITUTE OF CLASSICAL ARCHITECTURE &amp; CLASSICAL AMERICA, 20 West 44th Street, Manhattan. Wednesday night at 7, a discussion on Swedish design, by Johan Cederlund and Lani Sternerup, authors of ''Classical America Series on Art and Architecture.'' Also sponsored by the General Society of Mechanics and Tradesmen. $10; free for members of the Institute and Society. Reservations: (212) 730-9646, Ext. 109.</p>
        <p>SUNDAY MORNING COFFEE CONCERTS, Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center. One-hour concerts with postperformance discussions with musicians. Sunday at 11 a.m., the Parker String Quartet. Tickets, $20, are available at the Alice Tully and Avery Fisher Hall box offices or through CenterCharge; (212) 721-6500.</p>
        <p>Walking Tours</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS CLUB Tomorrow at 10:30 a.m., a 12-mile walk from Coney Island, Brooklyn, to Chinatown, via the Brooklyn Bridge, meeting at Nathan's Famous, 1310 Surf Avenue, and ending with an optional dinner; (212) 242-5384. $3.</p>
        <p>MUNICIPAL ART SOCIETY Sunday at 2 p.m., ''Central Park in Winter,'' meeting at the General Sherman statue in Columbus Circle, Fifth Avenue and 59th Street. $15; $12 for members. (212) 935-3960.</p>
        <p>BIG ONION WALKING TOURS Tomorrow at 1 p.m., ''The 'Official' Gangs of New York Tour,'' meeting at City Hall Park, on the southeast corner of Broadway and Chambers Street, Lower Manhattan. $15; $12 for 63+; $10 for students and New-York Historical Society members. (212) 439-1090.</p>
        <p>'CANNONS TO CATACOMBS; A WALK THROUGH FORT TOTTEN'S MILITARY HISTORY' Tomorrow at 2 p.m. and Sunday at 1 p.m., free tours of a Civil War-era fortress, meeting north of the entrance at 212th Street and the Cross Island Parkway, Queens. Led by the Urban Park Rangers. Information: 311.</p>
        <p>GO TELL IT ON THE MOUNTAIN Sunday at 1 p.m., a free hike with the Urban Park Rangers in the Greenbelt of Staten Island atop Moses Mountain, created with landfill during the building of the Staten Island Expressway. Meets in the Visitors' Parking Lot at the end of Nevada Avenue. Information: 311.</p>
        <p>ADVENTURE ON A SHOESTRING Tomorrow at 2:30 p.m., ''A Salute to President Franklin D. Roosevelt,'' with a walk in Murray Hill in celebration of the 125th anniversary of his birth (on Jan. 30), meeting on the northeast corner of Madison Avenue and 34th Street. $5. (212) 265-2663.</p>
        <p>'HELL'S KITCHEN-A-POPPIN; THEN AND NOW,' Sunday at 11 a.m., the residential, business and theatrical histories of the area, meeting on the northwest corner of Ninth Avenue and 59th Street. Sponsored by Bonnie's Lost New York Walks and Talks. $15. (212) 594-8039.</p>
        <p>CENTRAL PARK CONSERVANCY Free weekend tours of Central Park. Tomorrow at 1 p.m., a ''Cross-Park Promenade'' meets at the statue of Samuel F. B. Morse, at Fifth Avenue and 72nd Street. Sunday at 1 p.m., ''Seneca Village'' covers one of the earliest communities of black American property owners, meeting on the southeast corner of Central Park West and 85th Street. centralparknyc.org.</p>
        <p>METRO TOUR SERVICE Today and tomorrow at 2 p.m., Brooklyn Heights, Fort Greene and Clinton Hill, Brooklyn. Sunday at 3 p.m., a gospel tour. Meet in front of the Marriott Hotel, Adams and Tillary Streets, downtown Brooklyn. $25. (718) 789-0430.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Around Town</p>
        <p>Museums and Sites</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY, Central Park West and 79th Street. Sunday, ''Living in America: Streets of Gold,'' the last of three events in conjunction with the ''Gold'' exhibition, featuring a panel discussion on hardships endured by a group of Chinese immigrants (2 p.m.); and a performance of South African music and dance (4 p.m.) Through May 28, ''The Butterfly Conservatory: Tropical Butterflies Alive in Winter,'' a display with hundreds of butterflies in a re-creation of their natural habitat. In the Imax theater, ''Roving Mars,'' a film about NASA's Mars Rover. Timed tickets to ''Gold'' and ''The Butterfly Conservatory,'' which include museum admission, are $21; $16 for students and 60+; $12 for 12 and younger. Imax tickets, which include museum admission, are $21; $16 for students and 60+; $12 for children under 12. Suggested museum admission: $14; $10.50 for students and 60+; children, $8. Combination tickets, including museum and Rose Center admission and the Hayden Planetarium space show (''Cosmic Collisions''): $22; $16.50 for students and 60+; $13 for 12 and younger; under 2, free. Admission that includes all activities: $30; $23 for students and 60+; $19 for 12 and younger. Museum hours: daily, 10 a.m. to 5:45 p.m. (to 8:45 p.m. on Fridays). (212) 769-5100 or (212) 769-5200; amnh.org.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF THE CITY OF NEW YORK, Fifth Avenue at 103rd Street. Through Sunday, ''It's in the Bag,'' more than 100 purses from the museum's costume collection, some dating to the 18th century. Sunday at 2 p.m., ''The Future of Black Fashion,'' a discussion with fashion designers and writers, co-sponsored by Essence Magazine, in conjunction with the exhibition ''Black Style Now,'' on view through Feb. 19. Opening Thursday, ''Robert Moses and the Modern City: Remaking the Metropolis,'' one of three exhibitions dedicated to Moses at cultural institutions in the city; the others are at the Queens Museum of Art and the Wallach Art Gallery at Columbia University. In conjunction with the exhibition, on Thursday at 5:30 p.m., ''Robert Moses and the Modern City,'' a symposium with city officials, writers and others, at the New York Academy of Medicine, 1216 Fifth Avenue, near 102nd Street; $20 ($10 for members); reservations requested, (212) 534-1672, Ext. 3395. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Suggested admission: $9; $5 for students and 62+; free for children under 12; $20 for families; free on Sundays, 10 a.m. to noon. (212) 534-1672, mcny.org.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF THE MOVING IMAGE, 36-01 35th Avenue, Astoria, Queens. Tonight at 7:30, ''Your Career in Animation,'' a seminar with producers, designers and animators, featuring a panel discussion, screenings and a book signing; $10; $7.50 for college students; $5 for those 5 to 18; and free for members. Hours: Wednesdays and Thursdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Fridays, noon to 8 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6:30 p.m.; and by appointment. Films and videos, unless noted, are free with admission: $10; 65+ and students, $7.50; 5 to 18, $5; free for members and children 4 and younger; free for everyone on Fridays from 4 to 8 p.m. Friday night screenings require admission. (718) 784-0077, movingimage.us.</p>
        <p>NEW-YORK HISTORICAL SOCIETY, 2 West 77th Street, Manhattan. Through May 20, ''Carry Me Home: Dispatches From the Civil War,'' an exhibition of letters, photographs and other documents that illustrate first-hand accounts of the war from the front lines. Tuesday at 5:30 p.m., a lecture by Robert E. Bonner, an author and Civil War historian. Monday at 6:30 p.m., the basketball great Kareem Abdul-Jabbar will discuss his book ''On the Shoulders of Giants.'' Fee for each lecture, $15; $10 for students, educators and 65+; $8 for members. Through Sept. 3, ''New York Divided: Slavery and the Civil War,'' a display of historical documents, photographs, political cartoons and other items. Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; to 8 p.m. on Fridays. $10; $7 for educators and 65+; $6 for students; free for those under 12. (212) 873-3400; nyhistory.org.</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>BENEFIT ART AUCTION AND PARTY, Cue Art Foundation, 511 West 25th Street, Chelsea. Tuesday, 6:30 to 9:30 p.m., silent and live auctions, with much of the proceeds, along with ticket sales, to benefit the 2007-8 exhibition season. $75. (212) 206-3583; cueartfoundation.org.</p>
        <p>'INSIDE THE GRAND LODGE OF NEW YORK,' 71 West 23rd Street, Chelsea. Tomorrow at 11 a.m., a tour of the Masonic lodge designed by Percy Knowles, meeting at the lodge. Sponsored by the Municipal Art Society. $15; $12 for members. (212) 935-3960.</p>
        <p>92ND STREET Y, 1395 Lexington Avenue. Tomorrow night at 8:45, an Israeli folk dance marathon; $15. Tuesday at 1 p.m., a tour of Gracie Mansion, followed by a tea in the grand ballroom, meeting at the mansion, East End Avenue at 88th Street; $35; photo ID and advance registration required: (212) 415-5500.</p>
        <p>NATIONAL BLACK FINE ART SHOW, Puck Building, 295 Lafayette Street, SoHo. Thursday through Feb. 4. Featuring more than 35 international exhibitors. Thursday, noon to 8 p.m. $15 admission includes show catalog; $10 for students; $35 for three-day pass. (212) 925-5275; blackfineartshow.com.</p>
        <p>UNITED STATES CUSTOM HOUSE TOUR Sunday at 2 p.m., a tour of this historic Lower Manhattan building, meeting on the northwest corner of Broadway and Battery Place. Sponsored by Bernie's New York. $10. (718) 655-1883.</p>
        <p>WATSON ADVENTURES Tomorrow at 5:30 p.m., ''The Murder at the Met Hunt,'' a search for a curator's murderer at the Metropolitan Museum of Art. Fee: $39, including museum admission. Meeting place and reservations: (877) 946-4868.</p>
        <p>THIRD ANNUAL BROOKLYN ISRAEL FILM FESTIVAL, Kane Street Synagogue, 236 Kane Street, Cobble Hill, Brooklyn. Tomorrow night at 8, a screening of the documentary ''39 Pounds of Love,'' directed by Dani Menkin, followed by a discussion with Mr. Menkin. Sunday at 7 p.m., the feature film ''Out of Sight, directed by Daniel Syrkin''; a discussion follows with its screenwriter, Noa Greenberg. $10 per screening at the door. (718) 875-1550.</p>
        <p>ELEVENTH NEW YORK SEPHARDIC JEWISH FILM FESTIVAL, Center for Jewish History, 15 West 16th Street, Flatiron district, and the JCC in Manhattan, 334 Amsterdam Avenue, at 76th Street. Opens Thursday night at 7 at the Center for Jewish History with a screening of ''Three Mothers'' by Dina Zvi-Riklis, introduced by the filmmaker. $10; $8 for members and students; $40 for a festival pass. Through Feb. 8. (212) 294-8350; americansephardifederation.org.</p>
        <p>HOME ENERGY SMART FAIR, Gateway National Recreation Area, Fort Wadsworth Visitor Center, Bay Street and School Road, Staten Island. Tomorrow at 10 a.m., programs and exhibitions demonstrating energy-efficient systems for home owners. Free. Sponsored by the Friends of Gateway, the National Park Service and the New York State Energy Research and Development Authority. (212) 228-3126.</p>
        <p>Spoken Word</p>
        <p>CARRERE &amp; HASTINGS LECTURE, Woodlawn Cemetery, Woolworth Chapel, Bainbridge and Jerome Avenues, Norwood, the Bronx. Sunday at 2 p.m., a lecture on this architectural firm, whose works include designs in the cemetery, by Charles D. Warren, one of the authors of a new two-volume set about the architects. Free. Sponsored by Friends of Woodlawn Cemetery. (718) 920-1469.</p>
        <p>'WHAT IS THE FUTURE OF THEATERS ON BROADWAY?,' Municipal Art Society of New York, Urban Center, 457 Madison Avenue, at 51st Street. Monday at 6:30 p.m., a panel discussion with representatives from major Broadway production companies. Free, but reservations requested: (212) 935-2075.</p>
        <p>TRIBUTE TO PRIMO LEVI, Istituto Italiano di Cultura, 686 Park Avenue, at 68th Street. Monday at 6 p.m., a panel discussion about Levi in commemoration of the 62nd anniversary of the liberation of Auschwitz (actual date, Jan. 27, 1945), where he was imprisoned in 1944; participants include Roald Hoffmann, the 1981 Nobel Prize winner in chemistry, and Oliver Sacks, the scientist and writer. Free, but reservations requested: (212) 879-4242, Ext. 371.</p>
        <p>GALWAY KINNELL 80TH-BIRTHDAY GALA, Cooper Union, 7 East Seventh Street, East Village. Thursday night at 7, a free reading in celebration of this Pulitzer Prize-winning poet, with E. L. Doctorow, Mark Doty, Edward Hirsch, Cornelius Eady, Grace Paley, Gerald Stern, and Mr. Kinnell. (212) 353-4195.</p>
        <p>ARTISTS, PRINTERS AND PUBLISHERS FORUM, Grolier Club of New York, 47 East 60th Street, Manhattan. Wednesday night at 6, a forum in conjunction with ''Hot Off the Press: Prints of 2006 from New York Printshops,'' which illustrates the collaboration of 50 artists with master printers in the area; on view through Feb. 3. Free, but limited seating. (212) 838-6690.</p>
        <p>INSTITUTE OF CLASSICAL ARCHITECTURE &amp; CLASSICAL AMERICA, 20 West 44th Street, Manhattan. Wednesday night at 7, a discussion on Swedish design, by Johan Cederlund and Lani Sternerup, authors of ''Classical America Series on Art and Architecture.'' Also sponsored by the General Society of Mechanics and Tradesmen. $10; free for members of the Institute and Society. Reservations: (212) 730-9646, Ext. 109.</p>
        <p>SUNDAY MORNING COFFEE CONCERTS, Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center. One-hour concerts with postperformance discussions with musicians. Sunday at 11 a.m., the Parker String Quartet. Tickets, $20, are available at the Alice Tully and Avery Fisher Hall box offices or through CenterCharge; (212) 721-6500.</p>
        <p>Walking Tours</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS CLUB Tomorrow at 10:30 a.m., a 12-mile walk from Coney Island, Brooklyn, to Chinatown, via the Brooklyn Bridge, meeting at Nathan's Famous, 1310 Surf Avenue, and ending with an optional dinner; (212) 242-5384. $3.</p>
        <p>MUNICIPAL ART SOCIETY Sunday at 2 p.m., ''Central Park in Winter,'' meeting at the General Sherman statue in Columbus Circle, Fifth Avenue and 59th Street. $15; $12 for members. (212) 935-3960.</p>
        <p>BIG ONION WALKING TOURS Tomorrow at 1 p.m., ''The 'Official' Gangs of New York Tour,'' meeting at City Hall Park, on the southeast corner of Broadway and Chambers Street, Lower Manhattan. $15; $12 for 63+; $10 for students and New-York Historical Society members. (212) 439-1090.</p>
        <p>'CANNONS TO CATACOMBS; A WALK THROUGH FORT TOTTEN'S MILITARY HISTORY' Tomorrow at 2 p.m. and Sunday at 1 p.m., free tours of a Civil War-era fortress, meeting north of the entrance at 212th Street and the Cross Island Parkway, Queens. Led by the Urban Park Rangers. Information: 311.</p>
        <p>GO TELL IT ON THE MOUNTAIN Sunday at 1 p.m., a free hike with the Urban Park Rangers in the Greenbelt of Staten Island atop Moses Mountain, created with landfill during the building of the Staten Island Expressway. Meets in the Visitors' Parking Lot at the end of Nevada Avenue. Information: 311.</p>
        <p>ADVENTURE ON A SHOESTRING Tomorrow at 2:30 p.m., ''A Salute to President Franklin D. Roosevelt,'' with a walk in Murray Hill in celebration of the 125th anniversary of his birth (on Jan. 30), meeting on the northeast corner of Madison Avenue and 34th Street. $5. (212) 265-2663.</p>
        <p>'HELL'S KITCHEN-A-POPPIN; THEN AND NOW,' Sunday at 11 a.m., the residential, business and theatrical histories of the area, meeting on the northwest corner of Ninth Avenue and 59th Street. Sponsored by Bonnie's Lost New York Walks and Talks. $15. (212) 594-8039.</p>
        <p>CENTRAL PARK CONSERVANCY Free weekend tours of Central Park. Tomorrow at 1 p.m., a ''Cross-Park Promenade'' meets at the statue of Samuel F. B. Morse, at Fifth Avenue and 72nd Street. Sunday at 1 p.m., ''Seneca Village'' covers one of the earliest communities of black American property owners, meeting on the southeast corner of Central Park West and 85th Street. centralparknyc.org.</p>
        <p>METRO TOUR SERVICE Today and tomorrow at 2 p.m., Brooklyn Heights, Fort Greene and Clinton Hill, Brooklyn. Sunday at 3 p.m., a gospel tour. Meet in front of the Marriott Hotel, Adams and Tillary Streets, downtown Brooklyn. $25. (718) 789-0430.</p>
        <p>Information about events to be considered for inclusion in Spare Times can be sent to weekend@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Information about events to be considered for inclusion in Spare Times can be sent to weekend@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
