<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Change Comes, Gradually, To the San Francisco Opera</title>
    <meta content="27oper" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/27/arts/music/27oper.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1821701"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Music"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">San Francisco Opera</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Midgette, Anne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gockley, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pountney, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Verdi, Giuseppe (1813-1901)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Samson and Delilah (Opera)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Macbeth (Opera)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">San Francisco Opera</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Gockley, David</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Borodina, Olga</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE2DC173FF934A15752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="484" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Change Comes, Gradually, To the San Francisco Opera</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Change Comes, Gradually, to the San Francisco Opera</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE MIDGETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Midgette, Anne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Gockley, who became general director of San Francisco Opera in Jan 2006, announces what amounts to his first season; 2007-2008 season includes some works he did not choose, Samson and Delilah and David Pountney staging of Verdi's Macbeth, but he has instigated other nine productions; list of his productions seem somewhat conservative for his reputation, but in world of opera change can often be slow as talent needs to be booked years in advance; other productions for season noted (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Significant changes are happening in America's opera landscape as new directors take over some of the country's major companies. But in a field in which artists are booked several years in advance, it takes a while for season programs to reflect those changes.</p>
        <p>This week David Gockley, who became general director of the San Francisco Opera in January 2006, announced what amounts to his first season. Not quite all of the 2007-8 season is his: he has inherited the opening production, ''Samson and Delilah'' (with Olga Borodina), and David Pountney's Zurich staging of Verdi's ''Macbeth'' (with Thomas Hampson). But he has at least instigated the other nine productions, although most are co-productions with other companies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>David Gockley, the new director, begins to make his presence felt, with moderation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Significant changes are happening in America's opera landscape as new directors take over some of the country's major companies. But in a field in which artists are booked several years in advance, it takes a while for season programs to reflect those changes.</p>
        <p>This week David Gockley, who became general director of the San Francisco Opera in January 2006, announced what amounts to his first season. Not quite all of the 2007-8 season is his: he has inherited the opening production, ''Samson and Delilah'' (with Olga Borodina), and David Pountney's Zurich staging of Verdi's ''Macbeth'' (with Thomas Hampson). But he has at least instigated the other nine productions, although most are co-productions with other companies.</p>
        <p>One highlight is already widely known: the world premiere of Philip Glass's ''Appomattox'' in October, upholding Mr. Gockley's reputation as a champion of contemporary American opera that he established during his more than 30 years in Houston. (New works by Stewart Wallace and Mark Adamo are reportedly planned for future seasons.)</p>
        <p>But the season is more conservative (or crowd-pleasing) than his reputation might indicate. It does include a ''Rake's Progress'' with the fine William Burden, which arrives in November/December in an international co-production by Robert Lepage -- once avant-garde, now embraced by everyone from Cirque du Soleil (''KÀ'') to the Metropolitan Opera (where he is working on the new ''Ring'' for 2010). And Rachel Portman's ''Little Prince,'' in the production that Francesca Zambello designed for its 2003 Houston world premiere, will come to the West Coast in a joint presentation with Cal Performances at Berkeley.</p>
        <p>But these hardly signal a future of cutting-edge modernity. In his repertory and casting choices Mr. Gockley is signaling that if he is taking a new road, it's broad and well paved, with lots of other traffic.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gockley said his program indicated ''a balance that goes from core musical values to international-quality casting to fresh productions and directors who are going to get us once again fascinated with these great works, but who I don't think are going to go in a direction that is going to be contrary to their essence.''</p>
        <p>Some of those directions are already familiar to East Coast audiences, or will be by the time they appear in the West, like Mary Zimmerman's ''Lucia di Lammermoor'' (with Natalie Dessay and Giuseppe Filianoti), which will open the Metropolitan Opera's 2007-8 season before traveling to San Francisco in June. Similarly, Ms. Zambello's ''Rheingold'' in June will kick off a new ''Ring'' cycle that already opened at the Washington Opera in March 2006.</p>
        <p>All new, by contrast, is a Graham Vick production of ''Tannhäuser'' (with Peter Seiffert) in September. Puccini's ''Rondine'' (with Angela Gheorghiu) and Maurice Sendak's production of ''The Magic Flute'' will round out the season.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gockley promises new announcements to come, particularly with regard to electronic media.</p>
        <p>''We're nipping at the heels of the Met,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Music</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
