<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Just Call It Airport Insecurity</title>
    <meta content="l20airport" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1820046"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3D91E30F933A15752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="520" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Just Call It Airport Insecurity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Letters from Harold Yasgur, Marci K Greenberg, Ari B Rubin, J B Lewis and Diane L Young describe incidents in which they unintentionally breached airport security without being detected; drawing (Kathryn Harrison Jan 15 Op-Ed)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In ''Once More Into the Security Breach'' (Op-Ed, Jan. 15), Kathryn Harrison describes how she was able to return to her plane at Newark Liberty International Airport to look for her wallet without being stopped.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In ''Once More Into the Security Breach'' (Op-Ed, Jan. 15), Kathryn Harrison describes how she was able to return to her plane at Newark Liberty International Airport to look for her wallet without being stopped.</p>
        <p>It boggles the mind to think that a person can walk onto a plane without detection, and go through checkpoints and alarmed doors without encountering security or airport personnel.</p>
        <p>This is an open invitation to those seeking to harm the public. An investigation is in order.</p>
        <p>Harold Yasgur  Hewlett, N.Y., Jan. 15, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I'm not surprised by Kathryn Harrison's security breach. In November, I went to La Guardia Airport for a flight to Orlando, Fla. I cleared security and headed down the concourse, checking my boarding pass for the gate number. I was shocked to see that the name on the pass was not my own.</p>
        <p>As it turned out, I was ticketed to fly out of Kennedy Airport and had mistakenly gone to La Guardia, where I checked my luggage and was given a boarding pass under another name at curbside check-in.</p>
        <p>My ID was ''checked'' against the name on this boarding pass at security, and I proceeded to the gate. But, they did get my lip gloss!</p>
        <p>Marci K. Greenberg  Winter Park, Fla., Jan. 15, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Less than a year ago, I reached into my backpack midflight from New York to Los Angeles and was horrified to find an eight-inch carving knife. I had placed the knife there the day before. It was my fault that I forgot to remove it, but how could the security workers miss it?</p>
        <p>With airport security procedures having become such an imposition on traveling, shouldn't we reconsider whether they are working?</p>
        <p>Ari B. Rubin  Venice, Calif., Jan. 15, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In 2004, I flew from Philadelphia to Dallas with a penknife in my pocket. It was my grandfather's, and I have carried it since my mother gave it to me after his passing almost 20 years ago.</p>
        <p>I hadn't flown since before 9/11 and did not think about the penknife until I approached the security gate.</p>
        <p>Realizing that my heedlessness could result in the loss of a precious family heirloom, I decided to say nothing and hope it would not be detected. It wasn't.</p>
        <p>Whether that is a happy ending to the story is debatable.</p>
        <p>J. B. Lewis  Winthrop, Me., Jan. 15, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I read Kathryn Harrison's article with a little smile on my face.</p>
        <p>I recently flew home from Washington, D.C. At the airport, my make-up and the little jar of fancy honey I was bringing home for my daughter were confiscated.</p>
        <p>They put me through the air-puff machine, swabbed my duffle bag down for residue, and carefully examined my laptop.</p>
        <p>Imagine my surprise as I was unpacking a bag at home and found an eight-inch lighter gizmo that we used on our last camping trip. So much for security.</p>
        <p>Diane L. Young  Rochester, Mich., Jan. 15, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
