<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seton Hall Drops Game After Losing A Starter</title>
    <meta content="20hoops" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1820082"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Georgetown University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seton Hall University</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E4D81E30F933A15752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="885" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seton Hall Drops Game After Losing A Starter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID PICKER</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Jan. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Georgetown University defeats Seton Hall University, 74-58; other men's college basketball results noted (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Seton Hall announced a heaping portion of bad news before Friday night's game against Georgetown. Its starting center and tallest player, the 6-foot-10 Grant Billmeier, was lost for the season.</p>
        <p>The Pirates never seemed to rebound -- literally and figuratively.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Seton Hall announced a heaping portion of bad news before Friday night's game against Georgetown. Its starting center and tallest player, the 6-foot-10 Grant Billmeier, was lost for the season.</p>
        <p>The Pirates never seemed to rebound -- literally and figuratively.</p>
        <p>Georgetown raced to an early lead and it dominated the boards in a 74-58 victory at Continental Arena.</p>
        <p>''I've been a head coach eight years, and I've never seen a stat where we got beat on the boards, 39 to 11,'' Seton Hall Coach Bobby Gonzalez said. ''We had one defensive rebound at halftime.''</p>
        <p>It got worse in the second half, when the Pirates (11-7, 3-3 Big East) managed only four rebounds.</p>
        <p>Georgetown (13-5, 3-2) had a significant height advantage. It started three players who were 6-8 or taller, including the 7-2 center Roy Hibbert. Seton Hall's tallest starter was Stan Gaines, who was listed at 6-7.</p>
        <p>Billmeier, a tri-captain, tore his left anterior cruciate ligament while playing defense during the opening minutes of Wednesday's 69-68 victory against Providence. He started 14 times this season and averaged 3.4 points and 3.4 rebounds a game.</p>
        <p>''He gives you 15, 20 minutes a night,'' Gonzalez said of Billmeier. ''He changes the rotation, he is a senior, he does play hard. He's a great energy guy. And so now you have one less body. It's a small team getting smaller.''</p>
        <p>John Garcia, at 6-9, became Seton Hall's tallest player. He came off the bench to grab three rebounds, which tied Paul Gause for the team high. Georgetown, which had been ranked eighth in the preseason but has fizzled out of the Top 25, had six players with at least three rebounds. DaJuan Summers had a game-high 10 rebounds and 17 points.</p>
        <p>''If I'm going to give this team anything, it's rebounds,'' Garcia said. ''I'm not going to make excuses.''</p>
        <p>Gonzalez hinted at an excuse anyway, saying that Seton Hall was fatigued from playing four games in nine days. And when the Hoyas raced to a 10-0 lead after just 2 minutes 10 seconds, the Pirates were not able to recover. They trailed, 34-21, at halftime and fell behind by as many as 20 points late in the game.</p>
        <p>Jonathan Wallace led Georgetown with a career-high 21 points, and he helped break down Seton Hall's full-court pressure and zone defense.</p>
        <p>''We handled their pressure better than I anticipated,'' Georgetown Coach John Thompson III said. ''Our guys were very poised and pretty attentive and seeing when their teammates were in trouble.''</p>
        <p>Brian Laing scored a team-high 19 points for the Pirates. But like five of his teammates, he had no rebounds.</p>
        <p>''We just didn't have the bodies and the energy and the juice to play a team like Georgetown tonight,'' Gonzalez said. ''It's just that simple.''</p>
        <p>LOYOLA, MD. 62, ST. PETER'S 55 -- Michael Tuck made four free throws in the final 11 seconds and finished with 14 points as Loyola of Maryland beat host Saint Peter's.</p>
        <p>Gerald Brown and Marquis Sullivan also scored 14 points each for the Greyhounds (10-7, 6-1 Metro Atlantic Athletic Conference), and Brett Harvey had a game-high eight assists.</p>
        <p>Akeem Gooding had 16 points and 6 rebounds -- both game highs -- to lead the Peacocks (3-15, 1-7), who made just 37 percent of their shots. Kevin Spann added 12 points, and Todd Sowell finished with 11 and Raul Orta had 10.</p>
        <p>Loyola led for most of the game but had trouble putting away the Peacocks, who rallied late and tied the score at 55-55 when Brandon Brock hit a jumper with 56 seconds left.</p>
        <p>But the Greyhounds closed the game with a 7-0 run keyed by Tuck's free throws. (AP)</p>
        <p>FAIRFIELD 72, SIENA 67 -- Michael Van Schaick scored 27 points to lead Fairfield in a victory against host Siena.</p>
        <p>Fairfield (5-15, 3-5 MAAC) rallied from a 9-point deficit with 5:32 remaining for the victory.</p>
        <p>Van Schaick tied the score at 66-66 with his fifth 3-pointer of the game with a minute left.</p>
        <p>After Kenny Hasbrouck missed a jumper for Siena, Van Schaick was fouled with 30 seconds left and converted both free throws.</p>
        <p>Siena (9-8, 5-3) had a chance to tie, but David Ryan missed the first of two free throws with 22 seconds left.</p>
        <p>After Jonathan Han made two free throws to put Fairfield up, 70-67, with 16 seconds to go, the Saints failed to get a shot off.</p>
        <p>Hasbrouck led the Saints with 23 points, and Michael Haddix had 14 points and 14 rebounds.</p>
        <p>Siena shot 46 percent from the field and 38 percent from 3-point range. The Saints limited the Stags to just 39 percent from the floor and 36 percent from long range. (AP)</p>
        <p>WOMEN</p>
        <p>MARYLAND 95, VIRGINIA 68 -- Crystal Langhorne had 17 points and 12 rebounds, Laura Harper had 21, and No. 3 Maryland bounced back from its first loss of the season by cruising past visiting Virginia.</p>
        <p>Kristi Toliver scored 20 points and Marissa Coleman added 16 for the Terrapins (19-1, 3-1 Atlantic Coast Conference), the defending national champions, who were coming off an 82-61 defeat at Duke on Saturday that dropped them from the top spot in the Associated Press poll.</p>
        <p>Lyndra Littles led Virginia (12-6, 2-2) with a career-high-tying 23points. The Cavaliers have lost fourin a row at Maryland. (AP)</p>
        <p>COLLEGES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
