<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Critic's Choice: New DVD's</title>
    <meta content="23dvd" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/23/movies/homevideo/23dvd.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070129T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1820799"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Critics Choice"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kehr, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anger, Kenneth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/DVD and Video</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">DVD (Digital Versatile Disk)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DVD (Digital Versatile Disk)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Criterion Collection</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E0DB1F30F930A15752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1029" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Critic's Choice: New DVD's</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New DVDs: ‘Films of Kenneth Anger’ and ‘Samurai Classics’</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dave Kehr</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kehr, Dave</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dave Kehr reviews DVD collections Films of Kenneth Anger, Volume I and Samurai Classics Remastered; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Films of Kenneth Anger, Volume 1</p>
        <p>Andy Warhol aside, Kenneth Anger may be the United States' best-known maker of experimental and avant-garde films. Yet though many Americans own or have at least taken a guilty, surreptitious leaf through ''Hollywood Babylon,'' Mr. Anger's famous if loosely researched compendium of film industry scandals, few have seen his movies: short works, shot on 16- and occasionally 35-millimeter film, that deal voluptuously in themes of sensual surrender, homoerotic desire and Devil worship.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kenneth Anger’s experimental films get a makeover on DVD. Plus, two Akira Kurosawa samurai films are remastered.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Films of Kenneth Anger, Volume 1</p>
        <p>Andy Warhol aside, Kenneth Anger may be the United States' best-known maker of experimental and avant-garde films. Yet though many Americans own or have at least taken a guilty, surreptitious leaf through ''Hollywood Babylon,'' Mr. Anger's famous if loosely researched compendium of film industry scandals, few have seen his movies: short works, shot on 16- and occasionally 35-millimeter film, that deal voluptuously in themes of sensual surrender, homoerotic desire and Devil worship.</p>
        <p>Beginning with his first widely screened film, the black-and-white ''Fireworks'' (1947), Mr. Anger's work has circulated through underground film societies and museum film departments, and briefly on VHS cassettes that did not do justice to his deeply saturated colors and seductively complex textures.</p>
        <p>Now, with Mr. Anger's 80th birthday coming up (Feb. 3), Fantoma Films has issued the first volume of Mr. Anger's collected work. The contents include ''Fireworks,'' ''Puce Moment'' (a color fragment from an unfinished feature released in 1949), ''Rabbit's Moon'' (1950), ''Eaux d'Artifice'' (1953) and the extended, ritualistic ''Inauguration of the Pleasure Dome'' (1954), which together cover about half of Mr. Anger's career. It's the friendlier half, with relatively little occult imagery (Mr. Anger is a disciple of the British mystic Aleister Crowley) and a great deal of pageantry.</p>
        <p>Two of the earliest, most fragile films, ''Fireworks'' and ''Rabbit's Moon,'' have been restored by the film archives of the University of California, Los Angeles. They have certainly never looked better in my memory, and all the films have been digitally scrubbed to remove many of the scratches and dust spots that are particularly distracting on 16 millimeter.</p>
        <p>With their veil of dirt and time removed, the Anger films no longer look as angrily marginal as they once did: these are extremely handsome films, designed and photographed with a discriminating eye. Though they traffic in many of the same tattered movie myths that would later turn into the delirious camp of Jack Smith's ''Flaming Creatures'' (1963) and Mike Kuchar's ''Sins of the Fleshapoids'' (1965), Mr. Anger, a child of Hollywood who appeared as a boy in William Dieterle and Max Reinhardt's Warner Brothers extravaganza, ''A Midsummer Night's Dream'' (1935), had the taste and the technical know-how to capture the hermetic world of silent film.</p>
        <p>''Fireworks,'' ''Rabbit's Moon'' and ''Eaux d'Artifice'' strive to capture the silvery textures of '20s nitrate film; the latter two are tinted in the dark blue that silent filmmakers used to indicate nighttime. ''Puce Moment'' anticipates the Technicolor epiphanies of Douglas Sirk in its opening sequence, as the unseen heroine shuffles through a collection of dresses from the 1920s (the legacy of Mr. Anger's grandmother, a studio costume designer), each more vibrantly colorful than the last.</p>
        <p>''Inauguration of the Pleasure Dome,'' the final and longest offering in this collection, is a ritual of initiation in which a magician, played by Mr. Anger, ingests a variety of substances that open the doors of his perception to a Day-Glo psychedelia very reflective of the 12 years between the first and final versions (1954 and 1966).</p>
        <p>The forthcoming second volume will presumably include ''Scorpio Rising'' (1963) and ''Kustom Kar Kommandos'' (1965), in which Mr. Anger found contemporary equivalents for the gods and monsters that haunted his dreams in the pop-culture forms of motorcycle gangs and street racers.</p>
        <p>The missing link between Caravaggio and Bruce Weber, Mr. Anger continues to astound and delight with imagery so luxuriant and mysterious that at times it feels almost frightening. Fantoma Films, $24.98, not rated.</p>
        <p>Samurai Classics Remastered</p>
        <p>The Criterion Collection has redressed an old wrong with new editions of ''Yojimbo'' (1961) and ''Sanjuro'' (1962), two samurai classics by Akira Kurosawa previously released by Criterion in flawed versions. The new transfers are anamorphic widescreen rather than letterbox releases; both have been digitally manipulated to bring out detail previously lost in shadows.</p>
        <p>As time passes, it is Kurosawa's genre films that seem to be gaining in stature (chief among them the superb ''Seven Samurai'' of 1956), while his more self-conscious art house efforts, like ''Ikiru'' (1952) and ''Red Beard'' (1965), fall away into the same graveyard of good intentions occupied by John Ford's non-westerns ''The Informer'' and ''The Long Voyage Home.''</p>
        <p>''Yojimbo,'' the story of a rogue samurai (Toshiro Mifune) who pits two rival gangs in a small town against each other while pretending to work for both sides, is as much a blatant rip-off of Dashiell Hammett's great noir novel ''Red Harvest,'' as Sergio Leone's pioneering spaghetti western ''For a Fistful of Dollars'' was a blatant rip-off of ''Yojimbo.'' Yet it was Kurosawa who successfully sued Leone, winning a piece of the profits of ''For a Fistful of Dollars'' as it went on to reshape the western in the late 1960s.</p>
        <p>''Sanjuro'' was reportedly rewritten to incorporate the comic cynicism of the unexpectedly successful ''Yojimbo,'' and if it is not quite as shapely and pointed a movie, it too has its sly, subversive moments.</p>
        <p>The two films, neither of which is rated, are available separately at $39.95 each, or together for $69.95.</p>
        <p>Also Out Today</p>
        <p>THE GUARDIAN -- The crusty Coast Guard veteran played by Kevin Costner gives some lessons in loyalty and self-sacrifice to the callow young recruit played by Ashton Kutcher. Andrew Davis, a director who's been at this for a while (''The Fugitive,'' 1993), guides a cast that includes Sela Ward and Melissa Sagemiller. Buena Vista Home Entertainment, $29.99, PG-13.</p>
        <p>SAW III: UNRATED WIDESCREEN EDITION -- That crafty moral philosopher, the Jigsaw Killer, once again poses this musical question: would you cut off your own leg if it meant escaping a hideous death? With Tobin Bell, Shawnee Smith and Angus Macfadyen; Darren Lynn Bousman directed. An R-rated edition is also available. Lionsgate, $29.95.</p>
        <p>THIS FILM IS NOT YET RATED -- The documentarian Kirby Dick (''Sick: The Life and Death of Bob Flanagan, Supermasochist'') takes a long, hard look at the occult process through which the Motion Picture Association of America determines which films are suitable for which audiences. Several filmmakers, including Darren Aronofsky, Kimberly Peirce and Mary Harron, describe their experiences with the ratings board. IFC, $24.95, unrated.</p>
        <p>Critics Choice</p>
        <p>Correction:  January 29, 2007, Monday  The Critic's Choice column on Tuesday, about new DVDs, referred imprecisely to the title of Sergio Leone's pioneering spaghetti western, which was modeled on Akira Kurosawa's ''Yojimbo.'' The Leone movie was released in the United States as ''A Fistful of Dollars'' and is known by that title -- not by ''For a Fistful of Dollars,'' which is a translation of the Italian title.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: January 29, 2007, Monday</p>
        <p>The Critic's Choice column on Tuesday, about new DVDs, referred imprecisely to the title of Sergio Leone's pioneering spaghetti western, which was modeled on Akira Kurosawa's ''Yojimbo.'' The Leone movie was released in the United States as ''A Fistful of Dollars'' and is known by that title -- not by ''For a Fistful of Dollars,'' which is a translation of the Italian title.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
