<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Subpoenas Sought Against 2 Times Reporters</title>
    <meta content="23time" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/23/business/media/23time.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1820859"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wiretapping and Other Eavesdropping Devices and Methods</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Times</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pellicano, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Halbfinger, David M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weiner, Allison Hope</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wiretapping and Other Eavesdropping Devices and Methods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Times</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pellicano, Anthony</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E6D91F30F930A15752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="446" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Subpoenas Sought Against 2 Times Reporters</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Subpoenas Sought Against 2 Times Reporters</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Defense lawyer in case involving Hollywood private eye Anthony Pellicano, accused of masterminding long-running wiretapping ring, calls for New York Times reporters David M Halbfinger and Allison Hope Weiner to be subpoenaed to find source of leaked conversations; New York Times says it will continue to fight to keep sources confidential (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A defense lawyer in the case involving Anthony Pellicano, the Hollywood private eye accused of masterminding a long-running wiretapping ring, called yesterday for two New York Times reporters to be subpoenaed to find out who leaked them recordings of conversations and other evidence in the case.</p>
        <p>On Jan. 11, The Times printed excerpts of 33 recorded conversations that Mr. Pellicano had with Terry N. Christensen, a lawyer for Kirk Kerkorian, the billionaire Hollywood mogul. The newspaper also put audio excerpts of the conversations on its Web site. Mr. Christensen has also been charged in connection with the wiretapping.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A defense lawyer in the case involving Anthony Pellicano called for two New York Times reporters to be subpoenaed to find out who leaked them recordings of conversations and other evidence in the case.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A defense lawyer in the case involving Anthony Pellicano, the Hollywood private eye accused of masterminding a long-running wiretapping ring, called yesterday for two New York Times reporters to be subpoenaed to find out who leaked them recordings of conversations and other evidence in the case.</p>
        <p>On Jan. 11, The Times printed excerpts of 33 recorded conversations that Mr. Pellicano had with Terry N. Christensen, a lawyer for Kirk Kerkorian, the billionaire Hollywood mogul. The newspaper also put audio excerpts of the conversations on its Web site. Mr. Christensen has also been charged in connection with the wiretapping.</p>
        <p>In papers filed last week in federal court, Mr. Christensen called on the judge, Dale S. Fischer of United States District Court, to force the two reporters, David M. Halbfinger and Allison Hope Weiner, to reveal their sources.</p>
        <p>In a hearing yesterday in Los Angeles, Terree A. Bowers, the lawyer representing Mr. Christensen, told the judge that the reporters might be ''criminally liable'' for their actions. He said in a telephone interview after the hearing that he told the judge that their posting of the conversations on the Internet violated his client's presumption of innocence.</p>
        <p>The judge asked Mr. Bowers to spell out specifically what relief he is seeking and how he would like her to deal with the case. In a statement, Catherine J. Mathis, a spokeswoman for The New York Times Company, said: ''We believe it is critically important for reporters to be able to protect their confidential sources of information and will continue to advocate for their ability to do so.''</p>
        <p>The judge also said she wanted to meet privately with Robert Ciaffa, the assistant United States attorney in San Diego, who is investigating the source of information leaked to The Times over the last year in what the government has said was a violation of the judge's order. Mr. Ciaffa, who did not attend the hearing, said in a telephone interview that he had no comment.</p>
        <p>Judge Fischer also indicated yesterday that she was studying a similar case involving two reporters for The San Francisco Chronicle who have refused to reveal their sources and are facing up to 18 months in jail. The reporters, Mark Fainaru-Wada and Lance Williams, published federal grand jury testimony in which athletes admitted to using steroids supplied by the Bay Area Laboratory Cooperative, known as Balco. The jail terms, as well as a $1,000-a-day fine imposed on The Chronicle, have been suspended pending an appeal, to be heard in March.</p>
        <p>The trial of Mr. Pellicano has been delayed until August because of the complexity of the case, the volume of evidence and lawyers' scheduling conflicts.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
