<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METROPOLITAN DIARY</title>
    <meta content="22diary" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/22/nyregion/22diary.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1820695"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Metropolitan Diary"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metropolitan Diary</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E7DC1F30F931A15752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="728" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METROPOLITAN DIARY</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Dear Diary</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>This event occurred the Friday before Christmas in the late afternoon.</p>
        <p>The setting was outside the local firehouse on East 85th Street.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Clearly annoyed, the woman stopped and turned to the firehouse, announcing in a loud voice: “It’s not funny! He’s my hamster, and he’s lost.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>This event occurred the Friday before Christmas in the late afternoon.</p>
        <p>The setting was outside the local firehouse on East 85th Street.</p>
        <p>A cab was parked and four firefighters with large flashlights were poking about the inside of the cab at each door. The cabdriver looked on. The passenger, a woman, was pacing the sidewalk in front of the firehouse. From the open door came the laughter of other firefighters.</p>
        <p>Clearly annoyed, the woman stopped and turned to the firehouse, announcing in a loud voice: ''It's not funny! He's my hamster, and he's lost.''</p>
        <p>It's nice to see that in the absence of trees and kittens, firefighters practice other urban pet rescues!</p>
        <p>The Rev. Philip Judge</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>A few weeks ago on Broadway, not far from Lincoln Center, I was admiring some very pretty scarves a street vendor was selling. A tourist -- by his accent, Scandinavian, I think -- approached me, seeking directions. ''How do I get to Carnegie Hall?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>I could hardly believe it: The man had presented me with a classic straight line, a once-in-a-lifetime opportunity! What else could I do? Helplessly, I gave the classic punch line: ''Practice, practice, practice.''</p>
        <p>The poor fellow stared uncomprehendingly at me, so I relented. I pointed downtown and told him to walk to 57th Street and turn left to Seventh Avenue. I also gave him subway directions.</p>
        <p>Joan M. Traub</p>
        <p>FEEDING PIGEONS</p>
        <p>If I give them far too many crumbs,</p>
        <p>Do they need a supplement of Tums?</p>
        <p>Am I blameworthy and ripe for a beating,</p>
        <p>Encouraging them in their rampant overeating?</p>
        <p>First, though, before you judge my charity,</p>
        <p>Tell me: Did he who made the pigeon make thee?</p>
        <p>Leon Freilich</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>I was waiting at a takeout counter at a Third Avenue deli when a woman came rushing in and said, ''I need three-quarters of a pound of turkey delivered to my vet for my dog.''</p>
        <p>In my next life, I want to come back as a dog.</p>
        <p>Nancy Pline</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>My 4-year-old daughter, Alexa, has been learning patterns in preschool. As we wandered around Chelsea one Sunday afternoon with no specific plans, she turned to me and said: ''Mommy, I have an idea. Let's get a manicure and then go shopping and then get a pedicure and then go shopping again. It's a pattern.''</p>
        <p>Elise M. Brett</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>Upon entering the Brice Marden exhibition at the Museum of Modern Art, I was taken aback by the rectangular canvases painted separately in hues of battleship gray, mud and olive green.</p>
        <p>I walked over to the security guard and asked his impression of the art. He replied, ''I don't look at the art, I look at the expressions on the faces of the people. Most of them look as though they have been dropped into a Home Depot.''</p>
        <p>Susan Birnbryer Madon</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>On a recent afternoon while riding the M42 bus, I spotted a sign in a food shop window: ''Meditarian Food.''</p>
        <p>Could they possibly be selling something we can add to our multitasking list and eat while meditating? And it was a nice, professionally made sign, too. I kind of feel they maybe meant ''Mediterranean Food.'' Do you think?</p>
        <p>Joe Baldwin</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>While walking through the Metropolitan Museum's exhibition ''Cézanne to Picasso,'' I stopped and looked at several very beautiful platters decorated by Matisse. I turned to the man next to me and said, ''Aren't they beautiful?''</p>
        <p>He answered sadly, ''Yes, but are they dishwasher-safe?''</p>
        <p>Michael Parrella</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>On a Wednesday night about 11:30, I was bringing a birthday cake in a huge plastic carrier to a friend's apartment, for a surprise party to be held there the following day.</p>
        <p>I walked through the Village and took the No. 6 train at Astor Place, getting a lot of curious stares from passers-by and riders, which I attributed to my unusual cargo and the late hour.</p>
        <p>By my stop at 23rd Street, I was feeling quite self-conscious -- that is, until I got off the train and saw a group of six or seven people sitting on a bench on the platform and hovering over an even larger cake, eating it ravenously with their bare hands.</p>
        <p>Moral of the story: In New York City, there is always someone doing something more bizarre than you.</p>
        <p>Jessica Smith</p>
        <p>Metropolitan Diary</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
