<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Struggle, Patterson Finds Touch for Storm</title>
    <meta content="22storm--" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/22/sports/ncaabasketball/22storm_.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1820685"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">St John's University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Syracuse University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Connecticut</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finley, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">St John's University</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Syracuse University</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Big East Conference</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EFDD1F30F931A15752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Struggle, Patterson Finds Touch for Storm</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After Struggle, Patterson Finds Touch for Storm</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL FINLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finley, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>St John's University men's basketball team defeats Syracuse University, 64-60; Connecticut University women's basketball team defeats St John's University, 74-56; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The clock was winding down, and the game was on track to be a case of more of the same for St. John's and the junior guard Avery Patterson. The Red Storm, which led by 8 points midway through the second half yesterday, had frittered away its lead, and Patterson was struggling. A fifth consecutive loss seemed to be a foregone conclusion.</p>
        <p>That is, until Patterson picked an opportune time to rediscover his shot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With St. John’s trailing by a point, Avery Patterson made a 3-pointer with 1 minute 28 seconds left and turned it into a 4-point play because of a foul as St. John's went on to defeat Syracuse on Sunday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The clock was winding down, and the game was on track to be a case of more of the same for St. John's and the junior guard Avery Patterson. The Red Storm, which led by 8 points midway through the second half yesterday, had frittered away its lead, and Patterson was struggling. A fifth consecutive loss seemed to be a foregone conclusion.</p>
        <p>That is, until Patterson picked an opportune time to rediscover his shot.</p>
        <p>With St. John's trailing by a point, he made a 3-pointer with 1 minute 28 seconds left and turned it into a 4-point play because of a foul by Syracuse's Eric Devendorf. Twenty-five seconds later, Patterson struck again, hitting a 3-pointer from the right baseline that helped St. John's defeat Syracuse, 64-60, at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>''My teammates kept encouraging me to shoot,'' said Patterson, who was 1 for 7 from the field before hitting the shot that put the Red Storm (11-8, 2-4 Big East) ahead. ''They kept telling me it was going to fall. It just happened at the end of the game.''</p>
        <p>Syracuse (15-5, 4-2), which had won four in a row , had its streak of 47 consecutive victories against teams from New York State ended.</p>
        <p>But it was not a perfect afternoon for St. John's. In the second half of the Garden doubleheader, the women's team fell to No. 6 Connecticut, 74-56.</p>
        <p>After his team's 71-63 loss at DePaul last Tuesday, St. John's Coach Norm Roberts started to lose his patience with a team that had underachieved for most of the season. Roberts said yesterday that he made the team practice twice Friday and that he questioned the effort of some players.</p>
        <p>''We were not playing to our ability and not playing with the passion and intensity we needed,'' he said. ''If we had been playing our butts off, I could have lived with that. But when we don't give ourselves a chance to win or to be as good as we can be, that's what frustrates me.''</p>
        <p>Early on yesterday, Roberts's message seemed to be getting through. The Red Storm jumped to a 13-2 lead while taking advantage of some sloppy play by the Orange. Syracuse regrouped and had the St. John's lead down to 29-28 at halftime, but the Red Storm again took control and increased its lead to 47-39 when Anthony Mason Jr. made a 3-pointer with 9:10 to go.</p>
        <p>To that point, Patterson had been a nonfactor, something that had often been the case this season. One of the more erratic players in the Big East, he recently endured a four-game stretch in which he averaged 4.3 points and shot 23 percent from the field. Yet, he said, he never stopped believing in his shot.</p>
        <p>''I'm a shooter, and I knew my shots would start falling,'' he said. ''All shooters go through slumps. I never lost any confidence in my shot.''</p>
        <p>But Patterson remained cold, and Devendorf took control. Scoring 10 points during a stretch of 2:39, he helped cut Syracuse's deficit to a point, and the Orange went ahead on a 3-pointer by Demetris Nichols with 1:48 to go.</p>
        <p>With the thousands of Syracuse fans in the building ready to celebrate another win, Patterson did his damage.</p>
        <p>''St. John's made two really good plays at the end of the game, and that was the difference,'' Syracuse Coach Jim Boeheim said.</p>
        <p>After Devendorf scored with 54 seconds left to cut the St. John's lead to 4, the Red Storm held the ball without being fouled. Eugene Lawrence missed a 3-pointer with 18 seconds left, but Qa'rraan Calhoun grabbed an offensive rebound to seal the victory.</p>
        <p>Mason led St. John's with 16 points. The Red Storm was playing without the oft-injured guard Daryll Hill, who is sidelined with a sore left knee and is also expected to miss tomorrow's game against Notre Dame. St. John's had lost six in a row to Syracuse.</p>
        <p>''We were supposed to be a really good team this season, and we are a good team,'' Mason said. ''But you can't lose four straight and not play hard. We weren't playing up to our potential, and we felt really bad about that. I think we came in more pepped up for this game.''</p>
        <p>Devendorf led Syracuse with 23 points. The Orange was only 4 for 14 from the free-throw line, in large part because Terrence Roberts missed 8 of 9 attempts.</p>
        <p>In the women's game, Mel Thomas had 19 points for Connecticut, which has beaten St. John's 23 consecutive times. She made five 3-pointers in the first half for the Huskies (16-2, 6-0), who were making their first appearance at the Garden.</p>
        <p>Kia Wright, who transferred to St. John's from UConn, led the Red Storm (5-12, 0-5) with 19 points.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
