<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Murder Trial Paints Portrait Of a Family Torn by Strife</title>
    <meta content="12murder" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/12/nyregion/12murder.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1818227"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Domestic Violence</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hartocollis, Anemona</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kramer, Jennie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Odierno, Christine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Odierno, Ben</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Domestic Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Domestic Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE6DE1330F931A25752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="643" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Murder Trial Paints Portrait Of a Family Torn by Strife</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Murder Trial Paints Portrait of a Family Torn by Strife</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANEMONA HARTOCOLLIS; Colin Moynihan contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hartocollis, Anemona</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jennie Kramer testifies at New York State Supreme Court in Manhattan that her daughter Christine Odierno told her on telephone that her husband Benjamin was about to kill her at their home after she served him with divorce papers; Christine claimed while dying that her husband stabbed her; had complained husband regularly beat her in domestic disputes, but family members disagree over who abuser was; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wearing a black velvet coat and a patterned blouse, the 86-year-old mother of the dead woman looked birdlike and frail as she walked to the witness stand.</p>
        <p>She remembered the last time she spoke to her daughter, Christine Odierno, by telephone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wearing a black velvet coat and a patterned blouse, the 86-year-old mother of the dead woman looked birdlike and frail as she walked to the witness stand.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Wearing a black velvet coat and a patterned blouse, the 86-year-old mother of the dead woman looked birdlike and frail as she walked to the witness stand.</p>
        <p>She remembered the last time she spoke to her daughter, Christine Odierno, by telephone.</p>
        <p>''Mom, I gave Ben the divorce papers, and he went bananas,'' the mother, Jennie Kramer, told the jury in State Supreme Court in Manhattan yesterday, quoting her daughter. ''He's going to kill me, Mom. He's going to kill me. He's going to kill me.''</p>
        <p>With that, Mrs. Kramer leaned forward, her head collapsing into her hands, and cried.</p>
        <p>It was the most emotional moment in the first day of the murder trial of Benjamin Odierno, accused of stabbing his wife, Christine, to death on April 24, 2005, in the kitchen of their Upper East Side town house, where she was cutting lettuce for dinner.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors say Mr. Odierno, 72, killed his wife, who was 57, three days after she gave him divorce papers -- purposely handing them over in a public place, they say, because she was afraid of him. They say she was a long-suffering victim of domestic abuse that always stayed hidden within the thick walls of their home on East 84th Street.</p>
        <p>When the police arrived, said the prosecutor, Kerry O'Connell, ''she was able to draw enough breath to say, 'My husband did this. My husband stabbed me in the heart.' ''</p>
        <p>The defense lawyer, Jack Litman, agreed that Mr. Odierno killed his wife. But he said that it was in self-defense, and that it was she who had been tormenting him, forcing him to see a psychiatrist.</p>
        <p>''He never raised a hand to her,'' Mr. Litman said. ''He acted and reacted instinctively to save his own life after she stabbed him.''</p>
        <p>He said Mr. Odierno, a landlord, had traumatic amnesia that prevented him from recalling the details of the night his wife died. The police, responding to a 911 call reporting a woman's screams, said that when they arrived they found Mr. Odierno stabbing himself in the abdomen.</p>
        <p>But what emerged most clearly from the first day of the trial was a portrait of a family deeply divided, in which some members take Mrs. Odierno's side, and others, including the couple's two grown sons, take her husband's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Litman told jurors that the sons would testify on behalf of their father. They would describe, he said, how their mother had grown increasingly unstable over the last eight or so years of her life. She became very thin, and ate only lettuce for dinner, obsessively separating the white parts from the green parts, Mr. Litman said in his opening statement.</p>
        <p>He said that Mrs. Odierno had exiled her husband from the couple's bedroom, forcing him to sleep in a single bed in a room he shared with Marcus, the younger son. She hoarded hundreds of rolls of toilet paper in the basement, Mr. Litman said, and screamed that her husband was abusing her loud enough for the neighbors to hear, yet nobody ever reported seeing any bruises.</p>
        <p>Mr. Litman hammered on the family divisions during cross-examination of Mrs. Odierno's mother.</p>
        <p>''You have a son, right?'' he asked Mrs. Kramer, who had testified that she was the mother of three daughters, including Christine, and a 61-year-old son, Bill.</p>
        <p>''Not anymore,'' she replied.</p>
        <p>''Now of course, Bill is still alive, isn't he?''</p>
        <p>''I think so,'' Mrs. Kramer replied.</p>
        <p>''The reason you're saying you don't know is because Bill supports Benjamin Odierno, is that right?'' Mr. Litman asked.</p>
        <p>''I have no idea what you mean,'' Mrs. Kramer said.</p>
        <p>''Did you see your son at the funeral?'' Mr. Litman asked.</p>
        <p>''Yes,'' Mrs. Kramer said.</p>
        <p>''Did you see him as a pallbearer?''</p>
        <p>''I think he was,'' Mrs. Kramer said. ''I'm not certain.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Litman had no further questions.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
