<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Listings: Jan. 12 - Jan. 18</title>
    <meta content="12theater" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1818173"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEED71230F931A25752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="15714" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Listings: Jan. 12 - Jan. 18</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the New York metropolitan region this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'THE FEVER' In previews; opens on Jan. 24. Wallace Shawn stars in his own play about a man who wakes up in a war-torn country feeling under the weather (1:40). Acorn Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'FRANK'S HOME' Previews start tomorrow. Opens on Jan. 30. Richard Nelson's new bio-play about the life and work of Frank Lloyd Wright stars Peter Weller (as Wright) and Harris Yulin (who plays Louis Sullivan) (1:45). Playwrights Horizons Mainstage, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 719-4200.</p>
        <p>'THE GAZILLION BUBBLE SHOW' Performances begin on Wednesday. Fan Yan holds the world's record for the largest bubble ever blown, and in an even more amazing feat, he's parlayed this oddball stunt into a bubble-themed, family-friendly show (2:00). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'IN THE HEIGHTS' In previews; opens on Feb. 8. A new Off Broadway musical about two days in the life of Washington Heights, presented from the vantage point of a corner bodega (2:10). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'KIKI AND HERB' On the heels of a Broadway stint, these cabaret hipsters return to their downtown roots (1:30). Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555.</p>
        <p>'THE MERCHANT OF VENICE' In previews; opens on Feb. 4. F. Murray Abraham plays Shylock in this Theater for a New Audience production. Darko Tresnjak directs (2:20). The Duke on 42nd Street, 229 West 42nd Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'A SPANISH PLAY' In previews; opens on Feb. 1. Zoe Caldwell leads an extraordinary cast (Linda Emond, Denis O'Hare, Larry Pine, Katherine Borowitz) in Yasmina Reza's new backstage play, in which real life and fiction blur (1:30). Classic Stage Company, 136 East 13th Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101.</p>
        <p>'TRANSLATIONS' In previews; opens on Jan. 25. Brian Friel's drama about a British officer in 19th-century rural Ireland deals with themes of language, imperialism and culture clash. Garry Hynes directs (2:15). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE APPLE TREE' The amazing Kristin Chenoweth gives Imax-screen-size life to three curvaceous doodles who by rights shouldn't be any larger than figures in the Sunday funnies. Jerry Bock and Sheldon Harnick's 1966 musical, directed by Gary Griffin, shows its age but is given theatrical verve by Ms. Chenoweth, Brian d'Arcy James and Marc Kudisch (2:30). Studio 54, 254 West 54th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>'A CHORUS LINE' If you want to know why this show was such a big deal when it opened 31 years ago, you need only experience the thrilling first five minutes of this revival. Otherwise, this archivally exact production, directed by Bob Avian, feels like a vintage car that has been taken out of the garage, polished up and sent on the road once again (2:00). Schoenfeld Theater, 236 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE COAST OF UTOPIA' The exhilarating first two installments of Tom Stoppard's trilogy about 19th-century Russian intellectuals dreaming of revolution, these productions pulse with the dizzy, spring-green arrogance and anxiety of a new generation moving as fast as it can toward the future. Jack O'Brien directs a fresh, vigorous and immense cast that includes Brian F. O'Byrne, Jennifer Ehle, Billy Crudup and Ethan Hawke (2:45). Vivian Beaumont Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'COMPANY' Fire, beckoning and dangerous, flickers beneath the frost of John Doyle's elegant, unexpectedly stirring revival of Stephen Sondheim and George Furth's era-defining musical from 1970, starring a compellingly understated Raul Esparza. Like Mr. Doyle's ''Sweeney Todd,'' this production finds new clarity of feeling in Sondheim by melding the roles of performers and musicians (2:20). Barrymore Theater, 243 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE' (Tony Awards, best book of a musical and best original score, 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920s stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, it has theatergoers responding as if they were withering houseplants finally being watered after long neglect. Bob Martin and Sutton Foster are the standouts in the avid, energetic cast (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* ' 'GREY GARDENS' Christine Ebersole is absolutely glorious as the middle-aged, time-warped debutante called Little Edie Beale in this uneven musical adaptation of the notorious 1975 documentary of the same title. She and the wonderful Mary Louise Wilson (as her bedridden mother), in the performances of their careers, make ''Grey Gardens'' an experience no passionate theatergoer should miss (2:40). Walter Kerr Theater, 219 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE LITTLE DOG LAUGHED' The comedy of manners, a form widely believed to be extinct in the American theater, has actually resurfaced on Broadway with all its vital signs intact in Douglas Carter Beane's breezy but trenchant satire about truth and illusion, Hollywood style. With the wonderful Julie White as the movie agent you hate to love (but just can't help it) (2:00). Cort Theater, 138 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MARY POPPINS' This handsome, homily-packed, mechanically ingenious and rather tedious musical, adapted from the P. L. Travers stories and the 1964 Disney film, is ultimately less concerned with inexplicable magic than with practical psychology. Ashley Brown, who sings prettily as the family-mending nanny, looks like Joan Crawford trying to be nice and sounds like Dr. Phil. Directed by Richard Eyre and Matthew Bourne (2:30). New Amsterdam Theater, 214 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LES MISÉRABLES' This premature revival, a slightly scaled-down version of the well-groomed behemoth that closed only three years ago, appears to be functioning in a state of mild sedation. Appealingly sung and freshly orchestrated, this fast-moving adaptation of Victor Hugo's novel isn't sloppy or blurry. But its pulse rate stays well below normal (2:55). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' Duncan Sheik and Steven Sater's bold adaptation of the Frank Wedekind play is the freshest and most exciting new musical Broadway has seen in some time. Set in 19th-century Germany but with a ravishing rock score, it exposes the splintered emotional lives of adolescents just discovering the joys and sorrows of sex. Performed with brio by a great cast, with supple direction by Michael Mayer and inventive choreography by Bill T. Jones (2:00). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN'  This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a superdeluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE VERTICAL HOUR' David Hare's soggy consideration of the Anglo-American cultural divide stars Julianne Moore (representing the Americans) and Bill Nighy (leading the British), directed by Sam Mendes. The Yanks don't stand a chance. With his irresistibly mannered performance as a laconic doctor, Mr. Nighy mops the floor with Ms. Moore. Actually, he mops the floor with Mr. Hare's play (2:20). Music Box Theater, 239 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE BIG VOICE: GOD OR MERMAN?' Think of two gifted and smart gay men with years of life together deploying their considerable talents from the two pianos you happen to have in your living room. The result is a hilarious and very touching memoir of two decades of love and the funky glories of show business life (2:00). Actors Temple Theater, 339 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Honor Moore)</p>
        <p>*'THE CLEAN HOUSE' Sarah Ruhl's comedy about the painful but beautiful disorder of life has arrived in New York at last in a gorgeous production directed by Bill Rauch. Blair Brown and Jill Clayburgh delight as sisters with different views on the meaning of cleaning, and Vanessa Aspillaga is equally good as the depressed maid with little affection for her work but a deep conviction that a good joke can be a matter of life and death (2:15). Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, Lincoln Center, 150 West 65th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'DAI (ENOUGH)' Iris Bahr's unnerving one-woman show doesn't have much to add to the Middle East debate, but it sure leaves a lasting impression. Ms. Bahr plays an assortment of characters who have the misfortune of being in a Tel Aviv cafe that is about to be visited by the havoc common to such establishments. The attack is rendered in jarring fashion, repeatedly; you watch the play on pins and needles, waiting for the next burst. Gimmicky? Sure. But viscerally effective (1:40). Culture Project, 55 Mercer Street, at Broome Street, SoHo, (212) 253-9983. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'EVIL DEAD: THE MUSICAL' This likable horror comedy based on Sam Raimi's gory movies wants to be the next ''Rocky Horror Show.'' To that end, it offers deadpan lyrics, self-referential humor and geysers of stage blood (2:00). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>'THE FANTASTICKS' A revival -- well, more like a resuscitation -- of the Little Musical That Wouldn't Die. This sweet-as-ever production of Tom Jones and Harvey Schmidt's commedia-dell'arte-style confection is most notable for Mr. Jones's touching performance (under the pseudonym Thomas Bruce) as the Old Actor, a role he created when the show opened in 1960. Mr. Jones also directs (2:05). Snapple Theater Center, 210 West 50th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JACQUES BREL IS ALIVE AND WELL AND LIVING IN PARIS' A powerfully sung revival of the 1968 revue, presented with affectionate nostalgia by the director Gordon Greenberg. As in the original, two men and two women perform a wide selection of Brel's plaintive ballads and stirring anthems (2:00). Zipper Theater, 336 West 37th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'A JEW GROWS IN BROOKLYN' You don't have to be Jewish or Brooklynish to empathize with Jake Ehrenreich, but in terms of fully appreciating his essentially one-man show, it probably helps. Especially the Catskills jokes (2:05). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 560-8912. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'MEET ME IN ST. LOUIS' This musical is too big for its stage, but the young turn-of-the-last-century sweethearts have great chemistry, and there are four terrific songs (2:00). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'MY MOTHER'S ITALIAN, MY FATHER'S JEWISH AND I'M IN THERAPY'  Steve Solomon does skillful impersonations in his one-man show, but some of his jokes are as old as the hills (1:30). Little Shubert Theater, 422 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'NO CHILD'  Teachers will love Nilaja Sun's one-woman show about the challenges of teaching drama at Malcolm X High School (1:10). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, at Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'REGRETS ONLY' Old acquaintance comes under siege in Paul Rudnick's chiffon-thin comedy about the varieties of love and marriage. But no one who sees this latest offering from one of the funniest quipmeisters alive is going to doubt that Christine Baranski is a one-liner's best friend (2:00). City Center Stage I, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RIDDLELIKELOVE (WITH A SIDE OF KETCHUP)' This one-woman show, in which Julie Fitzpatrick tells of her friendship with a deaf woman, is cloying and thin, but the sign-language interpretation provided at each performance gives it an interesting extra dimension, helping to bring the subject to life (1:30). Ensemble Studio Theater, 549 West 52nd Street, Clinton, (212) 352-3101. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'ROOM SERVICE' The Peccadillo Theater Company puts a charge into this comedy from the 1930s, thanks to a brisk pace by the director, Dan Wackerman, and a dozen dandy performances. David Edwards is the would-be producer whose bills threaten to swamp his efforts to put a show on Broadway, and Fred Berman is particularly fine as his director (2:00). SoHo Playhouse, 15 Vandam Street, South Village, (212) 691-1555. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'SUDDENLY LAST SUMMER'  As the luscious (and lobotomy-threatened) damsel in distress in Tennessee Williams's famously lurid melodrama, Carla Gugino gives a gutsy assurance to a production that otherwise lacks compelling confidence. Mark Brokaw directs a cast that includes Blythe Danner, in a fascinating but misconceived performance as a smothering mother from hell (1:30). Laura Pels Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'25 QUESTIONS FOR A JEWISH MOTHER' This is the comedian Judy Gold's fiercely funny monologue, based on her own life as a single Jewish lesbian mother and interviews with more than 50 other Jewish mothers (1:20). St. Luke's Theater, 308 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Phoebe Hoban)</p>
        <p>'TWO TRAINS RUNNING'  Directed by Lou Bellamy, a rough-edged revival of August Wilson's 1992 play about the stark economics of life and death for African-Americans, set in a dying diner in Pittsburgh in the late 1960s. The pace drags in this production, but it remains a bracing reminder of Mr. Wilson's singular talent for making cold, hard numbers sing hot, molten blues (3:40). Signature Theater at Peter Norton Space, 555 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 352-3101. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE VOYSEY INHERITANCE' David Mamet has cleanly and cannily adapted Harley Granville Barker's 1905 play about corruption in the genteel world of Victorian finance. An excellent cast and a sumptuous production bring extra immediacy to a tale of embezzlement and entitlement that feels as fresh as tomorrow's stock options (1:50). Atlantic Theater, 336 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'FLUKE' A meditative collage of enigmatic riffs on ''Moby-Dick'' presented by the rambunctious experimental company Radiohole (1:30). Collapsable Hole, 146 Metropolitan Avenue, at Berry Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 388-2251. (Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'T J AND DAVE' The comics T. J. Jagodowski and Dave Pasquesi miraculously improvise a one-hour play at every performance. This is an impressive feat of mental athletics, but the results are also observant, complex and frequently enormously funny (1:00). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden Theater, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' Singing CliffsNotes for Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' Often more entertaining than the real thing (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS'  The biomusical that walks like a man (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT'  A singing scrapbook for Monty Python fans (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' ''A Chorus Line'' with pimples (1:45). Circle in the Square, 254 West 50th Street, Manhattan, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'BUTLEY'  In this uneasy revival of Simon Gray's portrait of a toxic English professor, directed by Nicholas Martin, Nathan Lane fires off witticisms as if they were silver bullets with ''Made in Britain'' engraved on them. A less-than-perfect marriage of a first-rate actor with a first-rate play (2:30). Booth Theater, 222 West 45th Street, Manhattan, (212) 239-6200; closes on Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'AN OAK TREE' Tim Crouch plays a hypnotist in this elusive puzzle of a play about grief and the power of suggestion (1:05). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, at Seventh Avenue, West Village, (212) 239-6200; closes on Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'PURITY' The provocateur Thomas Bradshaw's horror show confronts black-on-black racism (1:15). Performance Space 122, 150 First Avenue, at Ninth Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101; closes on Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'SLAVA'S SNOWSHOW' Clowns chosen by the Russian master Slava Polunin stir up laughter and enjoyment. A show that touches the heart as well as tickles the funny bone (1:30). Union Square Theater, 100 East 17th Street, (212) 307-4100; closes on Sunday. (Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>'BABEL' (R, 143 minutes, in English, Spanish, Japanese, Berber, Arabic and sign language) This hugely ambitious movie tells four loosely linked, not quite simultaneous stories set on three different continents, with dialogue in several languages. The themes, to the extent they are decipherable, include loss, fate and the terrible consequences of miscommunication. Written by Guillermo Arriaga and directed by Alejandro Gonzalez Iñárritu, the movie is an intellectual muddle but a visceral tour de force, and the power of the filmmaking almost overcomes the fuzziness of the ideas. Almost. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>'BLACK CHRISTMAS' (R, 100 minutes) It's been more than 30 years since the original ''Black Christmas'' revealed how much fun it could be to unleash a psycho in a sorority house. Glen Morgan's disastrous remake not only sidelines the original's hilariously obscene phone calls but also drags its unseen killer, and his psychoses, into the light. Smothering terror beneath a blanket of unnecessary information, the movie is no more than a dismal Christmas card to its predecessor. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'BLOOD DIAMOND' (R, 138 minutes) The makers of this foolish thriller about illegal diamond trafficking in Africa, starring an excellent Leonardo DiCaprio, want you to know there may be blood on your hands, specifically your wedding finger. Too bad they haven't thought through what it means to turn human misery into entertainment. (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'BORAT: CULTURAL LEARNINGS OF AMERICA FOR MAKE BENEFIT GLORIOUS NATION OF KAZAKHSTAN' (R, 89 minutes) In this brainy, merciless comedy, a Kazakh journalist named Borat Sagdiyev, a k a the British comic Sacha Baron Cohen, invades America. America laughs, cries, surrenders. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'CASINO ROYALE' (PG-13, 144 minutes) The latest James Bond vehicle finds the British spy leaner, meaner and now played by an attractive piece of blond rough named Daniel Craig. Zap, pow, ka-ching! (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'CHARLOTTE'S WEB' (G, 113 minutes) Gary Winick's adaptation of E. B. White's great children's novel is faithful to the wit and feeling of the source. The celebrity-voiced animals are charming, and Julia Roberts is in fine form as the heroic spider, whose writing ability saves the life of a pig. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'CHILDREN OF MEN' (R, 100 minutes) The end is nigh in this superbly directed political thriller by Alfonso Cuarón about a nervously plausible future. Based on the P. D. James book, the film stars an excellent Clive Owen and features equally sterling support from the actors Michael Caine, Danny Huston and Chiwetel Ejiofior, among others, as well as the great cinematographer Emmanuel Lubezki. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'CODE NAME: THE CLEANER' (PG-13, 91 minutes) Cedric the Entertainer clogs the arteries of what could have been a savvy riff on the ''Bourne'' films with way too much ham, playing a janitor who wakes up with amnesia, a dead man beside him. A missing computer chip fuels the plot, aided by Lucy Liu and Nicollette Sheridan. Though it's all too dumb to amuse grownups, it's harmless fun for tweener types. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'COMEDY OF POWER' (No rating, 110 minutes, in French) Isabelle Huppert is brisk and fierce as a French investigative judge going after corrupt fat cats. The director, Claude Chabrol, is more interested in the forms of ruling-class behavior than in the details of high-level criminality, but his detached, complacent style makes for an interesting contrast with Ms. Huppert's conviction. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'CURSE OF THE GOLDEN FLOWER' (R, 114 minutes, in Mandarin) The Chinese director Zhang Yimou aims for Shakespeare and winds up with Jacqueline Susann in this Tang dynasty melodrama roiling with incest, fraternal rivalry and madness-inducing fungus. As an emperor and empress fighting for control of their three sons, Chow Yun Fat and Gong Li lend the film a core of marital toxicity that's deliciously unstable. Directing with operatic delirium, Mr. Zhang has created a movie in which the line between tragedy and black comedy has been all but erased. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'THE DEAD GIRL' (R, 93 minutes) An impressively well-acted movie, ''The Dead Girl'' has a chip on its shoulder. The relentless emotional violence in it, a compendium of five vignettes related to a young woman whose naked, mutilated corpse is discovered on a barren hillside, is of a level rarely found in movies, even those steeped in gore. There is some gore in ''The Dead Girl,'' but it is eclipsed in intensity by the verbal abuse hurled by its desperately unhappy characters at the people closest to them. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'THE DEPARTED' (R, 150 minutes) Martin Scorsese's cubistic entertainment about men divided by power, loyalty and their own selves is at once a success and a relief. Based on the crackling Hong Kong thriller ''Infernal Affairs,'' it features fine twinned performances from Matt Damon and Leonardo DiCaprio, and a showboating Jack Nicholson. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'DHOOM 2' (No rating, 151 minutes, in Hindi) A slick and satisfying example of the new, thoroughly modern Bollywood, this cops-and-robbers tale is animated by old-fashioned star power. Hrithik Roshan plays the ''smartest and coolest thief alive,'' and Aishwarya Rai is the small-time crook who loves him. (Rachel Saltz)</p>
        <p>'ERAGON' (PG, 99 minutes) This lad-and-his-dragon fantasy set in a land bristling with Tolkienesque nomenclature and earnest British actors is as lacking in fresh ideas as Tim Allen's manager. Directed by the wonderfully named Stefen Fangmeier, it boasts the usual genre lineup: an evil king (John Malkovich), a whey-faced hero (Edward Speleers) and a serene warrior-maiden (Sienna Guillory), as well as the required rebel hordes and bucolic landscapes. Some of the characters won't be returning for the sequel, but no matter. In all likelihood, neither will the audience. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* 'FLUSHED AWAY' (PG, 85 minutes) Sewer rats, singing leeches and whimsical British anarchy -- this computer-animated feature from Aardman Animations (''Wallace and Gromit,'' ''Chicken Run'') is completely delightful. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'FOR YOUR CONSIDERATION' (PG-13, 86 minutes) This satire of pre-Oscar-nomination buzz in Hollywood is far and away the broadest comedy Christopher Guest and his improvisatory company have made. It is also the flimsiest, and unlike Mr. Guest's earlier films, it has no airs of being a fake documentary. As farce trumps satire, the humor's subversive edge is lost, along with meaningful character development, with the brilliant exception of Catherine O'Hara. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'FREEDOM WRITERS' (PG-13, 123 minutes) Hilary Swank uses her characteristic neediness to fine effect in a true-to-life story about a teacher making a difference in a Southern California high school. The writer and director Richard LaGravenese provides the smartly laid foundation, but it's the kids who give the film its strong emotional tug. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE GOOD GERMAN' (R, 102 minutes) In his adaptation of the Joseph Kanon novel, Steven Soderbergh tries to resurrect the magic of classical Hollywood, principally by sucking out all the air, energy and pleasure from his own filmmaking. It's no wonder George Clooney, who stars alongside a vamping Cate Blanchett, looks confused. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'HAPPILY N'EVER AFTER' (PG, 87 minutes) Like Dreamworks's ''Shrek'' comedies, ''Happily'' is a grab-bag parody set in a fantasyland derived from bedtime stories and Disney films. The adopted chambermaid Ella (voiced by Sarah Michelle Gellar, drawn like Winona Ryder) and the poor dishwasher Rick (Freddie Prinze Jr.) battle Ella's wicked stepmother, Frieda (Sigourney Weaver). Despite self-aware touches, this is another tired kidsploitation product in which a wasp-waisted ingénue and a shallow beau drive the plot and live happily ever after. (Matt Zoller Seitz)</p>
        <p>'HAPPY FEET' (PG, 100 minutes) The director George Miller gets happy and snappy, then goes dark and deep, in a musical about an animated penguin who was born to dance. Take hankies. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'INLAND EMPIRE' (No rating, 179 minutes) David Lynch's extraordinary, savagely uncompromised new film stars a dazzling Laura Dern as an actress who tumbles down rabbit holes inside rabbit holes inside rabbit holes. As cracked as Mad magazine, though generally more difficult to parse, the film has the power of nightmares and is one of the few this year that deserve to be called art. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE LAST KING OF SCOTLAND' (R, 121 minutes) Kevin Macdonald paints a queasily enjoyable portrait of the Ugandan dictator Idi Amin from inside the palace walls. Forest Whitaker plays the mad king, while James McAvoy plays the fool. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'LETTERS FROM IWO JIMA' (R, 141 minutes, in Japanese) Another masterwork from Clint Eastwood's astonishing late period, and one of the best war movies ever. Ken Watanabe is especially fine as the general commanding Japanese troops in the doomed defense of the island of Iwo Jima. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'LITTLE CHILDREN' (R, 130 minutes) Todd Field's adaptation of Tom Perrotta's novel of suburban adultery is unfailingly intelligent and faultlessly acted. Kate Winslet and Patrick Wilson are superb as the parents of young children who meet at the playground and enact a two-handed variation on ''Madame Bovary'' against a backdrop of social paranoia and middle-class malaise. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'MISS POTTER' (PG, 92 minutes) In ''Miss Potter,'' Renée Zellweger, her face pickled in cheeriness, is Beatrix Potter, the creator of Peter Rabbit, Squirrel Nutkin and Mrs. Tittlemouse, among other beloved characters in children's literature. As portrayed by Ms. Zellweger, Potter is almost as chipper as Julie Andrews's Mary Poppins, a proto-feminist, proto-environmentalist and perfect lady to boot. There was plenty of drama in Potter's life, but the movie turns major conflicts and losses into minor setbacks in a charmed, entirely virtuous life. The movie is far too nice for its own good. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'NIGHT AT THE MUSEUM' (PG, 108 minutes) In this chaotic, overstuffed family comedy, Ben Stiller is a night watchman at the American Museum of Natural History, where the exhibits come to life at night and attack him and one another. This computerized spectacle spares no expense, but the storytelling is weak, and the hit-or-miss jokes miss more than hit. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'NOTES ON A SCANDAL' (R, 92 minutes) Judi Dench and Cate Blanchett play a misogynistic game of cat and mouse from which no one emerges unscathed, including the audience. Adapted by Patrick Marber from a novel by Zoë Heller and directed by Richard Eyre. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'PAN'S LABYRINTH' (R, 119 minutes, in Spanish) Guillermo del Toro's tale of a young girl's ordeal in post-Civil-War fascist Spain is either a fairy tale in the guise of a political allegory or vice versa. In either case it is a moving, enchanting, strange and humane example of popular art at its very best. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE PAINTED VEIL' (PG-13, 125 minutes) Nicely directed by John Curran, this version of the W. Somerset Maugham novel draws you in by turning a distaff bildungsroman into a fine romance with Naomi Watts and Edward Norton. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'PERFUME: THE STORY OF A MURDERER' (R, 147 minutes) There's no other way to say it: Tom Tykwer's excruciatingly literal-minded adaptation of the best-selling novel about an 18th-century serial killer with an acute sense of smell is a real stinker. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE PURSUIT OF HAPPYNESS' (PG-13, 117 minutes) How you respond to this fairy tale in realist drag may depend on whether you find Will Smith's performances so overwhelmingly winning that you buy the idea that poverty is a function of bad luck and bad choices, and success the result of heroic toil and dreams. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'THE QUEEN' (PG-13, 103 minutes) Directed by Stephen Frears from a very smart script by Peter Morgan, and starring a magnificent Helen Mirren in the title role, ''The Queen'' pries open a window in the House of Windsor around the time of the death of Diana, Princess of Wales, blending fact with fiction. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'ROCKY BALBOA' (PG, 102 minutes) Surprisingly, the sixth installment of this franchise is no embarrassment. Like its forerunners, it goes the distance almost in spite of itself. It's all heart and no credibility, except as a raw-boned fable. From the very beginning, Rocky Balboa was about as lifelike a character as Popeye pumped up with spinach. But that may be the point of a series that peddles the notion that if you dream it hard enough, you can live it. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'UNACCOMPANIED MINORS' (PG, 89 minutes) The title doubles as an advisory. Your kids may like it; pick them up when it's over. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'VENUS' (R, 91 minutes) A modest, diverting, touching tale of a young woman who attracts the interest -- avuncular and also erotic -- of an aging actor, played with effortless aplomb by the great Peter O'Toole. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'VOLVER' (R, 121 minutes, in Spanish) Another keeper from Pedro Almodóvar, with Penélope Cruz -- as a resilient widow -- in her best role to date. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'WE ARE MARSHALL' (PG, 128 minutes) This fact-based story of a West Virginia college town recovering from the death of its entire football team in a 1970 plane crash is a stiff, manipulative dud that gets wrong everything ''Friday Night Lights'' got right. Matthew McConaughey hams it up as the college's goofy new coach, who whips the replacement team into decent shape. (Holden)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>Sven Nykvist Remembered (Tonight through Sunday) Three films this weekend highlight the achievements of this great Swedish cinematographer, who died in September. ''The Silence'' (1963) is one of several films he shot for the director Ingmar Bergman, this time in brooding black and white; ''An-Margritt'' is a 1969 Norwegian film by Arne Skouen featuring one of Mr. Bergman's favorite performers, Liv Ullmann, as a young woman struggling to survive in a 17th-century mining community; ''Crimes and Misdemeanors'' (1989) finds Woody Allen in a Bergmanesque mood, contemplating the silence of God as Nykvist lights a strangely Nordic New York City. Museum of Modern Art, Roy and Niuta Titus Theaters, (212) 708-9400, moma.org; $10. (David Kehr)</p>
        <p>CRITICS CHOICE: GREAT DOCUMENTARIES (Tomorrow and Sunday) Members of the New York Film Critics Circle introduce some of their favorite nonfiction films. ''The Thin Blue Line,'' presented tomorrow by Mike D'Angelo of Esquire magazine, is the 1993 Errol Morris film that reopened a Dallas murder case, resulting in the exoneration of the man convicted for the crime, told in a slick, semifictional style. Also tomorrow, Stephen Whitty of The Star-Ledger offers ''Paradise Lost: The Child Murders at Robin Hood Hills,'' a look at a multiple killing in the deep South by the directors Joe Berlinger and Bruce Sinofsky, who will attend. On Sunday, J. Hoberman of The Village Voice reaches further back into the past for Dziga Vertov's deliriously subjective Soviet propaganda film of 1928, ''The Man with a Movie Camera,'' which will be shown in an archival print from the George Eastman House. (Through Feb. 25.) Museum of the Moving Image, 35th Avenue, at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718) 784-0077, movingimage.us; $10. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>THE 2007 NY JEWISH FILM FESTIVAL (Tomorrow through Thursday) Among this week's many programs: Lisa Azuelos's ''Gorgeous,'' about a group of North African Jewish women who meet to discuss their new lives in Paris; ''Love and Sacrifice,'' a newly restored Yiddish melodrama shot in New York in 1936 by the director George Roland; and ''Our Children,'' a 1948 comedy starring Shimon Dzigan and Israel Shumacher that is said to be the last Yiddish-language film made in Poland. (Through Jan. 25.) Walter Reade Theater 165 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 975-5600, filmlinc.org; $10. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>TUNDE ADEBIMPE AND ALIANnA KALABA (Tomorrow) Time was when the members of TV on the Radio, now the most critically adored band in New York, played in tiny clubs, blending electronic noises with Tunde Adebimpe's haunting falsetto. They have since graduated to much bigger gigs, but tomorrow at Tonic, the Lower East Side headquarters of the avant-garde, Mr. Adebimpe collaborates with Alianna Kalaba, the drummer of the Chicago band We Ragazzi. What will they do? Perhaps they don't even know, and that's why it will be good. Also on the bill are Pit Er Pat, Matteah Baim and Bear in Heaven. At 10 p.m., 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; $10. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>ANTI-SOCIAL MUSIC (Tomorrow) The final frontier for weird rock is classical music. Anti-Social Music, a collective of New York musicians who play in various pop and new-music bands -- including some big ones, like the Hold Steady -- is one of a handful of groups that boldly go into this realm, playing works for strings, woodwinds and other instruments by its 11 members (six of whom have degrees in music composition, the group's Web site, antisocialmusic.org, declares). Skeptics note: it can get pretty rowdy. At 9 p.m., BAMCafé, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100, bam.org; no cover. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MAX BEMIS (Sunday) Screamed warnings of being at the end of one's rope are standard issue in emo. But Mr. Bemis, the singer of the Los Angeles band Say Anything, isn't kidding: the group's latest release was delayed when he went missing, only to turn up in a mental institution in Houston. His songs bounce manically from exuberant to cynical, tender to bombastic, and, even at their most despairing, have a certain swaggering showmanship. He plays a solo acoustic show with Andy Jackson, the guitarist of the band Hot Rod Circuit. At 7 p.m., Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3006, knittingfactory.com; $12. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ANDREW BIRD (Wednesday) A talented multi-instrumentalist, Mr. Bird shows off his fiddle and guitar playing in songs that are as wistful as they are fantastical. But his most impressive technique is not on fiddle or guitar, nor on the electronic effects that he uses to make the music breathe; rather, it's his dexterous, expressive whistling, which floats high above in eerily beautiful tones. With John Southworth. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>CARNIVORE (Tomorrow) For fans of obscure New York metal only: before founding Type O Negative, Peter Steele led Carnivore, one of the most aggressive and, perhaps not coincidentally, offensive bands of the mid-'80s thrash scene. (Typical song title: ''Jesus Hitler.'') The new version of the band does not include any original members besides Mr. Steele. With Krieg, Lair of the Minotaur, A.C., Embalmer, Dimentianon and Annunaki. At 7 p.m., Northsix, 66 North Sixth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 599-5103, northsix.com; $30. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* COLD WAR KIDS (Wednesday) The craggy guitars and piano, verge-of-a-breakdown vocals and elliptical songwriting of this band from Austin, Tex., put it at the top of the music-blogger food chain last year. Now comes the hard part: maintaining popularity as the Internet eye roves again. This month the band is bouncing back and forth between New York and Los Angeles each week in a ''bicoastal residency.'' At 8 p.m., Union Hall, 702 Union Street, at Fifth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 638-4400, unionhallny.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ROBERT CRAY (Tuesday) The embodiment of the clean, commercial -- some might say rootless -- style that has defined the blues since the 1980s, Mr. Cray has an elegant touch with his Fender Stratocaster, and sings about desire and infidelity in a cool croon that is closer to pop than to Howlin' Wolf. At 8 p.m., B. B. King Blues Club and Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $47 in advance, $50 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>dB'S (Tomorrow) In the early 1980s, the dB's, four guys from North Carolina who relocated to New York, were local favorites for their nervy, hummable hybrid of New Wave and the jangly pop-rock of the Byrds and Big Star, with some country thrown in as well. The reunited band -- Peter Holsapple, Chris Stamey, Will Rigby and Gene Holder -- recorded a song for Hurricane Katrina relief and are working on a new album. The two opening acts here are family: Mitch Easter and his band, and the Sneakers, consisting of Mr. Stamey, Mr. Rigby, Mr. Easter and Robert Keely. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; $16 in advance, $18 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MARK EITZEL (Thursday) Depression is Mr. Eitzel's element; as leader of the American Music Club and through a solo career, he has anatomized melancholy down to the molecular level. In a weary voice, with tunes that blur folk songs and torch songs in a smoky haze, he looks at estrangement and betrayal, loneliness and separation, and bad luck. It's easy to believe him when he sings, ''I'm tired to the bone of always telling you goodbye.'' With the Black Swans. At 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; $12 in advance, $14 at the door. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>* FALL OUT BOY (Tuesday) One of the first groups to get wide attention for its popularity on MySpace, Fall Out Boy, from Chicago, is the model second-wave (or is this the third?) emo band: snarky and jumpy, interested in relationships over solitude, and bursting with melodic pop-punk riffs that come down from Green Day and Blink-182. With New Found Glory, Lifetime and Permanent Me. At 6:15 p.m., Hammerstein Ballroom, 311 West 34th Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-7171, mcstudios.com; $35. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PAUL GREEN SCHOOL OF ROCK MUSIC (Tomorrow and Sunday) As seen in the documentary ''Rock School,'' Mr. Green offers an extensive curriculum at his Philadelphia school, teaching youngsters the rock 'n' roll canon, as well as the fundamentals of power chords and budda-budda bass lines. Here his students offer their version of ''Jesus Christ Superstar.'' At 2:30 p.m., Rebel, 251 West 30th Street, Manhattan, (212) 695-2747, rebelnyc.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>GRUPO NICHE, JIMMY BOSCH (Tomorrow) Grupo Niche, from Colombia, holds on to the high-powered horns-and-percussion salsa forged in the 1970s. Jimmy Bosch is a trombonist who savors the Latin jazz tradition of the descarga, a jam session everyone can dance to. This ''hard salsa'' takes musical chances but never lets go of the beat. At 8 p.m., Lehman Center for the Performing Arts, 250 Bedford Park Boulevard West and Goulden Avenue, the Bronx, (718) 960-8833, lehmancenter.org; $30 to $45. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>* HASSAN HAKMOUN (Tomorrow) A leading ambassador of the ecstatic, vaguely bluesy Gnawa music of Morocco, Mr. Hakmoun, who created a sensation in the world-music circuit when he arrived in New York 20 years ago, plays one of his somewhat rare traditional concerts. Playing the sintir (a long-necked, resonant lute), Mr. Hakmoun leads spellbinding trance ceremonies, and with castanets around his ankles, performs acrobatic dances. Also on the bill is Berber music by Abderahim Boutat. At 8 p.m., Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 545-7536,symphonyspace.org or worldmusicinstitute.org; $27; $15 for students. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>HOLMES BROTHERS (Tuesday) Steeped in blues and gospel, Sherman and Wendell Holmes harmonize and raise the rafters with songs that draw hope from hard times. Their version of gospel is a close neighbor of Southern soul and country. At 7:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; $20. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>LITTLE RICHARD (Monday) He may always be most celebrated for bringing scat to rock (''A-wop-bop-a-loo-bop, a-lop-bam-boom!''), but Little Richard's delirious falsetto ''oooh!'' and androgynous showmanship have influenced everybody from Paul McCartney to Prince. At 8 p.m., B. B. King Blues Club and Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $60 in advance, $64 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BARRY MANILOW (Tuesday through Thursday) If Velveeta could sing  At 8 p.m., Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741, thegarden.com; $49.50 to $279.50. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>LIZ McCOMB (Thursday) A mezzo pop-gospel singer who grew up in Cleveland but has lived in Europe for the last 25 years, Ms. McComb moves from smoothness to Pentecostal abandon; she has been something of an ambassador in France and not that well known in her home country. At 7:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; $20. (Ben Ratliff)</p>
        <p>MOS DEF'S BIG BAND (Wednesday) Lincoln Center's American Songbook series, getting gradually more adventurous each year, opens with Mos Def, the talented and always surprising rapper and actor. Here he picks up a musical avocation, crooning with a big band, in music by Miles Davis and others. At 8:30 p.m., Allen Room, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, Broadway at 60th Street, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MY BRIGHTEST DIAMOND (Wednesday) In an expressively slippery voice, Shara Worden, who performs as My Brightest Diamond, spins luxurious fantasies that leap in scale from music boxes to colliding heavenly bodies. With Jeremy Denk and Soovin Kim, and Gabriel Kahane. At 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; $8. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ANDERS PARKER (Wednesday) Mr. Parker, who led the band Varnaline, immerses his songs in the stoic drama of country and folk music, resulting in a melancholy that is sometimes indistinguishable from cynicism. (''The hours I've wasted here I could have wasted anywhere.'') With the 'mericans. At 8 p.m., Living Room, 154 Ludlow Street, near Stanton Street, Lower East Side, (212) 533-7235, livingroomny.com; $8. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>STEVE ROSS (Tonight) In ''Americans in Paris,'' this ever-dapper singer and pianist performs a program of Parisian-scented songs in conjunction with an exhibition of paintings, ''Americans in Paris, 1860-1900,'' on view through Jan. 28. Expect lots of Cole Porter, whose airy spirit Mr. Ross channels with lilting, lighthearted suavity. At 7, Metropolitan Museum of Art, (212) 570-3949, metmuseum.org; $40. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>RON SEXSMITH (Tonight) Mr. Sexsmith seems self-effacing and hesitant at first, with a voice that sidles up to notes like a wallflower trying to slip into a party unnoticed. But behind the outward modesty is a craftsman who stubbornly upholds the verities of 1960s songwriting, placing supple melodies atop unexpected harmonies and offering wistful regret and consolation in equal parts. With Kim Taylor. At 8:30, Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; $17. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>SLOAN (Thursday) Like modern metafictions, Sloan's pop-rock songs twist inward on themselves. With their winsome tunes and neo-Beatles intricacies, Sloan's songs are not just about unrequited yearnings, but also about the process of writing pop songs about unrequited yearnings. They're rarely so clever that their heart doesn't come through. With Spiral Beach and the Love Loves. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; $20. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>TEXT OF LIGHT (Tonight) Lee Ranaldo of Sonic Youth and Alan Licht offer a guitar soundtrack to photographs and films by Laszlo Moholy-Nagy, the Hungarian artist and Bauhaus principal, and also improvise musical accompaniment to avant-garde films by Stan Brakhage and others. The performance is presented by the Whitney Museum in conjunction with an exhibition, ''Albers and Moholy-Nagy: From the Bauhaus to the New World,'' on view until Jan. 21. At 7:30, 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676, whitney.org; free with pay-what-you wish admission to the museum, after 6. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>WHEATUS (Monday) Seven years after this cheeky Long Island power-pop band scored a minor novelty hit with its Weezeresque ''Teenage Dirtbag,'' it soldiers on. New topics include BMX bikers and even the twin towers, which Brendan B. Brown, the group's leader and songwriter, says reminded him of ''Motown '60s skinny ties.'' With Midstates and Mason Dixon. At 8:30 p.m., Northsix, 66 North Sixth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 599-5103, northsix.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>CLAUDIA ACUÑA (Tuesday through Thursday) Ms. Acuña is a vocalist attracted to lyrical high drama and guided by the pulse and passion of her native Chile. She sounds best when supported by sympathetic musicians like the pianist Jason Lindner, who leads her rhythm section here. (Through next Friday.) At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $25. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>BEN ALLISON (Tomorrow) Mr. Allison, a bassist and composer, has a knack for assembling hardy and sophisticated ensembles like this one, with Michael Blake on saxophones, Frank Kimbrough on Wurlitzer keyboard and Michael Sarin on drums. At 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* KENNY BARRON TRIO (Tuesday through Thursday) Kenny Barron is the leading practitioner of an elegant, economical and rhythmically surefooted piano style that thrives in any mainstream setting; he'll explore at least a few different styles here, with Kiyoshi Kitagawa on bass and Francisco Mela on drums. (Through Jan. 21). At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>RICHARD BONA (Tonight) Mr. Bona, the Cameroonian bassist and singer, received a Grammy nomination in the contemporary world music category for his album ''Tiki'' (Decca), which he will revisit here. At 9:30, Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 539-8778, joespub.com; cover, $20, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JAMES CARNEY GROUP (Tomorrow and Sunday) James Carney, a smart keyboardist and a broadly imaginative composer, leads a trio with the flexible rhythm team of Chris Lightcap on bass and Mark Ferber on drums. Tomorrow at 9 p.m., Biscuit BBQ, 230 Fifth Avenue, at President Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 399-2161, biscuitbbq.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. Sunday at 9 p.m., Bar 4, 444 Seventh Avenue, at 15th Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 832-9800, bar4.net; suggested cover, $5. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GERALD CLAYTON TRIO (Tomorrow) Gerald Clayton was the popular favorite at last year's Thelonious Monk International Jazz Piano Competition, though he finished second. His eloquent and full-bodied style finds a good showcase in a trio with David Wong on bass and Pete Van Ostrand on drums. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>COMMON THREAD/BRASS CONSCIOUSNESS (Wednesday) Common Thread is a cadre of incisive players currently or formerly apprenticed to the influential avant-garde saxophonist Steve Coleman: the trumpeters Jonathan Finlayson and Shane Endsley, the trombonist Tim Albright, the bassist Chris Lightcap and the drummer Marcus Gilmore. Brass Consciousness, which plays a later set, adds one more trumpeter, Ralph Alessi. At 8 and 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10 per set. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* 'CUBANA BE, CUBANA BOP' (Tonight and tomorrow night) The precision-honed Afro-Latin Jazz Orchestra, under the direction of the pianist Arturo O'Farrill, presents a tribute to the pioneering Latin jazz of Dizzy Gillespie, who first performed the George Russell composition ''Cubano Be, Cubano Bop'' with his big band in the 1940s. Also on the program are reliable Gillespie flag-wavers from the same era, like ''Manteca.'' At 8, Rose Theater, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 721-6500, jalc.org; cover, $32.50 to $127.50. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DANCE NOW MUSIC (Tuesday through Thursday) Avant-garde music and movement are equal partners in this off-season Vision Festival series, which runs through next Sunday. Next week's highlights include trios led by the multireedists Joe McPhee (Tuesday) and Cooper-Moore (Wednesday), and a duo by the dancer Julia Wilkins and the alto saxophonist Matana Roberts (Thursday). (Through Jan. 21.) At 7:30 p.m., Teatro La Tea at Clemente Soto Vélez Cultural Center, 107 Suffolk Street, near Rivington Street, Lower East Side, (212) 696-6681, visionfestival.org; $20 a night ($10 for students), or three nights for $40. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SCOTT DUBOIS QUARTET (Wednesday) Scott DuBois, a guitarist equally devoted to intricate compositional forms and spacious free improvisation, celebrates the release of a new album, ''Tempest'' (Soul Note); his former teacher, the saxophonist David Liebman, joins a group with Thomas Morgan on bass and Gerald Cleaver on drums. At 10, 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ANDREW DURKIN'S INDUSTRIAL JAZZ GROUP/DARCY JAMES ARGUE'S SECRET SOCIETY (Sunday) Two powerful big bands, each guided by a clear vision. The Industrial Jazz Group, based in Los Angeles and led by the pianist Andrew Durkin, offers retro sounds with an ironic touch; the Secret Society, let by the composer Darcy James Argue, is future-minded and dead serious. At 8 p.m., Bowery Poetry Club, 308 Bowery, near Bleecker Street, East Village, (212) 614-0505; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>HARRIS EISENSTADT LOW TRIO (Sunday) The drummer Harris Eisenstadt features a lower register, and his own tunes, in this experimental trio with Jose Davila on tuba and Ben Gerstein on trombone. At 7 p.m., Jimmy's, 43 East Seventh Street, East Village, (212) 982-3006, freestylejazz.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SONNY FORTUNE QUARTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) Since the 1960s, countless saxophonists have adopted the methodology of John Coltrane, but few have captured his restless spirit. Sonny Fortune, the saxophonist of choice for the Coltrane drummer Elvin Jones, is chief among them. At 8, 10 and midnight, Sweet Rhythm, 88 Seventh Avenue South, at Bleecker Street, West Village, (212) 255-3626, sweetrhythmny.com; cover, $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>AL FOSTER QUARTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) The well-traveled Al Foster has a lithe touch as a drummer, ideal for modern jazz and more than suitable for funk; his band consists of the tenor saxophonist Eli Degibri, the pianist Kevin Hays and the bassist Doug Weiss. At 8, 10 and 11:30, Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, (212) 864-6662, smokejazz.com; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>HARRISON ON HARRISON (Tonight) On a recent album, the guitarist Joel Harrison interprets songs by a slightly more famous figure with the same surname, George Harrison. He repeats the same homage here, with David Binney on alto saxophone, Gary Versace on piano, Stephan Crump on bass and Ben Wittman on drums. At 7, Rubin Museum of Art, 150 West 17th Street, Chelsea, (212) 620-5000, Ext. 344, rmanyc.org; $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JON HENDRICKS (Wednesday and Thursday) Mr. Hendricks is the godfather of vocalese, and still irrepressible, though his voice has weathered over the years. On Tuesday he sits in with David Berger's Sultans of Swing; for the rest of the week he leads something called LHR Redux, in reference to his groundbreaking vocal trio Lambert, Hendricks and Ross. (You wonder whether he'll mention that Annie Ross, listed below, has her own gig downtown.) (Through Jan. 20.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $40, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JOHN HOLLENBECK'S CLAUDIA QUINTET (Tomorrow) This improvising chamber ensemble pursues texturally oriented and often contrapuntal exploration; Mr. Hollenbeck's drumming is one color on a palette that also includes Chris Speed's clarinet and tenor saxophone, Ted Reichman's accordion, John Hebert's bass and Matt Moran's vibraphone. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $12, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* HANK JONES TRIO (Tuesday through Thursday) Mr. Jones, one of the most estimable pianists in postwar jazz, augments his stately trio with a pair of prominent guests: the trumpeter Roy Hargrove and the singer Roberta Gambarini. (Through Jan. 21.) At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592 bluenote.net; cover, $35 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GEOFFREY KEEZER TRIO (Tonight and tomorrow night) A versatile post-bop piano trio, led by the articulate Geoffrey Keezer and featuring the bassist Tal Wilkenfeld and the drummer Terreon Gully. At 9:30 and 11:15, AC Pianocraft Showroom, 333 West 52nd Street, Clinton, (212) 254-1840, acpianocraft.com; $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DANIEL LEVIN QUARTET (Monday) Daniel Levin, a cellist, makes music full of pregnant pauses and gradual crescendos. He has dynamic cohorts in Rob Brown on alto saxophone, Joe Morris on bass and Matt Moran on drums. At 10 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVID LIEBMAN (Tonight) An incantatory saxophonist working in the post-Coltrane idiom, Mr. Liebman plays here with the bassist Ronan Guilfoyle and the drummer Tom Rainey. At 10, 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CHRIS LIGHTCAP QUINTET (Tonight) A bassist with credentials in both straight-ahead and experimental circles, Chris Lightcap fronts a group that effectively splits the difference: Chris Cheek and Tony Malaby on tenor saxophones, Jacob Sacks on Fender Rhodes piano and Ted Poor on drums. At 9 and 10:30, , Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $12, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>RENÉ MARIE (Tuesday through Thursday) A soulful jazz singer and vibrant performer with a growing book of sturdy original tunes. (Through Jan. 21.) At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>AARON PARKS QUARTET (Tomorrow) Aaron Parks, a precocious member of Terence Blanchard's groove-oriented band, leads his own working quartet with Mike Moreno on guitar, Derrick Hodge on bass and Kendrick Scott on drums. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>RE:ACTION (Wednesday) The bassist Sean Conly features his own compositions in this aptly titled band, with Tony Malaby and Michaël Attias on saxophones and Take Toriyama on drums. At 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ERIC REED QUARTET (Tonight) The pianist Eric Reed applies his trademark sophistication to the sound of a quartet featuring Stacey Dillard on tenor and soprano saxophones. At 7:30, 9:30 and 11:30, Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $30. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ANNIE ROSS (Tuesday) Ms. Ross has covered every inch of territory as a jazz singer, and yet she has her own style: supple, surefooted and knowing. She performs with a small group that includes Jon Weber on piano and Leroy Williams on drums. At 7 p.m., Metropolitan Room at Gotham, 34 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 206-0440, metropolitanroom.com; cover, $25, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ANGELICA SANCHEZ/TONY MALABY/TOM RAINEY (Sunday) A collective trio that treads a middle ground between lyricism and abstraction, with Ms. Sanchez on piano, Mr. Malaby on saxophones and Mr. Rainey on drums. At 8:30 and 10 p.m., Jimmy's, 43 East Seventh Street, East Village, (212) 982-3006, freestylejazz.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JENNY SCHEINMAN (Tuesday) Ms. Scheinman is that rare jazz violinist who embraces her instrument's folksier side without making concessions to genre. Her Tuesday night engagement features different players each week; this time around, the cast includes the clarinetist Doug Wieselman and the guitarist Steve Cardenas. At 7 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TERELL STAFFORD (Tomorrow) Mr. Stafford, a bright and assertive trumpeter, previews material from his next album, ''New Beginnings'' (MaxJazz), with a quintet that includes Tim Warfield Jr. on saxophones, Bruce Barth at the piano, Derrick Hodge on bass and Dana Hall on drums. At 7:30, 9:30 and 11:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $30. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LOREN STILLMAN AND TRIO ALTO (Thursday) ''Trio Alto Volume One'' (Steeplechase), the most recent album by the alto saxophonist Loren Stillman, suggests an explorer with one foot planted in tradition and the other caught in midstride. Mr. Stillman leads a different rhythm section here -- Sean Conly on bass and Take Toriyama on drums -- but his confident and probing approach should come across just fine. At 8:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* TERRASSON, OKEGWO, PARKER (Wednesday and Thursday) Throughout the latter half of the 1990s, the pianist Jacky Terrasson led one of jazz's fresher-sounding acoustic piano trios, distinguished not only by his fluid pianism but also by the resonant bass tone of Ugonna Okegwo and the pared-down percussive drive of Leon Parker. Last spring the trio regrouped as a collective, with uneven but deeply promising results. At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>J. D. WALTER / REFUGE TRIO (Tomorrow) J. D. Walter's voice is a flexible instrument, given to soaring scat solos and growling burrs. Another expressive vocalist, Theo Bleckmann, leads the Refuge Trio, with Gary Versace on keyboards and John Hollenbeck on drums. At 7 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, East Village, (212) 539-8778, joespub.com; cover, $15, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>* 'CONCRETE' (Wednesday and Thursday) Robert Ashley's operas have been compared to James Joyce's writing: the composer examines the ordinary world, and its language, by running it through the filters of his own creativity. ''Concrete,'' here in its world premiere, is billed as ''an old man's musing'' about people he has cared about. Mr. Ashley's orchestra will consist of computer samples that vary at each performance, and the singers will key their pitches and inflections to the sounds, creating music truly born of speech, with a conversational spontaneity. Many of the singers have worked with Mr. Ashley for decades, including Joan La Barbara, Jacqueline Humbert and Sam Ashley, the composer's son. (Through Jan. 21.) At 8 p.m., La MaMa Annex Theater, 74A East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 475-7710, lamama.org; $15 and $20. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>'THE FIRST EMPEROR' (Tomorrow) The excitement of a world premiere at the Met, combined with widespread interest among the general public in the composer Tan Dun, who won an Oscar for his film score to ''Crouching Tiger, Hidden Dragon,'' have resulted in a sold-out run for ''The First Emperor.'' Though the story of Qin Shi Huang, the first emperor of China, who unified the country through brutality and conquest, is compelling, Mr. Tan's ponderous score is a huge disappointment. There are gripping moments, especially some propulsive orchestra passages that incorporate Chinese instruments. But the opera's lyrical flights are slow-moving, ponderous and sometimes cloying. Mr. Tan has tried to meld Chinese melody and Italianate lyricism. His music, though, seems caught in some nowhere land between ''Crouching Tiger'' and Puccini's ''Turandot.'' Even the great Plácido Domingo, bravely taking on the challenging title role, cannot save the show. The colorful production is by the Chinese film director Zhang Yimou (''House of Flying Daggers''). Mr. Tan conducts. At 1:30 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; sold out. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* 'MOSTLY OPERETTA' (Tonight, Monday, Tuesday and Thursday) Once popular entertainment, today often presented as hackneyed spectacle, operetta deserves to be rehabilitated for the 21st century. At least, this is the premise of an ambitious festival at the Austrian Cultural Forum that presents both the familiar (excerpts from Lehar's ''Merry Widow'') and the less familiar (Lehar's little-known songs), sung by operetta specialists, with innovative, cutting-edge visuals by Victoria Coeln. Tonight's program (in English) is a salute to operettas that appeared on Broadway; Monday and Tuesday's is an all-Lehar program; and Thursday's juxtaposes Lehar and Kalman with less-known composers like Rudolf Friml and Leo Fall. Tonight at 8 (introductory lecture at 7); Monday, Tuesday and Thursday nights at 7; 11 East 52nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 319-5300, acfny.org; free, but reservations are required. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK GILBERT AND SULLIVAN PLAYERS (Tonight through Sunday) When this troupe was founded by Albert Bergeret in 1974, it was one of a handful of small companies devoted to the Savoyard repertory in New York. Now it is the only one left, and its performances, with Mr. Bergeret still at the helm, and with casts well drilled in the style, are always a treat. Its current season includes two perennial favorites, ''The Mikado'' and ''Yeomen of the Guard,'' and the company can be counted on to bring their splendid silliness to life. ''The Mikado'' is tonight at 8, tomorrow at 2 p.m. and Sunday at 3 p.m.; ''Yeomen of the Guard'' is tomorrow night at 8. City Center, 131 West 55th Street, Manhattan, (212) 581-1212, nycitycenter.org; $40 to $96. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* 'OTELLO' (Wednesday) Rossini's 1816 version of ''Otello'' predates Verdi's great opera by more than 70 years. Choosing Shakespeare's complex play as a subject was a risky stroke for Rossini at the time. The Naples opera company that presented it forced the composer to tweak, soften and simplify the story. The first two acts are uneven. But the great third act, dominated by Rossini's noble music for the anguished Desdemona, struck the composer Meyerbeer as ''really godlike.'' The Opera Orchestra of New York is billing its concert performance as the first New York presentation of Rossini's work. In any event, the cast looks promising, with the soprano Ruxandra Donose as Desdemona and the tenor Robert McPherson as Iago. (The tenor Ramón Vargas was to have sung the title role, but dropped out because of illness; he is being replaced by Bruce Ford.) Eve Queler conducts. At 7:30 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $25 to $125. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'THE TENDER LAND' (Tomorrow and Sunday) In 1976, when the enterprising Bronx Opera Company first presented Copland's ''Tender Land,'' the composer participated in rehearsals and attended productions. For its current production, the company is using the effective chamber version of the orchestral score, arranged by Murry Sidlin. Royston Coppenger is the director. Elizabeth W. Scott conducts tomorrow, and Michael Spierman on Sunday. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Sunday at 2 p.m., Lovinger Theater, Lehman College, Bedford Park Boulevard West and Goulden Avenue, Bedford Park, the Bronx, (718) 960-8833, bronxopera.org; $15 to $30. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'LE VILLI' (Tonight through Sunday) This opera, Puccini's first work for the stage, is a short tale of a trusting young woman from a Black Forest town in medieval Germany who is forsaken by her betrothed. When the grieving woman dies, her guilt-stricken fiancé is subjected to supernatural justice. Though the score was deeply influenced by operatic styles of the day, Puccini's intensely lyrical and richly harmonic voice comes through. The adventurous Dicapo Opera Theater presents a choreographic production of this seldom-heard work on a double bill with a staged performance of Puccini's major sacred work, the ''Messa di Gloria.'' Francisco Bonnin conducts. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 4 p.m., Dicapo Opera Theater, at St. Jean Baptiste Church, 184 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212) 288-9438, dicapo.com; $47.50. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'DIE ZAUBERFLÖTE' (Tonight) This revival of Julie Taymor's production continues at the Metropolitan Opera, complete with the magical puppets and stage effects that made it an audience hit when it opened in 2004. James Levine conducts a cast that includes Lisa Milne as Pamina, Erika Miklosa as Queen of the Night, Matthew Polenzani as Tamino, Rodion Pogossov as Papageno, Eike Wilm Schulte as the Speaker and Morris Robinson as Sarastro. At 8, Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $110 to $205 tickets remaining. (Vivien Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>ISABEL BAYRAKDARIAN AND RUSSELL BRAUN (Sunday) Patriotism has brought the fine Canadian soprano Isabel Bayrakdarian and the light Canadian baritone Russell Braun together frequently before. But the motivation for this weekend's joint recital is the George London Foundation, which presents the two singers, together with their spouses, the pianists Carolyn Maule and Serouj Kradjian, in a program of Schumann, Schubert, Debussy and Pauline Viardot (whose songs Ms. Bayrakdarian has recorded, very well). At 4 p.m., Morgan Library &amp; Museum, 225 Madison Avenue, at 36th Street, (212) 877-6347, www.themorgan.org; $45; $30 for Morgan members. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>CALEFAX (Sunday) The intimate chamber music hall at the Frick Collection has become a reliable place to discover soloists and ensembles who are new to New York but prove durable additions to the city's musical life. Calefax, a reed quintet from the Netherlands, makes its debut with an era-spanning program that runs from music by Ockeghem (born in 1410) through Sander Germanus (born in 1972). At 5 p.m., 1 East 70th Street, Manhattan, (212) 288-0700, frick.org; $25. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>CARNEGIE HALL FESTIVAL CHORUS (Tomorrow) Helmuth Rilling leads the Carnegie Hall Festival Chorus and the excellent Orchestra of St. Luke's in a performance of Bach's monumental ''St. Matthew Passion.'' The soloists are the tenor James Taylor, who sings the Evangelist; the bass Klaus Häger, who sings Jesus; the soprano Sibylla Rubens; the mezzo-soprano Ingeborg Danz; the tenor Thomas Cooley; and the bass Michael Nagy. At 7 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $25 to $82. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>CHAMBERFEST (Tuesday through Thursday) ChamberFest is an appropriate name for this series of concerts, which showcase Juilliard students who have spent their final week of winter break in daily rehearsals and coaching sessions. The program on Tuesday includes Strauss's ''Till Eulenspiegels Lustige Streiche'' and Debussy's String Quartet; Wednesday night's concert includes Ravel's ''Introduction et Allegro'' and Brahms's Clarinet Trio, while on Thursday, works by Prokofiev, Brahms and Walton will be performed. At 8 p.m., Paul Hall, Juilliard School, 60 Lincoln Center Plaza, at 65th Street, (212) 769-7406, juilliard.edu; free. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* EIGHTH BLACKBIRD (Tonight and tomorrow) This inventive and energetic young new-music ensemble from Chicago has built its audience with eclectic programming and commissioning. It has also impressed listeners by playing complex scores by memory, a feat rarely seen in ensembles playing even much more familiar music. The group's program tonight includes works by Steve Mackey, Jennifer Higdon, Gordon Fitzell and David M. Gordon. Tomorrow it is performing as part of the closing concert of the Chamber Music America national conference. Tonight at 8, the Kitchen, 512 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 255-5793, thekitchen.org; $10. Tomorrow at 4 p.m., St. Luke's Lutheran Church, 308 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 242-2022, chamber-music.org; free. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>ALLISON ELDREDGE (Tonight) This cellist, a faculty member at the New England Conservatory, performs Beethoven's Sonata in G minor (Op. 5, No. 2); Hindemith's Sonata; Brahms's Sonata in F; and Paganini's virtuoso Variations on One String on a Theme of Paganini. Max Levinson, her husband, is the pianist. At 8, Weill Recital Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $20; $10 for students and 65+. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>GUARNERI STRING QUARTET (Sunday) In its continuing campaign to make classical music available to all, the indispensable Peoples' Symphony Concerts, which offer leading artists and ensembles at very affordable prices, present the Guarneri String Quartet at Town Hall in a program of works by Haydn, Dohnanyi and Dvorak. At 2 p.m., 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 586-4680, pscny.org; $9 and $11. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>MET ORCHESTRA (Sunday) High in fiber, high in calories and generally high in content, the Met Orchestra's Carnegie Hall concerts are the Danny Meyer meals of classical music. They are long, satisfying and generally delectable, depending on the condition of the chef-conductor, James Levine. The program offers something for every taste, including the expected high-modernist course -- the premiere of ''Theologoumenon'' by Charles Wuorinen -- and the expected star soloist: the brilliant, rigorous violinist Christian Tetzlaff, playing the Beethoven concerto. But the main course is the Brahms Third. At 3 p.m., (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $50 to $160. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK COLLEGIUM (Tonight) Those favoring a reductive sweep of music history called Arnold Schoenberg and his contemporaries the Second Viennese school, the implication being that the thriving music world running roughly from Mozart through Beethoven and Schubert was the First. But what of Viennese music before that? The New York Collegium explores Baroque-era Viennese music, with works by Biber, Schmelzer and others who might prove worth a fresh look. At 8 (preconcert talk at 7), Church of St. Vincent Ferrer, Lexington Avenue at 66th Street, (212) 717-9246, nycollegium.org; $30 to $60. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC (Tomorrow and Thursday) Zubin Mehta, music director of the Philharmonic from 1978 to 1991, returns to conduct the orchestra in Bruckner's Symphony No. 7. But the highlight of the evening is likely to be Alisa Weilerstein, a passionate and highly talented 24-year-old cellist, who makes her subscription debut with the orchestra, playing Elgar's intense Cello Concerto. On Thursday Riccardo Muti conducts a program including Scriabin's ''Divin Poème'' and Tchaikovsky's Violin Concerto, with the excellent Russian violinist Vadim Repin as soloist. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Thursday at 7:30 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nyphil.org; $28 to $96. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>'SONGS OF PEACE AND WAR' (Wednesday) Delving into the song repertory to uncover surprising and pleasing nuggets, the New York Festival of Song has as much to teach singers as audiences. For their second collaboration with singers enrolled at the Juilliard School, the directors Steven Blier and Michael Barrett return to a program that originated in 2003, offering a range of songs, by composers from Shostakovich to Bob Dylan, on themes that remain all too timely. At 8 p.m., Peter Jay Sharp Theater, Juilliard School, 155 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 769-7406, www .nyfos.org; free, but tickets are required. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>TRIBUTE TO ARTURO TOSCANINI (Tuesday) The Symphonica Toscanini, founded last year in Rome, with Lorin Maazel as its music director, is introducing itself to New York in a collaboration with Mr. Maazel's other orchestra, the New York Philharmonic. The concert, billed as a tribute to the Italian orchestra's namesake on the 50th anniversary of his death, includes Strauss's ''Don Juan'' and Tchaikovsky's ''Francesca da Rimini,'' as well as arias by Cilea, Puccini and Rossini. Renée Fleming is the soloist. At 7:30 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nyphil.org; $50 to $175. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>CLARE BYRNE DANCE (Tonight through Sunday) Clare Byrne, a nicely quirky longtime presence in New York modern dance, describes her ''Rounds, the First Last Dance, or the Last First Dance, or an Ordination'' as calling up ''the doing-ness of dance.'' Uh-oh. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 3 p.m., Dance New Amsterdam, 280 Broadway, at Chambers Street, TriBeCa, (212) 279-4200, ticketcentral.com; $20. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>CEDAR LAKE CONTEMPORARY BALLET (Thursday) The company opens its winter season with a program of dance by Jacopo Godani of Italy, Edgar Zendejas of Mexico and New York's own Benoit-Swan Pouffer, who directs Cedar Lake. (Through Jan. 27.) At 8 p.m., Cedar Lake Theater, 547 West 26th Street, Chelsea, (212) 868-4444, smarttix.com; $30; $20 for 65+ and students with ID. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* Yoshiko Chuma &amp; The School of Hard Knocks (Tuesday through Thursday) In her first appearance at Dance Theater Workshop since the 1980s, Yoshiko Chuma uses 15 musicians and dancers to explore the stories of artists living in Albania, Macedonia, Japan and the United States. Don't miss what should be a layered, evocative depiction of nations struggling amid war. (Through Jan. 20.) At 7:30 p.m., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077, dtw.org; $15 and $25. (Claudia La Rocco)</p>
        <p>COMPANY EAST (Tonight through Sunday) Hiroshi Jin's Company East makes its United States debut in a dance-theater production of ''Medea'' that incorporates elements of Noh theater, Western modern dance and karate stances. Tonight and tomorrow night at 7:30, Sunday at 2:30 and 7:30 p.m., La MaMa E.T.C., 74A East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 475-7710, lamama.org; $20; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>COMPLEXIONS CONTEMPORARY BALLET (Tonight through Sunday) This company, founded in 1994 by Dwight Rhoden and Desmond Richardson, is notable for its wonderful dancers and, often, less-than-wonderful choreography. But this season looks promising, with a work by Mr. Rhoden to the music of Marvin Gaye; new pieces by Jodie Gates; and a solo for Mr. Richardson -- one of dance's true stars -- by Taye Diggs. Yes, that Taye Diggs. Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 2 and 7:30 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800, joyce.org; $42; $32 for Joyce members. (Roslyn Sulcas)</p>
        <p>* DANCE ON CAMERA FESTIVAL (Today and tomorrow) Presented by the Dance Films Association and the Film Society of Lincoln Center, this festival ranges more widely than ever, with nine dance programs created for the camera, documentaries and archival compilations. Other programs, at other locations, include a retrospective of work by Elaine Summers and discussions on editing and creating dance with a narrative. Today at 1, 3:30, 6:15 and 8:30 p.m.; tomorrow at 2 and 4 p.m., Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 496-3809, dancefilms.org; $10; $5 for 65+ and children 6 through 12. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>JEAN ISAACS SAN DIEGO DANCE THEATER (Tonight and tomorrow night) This program includes a new piece by Jeffrey Gerodias, a former Alvin Ailey dancer, and four quartets to music by Steve Reich. At 8:30, Danspace Project, St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194, danspaceproject.org; $20; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* Japanese Contemporary Dance Showcase (Tuesday through Thursday) If it's January in New York, it must be time for Japanese dance. For this event's 10th anniversary, the Japan Society has relocated to the Joyce. But the eclectic, pop-influenced sampler should be just as strange and beguiling as ever. Two programs feature work by Pappa Tarahumara, Kim Itoh &amp; the Glorious Future, Leni-Basso and Noism07. (Through Jan. 21.) Tuesday through Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800; $30; $23 for members. (La Rocco)</p>
        <p>* LOWER LIGHTS COLLECTIVE (Tonight, tomorrow and Thursday) Members of this multimedia group have worked with some pretty impressive people in dance. And how can you go wrong with a group that describes its collaborative process as ignoring one another while allowing for the subtle influence of what is seen out of the corner of the eye? In its new ''CRAM,'' the group will pour dance; a ''live horror film''; sound and noise installations; a ''living sculpture'' using potatoes as percussion; and an orchestra of instruments made from architectural salvage into every cranny of this space. (Through Jan. 20.) At 8 p.m., Chocolate Factory, 5-49 49th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (212) 352-3101, chocolatefactorytheater.org; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>NETA DANCE COMPANY (Sunday) Produced by Neta Pulvermacher and Marisa Beatty, this second season of monthly dance-and-talk series, ''The A.W.A.R.D. Show,'' opens with a program featuring dance by Amanda Loulaki, Kiyoko Kashiwagi, Ming-Lung Yang and Mei-Yin Ng. The series, which runs through May 20, concludes with one participant receiving a $10,000 grant. At 7 p.m., Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, between Houston and Prince Streets, (212) 334-7479, joyce.org; free. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* NEW YORK CITY BALLET (Tonight through Sunday, and Tuesday through Thursday) The last four performances of ''The Sleeping Beauty,'' with Wendy Whelan, Nikolaj Hübbe and Jennie Somogyi (Friday); Ashley Bouder, Benjamin Millepied and Amanda Hankes (Saturday matinee); Megan Fairchild, Joaquin De Luz and Ellen Bar (Saturday evening); and Sterling Hyltin, Jared Angle and Teresa Reichlen (Sunday matinee). Next week the company begins its controversial theme programming, beginning on Tuesday with ''Stravinsky and Balanchine: An Eternal Partnership'' (''Agon,'' ''Monumentum/Movements,'' ''Duo Concertant'' and ''Symphony in Three Movements''). The project continues on Wednesday and Thursday with ''Tradition and Innovation'' (George Balanchine's ''Mozartiana'' and ''Tchaikovsky Piano Concerto No. 2,'' and Mauro Bigonzetti's ''In Vento''). Who knows? The selections may well encourage audiences to ruminate on these weighty conceits. Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 3 p.m., Tuesday and Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 870-5570, nycballet.com; $20 to $95. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* PEAK PERFORMANCES @ MONTCLAIR: TRISHA BROWN (Thursday) Ms. Brown, now 70, celebrates her long and influential career in modern dance with a new work, ''I love my robots,'' that suggests that she is as innovative as ever. A collaboration with the visual artist Kenjiro Okazaki and the performance artist Laurie Anderson, ''robots'' will feature what Mr. Okazaki describes as two interactive ''sculptural apparitions.'' The evening also includes performances of Ms. Brown's 1983 ''Set and Reset'' and her 2005 ''how long does the subject linger on the edge of the volume?'' (Through Jan. 21.) At 7:30 p.m., Alexander Kasser Theater, Montclair State University, 1 Normal Avenue, Montclair, N.J., (973) 655-5112, peakperfs.org; $35. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>LAURA PETERSON CHOREOGRAPHY (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ms. Peterson, who has danced with everyone from Risa Jaroslow to Poppo and the GoGo Boys, describes her new ''I Love Dan Flavin'' as a tongue-in-cheek futuristic dance with fluorescent light and pioneering techno music. (Through Jan. 27.) At 8, Dixon Place, 258 Bowery, between Houston and Prince Streets, Lower East Side, (212) 219-0736, Ext. 11, dixonplace.org; $12 to $15 or T.D.F. vouchers; $10 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Martine Pisani (Thursday) Three may be a crowd, but in ''Bande à Part'' (''Band of Outsiders''), four is a solo. The French choreographer Martine Pisani seeks to mold the work of four performers into one solo, a single performer at a time, while the rest of the ensemble looks on. (Through Jan. 21.) At 8:30 p.m., Danspace Project, St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194; $15 or T.D.F. vouchers. (La Rocco)</p>
        <p>VISION DANCE MUSIC SERIES (Tuesday through Thursday) This six-day festival has two to four shows a night featuring collaborations among dance and music artists like Sally Silvers, Baraka de Soleil and Gloria McLean. (Through Jan. 21.) At 7:30 p.m., Teatro La Tea @ Clemente Soto Vélez Cultural Center, 107 Suffolk Street, Lower East Side, (212) 696-6681, visionfestival.org; $20 a night; $10 a night for students and 65+; $40 for three nights. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* American Museum of Natural History: 'GOLD,' through Aug. 19. Having delved into pearls, diamonds and amber, the museum applies its time-tested show-and-tell formula to gold. An astounding array of art, artifacts and natural samples, larded with fascinating facts and tales, ranges from prehistoric times to the present. Stops along the way include pre-Columbian empires, sunken treasure, Bangladesh dowry rituals and the moon landing. It turns out that gold comes from the earth in forms as beautiful as anything man has thought to do with it. Central Park West and 79th Street, (212) 769-5100, amnh.org. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>China Institute: 'Shu,' through Feb. 24. This second installation of a two-part show glances back at the period of artistic expansion in the 1970s, and its contraction, after the 1989 Tiananmen Square protests. Qiu Zhijie's photographic ''library,'' which papers the walls of the China Institute's main staircase, makes evident the information explosion in the 80s. Among the thousands of titles are Chinese classics, books on natural sciences and treatises by Plato, Disraeli and Harold Bloom. Such a trove might have been considered a treasure before Tiananmen Square; afterward, such resources became sources of angst. The figure that appears throughout Zhang Xiaogang's 1991 series ''Private Notes,'' for example, looks as if he is losing his mind -- and his head, torso and myriad other body parts -- as he struggles to write letters and decode illegible manuscripts. Without easy access to words, the images imply, there can be no such thing as free expression. 125 East 65th Street, (212) 744-8181, chinainstitute.org. (Bridget L. Goodbody)</p>
        <p>Cooper-Hewitt National Design Museum: 'DESIGN LIFE NOW: NATIONAL DESIGN TRIENNIAL 2006,' through July 29. This ambitious show illuminates the volatile, contradictory and ever-expanding field, but fails to call it to order. The inclusions cover medical innovation, military hardware, frivolous reiterations of received ideas, sundry Web sites and magazines, haute couture, architecture and more varieties of recycling than you can easily count. The show coalesces into deliberately orchestrated skirmishes between conflicting principles and entities: corporate and private, decorative and essential. 2 East 91st Street, (212) 849-8400, ndm.si.edu. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'Spanish Painting from El Greco to Picasso, TIME, TRUTH, AND HISTORY' through March 28. This show is carried along on its sheer star power and optical finesse. There are dozens of Goyas and Velázquezes and Zurbaráns and El Grecos and Riberas and Dalís and Picassos, many famous, many not. The big point is that Spanish art did not constantly reinvent itself over time. It was a bubble culture, sustained for centuries by its political and religious isolation and its national loner mindset. Velázquez's painting of a dwarf is alone worth crossing a continent to see. 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3500, guggenheim.org. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* THE METropolitan museum of art: 'GLITTER AND DOOM: GERMAN PORTRAITS FROM THE 1920s,' through Feb. 19. This show's 100 paintings and drawings are by 10 artists, among them George Grosz, Christian Schad, Rudolf Schlichter and Karl Hubbuch, and most conspicuously the unrelentingly savage Otto Dix and his magnificent other, Max Beckmann. In their works the Weimar Republic's porous worlds reassemble. We look into the faces of forward-looking museum directors and cabaret performers, society matrons and scarred war veterans, prostitutes and jaded aristocrats who were watching their world slide from one cataclysm to the next. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* THE MET: 'LOUIS COMFORT TIFFANY AND LAURELTON HALL -- AN ARTIST'S COUNTRY ESTATE,' through May 20. Laurelton Hall may have burned to the ground in 1957, but this exhibition does an excellent job of reassembling what remains of this extraordinary house-museum and its gardens, which Tiffany created for himself in the early 1900s. The Gilded Age opulence of the place, which occupied 580 acres overlooking Long Island Sound -- and of the Tiffany residences preceding it -- is conveyed most blatantly by the Temple-of-Dendur-size Daffodil Terrace, in wood, marble and glass. The main events are the glass windows, vases and lamps, where Tiffany's genius for color, love of the exotic and reverence for nature coalesce into an unforgettable mystical materialism. (See above.) (Smith)</p>
        <p>* MORGAN LIBRARY &amp; MUSEUM: 'SAUL STEINBERG: ILLUMINATIONS,' through March 4. Saul Steinberg's famous New Yorker cover positioning Manhattan at the center of the world may be his best-known drawing, but he took on everything with visual puns, manic doodles, grandiloquent calligraphy and other inspired artifice. As this show of more than 100 drawings, collages and constructions goes on, Steinberg's progress is evident: from relatively simple cartoons like ''Feet on Chair'' (1946), in which a fellow reading a newspaper parks his feet on the seat of an ornate Victorian monstrosity, to complex comments on the state of the world, like ''Street War (Cadavre Exquisis)'' (about 1972-74), derived from news clips of postcolonial troubles in the Middle East and Africa. The flow of his work amazes. 225 Madison Avenue, at 36th Street, (212) 685-0008, morganlibrary.org. (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>* MUSEUM OF THE CITY OF NEW YORK: 'A CITY ON PAPER: SAUL STEINBERG'S NEW YORK,' through March 25. A very lively adjunct to the Morgan show, this smaller display of some 40 drawings focuses on New York. An architect, Steinberg was particularly attracted to edifices like the Chrysler Building, which appears here looming majestically over brownstones and in another incarnation, from a perspective directly below it, looking positively squat. New York people, in Steinberg's eyes, could be monuments, too. You may think you know Steinberg's work, but these shows make it new. 1220 Fifth Avenue at 103rd Street, (212) 534-1672, mcny.org. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>Whitney Museum of American Art: 'Kiki Smith: A Gathering, 1980-2005,' through Feb. 11. Many things fly and float here: men and women, harpies and angels, birds and beasts, toadstools and stars. And some things fall to earth, or rather to the museum's black stone floors, maybe to rise again, maybe not. The whole show, a midcareer retrospective, suggests a Victorian fairy tale, its tone at once light, grievous and dreamlike. But fanciful as it is, Ms. Smith's art is also deeply, corporeally realistic. It wears moral and mortal seriousness on its sleeve, if not tattooed on its wrist. It is about life and death, the essential things. 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676, whitney.org. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>* SERGIO PREGO To take the fullest pleasure in this exhibition, you must stand perfectly still and quiet in front of ''Black Monday'' (2006), a single-channel video of still life photographs of con trolled fireworks explosions taken inside an abandoned factory in Bilbao, Spain. In all, the artist took more than a thousand photographs of 17 different explosions, using 40 cameras. He then scanned them into a computer, cropped them and ran them together to create the video. He also composed what he calls ''a sequencing of sounds,'' a series of repeating ambient electronic noises that serve as the soundtrack. The result is a multifaceted representation of something that is usually invisible to the eye: explosion clouds immobilized in time and space, forming immensely beautiful sculptural shapes. Lehmann Maupin Gallery, 540 West 26th Street, Chelsea, (212) 255-2923, www.lehmannmaupin.com, through Feb 10. (Benjamin Genocchio)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* HENRY DARGER: THE VIVIAN GIRLS EMERGE Further proof that Henry Darger's epic art did not spring whole from a fevered outsider brain is provided by a cache of his early forays into image collecting and collage. Most spectacular is ''The Battle of Calverhine,'' a leathery, reliclike panorama of carefully knit and hand-tinted found images. It teems with all things Darger (and not a little Pop) and has never been exhibited in this country. Andrew Edlin Gallery, 529 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 206-9723; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* CANDIDA HOFER  In large color photographs of the different galleries of the Louvre, taken on Tuesdays when the museum is closed, both the long, vaulted spaces and the painting and sculpture they contain speak of different times and styles. Equally affecting, if not a little frightening, is the lavish, timeless grandeur of these vistas. A palace that became a museum, the Louvre is also a precursor of the barrel-vaulted arcades that sprang up in Paris in the first half of the 19th century. Most of them are gone, but the Louvre's arcades live on. Sort of. Sonnabend Gallery, 536 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 627-1018; closes tomorrow(Smith)</p>
        <p>NINA KATCHADOURIAN: 'OFFICE SEMAPHORE' Ms. Katchadourian has borrowed marine flag signaling techniques to create an interactive art project consisting of an old-fashioned tourist telescope installed at the corner of a plaza in the middle of the financial district, its lens trained on the window of an upper-floor office in a nearby skyscraper. Each day the man working in the office, or his assistant, arranges objects on his widow sill. The combination and order of the objects represent a specific message, which viewers down on the plaza can interpret using a key-chart on the telescope. 1 Chase Manhattan Plaza, corner of Liberty and William Streets, Lower Manhattan; stairway entrance to the plaza is on William Street, at Cedar Street; www.publicartfund.org; closes on Sunday. (Genocchio)</p>
        <p>* The MET: 'SEAN SCULLY: WALL OF LIGHT' The capacious, day-lighted mezzanine galleries at the Met are the perfect setting for Sean Scully's bold and energizing ''Wall of Light'' paintings from the series he started in 1998. These large-scale oils on canvas wow the viewer with their scale, intensity of color and sheer dominance of space. They are complemented by tiny independent watercolors that Mr. Scully sees as ''antidotes'' to the big ones. All have this in common: They are richly painted surfaces of close-laid vertical and horizontal bars (he calls them bricks), whose arrangement suggests constructed walls of stone. Although they appear totally abstract, with their all-over arrangements of bars that superficially vary only in color, size and juxtaposition, they evoke landscapes, people, events, the work of other artists. ''I'm trying to turn stone into light,'' Mr. Scully has said, and the more you look at them, the more filled with light and life they become. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org; closes on Monday. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>HELEN MIRRA: BREAK CAMP This show of carefully composed, low-lying sculptures made from cut-up wood pallets has a smooth, almost Zen serenity, but its thoughtful brand of Post-Minimalism seems both precious and overly familiar, creating the impression of an engaging sensibility that could aim much higher. Peter Freeman Inc., 560 Broadway, at Prince Street, SoHo, (212) 966-5154; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Museum of Arts &amp; Design: 'Simply DROOG: 10 + 3 YEARS OF CREATING DISCUSSION AND INNOVATION' . Droog Design, a many-headed, loosely affiliated collective of usually, but not entirely, Dutch designers and architects, has probably generated more discussion than innovation in its 13 years of existence. Presented in a free-flowing, Droog-designed layout, this show vigorously continues the process. It includes about 150 mostly domestic objects by scores of designers. Some are great, some are silly, some are Conceptual Art. But there is plenty to sink your teeth into, especially with help from the small free brochure containing label information and rationales for each item. 40 West 53rd Street, (212) 956-3535, madmuseum.org; closes on Sunday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Moma: 'BRICE MARDEN: A RETROSPECTIVE OF PAINTINGS AND DRAWINGS' This quietly magnificent 40-year retrospective pays tribute to an artist who helped rebuild painting in the 1970s, working back from the brink of single-panel monochromes to elegant tangles of thick line on vibrant monochrome grounds that encompass a tremendous emotional range and sense of physical energy, and give the lie to the idea that any art can be purely formal or completely abstract. Mr. Marden converted the rule-ridden zone of Minimalist abstraction into a capacious yet disciplined place, pushing it toward landscape, the figure and its roots in Abstract Expressionism and beyond, in non-Western art. And he may have saved the best for last. (212) 708-9400; closes on Monday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center: 'DEFAMATION OF CHARACTER'  With 46 artists and a mix of usual and unusual suspects, this exhibition forms a black hole in which Dada, Fluxus, Punk, Pop, Conceptual and Neo-Conceptual mingle like cackling furies, along with Performance art, feminism, abject art and various forms of appropriation. While its dour tone becomes a bit relentless, it is admirably consistent and shows artists grappling with reality, which has its own kind of comfort. 22-25 Jackson Avenue, at 46th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 784-2084, ps1.org; closes on Monday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center: 'THE GOLD STANDARD' Gold is both color and subject in this glittering, pertinent show, installed on creamy yellow walls. Even though a generally dim view of contemporary society prevails, it is scary how good gold makes everything look. (See above.) Closes on Monday (Smith)</p>
        <p>Sigmar Polke Painting is man's oldest conjuring trick, and Sigmar Polke is one of its reigning magicians. In this show, new paintings and those from the 1980s, all two-sided and painted with resin, surround a small selection of German Baroque amber (Bernstein is German for amber) jewelry and exquisite tchotchkes. The show simulates a Wunderkammer, a darkened wonder cabinet of the 17th or 18th century. The paintings, made translucent by the resin, nearly defy deciphering. Doodles and abstract splashes of white paint overlay murky washes of glowing resin on both sides of their membranous support, then cast dim shadows on the wall behind, so that the pictures seem suspended in midair, floating. Michael Werner Gallery, 4 East 77th Street, (212) 988-1623, www.michaelwerner.net; closes tomorrow (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>Queens Museum of Art: 'Queens International 2006: Everything All at Once' . The 52 artists and two collaboratives in this exhibition are natives of various regions of North America, as well as of Bosnia, China, India, Iran, Japan, Korea, the Netherlands, Peru and Venezuela. The only common ground, perhaps, is that they all live in Queens. Instead of arranging the work according to medium, ethnicity or generalized themes, the curators follow the edict of the exhibition's subtitle. The show tries to balance the interests of the art crowd and local residents. Sometimes these concerns dovetail nicely, as in Sophia Peer's quick-cut video ''Everyday,'' which shows her aging parents moving around their cramped home in Queens like latter-day, empty-nest Bunkers. Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, (718) 592-9700, www.queensmuseum.org; closes on Sunday. (Martha Schwendener)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the New York metropolitan region this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'THE FEVER' In previews; opens on Jan. 24. Wallace Shawn stars in his own play about a man who wakes up in a war-torn country feeling under the weather (1:40). Acorn Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'FRANK'S HOME' Previews start tomorrow. Opens on Jan. 30. Richard Nelson's new bio-play about the life and work of Frank Lloyd Wright stars Peter Weller (as Wright) and Harris Yulin (who plays Louis Sullivan) (1:45). Playwrights Horizons Mainstage, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 719-4200.</p>
        <p>'THE GAZILLION BUBBLE SHOW' Performances begin on Wednesday. Fan Yan holds the world's record for the largest bubble ever blown, and in an even more amazing feat, he's parlayed this oddball stunt into a bubble-themed, family-friendly show (2:00). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'IN THE HEIGHTS' In previews; opens on Feb. 8. A new Off Broadway musical about two days in the life of Washington Heights, presented from the vantage point of a corner bodega (2:10). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'KIKI AND HERB' On the heels of a Broadway stint, these cabaret hipsters return to their downtown roots (1:30). Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555.</p>
        <p>'THE MERCHANT OF VENICE' In previews; opens on Feb. 4. F. Murray Abraham plays Shylock in this Theater for a New Audience production. Darko Tresnjak directs (2:20). The Duke on 42nd Street, 229 West 42nd Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'A SPANISH PLAY' In previews; opens on Feb. 1. Zoe Caldwell leads an extraordinary cast (Linda Emond, Denis O'Hare, Larry Pine, Katherine Borowitz) in Yasmina Reza's new backstage play, in which real life and fiction blur (1:30). Classic Stage Company, 136 East 13th Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101.</p>
        <p>'TRANSLATIONS' In previews; opens on Jan. 25. Brian Friel's drama about a British officer in 19th-century rural Ireland deals with themes of language, imperialism and culture clash. Garry Hynes directs (2:15). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE APPLE TREE' The amazing Kristin Chenoweth gives Imax-screen-size life to three curvaceous doodles who by rights shouldn't be any larger than figures in the Sunday funnies. Jerry Bock and Sheldon Harnick's 1966 musical, directed by Gary Griffin, shows its age but is given theatrical verve by Ms. Chenoweth, Brian d'Arcy James and Marc Kudisch (2:30). Studio 54, 254 West 54th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>'A CHORUS LINE' If you want to know why this show was such a big deal when it opened 31 years ago, you need only experience the thrilling first five minutes of this revival. Otherwise, this archivally exact production, directed by Bob Avian, feels like a vintage car that has been taken out of the garage, polished up and sent on the road once again (2:00). Schoenfeld Theater, 236 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE COAST OF UTOPIA' The exhilarating first two installments of Tom Stoppard's trilogy about 19th-century Russian intellectuals dreaming of revolution, these productions pulse with the dizzy, spring-green arrogance and anxiety of a new generation moving as fast as it can toward the future. Jack O'Brien directs a fresh, vigorous and immense cast that includes Brian F. O'Byrne, Jennifer Ehle, Billy Crudup and Ethan Hawke (2:45). Vivian Beaumont Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'COMPANY' Fire, beckoning and dangerous, flickers beneath the frost of John Doyle's elegant, unexpectedly stirring revival of Stephen Sondheim and George Furth's era-defining musical from 1970, starring a compellingly understated Raul Esparza. Like Mr. Doyle's ''Sweeney Todd,'' this production finds new clarity of feeling in Sondheim by melding the roles of performers and musicians (2:20). Barrymore Theater, 243 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE' (Tony Awards, best book of a musical and best original score, 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920s stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, it has theatergoers responding as if they were withering houseplants finally being watered after long neglect. Bob Martin and Sutton Foster are the standouts in the avid, energetic cast (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* ' 'GREY GARDENS' Christine Ebersole is absolutely glorious as the middle-aged, time-warped debutante called Little Edie Beale in this uneven musical adaptation of the notorious 1975 documentary of the same title. She and the wonderful Mary Louise Wilson (as her bedridden mother), in the performances of their careers, make ''Grey Gardens'' an experience no passionate theatergoer should miss (2:40). Walter Kerr Theater, 219 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE LITTLE DOG LAUGHED' The comedy of manners, a form widely believed to be extinct in the American theater, has actually resurfaced on Broadway with all its vital signs intact in Douglas Carter Beane's breezy but trenchant satire about truth and illusion, Hollywood style. With the wonderful Julie White as the movie agent you hate to love (but just can't help it) (2:00). Cort Theater, 138 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MARY POPPINS' This handsome, homily-packed, mechanically ingenious and rather tedious musical, adapted from the P. L. Travers stories and the 1964 Disney film, is ultimately less concerned with inexplicable magic than with practical psychology. Ashley Brown, who sings prettily as the family-mending nanny, looks like Joan Crawford trying to be nice and sounds like Dr. Phil. Directed by Richard Eyre and Matthew Bourne (2:30). New Amsterdam Theater, 214 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LES MISÉRABLES' This premature revival, a slightly scaled-down version of the well-groomed behemoth that closed only three years ago, appears to be functioning in a state of mild sedation. Appealingly sung and freshly orchestrated, this fast-moving adaptation of Victor Hugo's novel isn't sloppy or blurry. But its pulse rate stays well below normal (2:55). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' Duncan Sheik and Steven Sater's bold adaptation of the Frank Wedekind play is the freshest and most exciting new musical Broadway has seen in some time. Set in 19th-century Germany but with a ravishing rock score, it exposes the splintered emotional lives of adolescents just discovering the joys and sorrows of sex. Performed with brio by a great cast, with supple direction by Michael Mayer and inventive choreography by Bill T. Jones (2:00). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN'  This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a superdeluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE VERTICAL HOUR' David Hare's soggy consideration of the Anglo-American cultural divide stars Julianne Moore (representing the Americans) and Bill Nighy (leading the British), directed by Sam Mendes. The Yanks don't stand a chance. With his irresistibly mannered performance as a laconic doctor, Mr. Nighy mops the floor with Ms. Moore. Actually, he mops the floor with Mr. Hare's play (2:20). Music Box Theater, 239 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE BIG VOICE: GOD OR MERMAN?' Think of two gifted and smart gay men with years of life together deploying their considerable talents from the two pianos you happen to have in your living room. The result is a hilarious and very touching memoir of two decades of love and the funky glories of show business life (2:00). Actors Temple Theater, 339 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Honor Moore)</p>
        <p>*'THE CLEAN HOUSE' Sarah Ruhl's comedy about the painful but beautiful disorder of life has arrived in New York at last in a gorgeous production directed by Bill Rauch. Blair Brown and Jill Clayburgh delight as sisters with different views on the meaning of cleaning, and Vanessa Aspillaga is equally good as the depressed maid with little affection for her work but a deep conviction that a good joke can be a matter of life and death (2:15). Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, Lincoln Center, 150 West 65th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'DAI (ENOUGH)' Iris Bahr's unnerving one-woman show doesn't have much to add to the Middle East debate, but it sure leaves a lasting impression. Ms. Bahr plays an assortment of characters who have the misfortune of being in a Tel Aviv cafe that is about to be visited by the havoc common to such establishments. The attack is rendered in jarring fashion, repeatedly; you watch the play on pins and needles, waiting for the next burst. Gimmicky? Sure. But viscerally effective (1:40). Culture Project, 55 Mercer Street, at Broome Street, SoHo, (212) 253-9983. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'EVIL DEAD: THE MUSICAL' This likable horror comedy based on Sam Raimi's gory movies wants to be the next ''Rocky Horror Show.'' To that end, it offers deadpan lyrics, self-referential humor and geysers of stage blood (2:00). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>'THE FANTASTICKS' A revival -- well, more like a resuscitation -- of the Little Musical That Wouldn't Die. This sweet-as-ever production of Tom Jones and Harvey Schmidt's commedia-dell'arte-style confection is most notable for Mr. Jones's touching performance (under the pseudonym Thomas Bruce) as the Old Actor, a role he created when the show opened in 1960. Mr. Jones also directs (2:05). Snapple Theater Center, 210 West 50th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JACQUES BREL IS ALIVE AND WELL AND LIVING IN PARIS' A powerfully sung revival of the 1968 revue, presented with affectionate nostalgia by the director Gordon Greenberg. As in the original, two men and two women perform a wide selection of Brel's plaintive ballads and stirring anthems (2:00). Zipper Theater, 336 West 37th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'A JEW GROWS IN BROOKLYN' You don't have to be Jewish or Brooklynish to empathize with Jake Ehrenreich, but in terms of fully appreciating his essentially one-man show, it probably helps. Especially the Catskills jokes (2:05). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 560-8912. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'MEET ME IN ST. LOUIS' This musical is too big for its stage, but the young turn-of-the-last-century sweethearts have great chemistry, and there are four terrific songs (2:00). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'MY MOTHER'S ITALIAN, MY FATHER'S JEWISH AND I'M IN THERAPY'  Steve Solomon does skillful impersonations in his one-man show, but some of his jokes are as old as the hills (1:30). Little Shubert Theater, 422 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'NO CHILD'  Teachers will love Nilaja Sun's one-woman show about the challenges of teaching drama at Malcolm X High School (1:10). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, at Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'REGRETS ONLY' Old acquaintance comes under siege in Paul Rudnick's chiffon-thin comedy about the varieties of love and marriage. But no one who sees this latest offering from one of the funniest quipmeisters alive is going to doubt that Christine Baranski is a one-liner's best friend (2:00). City Center Stage I, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RIDDLELIKELOVE (WITH A SIDE OF KETCHUP)' This one-woman show, in which Julie Fitzpatrick tells of her friendship with a deaf woman, is cloying and thin, but the sign-language interpretation provided at each performance gives it an interesting extra dimension, helping to bring the subject to life (1:30). Ensemble Studio Theater, 549 West 52nd Street, Clinton, (212) 352-3101. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'ROOM SERVICE' The Peccadillo Theater Company puts a charge into this comedy from the 1930s, thanks to a brisk pace by the director, Dan Wackerman, and a dozen dandy performances. David Edwards is the would-be producer whose bills threaten to swamp his efforts to put a show on Broadway, and Fred Berman is particularly fine as his director (2:00). SoHo Playhouse, 15 Vandam Street, South Village, (212) 691-1555. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'SUDDENLY LAST SUMMER'  As the luscious (and lobotomy-threatened) damsel in distress in Tennessee Williams's famously lurid melodrama, Carla Gugino gives a gutsy assurance to a production that otherwise lacks compelling confidence. Mark Brokaw directs a cast that includes Blythe Danner, in a fascinating but misconceived performance as a smothering mother from hell (1:30). Laura Pels Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'25 QUESTIONS FOR A JEWISH MOTHER' This is the comedian Judy Gold's fiercely funny monologue, based on her own life as a single Jewish lesbian mother and interviews with more than 50 other Jewish mothers (1:20). St. Luke's Theater, 308 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Phoebe Hoban)</p>
        <p>'TWO TRAINS RUNNING'  Directed by Lou Bellamy, a rough-edged revival of August Wilson's 1992 play about the stark economics of life and death for African-Americans, set in a dying diner in Pittsburgh in the late 1960s. The pace drags in this production, but it remains a bracing reminder of Mr. Wilson's singular talent for making cold, hard numbers sing hot, molten blues (3:40). Signature Theater at Peter Norton Space, 555 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 352-3101. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE VOYSEY INHERITANCE' David Mamet has cleanly and cannily adapted Harley Granville Barker's 1905 play about corruption in the genteel world of Victorian finance. An excellent cast and a sumptuous production bring extra immediacy to a tale of embezzlement and entitlement that feels as fresh as tomorrow's stock options (1:50). Atlantic Theater, 336 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'FLUKE' A meditative collage of enigmatic riffs on ''Moby-Dick'' presented by the rambunctious experimental company Radiohole (1:30). Collapsable Hole, 146 Metropolitan Avenue, at Berry Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 388-2251. (Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'T J AND DAVE' The comics T. J. Jagodowski and Dave Pasquesi miraculously improvise a one-hour play at every performance. This is an impressive feat of mental athletics, but the results are also observant, complex and frequently enormously funny (1:00). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden Theater, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' Singing CliffsNotes for Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' Often more entertaining than the real thing (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS'  The biomusical that walks like a man (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT'  A singing scrapbook for Monty Python fans (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' ''A Chorus Line'' with pimples (1:45). Circle in the Square, 254 West 50th Street, Manhattan, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'BUTLEY'  In this uneasy revival of Simon Gray's portrait of a toxic English professor, directed by Nicholas Martin, Nathan Lane fires off witticisms as if they were silver bullets with ''Made in Britain'' engraved on them. A less-than-perfect marriage of a first-rate actor with a first-rate play (2:30). Booth Theater, 222 West 45th Street, Manhattan, (212) 239-6200; closes on Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'AN OAK TREE' Tim Crouch plays a hypnotist in this elusive puzzle of a play about grief and the power of suggestion (1:05). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, at Seventh Avenue, West Village, (212) 239-6200; closes on Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'PURITY' The provocateur Thomas Bradshaw's horror show confronts black-on-black racism (1:15). Performance Space 122, 150 First Avenue, at Ninth Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101; closes on Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'SLAVA'S SNOWSHOW' Clowns chosen by the Russian master Slava Polunin stir up laughter and enjoyment. A show that touches the heart as well as tickles the funny bone (1:30). Union Square Theater, 100 East 17th Street, (212) 307-4100; closes on Sunday. (Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>'BABEL' (R, 143 minutes, in English, Spanish, Japanese, Berber, Arabic and sign language) This hugely ambitious movie tells four loosely linked, not quite simultaneous stories set on three different continents, with dialogue in several languages. The themes, to the extent they are decipherable, include loss, fate and the terrible consequences of miscommunication. Written by Guillermo Arriaga and directed by Alejandro Gonzalez Iñárritu, the movie is an intellectual muddle but a visceral tour de force, and the power of the filmmaking almost overcomes the fuzziness of the ideas. Almost. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>'BLACK CHRISTMAS' (R, 100 minutes) It's been more than 30 years since the original ''Black Christmas'' revealed how much fun it could be to unleash a psycho in a sorority house. Glen Morgan's disastrous remake not only sidelines the original's hilariously obscene phone calls but also drags its unseen killer, and his psychoses, into the light. Smothering terror beneath a blanket of unnecessary information, the movie is no more than a dismal Christmas card to its predecessor. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'BLOOD DIAMOND' (R, 138 minutes) The makers of this foolish thriller about illegal diamond trafficking in Africa, starring an excellent Leonardo DiCaprio, want you to know there may be blood on your hands, specifically your wedding finger. Too bad they haven't thought through what it means to turn human misery into entertainment. (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'BORAT: CULTURAL LEARNINGS OF AMERICA FOR MAKE BENEFIT GLORIOUS NATION OF KAZAKHSTAN' (R, 89 minutes) In this brainy, merciless comedy, a Kazakh journalist named Borat Sagdiyev, a k a the British comic Sacha Baron Cohen, invades America. America laughs, cries, surrenders. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'CASINO ROYALE' (PG-13, 144 minutes) The latest James Bond vehicle finds the British spy leaner, meaner and now played by an attractive piece of blond rough named Daniel Craig. Zap, pow, ka-ching! (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'CHARLOTTE'S WEB' (G, 113 minutes) Gary Winick's adaptation of E. B. White's great children's novel is faithful to the wit and feeling of the source. The celebrity-voiced animals are charming, and Julia Roberts is in fine form as the heroic spider, whose writing ability saves the life of a pig. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'CHILDREN OF MEN' (R, 100 minutes) The end is nigh in this superbly directed political thriller by Alfonso Cuarón about a nervously plausible future. Based on the P. D. James book, the film stars an excellent Clive Owen and features equally sterling support from the actors Michael Caine, Danny Huston and Chiwetel Ejiofior, among others, as well as the great cinematographer Emmanuel Lubezki. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'CODE NAME: THE CLEANER' (PG-13, 91 minutes) Cedric the Entertainer clogs the arteries of what could have been a savvy riff on the ''Bourne'' films with way too much ham, playing a janitor who wakes up with amnesia, a dead man beside him. A missing computer chip fuels the plot, aided by Lucy Liu and Nicollette Sheridan. Though it's all too dumb to amuse grownups, it's harmless fun for tweener types. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'COMEDY OF POWER' (No rating, 110 minutes, in French) Isabelle Huppert is brisk and fierce as a French investigative judge going after corrupt fat cats. The director, Claude Chabrol, is more interested in the forms of ruling-class behavior than in the details of high-level criminality, but his detached, complacent style makes for an interesting contrast with Ms. Huppert's conviction. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'CURSE OF THE GOLDEN FLOWER' (R, 114 minutes, in Mandarin) The Chinese director Zhang Yimou aims for Shakespeare and winds up with Jacqueline Susann in this Tang dynasty melodrama roiling with incest, fraternal rivalry and madness-inducing fungus. As an emperor and empress fighting for control of their three sons, Chow Yun Fat and Gong Li lend the film a core of marital toxicity that's deliciously unstable. Directing with operatic delirium, Mr. Zhang has created a movie in which the line between tragedy and black comedy has been all but erased. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'THE DEAD GIRL' (R, 93 minutes) An impressively well-acted movie, ''The Dead Girl'' has a chip on its shoulder. The relentless emotional violence in it, a compendium of five vignettes related to a young woman whose naked, mutilated corpse is discovered on a barren hillside, is of a level rarely found in movies, even those steeped in gore. There is some gore in ''The Dead Girl,'' but it is eclipsed in intensity by the verbal abuse hurled by its desperately unhappy characters at the people closest to them. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'THE DEPARTED' (R, 150 minutes) Martin Scorsese's cubistic entertainment about men divided by power, loyalty and their own selves is at once a success and a relief. Based on the crackling Hong Kong thriller ''Infernal Affairs,'' it features fine twinned performances from Matt Damon and Leonardo DiCaprio, and a showboating Jack Nicholson. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'DHOOM 2' (No rating, 151 minutes, in Hindi) A slick and satisfying example of the new, thoroughly modern Bollywood, this cops-and-robbers tale is animated by old-fashioned star power. Hrithik Roshan plays the ''smartest and coolest thief alive,'' and Aishwarya Rai is the small-time crook who loves him. (Rachel Saltz)</p>
        <p>'ERAGON' (PG, 99 minutes) This lad-and-his-dragon fantasy set in a land bristling with Tolkienesque nomenclature and earnest British actors is as lacking in fresh ideas as Tim Allen's manager. Directed by the wonderfully named Stefen Fangmeier, it boasts the usual genre lineup: an evil king (John Malkovich), a whey-faced hero (Edward Speleers) and a serene warrior-maiden (Sienna Guillory), as well as the required rebel hordes and bucolic landscapes. Some of the characters won't be returning for the sequel, but no matter. In all likelihood, neither will the audience. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* 'FLUSHED AWAY' (PG, 85 minutes) Sewer rats, singing leeches and whimsical British anarchy -- this computer-animated feature from Aardman Animations (''Wallace and Gromit,'' ''Chicken Run'') is completely delightful. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'FOR YOUR CONSIDERATION' (PG-13, 86 minutes) This satire of pre-Oscar-nomination buzz in Hollywood is far and away the broadest comedy Christopher Guest and his improvisatory company have made. It is also the flimsiest, and unlike Mr. Guest's earlier films, it has no airs of being a fake documentary. As farce trumps satire, the humor's subversive edge is lost, along with meaningful character development, with the brilliant exception of Catherine O'Hara. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'FREEDOM WRITERS' (PG-13, 123 minutes) Hilary Swank uses her characteristic neediness to fine effect in a true-to-life story about a teacher making a difference in a Southern California high school. The writer and director Richard LaGravenese provides the smartly laid foundation, but it's the kids who give the film its strong emotional tug. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE GOOD GERMAN' (R, 102 minutes) In his adaptation of the Joseph Kanon novel, Steven Soderbergh tries to resurrect the magic of classical Hollywood, principally by sucking out all the air, energy and pleasure from his own filmmaking. It's no wonder George Clooney, who stars alongside a vamping Cate Blanchett, looks confused. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'HAPPILY N'EVER AFTER' (PG, 87 minutes) Like Dreamworks's ''Shrek'' comedies, ''Happily'' is a grab-bag parody set in a fantasyland derived from bedtime stories and Disney films. The adopted chambermaid Ella (voiced by Sarah Michelle Gellar, drawn like Winona Ryder) and the poor dishwasher Rick (Freddie Prinze Jr.) battle Ella's wicked stepmother, Frieda (Sigourney Weaver). Despite self-aware touches, this is another tired kidsploitation product in which a wasp-waisted ingénue and a shallow beau drive the plot and live happily ever after. (Matt Zoller Seitz)</p>
        <p>'HAPPY FEET' (PG, 100 minutes) The director George Miller gets happy and snappy, then goes dark and deep, in a musical about an animated penguin who was born to dance. Take hankies. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'INLAND EMPIRE' (No rating, 179 minutes) David Lynch's extraordinary, savagely uncompromised new film stars a dazzling Laura Dern as an actress who tumbles down rabbit holes inside rabbit holes inside rabbit holes. As cracked as Mad magazine, though generally more difficult to parse, the film has the power of nightmares and is one of the few this year that deserve to be called art. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE LAST KING OF SCOTLAND' (R, 121 minutes) Kevin Macdonald paints a queasily enjoyable portrait of the Ugandan dictator Idi Amin from inside the palace walls. Forest Whitaker plays the mad king, while James McAvoy plays the fool. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'LETTERS FROM IWO JIMA' (R, 141 minutes, in Japanese) Another masterwork from Clint Eastwood's astonishing late period, and one of the best war movies ever. Ken Watanabe is especially fine as the general commanding Japanese troops in the doomed defense of the island of Iwo Jima. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'LITTLE CHILDREN' (R, 130 minutes) Todd Field's adaptation of Tom Perrotta's novel of suburban adultery is unfailingly intelligent and faultlessly acted. Kate Winslet and Patrick Wilson are superb as the parents of young children who meet at the playground and enact a two-handed variation on ''Madame Bovary'' against a backdrop of social paranoia and middle-class malaise. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'MISS POTTER' (PG, 92 minutes) In ''Miss Potter,'' Renée Zellweger, her face pickled in cheeriness, is Beatrix Potter, the creator of Peter Rabbit, Squirrel Nutkin and Mrs. Tittlemouse, among other beloved characters in children's literature. As portrayed by Ms. Zellweger, Potter is almost as chipper as Julie Andrews's Mary Poppins, a proto-feminist, proto-environmentalist and perfect lady to boot. There was plenty of drama in Potter's life, but the movie turns major conflicts and losses into minor setbacks in a charmed, entirely virtuous life. The movie is far too nice for its own good. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'NIGHT AT THE MUSEUM' (PG, 108 minutes) In this chaotic, overstuffed family comedy, Ben Stiller is a night watchman at the American Museum of Natural History, where the exhibits come to life at night and attack him and one another. This computerized spectacle spares no expense, but the storytelling is weak, and the hit-or-miss jokes miss more than hit. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'NOTES ON A SCANDAL' (R, 92 minutes) Judi Dench and Cate Blanchett play a misogynistic game of cat and mouse from which no one emerges unscathed, including the audience. Adapted by Patrick Marber from a novel by Zoë Heller and directed by Richard Eyre. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'PAN'S LABYRINTH' (R, 119 minutes, in Spanish) Guillermo del Toro's tale of a young girl's ordeal in post-Civil-War fascist Spain is either a fairy tale in the guise of a political allegory or vice versa. In either case it is a moving, enchanting, strange and humane example of popular art at its very best. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE PAINTED VEIL' (PG-13, 125 minutes) Nicely directed by John Curran, this version of the W. Somerset Maugham novel draws you in by turning a distaff bildungsroman into a fine romance with Naomi Watts and Edward Norton. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'PERFUME: THE STORY OF A MURDERER' (R, 147 minutes) There's no other way to say it: Tom Tykwer's excruciatingly literal-minded adaptation of the best-selling novel about an 18th-century serial killer with an acute sense of smell is a real stinker. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE PURSUIT OF HAPPYNESS' (PG-13, 117 minutes) How you respond to this fairy tale in realist drag may depend on whether you find Will Smith's performances so overwhelmingly winning that you buy the idea that poverty is a function of bad luck and bad choices, and success the result of heroic toil and dreams. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'THE QUEEN' (PG-13, 103 minutes) Directed by Stephen Frears from a very smart script by Peter Morgan, and starring a magnificent Helen Mirren in the title role, ''The Queen'' pries open a window in the House of Windsor around the time of the death of Diana, Princess of Wales, blending fact with fiction. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'ROCKY BALBOA' (PG, 102 minutes) Surprisingly, the sixth installment of this franchise is no embarrassment. Like its forerunners, it goes the distance almost in spite of itself. It's all heart and no credibility, except as a raw-boned fable. From the very beginning, Rocky Balboa was about as lifelike a character as Popeye pumped up with spinach. But that may be the point of a series that peddles the notion that if you dream it hard enough, you can live it. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'UNACCOMPANIED MINORS' (PG, 89 minutes) The title doubles as an advisory. Your kids may like it; pick them up when it's over. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'VENUS' (R, 91 minutes) A modest, diverting, touching tale of a young woman who attracts the interest -- avuncular and also erotic -- of an aging actor, played with effortless aplomb by the great Peter O'Toole. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'VOLVER' (R, 121 minutes, in Spanish) Another keeper from Pedro Almodóvar, with Penélope Cruz -- as a resilient widow -- in her best role to date. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'WE ARE MARSHALL' (PG, 128 minutes) This fact-based story of a West Virginia college town recovering from the death of its entire football team in a 1970 plane crash is a stiff, manipulative dud that gets wrong everything ''Friday Night Lights'' got right. Matthew McConaughey hams it up as the college's goofy new coach, who whips the replacement team into decent shape. (Holden)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>Sven Nykvist Remembered (Tonight through Sunday) Three films this weekend highlight the achievements of this great Swedish cinematographer, who died in September. ''The Silence'' (1963) is one of several films he shot for the director Ingmar Bergman, this time in brooding black and white; ''An-Margritt'' is a 1969 Norwegian film by Arne Skouen featuring one of Mr. Bergman's favorite performers, Liv Ullmann, as a young woman struggling to survive in a 17th-century mining community; ''Crimes and Misdemeanors'' (1989) finds Woody Allen in a Bergmanesque mood, contemplating the silence of God as Nykvist lights a strangely Nordic New York City. Museum of Modern Art, Roy and Niuta Titus Theaters, (212) 708-9400, moma.org; $10. (David Kehr)</p>
        <p>CRITICS CHOICE: GREAT DOCUMENTARIES (Tomorrow and Sunday) Members of the New York Film Critics Circle introduce some of their favorite nonfiction films. ''The Thin Blue Line,'' presented tomorrow by Mike D'Angelo of Esquire magazine, is the 1993 Errol Morris film that reopened a Dallas murder case, resulting in the exoneration of the man convicted for the crime, told in a slick, semifictional style. Also tomorrow, Stephen Whitty of The Star-Ledger offers ''Paradise Lost: The Child Murders at Robin Hood Hills,'' a look at a multiple killing in the deep South by the directors Joe Berlinger and Bruce Sinofsky, who will attend. On Sunday, J. Hoberman of The Village Voice reaches further back into the past for Dziga Vertov's deliriously subjective Soviet propaganda film of 1928, ''The Man with a Movie Camera,'' which will be shown in an archival print from the George Eastman House. (Through Feb. 25.) Museum of the Moving Image, 35th Avenue, at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718) 784-0077, movingimage.us; $10. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>THE 2007 NY JEWISH FILM FESTIVAL (Tomorrow through Thursday) Among this week's many programs: Lisa Azuelos's ''Gorgeous,'' about a group of North African Jewish women who meet to discuss their new lives in Paris; ''Love and Sacrifice,'' a newly restored Yiddish melodrama shot in New York in 1936 by the director George Roland; and ''Our Children,'' a 1948 comedy starring Shimon Dzigan and Israel Shumacher that is said to be the last Yiddish-language film made in Poland. (Through Jan. 25.) Walter Reade Theater 165 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 975-5600, filmlinc.org; $10. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>TUNDE ADEBIMPE AND ALIANnA KALABA (Tomorrow) Time was when the members of TV on the Radio, now the most critically adored band in New York, played in tiny clubs, blending electronic noises with Tunde Adebimpe's haunting falsetto. They have since graduated to much bigger gigs, but tomorrow at Tonic, the Lower East Side headquarters of the avant-garde, Mr. Adebimpe collaborates with Alianna Kalaba, the drummer of the Chicago band We Ragazzi. What will they do? Perhaps they don't even know, and that's why it will be good. Also on the bill are Pit Er Pat, Matteah Baim and Bear in Heaven. At 10 p.m., 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; $10. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>ANTI-SOCIAL MUSIC (Tomorrow) The final frontier for weird rock is classical music. Anti-Social Music, a collective of New York musicians who play in various pop and new-music bands -- including some big ones, like the Hold Steady -- is one of a handful of groups that boldly go into this realm, playing works for strings, woodwinds and other instruments by its 11 members (six of whom have degrees in music composition, the group's Web site, antisocialmusic.org, declares). Skeptics note: it can get pretty rowdy. At 9 p.m., BAMCafé, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100, bam.org; no cover. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MAX BEMIS (Sunday) Screamed warnings of being at the end of one's rope are standard issue in emo. But Mr. Bemis, the singer of the Los Angeles band Say Anything, isn't kidding: the group's latest release was delayed when he went missing, only to turn up in a mental institution in Houston. His songs bounce manically from exuberant to cynical, tender to bombastic, and, even at their most despairing, have a certain swaggering showmanship. He plays a solo acoustic show with Andy Jackson, the guitarist of the band Hot Rod Circuit. At 7 p.m., Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3006, knittingfactory.com; $12. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ANDREW BIRD (Wednesday) A talented multi-instrumentalist, Mr. Bird shows off his fiddle and guitar playing in songs that are as wistful as they are fantastical. But his most impressive technique is not on fiddle or guitar, nor on the electronic effects that he uses to make the music breathe; rather, it's his dexterous, expressive whistling, which floats high above in eerily beautiful tones. With John Southworth. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>CARNIVORE (Tomorrow) For fans of obscure New York metal only: before founding Type O Negative, Peter Steele led Carnivore, one of the most aggressive and, perhaps not coincidentally, offensive bands of the mid-'80s thrash scene. (Typical song title: ''Jesus Hitler.'') The new version of the band does not include any original members besides Mr. Steele. With Krieg, Lair of the Minotaur, A.C., Embalmer, Dimentianon and Annunaki. At 7 p.m., Northsix, 66 North Sixth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 599-5103, northsix.com; $30. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* COLD WAR KIDS (Wednesday) The craggy guitars and piano, verge-of-a-breakdown vocals and elliptical songwriting of this band from Austin, Tex., put it at the top of the music-blogger food chain last year. Now comes the hard part: maintaining popularity as the Internet eye roves again. This month the band is bouncing back and forth between New York and Los Angeles each week in a ''bicoastal residency.'' At 8 p.m., Union Hall, 702 Union Street, at Fifth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 638-4400, unionhallny.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ROBERT CRAY (Tuesday) The embodiment of the clean, commercial -- some might say rootless -- style that has defined the blues since the 1980s, Mr. Cray has an elegant touch with his Fender Stratocaster, and sings about desire and infidelity in a cool croon that is closer to pop than to Howlin' Wolf. At 8 p.m., B. B. King Blues Club and Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $47 in advance, $50 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>dB'S (Tomorrow) In the early 1980s, the dB's, four guys from North Carolina who relocated to New York, were local favorites for their nervy, hummable hybrid of New Wave and the jangly pop-rock of the Byrds and Big Star, with some country thrown in as well. The reunited band -- Peter Holsapple, Chris Stamey, Will Rigby and Gene Holder -- recorded a song for Hurricane Katrina relief and are working on a new album. The two opening acts here are family: Mitch Easter and his band, and the Sneakers, consisting of Mr. Stamey, Mr. Rigby, Mr. Easter and Robert Keely. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; $16 in advance, $18 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MARK EITZEL (Thursday) Depression is Mr. Eitzel's element; as leader of the American Music Club and through a solo career, he has anatomized melancholy down to the molecular level. In a weary voice, with tunes that blur folk songs and torch songs in a smoky haze, he looks at estrangement and betrayal, loneliness and separation, and bad luck. It's easy to believe him when he sings, ''I'm tired to the bone of always telling you goodbye.'' With the Black Swans. At 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; $12 in advance, $14 at the door. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>* FALL OUT BOY (Tuesday) One of the first groups to get wide attention for its popularity on MySpace, Fall Out Boy, from Chicago, is the model second-wave (or is this the third?) emo band: snarky and jumpy, interested in relationships over solitude, and bursting with melodic pop-punk riffs that come down from Green Day and Blink-182. With New Found Glory, Lifetime and Permanent Me. At 6:15 p.m., Hammerstein Ballroom, 311 West 34th Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-7171, mcstudios.com; $35. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PAUL GREEN SCHOOL OF ROCK MUSIC (Tomorrow and Sunday) As seen in the documentary ''Rock School,'' Mr. Green offers an extensive curriculum at his Philadelphia school, teaching youngsters the rock 'n' roll canon, as well as the fundamentals of power chords and budda-budda bass lines. Here his students offer their version of ''Jesus Christ Superstar.'' At 2:30 p.m., Rebel, 251 West 30th Street, Manhattan, (212) 695-2747, rebelnyc.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>GRUPO NICHE, JIMMY BOSCH (Tomorrow) Grupo Niche, from Colombia, holds on to the high-powered horns-and-percussion salsa forged in the 1970s. Jimmy Bosch is a trombonist who savors the Latin jazz tradition of the descarga, a jam session everyone can dance to. This ''hard salsa'' takes musical chances but never lets go of the beat. At 8 p.m., Lehman Center for the Performing Arts, 250 Bedford Park Boulevard West and Goulden Avenue, the Bronx, (718) 960-8833, lehmancenter.org; $30 to $45. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>* HASSAN HAKMOUN (Tomorrow) A leading ambassador of the ecstatic, vaguely bluesy Gnawa music of Morocco, Mr. Hakmoun, who created a sensation in the world-music circuit when he arrived in New York 20 years ago, plays one of his somewhat rare traditional concerts. Playing the sintir (a long-necked, resonant lute), Mr. Hakmoun leads spellbinding trance ceremonies, and with castanets around his ankles, performs acrobatic dances. Also on the bill is Berber music by Abderahim Boutat. At 8 p.m., Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 545-7536,symphonyspace.org or worldmusicinstitute.org; $27; $15 for students. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>HOLMES BROTHERS (Tuesday) Steeped in blues and gospel, Sherman and Wendell Holmes harmonize and raise the rafters with songs that draw hope from hard times. Their version of gospel is a close neighbor of Southern soul and country. At 7:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; $20. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>LITTLE RICHARD (Monday) He may always be most celebrated for bringing scat to rock (''A-wop-bop-a-loo-bop, a-lop-bam-boom!''), but Little Richard's delirious falsetto ''oooh!'' and androgynous showmanship have influenced everybody from Paul McCartney to Prince. At 8 p.m., B. B. King Blues Club and Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $60 in advance, $64 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BARRY MANILOW (Tuesday through Thursday) If Velveeta could sing  At 8 p.m., Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741, thegarden.com; $49.50 to $279.50. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>LIZ McCOMB (Thursday) A mezzo pop-gospel singer who grew up in Cleveland but has lived in Europe for the last 25 years, Ms. McComb moves from smoothness to Pentecostal abandon; she has been something of an ambassador in France and not that well known in her home country. At 7:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; $20. (Ben Ratliff)</p>
        <p>MOS DEF'S BIG BAND (Wednesday) Lincoln Center's American Songbook series, getting gradually more adventurous each year, opens with Mos Def, the talented and always surprising rapper and actor. Here he picks up a musical avocation, crooning with a big band, in music by Miles Davis and others. At 8:30 p.m., Allen Room, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, Broadway at 60th Street, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MY BRIGHTEST DIAMOND (Wednesday) In an expressively slippery voice, Shara Worden, who performs as My Brightest Diamond, spins luxurious fantasies that leap in scale from music boxes to colliding heavenly bodies. With Jeremy Denk and Soovin Kim, and Gabriel Kahane. At 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; $8. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ANDERS PARKER (Wednesday) Mr. Parker, who led the band Varnaline, immerses his songs in the stoic drama of country and folk music, resulting in a melancholy that is sometimes indistinguishable from cynicism. (''The hours I've wasted here I could have wasted anywhere.'') With the 'mericans. At 8 p.m., Living Room, 154 Ludlow Street, near Stanton Street, Lower East Side, (212) 533-7235, livingroomny.com; $8. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>STEVE ROSS (Tonight) In ''Americans in Paris,'' this ever-dapper singer and pianist performs a program of Parisian-scented songs in conjunction with an exhibition of paintings, ''Americans in Paris, 1860-1900,'' on view through Jan. 28. Expect lots of Cole Porter, whose airy spirit Mr. Ross channels with lilting, lighthearted suavity. At 7, Metropolitan Museum of Art, (212) 570-3949, metmuseum.org; $40. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>RON SEXSMITH (Tonight) Mr. Sexsmith seems self-effacing and hesitant at first, with a voice that sidles up to notes like a wallflower trying to slip into a party unnoticed. But behind the outward modesty is a craftsman who stubbornly upholds the verities of 1960s songwriting, placing supple melodies atop unexpected harmonies and offering wistful regret and consolation in equal parts. With Kim Taylor. At 8:30, Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; $17. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>SLOAN (Thursday) Like modern metafictions, Sloan's pop-rock songs twist inward on themselves. With their winsome tunes and neo-Beatles intricacies, Sloan's songs are not just about unrequited yearnings, but also about the process of writing pop songs about unrequited yearnings. They're rarely so clever that their heart doesn't come through. With Spiral Beach and the Love Loves. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; $20. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>TEXT OF LIGHT (Tonight) Lee Ranaldo of Sonic Youth and Alan Licht offer a guitar soundtrack to photographs and films by Laszlo Moholy-Nagy, the Hungarian artist and Bauhaus principal, and also improvise musical accompaniment to avant-garde films by Stan Brakhage and others. The performance is presented by the Whitney Museum in conjunction with an exhibition, ''Albers and Moholy-Nagy: From the Bauhaus to the New World,'' on view until Jan. 21. At 7:30, 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676, whitney.org; free with pay-what-you wish admission to the museum, after 6. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>WHEATUS (Monday) Seven years after this cheeky Long Island power-pop band scored a minor novelty hit with its Weezeresque ''Teenage Dirtbag,'' it soldiers on. New topics include BMX bikers and even the twin towers, which Brendan B. Brown, the group's leader and songwriter, says reminded him of ''Motown '60s skinny ties.'' With Midstates and Mason Dixon. At 8:30 p.m., Northsix, 66 North Sixth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 599-5103, northsix.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>CLAUDIA ACUÑA (Tuesday through Thursday) Ms. Acuña is a vocalist attracted to lyrical high drama and guided by the pulse and passion of her native Chile. She sounds best when supported by sympathetic musicians like the pianist Jason Lindner, who leads her rhythm section here. (Through next Friday.) At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $25. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>BEN ALLISON (Tomorrow) Mr. Allison, a bassist and composer, has a knack for assembling hardy and sophisticated ensembles like this one, with Michael Blake on saxophones, Frank Kimbrough on Wurlitzer keyboard and Michael Sarin on drums. At 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* KENNY BARRON TRIO (Tuesday through Thursday) Kenny Barron is the leading practitioner of an elegant, economical and rhythmically surefooted piano style that thrives in any mainstream setting; he'll explore at least a few different styles here, with Kiyoshi Kitagawa on bass and Francisco Mela on drums. (Through Jan. 21). At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>RICHARD BONA (Tonight) Mr. Bona, the Cameroonian bassist and singer, received a Grammy nomination in the contemporary world music category for his album ''Tiki'' (Decca), which he will revisit here. At 9:30, Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 539-8778, joespub.com; cover, $20, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JAMES CARNEY GROUP (Tomorrow and Sunday) James Carney, a smart keyboardist and a broadly imaginative composer, leads a trio with the flexible rhythm team of Chris Lightcap on bass and Mark Ferber on drums. Tomorrow at 9 p.m., Biscuit BBQ, 230 Fifth Avenue, at President Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 399-2161, biscuitbbq.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. Sunday at 9 p.m., Bar 4, 444 Seventh Avenue, at 15th Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 832-9800, bar4.net; suggested cover, $5. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GERALD CLAYTON TRIO (Tomorrow) Gerald Clayton was the popular favorite at last year's Thelonious Monk International Jazz Piano Competition, though he finished second. His eloquent and full-bodied style finds a good showcase in a trio with David Wong on bass and Pete Van Ostrand on drums. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>COMMON THREAD/BRASS CONSCIOUSNESS (Wednesday) Common Thread is a cadre of incisive players currently or formerly apprenticed to the influential avant-garde saxophonist Steve Coleman: the trumpeters Jonathan Finlayson and Shane Endsley, the trombonist Tim Albright, the bassist Chris Lightcap and the drummer Marcus Gilmore. Brass Consciousness, which plays a later set, adds one more trumpeter, Ralph Alessi. At 8 and 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10 per set. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* 'CUBANA BE, CUBANA BOP' (Tonight and tomorrow night) The precision-honed Afro-Latin Jazz Orchestra, under the direction of the pianist Arturo O'Farrill, presents a tribute to the pioneering Latin jazz of Dizzy Gillespie, who first performed the George Russell composition ''Cubano Be, Cubano Bop'' with his big band in the 1940s. Also on the program are reliable Gillespie flag-wavers from the same era, like ''Manteca.'' At 8, Rose Theater, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 721-6500, jalc.org; cover, $32.50 to $127.50. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DANCE NOW MUSIC (Tuesday through Thursday) Avant-garde music and movement are equal partners in this off-season Vision Festival series, which runs through next Sunday. Next week's highlights include trios led by the multireedists Joe McPhee (Tuesday) and Cooper-Moore (Wednesday), and a duo by the dancer Julia Wilkins and the alto saxophonist Matana Roberts (Thursday). (Through Jan. 21.) At 7:30 p.m., Teatro La Tea at Clemente Soto Vélez Cultural Center, 107 Suffolk Street, near Rivington Street, Lower East Side, (212) 696-6681, visionfestival.org; $20 a night ($10 for students), or three nights for $40. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SCOTT DUBOIS QUARTET (Wednesday) Scott DuBois, a guitarist equally devoted to intricate compositional forms and spacious free improvisation, celebrates the release of a new album, ''Tempest'' (Soul Note); his former teacher, the saxophonist David Liebman, joins a group with Thomas Morgan on bass and Gerald Cleaver on drums. At 10, 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ANDREW DURKIN'S INDUSTRIAL JAZZ GROUP/DARCY JAMES ARGUE'S SECRET SOCIETY (Sunday) Two powerful big bands, each guided by a clear vision. The Industrial Jazz Group, based in Los Angeles and led by the pianist Andrew Durkin, offers retro sounds with an ironic touch; the Secret Society, let by the composer Darcy James Argue, is future-minded and dead serious. At 8 p.m., Bowery Poetry Club, 308 Bowery, near Bleecker Street, East Village, (212) 614-0505; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>HARRIS EISENSTADT LOW TRIO (Sunday) The drummer Harris Eisenstadt features a lower register, and his own tunes, in this experimental trio with Jose Davila on tuba and Ben Gerstein on trombone. At 7 p.m., Jimmy's, 43 East Seventh Street, East Village, (212) 982-3006, freestylejazz.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SONNY FORTUNE QUARTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) Since the 1960s, countless saxophonists have adopted the methodology of John Coltrane, but few have captured his restless spirit. Sonny Fortune, the saxophonist of choice for the Coltrane drummer Elvin Jones, is chief among them. At 8, 10 and midnight, Sweet Rhythm, 88 Seventh Avenue South, at Bleecker Street, West Village, (212) 255-3626, sweetrhythmny.com; cover, $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>AL FOSTER QUARTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) The well-traveled Al Foster has a lithe touch as a drummer, ideal for modern jazz and more than suitable for funk; his band consists of the tenor saxophonist Eli Degibri, the pianist Kevin Hays and the bassist Doug Weiss. At 8, 10 and 11:30, Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, (212) 864-6662, smokejazz.com; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>HARRISON ON HARRISON (Tonight) On a recent album, the guitarist Joel Harrison interprets songs by a slightly more famous figure with the same surname, George Harrison. He repeats the same homage here, with David Binney on alto saxophone, Gary Versace on piano, Stephan Crump on bass and Ben Wittman on drums. At 7, Rubin Museum of Art, 150 West 17th Street, Chelsea, (212) 620-5000, Ext. 344, rmanyc.org; $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JON HENDRICKS (Wednesday and Thursday) Mr. Hendricks is the godfather of vocalese, and still irrepressible, though his voice has weathered over the years. On Tuesday he sits in with David Berger's Sultans of Swing; for the rest of the week he leads something called LHR Redux, in reference to his groundbreaking vocal trio Lambert, Hendricks and Ross. (You wonder whether he'll mention that Annie Ross, listed below, has her own gig downtown.) (Through Jan. 20.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $40, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JOHN HOLLENBECK'S CLAUDIA QUINTET (Tomorrow) This improvising chamber ensemble pursues texturally oriented and often contrapuntal exploration; Mr. Hollenbeck's drumming is one color on a palette that also includes Chris Speed's clarinet and tenor saxophone, Ted Reichman's accordion, John Hebert's bass and Matt Moran's vibraphone. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $12, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* HANK JONES TRIO (Tuesday through Thursday) Mr. Jones, one of the most estimable pianists in postwar jazz, augments his stately trio with a pair of prominent guests: the trumpeter Roy Hargrove and the singer Roberta Gambarini. (Through Jan. 21.) At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592 bluenote.net; cover, $35 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GEOFFREY KEEZER TRIO (Tonight and tomorrow night) A versatile post-bop piano trio, led by the articulate Geoffrey Keezer and featuring the bassist Tal Wilkenfeld and the drummer Terreon Gully. At 9:30 and 11:15, AC Pianocraft Showroom, 333 West 52nd Street, Clinton, (212) 254-1840, acpianocraft.com; $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DANIEL LEVIN QUARTET (Monday) Daniel Levin, a cellist, makes music full of pregnant pauses and gradual crescendos. He has dynamic cohorts in Rob Brown on alto saxophone, Joe Morris on bass and Matt Moran on drums. At 10 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVID LIEBMAN (Tonight) An incantatory saxophonist working in the post-Coltrane idiom, Mr. Liebman plays here with the bassist Ronan Guilfoyle and the drummer Tom Rainey. At 10, 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CHRIS LIGHTCAP QUINTET (Tonight) A bassist with credentials in both straight-ahead and experimental circles, Chris Lightcap fronts a group that effectively splits the difference: Chris Cheek and Tony Malaby on tenor saxophones, Jacob Sacks on Fender Rhodes piano and Ted Poor on drums. At 9 and 10:30, , Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $12, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>RENÉ MARIE (Tuesday through Thursday) A soulful jazz singer and vibrant performer with a growing book of sturdy original tunes. (Through Jan. 21.) At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>AARON PARKS QUARTET (Tomorrow) Aaron Parks, a precocious member of Terence Blanchard's groove-oriented band, leads his own working quartet with Mike Moreno on guitar, Derrick Hodge on bass and Kendrick Scott on drums. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>RE:ACTION (Wednesday) The bassist Sean Conly features his own compositions in this aptly titled band, with Tony Malaby and Michaël Attias on saxophones and Take Toriyama on drums. At 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ERIC REED QUARTET (Tonight) The pianist Eric Reed applies his trademark sophistication to the sound of a quartet featuring Stacey Dillard on tenor and soprano saxophones. At 7:30, 9:30 and 11:30, Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $30. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ANNIE ROSS (Tuesday) Ms. Ross has covered every inch of territory as a jazz singer, and yet she has her own style: supple, surefooted and knowing. She performs with a small group that includes Jon Weber on piano and Leroy Williams on drums. At 7 p.m., Metropolitan Room at Gotham, 34 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 206-0440, metropolitanroom.com; cover, $25, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ANGELICA SANCHEZ/TONY MALABY/TOM RAINEY (Sunday) A collective trio that treads a middle ground between lyricism and abstraction, with Ms. Sanchez on piano, Mr. Malaby on saxophones and Mr. Rainey on drums. At 8:30 and 10 p.m., Jimmy's, 43 East Seventh Street, East Village, (212) 982-3006, freestylejazz.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JENNY SCHEINMAN (Tuesday) Ms. Scheinman is that rare jazz violinist who embraces her instrument's folksier side without making concessions to genre. Her Tuesday night engagement features different players each week; this time around, the cast includes the clarinetist Doug Wieselman and the guitarist Steve Cardenas. At 7 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TERELL STAFFORD (Tomorrow) Mr. Stafford, a bright and assertive trumpeter, previews material from his next album, ''New Beginnings'' (MaxJazz), with a quintet that includes Tim Warfield Jr. on saxophones, Bruce Barth at the piano, Derrick Hodge on bass and Dana Hall on drums. At 7:30, 9:30 and 11:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $30. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LOREN STILLMAN AND TRIO ALTO (Thursday) ''Trio Alto Volume One'' (Steeplechase), the most recent album by the alto saxophonist Loren Stillman, suggests an explorer with one foot planted in tradition and the other caught in midstride. Mr. Stillman leads a different rhythm section here -- Sean Conly on bass and Take Toriyama on drums -- but his confident and probing approach should come across just fine. At 8:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* TERRASSON, OKEGWO, PARKER (Wednesday and Thursday) Throughout the latter half of the 1990s, the pianist Jacky Terrasson led one of jazz's fresher-sounding acoustic piano trios, distinguished not only by his fluid pianism but also by the resonant bass tone of Ugonna Okegwo and the pared-down percussive drive of Leon Parker. Last spring the trio regrouped as a collective, with uneven but deeply promising results. At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>J. D. WALTER / REFUGE TRIO (Tomorrow) J. D. Walter's voice is a flexible instrument, given to soaring scat solos and growling burrs. Another expressive vocalist, Theo Bleckmann, leads the Refuge Trio, with Gary Versace on keyboards and John Hollenbeck on drums. At 7 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, East Village, (212) 539-8778, joespub.com; cover, $15, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>* 'CONCRETE' (Wednesday and Thursday) Robert Ashley's operas have been compared to James Joyce's writing: the composer examines the ordinary world, and its language, by running it through the filters of his own creativity. ''Concrete,'' here in its world premiere, is billed as ''an old man's musing'' about people he has cared about. Mr. Ashley's orchestra will consist of computer samples that vary at each performance, and the singers will key their pitches and inflections to the sounds, creating music truly born of speech, with a conversational spontaneity. Many of the singers have worked with Mr. Ashley for decades, including Joan La Barbara, Jacqueline Humbert and Sam Ashley, the composer's son. (Through Jan. 21.) At 8 p.m., La MaMa Annex Theater, 74A East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 475-7710, lamama.org; $15 and $20. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>'THE FIRST EMPEROR' (Tomorrow) The excitement of a world premiere at the Met, combined with widespread interest among the general public in the composer Tan Dun, who won an Oscar for his film score to ''Crouching Tiger, Hidden Dragon,'' have resulted in a sold-out run for ''The First Emperor.'' Though the story of Qin Shi Huang, the first emperor of China, who unified the country through brutality and conquest, is compelling, Mr. Tan's ponderous score is a huge disappointment. There are gripping moments, especially some propulsive orchestra passages that incorporate Chinese instruments. But the opera's lyrical flights are slow-moving, ponderous and sometimes cloying. Mr. Tan has tried to meld Chinese melody and Italianate lyricism. His music, though, seems caught in some nowhere land between ''Crouching Tiger'' and Puccini's ''Turandot.'' Even the great Plácido Domingo, bravely taking on the challenging title role, cannot save the show. The colorful production is by the Chinese film director Zhang Yimou (''House of Flying Daggers''). Mr. Tan conducts. At 1:30 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; sold out. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* 'MOSTLY OPERETTA' (Tonight, Monday, Tuesday and Thursday) Once popular entertainment, today often presented as hackneyed spectacle, operetta deserves to be rehabilitated for the 21st century. At least, this is the premise of an ambitious festival at the Austrian Cultural Forum that presents both the familiar (excerpts from Lehar's ''Merry Widow'') and the less familiar (Lehar's little-known songs), sung by operetta specialists, with innovative, cutting-edge visuals by Victoria Coeln. Tonight's program (in English) is a salute to operettas that appeared on Broadway; Monday and Tuesday's is an all-Lehar program; and Thursday's juxtaposes Lehar and Kalman with less-known composers like Rudolf Friml and Leo Fall. Tonight at 8 (introductory lecture at 7); Monday, Tuesday and Thursday nights at 7; 11 East 52nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 319-5300, acfny.org; free, but reservations are required. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK GILBERT AND SULLIVAN PLAYERS (Tonight through Sunday) When this troupe was founded by Albert Bergeret in 1974, it was one of a handful of small companies devoted to the Savoyard repertory in New York. Now it is the only one left, and its performances, with Mr. Bergeret still at the helm, and with casts well drilled in the style, are always a treat. Its current season includes two perennial favorites, ''The Mikado'' and ''Yeomen of the Guard,'' and the company can be counted on to bring their splendid silliness to life. ''The Mikado'' is tonight at 8, tomorrow at 2 p.m. and Sunday at 3 p.m.; ''Yeomen of the Guard'' is tomorrow night at 8. City Center, 131 West 55th Street, Manhattan, (212) 581-1212, nycitycenter.org; $40 to $96. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* 'OTELLO' (Wednesday) Rossini's 1816 version of ''Otello'' predates Verdi's great opera by more than 70 years. Choosing Shakespeare's complex play as a subject was a risky stroke for Rossini at the time. The Naples opera company that presented it forced the composer to tweak, soften and simplify the story. The first two acts are uneven. But the great third act, dominated by Rossini's noble music for the anguished Desdemona, struck the composer Meyerbeer as ''really godlike.'' The Opera Orchestra of New York is billing its concert performance as the first New York presentation of Rossini's work. In any event, the cast looks promising, with the soprano Ruxandra Donose as Desdemona and the tenor Robert McPherson as Iago. (The tenor Ramón Vargas was to have sung the title role, but dropped out because of illness; he is being replaced by Bruce Ford.) Eve Queler conducts. At 7:30 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $25 to $125. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'THE TENDER LAND' (Tomorrow and Sunday) In 1976, when the enterprising Bronx Opera Company first presented Copland's ''Tender Land,'' the composer participated in rehearsals and attended productions. For its current production, the company is using the effective chamber version of the orchestral score, arranged by Murry Sidlin. Royston Coppenger is the director. Elizabeth W. Scott conducts tomorrow, and Michael Spierman on Sunday. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Sunday at 2 p.m., Lovinger Theater, Lehman College, Bedford Park Boulevard West and Goulden Avenue, Bedford Park, the Bronx, (718) 960-8833, bronxopera.org; $15 to $30. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'LE VILLI' (Tonight through Sunday) This opera, Puccini's first work for the stage, is a short tale of a trusting young woman from a Black Forest town in medieval Germany who is forsaken by her betrothed. When the grieving woman dies, her guilt-stricken fiancé is subjected to supernatural justice. Though the score was deeply influenced by operatic styles of the day, Puccini's intensely lyrical and richly harmonic voice comes through. The adventurous Dicapo Opera Theater presents a choreographic production of this seldom-heard work on a double bill with a staged performance of Puccini's major sacred work, the ''Messa di Gloria.'' Francisco Bonnin conducts. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 4 p.m., Dicapo Opera Theater, at St. Jean Baptiste Church, 184 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212) 288-9438, dicapo.com; $47.50. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'DIE ZAUBERFLÖTE' (Tonight) This revival of Julie Taymor's production continues at the Metropolitan Opera, complete with the magical puppets and stage effects that made it an audience hit when it opened in 2004. James Levine conducts a cast that includes Lisa Milne as Pamina, Erika Miklosa as Queen of the Night, Matthew Polenzani as Tamino, Rodion Pogossov as Papageno, Eike Wilm Schulte as the Speaker and Morris Robinson as Sarastro. At 8, Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $110 to $205 tickets remaining. (Vivien Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>ISABEL BAYRAKDARIAN AND RUSSELL BRAUN (Sunday) Patriotism has brought the fine Canadian soprano Isabel Bayrakdarian and the light Canadian baritone Russell Braun together frequently before. But the motivation for this weekend's joint recital is the George London Foundation, which presents the two singers, together with their spouses, the pianists Carolyn Maule and Serouj Kradjian, in a program of Schumann, Schubert, Debussy and Pauline Viardot (whose songs Ms. Bayrakdarian has recorded, very well). At 4 p.m., Morgan Library &amp; Museum, 225 Madison Avenue, at 36th Street, (212) 877-6347, www.themorgan.org; $45; $30 for Morgan members. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>CALEFAX (Sunday) The intimate chamber music hall at the Frick Collection has become a reliable place to discover soloists and ensembles who are new to New York but prove durable additions to the city's musical life. Calefax, a reed quintet from the Netherlands, makes its debut with an era-spanning program that runs from music by Ockeghem (born in 1410) through Sander Germanus (born in 1972). At 5 p.m., 1 East 70th Street, Manhattan, (212) 288-0700, frick.org; $25. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>CARNEGIE HALL FESTIVAL CHORUS (Tomorrow) Helmuth Rilling leads the Carnegie Hall Festival Chorus and the excellent Orchestra of St. Luke's in a performance of Bach's monumental ''St. Matthew Passion.'' The soloists are the tenor James Taylor, who sings the Evangelist; the bass Klaus Häger, who sings Jesus; the soprano Sibylla Rubens; the mezzo-soprano Ingeborg Danz; the tenor Thomas Cooley; and the bass Michael Nagy. At 7 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $25 to $82. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>CHAMBERFEST (Tuesday through Thursday) ChamberFest is an appropriate name for this series of concerts, which showcase Juilliard students who have spent their final week of winter break in daily rehearsals and coaching sessions. The program on Tuesday includes Strauss's ''Till Eulenspiegels Lustige Streiche'' and Debussy's String Quartet; Wednesday night's concert includes Ravel's ''Introduction et Allegro'' and Brahms's Clarinet Trio, while on Thursday, works by Prokofiev, Brahms and Walton will be performed. At 8 p.m., Paul Hall, Juilliard School, 60 Lincoln Center Plaza, at 65th Street, (212) 769-7406, juilliard.edu; free. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* EIGHTH BLACKBIRD (Tonight and tomorrow) This inventive and energetic young new-music ensemble from Chicago has built its audience with eclectic programming and commissioning. It has also impressed listeners by playing complex scores by memory, a feat rarely seen in ensembles playing even much more familiar music. The group's program tonight includes works by Steve Mackey, Jennifer Higdon, Gordon Fitzell and David M. Gordon. Tomorrow it is performing as part of the closing concert of the Chamber Music America national conference. Tonight at 8, the Kitchen, 512 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 255-5793, thekitchen.org; $10. Tomorrow at 4 p.m., St. Luke's Lutheran Church, 308 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 242-2022, chamber-music.org; free. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>ALLISON ELDREDGE (Tonight) This cellist, a faculty member at the New England Conservatory, performs Beethoven's Sonata in G minor (Op. 5, No. 2); Hindemith's Sonata; Brahms's Sonata in F; and Paganini's virtuoso Variations on One String on a Theme of Paganini. Max Levinson, her husband, is the pianist. At 8, Weill Recital Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $20; $10 for students and 65+. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>GUARNERI STRING QUARTET (Sunday) In its continuing campaign to make classical music available to all, the indispensable Peoples' Symphony Concerts, which offer leading artists and ensembles at very affordable prices, present the Guarneri String Quartet at Town Hall in a program of works by Haydn, Dohnanyi and Dvorak. At 2 p.m., 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 586-4680, pscny.org; $9 and $11. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>MET ORCHESTRA (Sunday) High in fiber, high in calories and generally high in content, the Met Orchestra's Carnegie Hall concerts are the Danny Meyer meals of classical music. They are long, satisfying and generally delectable, depending on the condition of the chef-conductor, James Levine. The program offers something for every taste, including the expected high-modernist course -- the premiere of ''Theologoumenon'' by Charles Wuorinen -- and the expected star soloist: the brilliant, rigorous violinist Christian Tetzlaff, playing the Beethoven concerto. But the main course is the Brahms Third. At 3 p.m., (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $50 to $160. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK COLLEGIUM (Tonight) Those favoring a reductive sweep of music history called Arnold Schoenberg and his contemporaries the Second Viennese school, the implication being that the thriving music world running roughly from Mozart through Beethoven and Schubert was the First. But what of Viennese music before that? The New York Collegium explores Baroque-era Viennese music, with works by Biber, Schmelzer and others who might prove worth a fresh look. At 8 (preconcert talk at 7), Church of St. Vincent Ferrer, Lexington Avenue at 66th Street, (212) 717-9246, nycollegium.org; $30 to $60. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC (Tomorrow and Thursday) Zubin Mehta, music director of the Philharmonic from 1978 to 1991, returns to conduct the orchestra in Bruckner's Symphony No. 7. But the highlight of the evening is likely to be Alisa Weilerstein, a passionate and highly talented 24-year-old cellist, who makes her subscription debut with the orchestra, playing Elgar's intense Cello Concerto. On Thursday Riccardo Muti conducts a program including Scriabin's ''Divin Poème'' and Tchaikovsky's Violin Concerto, with the excellent Russian violinist Vadim Repin as soloist. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Thursday at 7:30 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nyphil.org; $28 to $96. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>'SONGS OF PEACE AND WAR' (Wednesday) Delving into the song repertory to uncover surprising and pleasing nuggets, the New York Festival of Song has as much to teach singers as audiences. For their second collaboration with singers enrolled at the Juilliard School, the directors Steven Blier and Michael Barrett return to a program that originated in 2003, offering a range of songs, by composers from Shostakovich to Bob Dylan, on themes that remain all too timely. At 8 p.m., Peter Jay Sharp Theater, Juilliard School, 155 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 769-7406, www .nyfos.org; free, but tickets are required. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>TRIBUTE TO ARTURO TOSCANINI (Tuesday) The Symphonica Toscanini, founded last year in Rome, with Lorin Maazel as its music director, is introducing itself to New York in a collaboration with Mr. Maazel's other orchestra, the New York Philharmonic. The concert, billed as a tribute to the Italian orchestra's namesake on the 50th anniversary of his death, includes Strauss's ''Don Juan'' and Tchaikovsky's ''Francesca da Rimini,'' as well as arias by Cilea, Puccini and Rossini. Renée Fleming is the soloist. At 7:30 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nyphil.org; $50 to $175. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>CLARE BYRNE DANCE (Tonight through Sunday) Clare Byrne, a nicely quirky longtime presence in New York modern dance, describes her ''Rounds, the First Last Dance, or the Last First Dance, or an Ordination'' as calling up ''the doing-ness of dance.'' Uh-oh. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 3 p.m., Dance New Amsterdam, 280 Broadway, at Chambers Street, TriBeCa, (212) 279-4200, ticketcentral.com; $20. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>CEDAR LAKE CONTEMPORARY BALLET (Thursday) The company opens its winter season with a program of dance by Jacopo Godani of Italy, Edgar Zendejas of Mexico and New York's own Benoit-Swan Pouffer, who directs Cedar Lake. (Through Jan. 27.) At 8 p.m., Cedar Lake Theater, 547 West 26th Street, Chelsea, (212) 868-4444, smarttix.com; $30; $20 for 65+ and students with ID. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* Yoshiko Chuma &amp; The School of Hard Knocks (Tuesday through Thursday) In her first appearance at Dance Theater Workshop since the 1980s, Yoshiko Chuma uses 15 musicians and dancers to explore the stories of artists living in Albania, Macedonia, Japan and the United States. Don't miss what should be a layered, evocative depiction of nations struggling amid war. (Through Jan. 20.) At 7:30 p.m., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077, dtw.org; $15 and $25. (Claudia La Rocco)</p>
        <p>COMPANY EAST (Tonight through Sunday) Hiroshi Jin's Company East makes its United States debut in a dance-theater production of ''Medea'' that incorporates elements of Noh theater, Western modern dance and karate stances. Tonight and tomorrow night at 7:30, Sunday at 2:30 and 7:30 p.m., La MaMa E.T.C., 74A East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 475-7710, lamama.org; $20; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>COMPLEXIONS CONTEMPORARY BALLET (Tonight through Sunday) This company, founded in 1994 by Dwight Rhoden and Desmond Richardson, is notable for its wonderful dancers and, often, less-than-wonderful choreography. But this season looks promising, with a work by Mr. Rhoden to the music of Marvin Gaye; new pieces by Jodie Gates; and a solo for Mr. Richardson -- one of dance's true stars -- by Taye Diggs. Yes, that Taye Diggs. Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 2 and 7:30 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800, joyce.org; $42; $32 for Joyce members. (Roslyn Sulcas)</p>
        <p>* DANCE ON CAMERA FESTIVAL (Today and tomorrow) Presented by the Dance Films Association and the Film Society of Lincoln Center, this festival ranges more widely than ever, with nine dance programs created for the camera, documentaries and archival compilations. Other programs, at other locations, include a retrospective of work by Elaine Summers and discussions on editing and creating dance with a narrative. Today at 1, 3:30, 6:15 and 8:30 p.m.; tomorrow at 2 and 4 p.m., Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 496-3809, dancefilms.org; $10; $5 for 65+ and children 6 through 12. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>JEAN ISAACS SAN DIEGO DANCE THEATER (Tonight and tomorrow night) This program includes a new piece by Jeffrey Gerodias, a former Alvin Ailey dancer, and four quartets to music by Steve Reich. At 8:30, Danspace Project, St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194, danspaceproject.org; $20; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* Japanese Contemporary Dance Showcase (Tuesday through Thursday) If it's January in New York, it must be time for Japanese dance. For this event's 10th anniversary, the Japan Society has relocated to the Joyce. But the eclectic, pop-influenced sampler should be just as strange and beguiling as ever. Two programs feature work by Pappa Tarahumara, Kim Itoh &amp; the Glorious Future, Leni-Basso and Noism07. (Through Jan. 21.) Tuesday through Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800; $30; $23 for members. (La Rocco)</p>
        <p>* LOWER LIGHTS COLLECTIVE (Tonight, tomorrow and Thursday) Members of this multimedia group have worked with some pretty impressive people in dance. And how can you go wrong with a group that describes its collaborative process as ignoring one another while allowing for the subtle influence of what is seen out of the corner of the eye? In its new ''CRAM,'' the group will pour dance; a ''live horror film''; sound and noise installations; a ''living sculpture'' using potatoes as percussion; and an orchestra of instruments made from architectural salvage into every cranny of this space. (Through Jan. 20.) At 8 p.m., Chocolate Factory, 5-49 49th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (212) 352-3101, chocolatefactorytheater.org; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>NETA DANCE COMPANY (Sunday) Produced by Neta Pulvermacher and Marisa Beatty, this second season of monthly dance-and-talk series, ''The A.W.A.R.D. Show,'' opens with a program featuring dance by Amanda Loulaki, Kiyoko Kashiwagi, Ming-Lung Yang and Mei-Yin Ng. The series, which runs through May 20, concludes with one participant receiving a $10,000 grant. At 7 p.m., Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, between Houston and Prince Streets, (212) 334-7479, joyce.org; free. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* NEW YORK CITY BALLET (Tonight through Sunday, and Tuesday through Thursday) The last four performances of ''The Sleeping Beauty,'' with Wendy Whelan, Nikolaj Hübbe and Jennie Somogyi (Friday); Ashley Bouder, Benjamin Millepied and Amanda Hankes (Saturday matinee); Megan Fairchild, Joaquin De Luz and Ellen Bar (Saturday evening); and Sterling Hyltin, Jared Angle and Teresa Reichlen (Sunday matinee). Next week the company begins its controversial theme programming, beginning on Tuesday with ''Stravinsky and Balanchine: An Eternal Partnership'' (''Agon,'' ''Monumentum/Movements,'' ''Duo Concertant'' and ''Symphony in Three Movements''). The project continues on Wednesday and Thursday with ''Tradition and Innovation'' (George Balanchine's ''Mozartiana'' and ''Tchaikovsky Piano Concerto No. 2,'' and Mauro Bigonzetti's ''In Vento''). Who knows? The selections may well encourage audiences to ruminate on these weighty conceits. Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 3 p.m., Tuesday and Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 870-5570, nycballet.com; $20 to $95. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* PEAK PERFORMANCES @ MONTCLAIR: TRISHA BROWN (Thursday) Ms. Brown, now 70, celebrates her long and influential career in modern dance with a new work, ''I love my robots,'' that suggests that she is as innovative as ever. A collaboration with the visual artist Kenjiro Okazaki and the performance artist Laurie Anderson, ''robots'' will feature what Mr. Okazaki describes as two interactive ''sculptural apparitions.'' The evening also includes performances of Ms. Brown's 1983 ''Set and Reset'' and her 2005 ''how long does the subject linger on the edge of the volume?'' (Through Jan. 21.) At 7:30 p.m., Alexander Kasser Theater, Montclair State University, 1 Normal Avenue, Montclair, N.J., (973) 655-5112, peakperfs.org; $35. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>LAURA PETERSON CHOREOGRAPHY (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ms. Peterson, who has danced with everyone from Risa Jaroslow to Poppo and the GoGo Boys, describes her new ''I Love Dan Flavin'' as a tongue-in-cheek futuristic dance with fluorescent light and pioneering techno music. (Through Jan. 27.) At 8, Dixon Place, 258 Bowery, between Houston and Prince Streets, Lower East Side, (212) 219-0736, Ext. 11, dixonplace.org; $12 to $15 or T.D.F. vouchers; $10 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Martine Pisani (Thursday) Three may be a crowd, but in ''Bande à Part'' (''Band of Outsiders''), four is a solo. The French choreographer Martine Pisani seeks to mold the work of four performers into one solo, a single performer at a time, while the rest of the ensemble looks on. (Through Jan. 21.) At 8:30 p.m., Danspace Project, St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194; $15 or T.D.F. vouchers. (La Rocco)</p>
        <p>VISION DANCE MUSIC SERIES (Tuesday through Thursday) This six-day festival has two to four shows a night featuring collaborations among dance and music artists like Sally Silvers, Baraka de Soleil and Gloria McLean. (Through Jan. 21.) At 7:30 p.m., Teatro La Tea @ Clemente Soto Vélez Cultural Center, 107 Suffolk Street, Lower East Side, (212) 696-6681, visionfestival.org; $20 a night; $10 a night for students and 65+; $40 for three nights. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* American Museum of Natural History: 'GOLD,' through Aug. 19. Having delved into pearls, diamonds and amber, the museum applies its time-tested show-and-tell formula to gold. An astounding array of art, artifacts and natural samples, larded with fascinating facts and tales, ranges from prehistoric times to the present. Stops along the way include pre-Columbian empires, sunken treasure, Bangladesh dowry rituals and the moon landing. It turns out that gold comes from the earth in forms as beautiful as anything man has thought to do with it. Central Park West and 79th Street, (212) 769-5100, amnh.org. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>China Institute: 'Shu,' through Feb. 24. This second installation of a two-part show glances back at the period of artistic expansion in the 1970s, and its contraction, after the 1989 Tiananmen Square protests. Qiu Zhijie's photographic ''library,'' which papers the walls of the China Institute's main staircase, makes evident the information explosion in the 80s. Among the thousands of titles are Chinese classics, books on natural sciences and treatises by Plato, Disraeli and Harold Bloom. Such a trove might have been considered a treasure before Tiananmen Square; afterward, such resources became sources of angst. The figure that appears throughout Zhang Xiaogang's 1991 series ''Private Notes,'' for example, looks as if he is losing his mind -- and his head, torso and myriad other body parts -- as he struggles to write letters and decode illegible manuscripts. Without easy access to words, the images imply, there can be no such thing as free expression. 125 East 65th Street, (212) 744-8181, chinainstitute.org. (Bridget L. Goodbody)</p>
        <p>Cooper-Hewitt National Design Museum: 'DESIGN LIFE NOW: NATIONAL DESIGN TRIENNIAL 2006,' through July 29. This ambitious show illuminates the volatile, contradictory and ever-expanding field, but fails to call it to order. The inclusions cover medical innovation, military hardware, frivolous reiterations of received ideas, sundry Web sites and magazines, haute couture, architecture and more varieties of recycling than you can easily count. The show coalesces into deliberately orchestrated skirmishes between conflicting principles and entities: corporate and private, decorative and essential. 2 East 91st Street, (212) 849-8400, ndm.si.edu. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'Spanish Painting from El Greco to Picasso, TIME, TRUTH, AND HISTORY' through March 28. This show is carried along on its sheer star power and optical finesse. There are dozens of Goyas and Velázquezes and Zurbaráns and El Grecos and Riberas and Dalís and Picassos, many famous, many not. The big point is that Spanish art did not constantly reinvent itself over time. It was a bubble culture, sustained for centuries by its political and religious isolation and its national loner mindset. Velázquez's painting of a dwarf is alone worth crossing a continent to see. 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3500, guggenheim.org. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* THE METropolitan museum of art: 'GLITTER AND DOOM: GERMAN PORTRAITS FROM THE 1920s,' through Feb. 19. This show's 100 paintings and drawings are by 10 artists, among them George Grosz, Christian Schad, Rudolf Schlichter and Karl Hubbuch, and most conspicuously the unrelentingly savage Otto Dix and his magnificent other, Max Beckmann. In their works the Weimar Republic's porous worlds reassemble. We look into the faces of forward-looking museum directors and cabaret performers, society matrons and scarred war veterans, prostitutes and jaded aristocrats who were watching their world slide from one cataclysm to the next. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* THE MET: 'LOUIS COMFORT TIFFANY AND LAURELTON HALL -- AN ARTIST'S COUNTRY ESTATE,' through May 20. Laurelton Hall may have burned to the ground in 1957, but this exhibition does an excellent job of reassembling what remains of this extraordinary house-museum and its gardens, which Tiffany created for himself in the early 1900s. The Gilded Age opulence of the place, which occupied 580 acres overlooking Long Island Sound -- and of the Tiffany residences preceding it -- is conveyed most blatantly by the Temple-of-Dendur-size Daffodil Terrace, in wood, marble and glass. The main events are the glass windows, vases and lamps, where Tiffany's genius for color, love of the exotic and reverence for nature coalesce into an unforgettable mystical materialism. (See above.) (Smith)</p>
        <p>* MORGAN LIBRARY &amp; MUSEUM: 'SAUL STEINBERG: ILLUMINATIONS,' through March 4. Saul Steinberg's famous New Yorker cover positioning Manhattan at the center of the world may be his best-known drawing, but he took on everything with visual puns, manic doodles, grandiloquent calligraphy and other inspired artifice. As this show of more than 100 drawings, collages and constructions goes on, Steinberg's progress is evident: from relatively simple cartoons like ''Feet on Chair'' (1946), in which a fellow reading a newspaper parks his feet on the seat of an ornate Victorian monstrosity, to complex comments on the state of the world, like ''Street War (Cadavre Exquisis)'' (about 1972-74), derived from news clips of postcolonial troubles in the Middle East and Africa. The flow of his work amazes. 225 Madison Avenue, at 36th Street, (212) 685-0008, morganlibrary.org. (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>* MUSEUM OF THE CITY OF NEW YORK: 'A CITY ON PAPER: SAUL STEINBERG'S NEW YORK,' through March 25. A very lively adjunct to the Morgan show, this smaller display of some 40 drawings focuses on New York. An architect, Steinberg was particularly attracted to edifices like the Chrysler Building, which appears here looming majestically over brownstones and in another incarnation, from a perspective directly below it, looking positively squat. New York people, in Steinberg's eyes, could be monuments, too. You may think you know Steinberg's work, but these shows make it new. 1220 Fifth Avenue at 103rd Street, (212) 534-1672, mcny.org. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>Whitney Museum of American Art: 'Kiki Smith: A Gathering, 1980-2005,' through Feb. 11. Many things fly and float here: men and women, harpies and angels, birds and beasts, toadstools and stars. And some things fall to earth, or rather to the museum's black stone floors, maybe to rise again, maybe not. The whole show, a midcareer retrospective, suggests a Victorian fairy tale, its tone at once light, grievous and dreamlike. But fanciful as it is, Ms. Smith's art is also deeply, corporeally realistic. It wears moral and mortal seriousness on its sleeve, if not tattooed on its wrist. It is about life and death, the essential things. 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676, whitney.org. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>* SERGIO PREGO To take the fullest pleasure in this exhibition, you must stand perfectly still and quiet in front of ''Black Monday'' (2006), a single-channel video of still life photographs of con trolled fireworks explosions taken inside an abandoned factory in Bilbao, Spain. In all, the artist took more than a thousand photographs of 17 different explosions, using 40 cameras. He then scanned them into a computer, cropped them and ran them together to create the video. He also composed what he calls ''a sequencing of sounds,'' a series of repeating ambient electronic noises that serve as the soundtrack. The result is a multifaceted representation of something that is usually invisible to the eye: explosion clouds immobilized in time and space, forming immensely beautiful sculptural shapes. Lehmann Maupin Gallery, 540 West 26th Street, Chelsea, (212) 255-2923, www.lehmannmaupin.com, through Feb 10. (Benjamin Genocchio)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* HENRY DARGER: THE VIVIAN GIRLS EMERGE Further proof that Henry Darger's epic art did not spring whole from a fevered outsider brain is provided by a cache of his early forays into image collecting and collage. Most spectacular is ''The Battle of Calverhine,'' a leathery, reliclike panorama of carefully knit and hand-tinted found images. It teems with all things Darger (and not a little Pop) and has never been exhibited in this country. Andrew Edlin Gallery, 529 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 206-9723; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* CANDIDA HOFER  In large color photographs of the different galleries of the Louvre, taken on Tuesdays when the museum is closed, both the long, vaulted spaces and the painting and sculpture they contain speak of different times and styles. Equally affecting, if not a little frightening, is the lavish, timeless grandeur of these vistas. A palace that became a museum, the Louvre is also a precursor of the barrel-vaulted arcades that sprang up in Paris in the first half of the 19th century. Most of them are gone, but the Louvre's arcades live on. Sort of. Sonnabend Gallery, 536 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 627-1018; closes tomorrow(Smith)</p>
        <p>NINA KATCHADOURIAN: 'OFFICE SEMAPHORE' Ms. Katchadourian has borrowed marine flag signaling techniques to create an interactive art project consisting of an old-fashioned tourist telescope installed at the corner of a plaza in the middle of the financial district, its lens trained on the window of an upper-floor office in a nearby skyscraper. Each day the man working in the office, or his assistant, arranges objects on his widow sill. The combination and order of the objects represent a specific message, which viewers down on the plaza can interpret using a key-chart on the telescope. 1 Chase Manhattan Plaza, corner of Liberty and William Streets, Lower Manhattan; stairway entrance to the plaza is on William Street, at Cedar Street; www.publicartfund.org; closes on Sunday. (Genocchio)</p>
        <p>* The MET: 'SEAN SCULLY: WALL OF LIGHT' The capacious, day-lighted mezzanine galleries at the Met are the perfect setting for Sean Scully's bold and energizing ''Wall of Light'' paintings from the series he started in 1998. These large-scale oils on canvas wow the viewer with their scale, intensity of color and sheer dominance of space. They are complemented by tiny independent watercolors that Mr. Scully sees as ''antidotes'' to the big ones. All have this in common: They are richly painted surfaces of close-laid vertical and horizontal bars (he calls them bricks), whose arrangement suggests constructed walls of stone. Although they appear totally abstract, with their all-over arrangements of bars that superficially vary only in color, size and juxtaposition, they evoke landscapes, people, events, the work of other artists. ''I'm trying to turn stone into light,'' Mr. Scully has said, and the more you look at them, the more filled with light and life they become. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org; closes on Monday. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>HELEN MIRRA: BREAK CAMP This show of carefully composed, low-lying sculptures made from cut-up wood pallets has a smooth, almost Zen serenity, but its thoughtful brand of Post-Minimalism seems both precious and overly familiar, creating the impression of an engaging sensibility that could aim much higher. Peter Freeman Inc., 560 Broadway, at Prince Street, SoHo, (212) 966-5154; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Museum of Arts &amp; Design: 'Simply DROOG: 10 + 3 YEARS OF CREATING DISCUSSION AND INNOVATION' . Droog Design, a many-headed, loosely affiliated collective of usually, but not entirely, Dutch designers and architects, has probably generated more discussion than innovation in its 13 years of existence. Presented in a free-flowing, Droog-designed layout, this show vigorously continues the process. It includes about 150 mostly domestic objects by scores of designers. Some are great, some are silly, some are Conceptual Art. But there is plenty to sink your teeth into, especially with help from the small free brochure containing label information and rationales for each item. 40 West 53rd Street, (212) 956-3535, madmuseum.org; closes on Sunday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Moma: 'BRICE MARDEN: A RETROSPECTIVE OF PAINTINGS AND DRAWINGS' This quietly magnificent 40-year retrospective pays tribute to an artist who helped rebuild painting in the 1970s, working back from the brink of single-panel monochromes to elegant tangles of thick line on vibrant monochrome grounds that encompass a tremendous emotional range and sense of physical energy, and give the lie to the idea that any art can be purely formal or completely abstract. Mr. Marden converted the rule-ridden zone of Minimalist abstraction into a capacious yet disciplined place, pushing it toward landscape, the figure and its roots in Abstract Expressionism and beyond, in non-Western art. And he may have saved the best for last. (212) 708-9400; closes on Monday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center: 'DEFAMATION OF CHARACTER'  With 46 artists and a mix of usual and unusual suspects, this exhibition forms a black hole in which Dada, Fluxus, Punk, Pop, Conceptual and Neo-Conceptual mingle like cackling furies, along with Performance art, feminism, abject art and various forms of appropriation. While its dour tone becomes a bit relentless, it is admirably consistent and shows artists grappling with reality, which has its own kind of comfort. 22-25 Jackson Avenue, at 46th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 784-2084, ps1.org; closes on Monday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center: 'THE GOLD STANDARD' Gold is both color and subject in this glittering, pertinent show, installed on creamy yellow walls. Even though a generally dim view of contemporary society prevails, it is scary how good gold makes everything look. (See above.) Closes on Monday (Smith)</p>
        <p>Sigmar Polke Painting is man's oldest conjuring trick, and Sigmar Polke is one of its reigning magicians. In this show, new paintings and those from the 1980s, all two-sided and painted with resin, surround a small selection of German Baroque amber (Bernstein is German for amber) jewelry and exquisite tchotchkes. The show simulates a Wunderkammer, a darkened wonder cabinet of the 17th or 18th century. The paintings, made translucent by the resin, nearly defy deciphering. Doodles and abstract splashes of white paint overlay murky washes of glowing resin on both sides of their membranous support, then cast dim shadows on the wall behind, so that the pictures seem suspended in midair, floating. Michael Werner Gallery, 4 East 77th Street, (212) 988-1623, www.michaelwerner.net; closes tomorrow (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>Queens Museum of Art: 'Queens International 2006: Everything All at Once' . The 52 artists and two collaboratives in this exhibition are natives of various regions of North America, as well as of Bosnia, China, India, Iran, Japan, Korea, the Netherlands, Peru and Venezuela. The only common ground, perhaps, is that they all live in Queens. Instead of arranging the work according to medium, ethnicity or generalized themes, the curators follow the edict of the exhibition's subtitle. The show tries to balance the interests of the art crowd and local residents. Sometimes these concerns dovetail nicely, as in Sophia Peer's quick-cut video ''Everyday,'' which shows her aging parents moving around their cramped home in Queens like latter-day, empty-nest Bunkers. Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, (718) 592-9700, www.queensmuseum.org; closes on Sunday. (Martha Schwendener)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
