<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Surprise Move, British Bank Lifts Rate</title>
    <meta content="12bank" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/12/business/worldbusiness/12bank.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1818283"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bank of England</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Timmons, Heather</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dougherty, Carter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Bank of England</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E2DD1330F931A25752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="657" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Surprise Move, British Bank Lifts Rate</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Surprise Move, British Bank Lifts Rate</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HEATHER TIMMONS and CARTER DOUGHERTY; Heather Timmons reported from London and Carter Dougherty from Frankfurt.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dougherty, Carter; Timmons, Heather</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Jan. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bank of England, in surprise move, raises interest rates 0.25 percent, to 5.25 percent, to head off rising inflation amid housing boom and strong economic growth; European Central Bank, meeting in Frankfurt, leaves borrowing costs at five-year high of 3.5 percent; hints it could raise rates as early as March to guard against rising prices if European economy continues to expand; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bank of England surprised investors on Thursday and raised interest rates by a quarter of a percentage point, to 5.25 percent, to head off rising inflation amid a boom in the housing market and strong economic growth.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the European Central Bank, meeting in Frankfurt, left borrowing costs at a five-year high of 3.5 percent. But the bank hinted it could increase rates as early as March to guard against rising prices if Europe's economy continued to expand.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bank of England raised interest rates by a quarter of a percentage point, to 5.25 percent, to head off rising inflation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Bank of England surprised investors on Thursday and raised interest rates by a quarter of a percentage point, to 5.25 percent, to head off rising inflation amid a boom in the housing market and strong economic growth.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the European Central Bank, meeting in Frankfurt, left borrowing costs at a five-year high of 3.5 percent. But the bank hinted it could increase rates as early as March to guard against rising prices if Europe's economy continued to expand.</p>
        <p>After a two-year slump, growth has been picking up steadily across much of the Continent, led by a recovery in Germany, the euro-zone's largest economy. The British economy has moved ahead even more rapidly, fueled by a housing market that helped the economy expand 2.7 percent in the third quarter, compared with the period a year earlier.</p>
        <p>Home prices in Britain have surged 15 percent over the last two years, according to the Halifax House Price Index.</p>
        <p>Still, the decision by the Bank of England to raise rates -- bringing them to the same level as in the United States -- surprised investors who had said they believed the bank's most recent increase, which was in November, would be its last for a while.</p>
        <p>The Bank of England has raised interest rates three times since August.</p>
        <p>One reason for such a view is that oil prices have eased in the last six months. Lower oil prices generally temper inflation by helping to trim prices on a range of consumer purchases, from gasoline to airplane seats. British Airways, for instance, said it was lowering some fuel surcharges as crude oil prices slid.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the British pound has also been enjoying a run-up against the dollar, the euro and other major currencies. In New York trading, the pound was fetching $1.9447 Thursday; in early December, it hit $1.98. Traders expect the pound to cross $2 by the end of the quarter, a mark not seen since 1992.</p>
        <p>''It is likely that inflation will rise further above the target in the near term,'' the Bank of England's monetary policy committee said.</p>
        <p>The bank's move alarmed businesses and some economists in Britain, who said it could harm the economy and curb spending. Many British consumers have taken on substantial amounts of debt, including home mortgages and credit card borrowings.</p>
        <p>''This is an unnecessary blow,'' said the director general of the British Retail Consortium, Kevin Hawkins.The Bank of England has ''overreacted by stepping up the pace,'' said Holger Schmieding, an economist with Bank of America in London. The worst case scenario, he added, would be for the Bank of England to raise rates another quarter of a point in a few months, and ''realize too late they are overdoing it.''</p>
        <p>The European Central Bank has steadily been lifting rates, and it forecast Thursday that the European economy would expand at a reasonable pace in 2007, led by Germany, which grew in 2006 by 2.5 percent, more than double the rate in 2005.</p>
        <p>For 2007, the economies of the 13 nations that share the euro are expected to expand at an average rate of about 2.6 percent.</p>
        <p>Although euro-zone inflation has fallen below the bank's goal of less than 2 percent for four consecutive months, the president of the European Central Bank, Jean-Claude Trichet, warned the bank would lift rates again in March if companies pass on previous increases in energy prices to their customers, or if the price of oil, which has retreated recently, spikes again.</p>
        <p>''I would say nothing here that would change expectations by the market that we could do something at the end of the first quarter,'' Mr. Trichet added. ''I would not contradict that.''</p>
        <p>The European Central Bank is responsible for setting euro interest rates and has ordered increases over the last year that some politicians have complained could put Europe's economic growth at risk.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
