<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Paid Notice: Deaths   RUBIN, LEONARD</title>
    <meta content="dn012907" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Classified" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Paid Death Notices" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1822329"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <person class="indexing_service">RUBIN, LEONARD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Paid Death Notice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Paid Death Notices</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E4D61F3AF93AA15752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="683" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Paid Notice: Deaths   RUBIN, LEONARD</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RUBIN--Leonard. Our cherished friend, mentor and leader, what a difference your life has made to the community, the world and to our class of 25! We treasure the many memories we share with wife and true partner Syril, adoring children, loving family, and a multitude of admiring and appreciative friends. With heartfelt sadness we will ever miss Lenny's unique and generous spirit, courageous leadership and exceptional wisdom. Love Always, Eleanor and Ed Epstein, Sandra and Arnold Gold, Bill Lippman, Barbara and Norman Seiden</p>
        <p>$(6$)RUBIN--Leonard. Dear Lenny, with your unwavering generosity and vision, you have built a house and made it a home, for thousands in your community. Your leadership will be missed. We extend our heartfelt sympathy to Syrile and the entire Rubin family. Amir and Joan Cohen Ilan and Iris Cohen</p>
        <p>$(6$)RUBIN--Leonard. It is with profound sadness that the JCC on the Palisades mourns the loss of Leonard Rubin, a great friend and remarkable man, who was one of the visionary founders of the JCC and epitomized the very essence of a world Jewish leader. A man of many passions, Mr. Rubin demonstrated extraordinary devotion to Jewish education and to Jewish continuity. He initiated important efforts that touched the lives of people around the world. A man of intellectual vibrancy, practical wisdom and deep ethical commitment, Lenny was an extraordinary leader, and for more than half a century, he was dedicated to promoting Jewish scholarship, identity and culture. He accomplished everything he set out to do with far-reaching and innovative results. A leader of heroic magnitude, Leonard served the JCC in many capacities. He was a founding member, President from 1966-1970, Chairman of the Board of Trustees, an active board member for decades and a driving force behind many JCC programs. His generous philanthropic support has been immeasurable and will never be forgotten. When the JCC sought to build its current facility in Tenafly, Leonard led the capital campaign which transformed a vision into reality. Believing that Jewish education was paramount, he established the first Judaic-Scholar-inResidence program at our JCC which now serves as a model for JCCs across the nation. Other programs that Lenny and his wife, Syril, generously established and supported include the nursery school, which bears their name, the Adult Reach Center for seniors with Alzheimers and dementia, a Teen Scholarship to Israel and the annual JCC Rubin Run. Leonard was also instrumental in countless Jewish organizations. He served as president of the World Confederation of Jewish Community Centers, as a Board member of the JCC Association, where he received the prestigious Community Builders Award. He also served on the Board of Directors of Shalom Hartman Institute in Jerusalem, as Chairman of the Board of the Jewish Home and Rehabilitation Center, as President of the Jewish Home at Rockleigh, as a President of UJA of Englewood and he was a driving force for the establishment of what is currently known as the UJA NNJ. He was a recipient of numerous awards, including the Brotherhood Award of the National Conference of Christians and Jews, the Appeal for Human Relations Award from the American Jewish Committee, the NJ Y Camps Harry S. Feller Memorial Award, and the Anti - Defamation Leagues Torch of Liberty Award. Our dear friend Lenny, will be remembered for his extraordinary generosity and commitment to the JCC on the Palisades, the Jewish community, the community at large and for inspiring generations of leaders. He possessed the rare gift of greatness and left an indelible mark on all our lives. We send our sincerest condolences to his wife Syril, his children, Daniel, the current President of the JCC on the Palisades, Robert, Toby, Leslie and Mark, his 12 grandchildren, Jed, Jamie, Tali, Sharon, Rebecca, Rachel, Julie, Alison, Sadie, Samantha, Dora, Jacob and one great-grandchild, Judah. He was deeply loved and will be sorely missed. May his memory be for a blessing. Funeral service will take place Sunday, January 28, at 11:00 am at the JCC on the Palisades, 411 East Clinton Avenue, Tenafly, NJ. 201-569-7900. Eleanor Epstein, Chair, Board of Trustees Avi Lewinson, Executive Director</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RUBIN--Leonard. Our cherished friend, mentor and leader, what a difference your life has made to the community, the world and to our class of 25! We treasure the many memories we share with wife and true partner Syril, adoring children, loving family, and a multitude of admiring and appreciative friends. With heartfelt sadness we will ever miss Lenny's unique and generous spirit, courageous leadership and exceptional wisdom. Love Always, Eleanor and Ed Epstein, Sandra and Arnold Gold, Bill Lippman, Barbara and Norman Seiden</p>
        <p>$(6$)RUBIN--Leonard. Dear Lenny, with your unwavering generosity and vision, you have built a house and made it a home, for thousands in your community. Your leadership will be missed. We extend our heartfelt sympathy to Syrile and the entire Rubin family. Amir and Joan Cohen Ilan and Iris Cohen</p>
        <p>$(6$)RUBIN--Leonard. It is with profound sadness that the JCC on the Palisades mourns the loss of Leonard Rubin, a great friend and remarkable man, who was one of the visionary founders of the JCC and epitomized the very essence of a world Jewish leader. A man of many passions, Mr. Rubin demonstrated extraordinary devotion to Jewish education and to Jewish continuity. He initiated important efforts that touched the lives of people around the world. A man of intellectual vibrancy, practical wisdom and deep ethical commitment, Lenny was an extraordinary leader, and for more than half a century, he was dedicated to promoting Jewish scholarship, identity and culture. He accomplished everything he set out to do with far-reaching and innovative results. A leader of heroic magnitude, Leonard served the JCC in many capacities. He was a founding member, President from 1966-1970, Chairman of the Board of Trustees, an active board member for decades and a driving force behind many JCC programs. His generous philanthropic support has been immeasurable and will never be forgotten. When the JCC sought to build its current facility in Tenafly, Leonard led the capital campaign which transformed a vision into reality. Believing that Jewish education was paramount, he established the first Judaic-Scholar-inResidence program at our JCC which now serves as a model for JCCs across the nation. Other programs that Lenny and his wife, Syril, generously established and supported include the nursery school, which bears their name, the Adult Reach Center for seniors with Alzheimers and dementia, a Teen Scholarship to Israel and the annual JCC Rubin Run. Leonard was also instrumental in countless Jewish organizations. He served as president of the World Confederation of Jewish Community Centers, as a Board member of the JCC Association, where he received the prestigious Community Builders Award. He also served on the Board of Directors of Shalom Hartman Institute in Jerusalem, as Chairman of the Board of the Jewish Home and Rehabilitation Center, as President of the Jewish Home at Rockleigh, as a President of UJA of Englewood and he was a driving force for the establishment of what is currently known as the UJA NNJ. He was a recipient of numerous awards, including the Brotherhood Award of the National Conference of Christians and Jews, the Appeal for Human Relations Award from the American Jewish Committee, the NJ Y Camps Harry S. Feller Memorial Award, and the Anti - Defamation Leagues Torch of Liberty Award. Our dear friend Lenny, will be remembered for his extraordinary generosity and commitment to the JCC on the Palisades, the Jewish community, the community at large and for inspiring generations of leaders. He possessed the rare gift of greatness and left an indelible mark on all our lives. We send our sincerest condolences to his wife Syril, his children, Daniel, the current President of the JCC on the Palisades, Robert, Toby, Leslie and Mark, his 12 grandchildren, Jed, Jamie, Tali, Sharon, Rebecca, Rachel, Julie, Alison, Sadie, Samantha, Dora, Jacob and one great-grandchild, Judah. He was deeply loved and will be sorely missed. May his memory be for a blessing. Funeral service will take place Sunday, January 28, at 11:00 am at the JCC on the Palisades, 411 East Clinton Avenue, Tenafly, NJ. 201-569-7900. Eleanor Epstein, Chair, Board of Trustees Avi Lewinson, Executive Director</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
